<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title xml:lang="it">Lysistrata (Λυσιστράτη, Lisistrata)</title>
                <title xml:lang="en">Lysistrata (Λυσιστράτη, Lysistrata)</title>
                <title xml:lang="pl">Lysistrata (Λυσιστράτη, Lysistrata)</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher><ref target="https://site.unibo.it/lares/">LARES Project</ref></publisher>
                <date when="2021"/>
                <idno type="filename">com_07_lysistrata</idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p><title>Lysistrata (Λυσιστράτη, Lizystrata, Bojomira, Gromiwoja)</title>, in Bartłomiej Bednarek, 
                    <title>Ofiara krwawa w Grecji starożytnej w świetle danych filologicznych. 
                        Stara komedia attycka</title>, Warszawa 2017, pp. 183-200</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change when="2021-11-10" who="Gaetano Spampinato">encoded in XML</change>
                <change when="2017" who="Bartłomiej Bednarek">written contents</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="edition" xml:lang="it">
                <div type="textpart" n="intro"> 
                    <p>Una commedia probabilmente messa in scena a Leneo nel 411 a.C. Il suo contenuto si riferisce alla difficilissima situazione militare, economica e demografica di Atene dopo la sconfitta della spedizione siciliana. Quando c'erano già molti indizi che la guerra del Peloponneso, che durava da vent'anni, non poteva che concludersi con una sconfitta, Aristofane propose una visione comica di fare la pace non come risultato della rinuncia di una delle parti, ma grazie alla mediazione delle donne.</p>
                    <p> Il nome dell'eroina eponima significa "esercito in dissoluzione" (da cui i concetti di polonizzazione di S. Srebrny). Forse allude al nome della sacerdotessa di Atena Polias che ricopriva la sua carica in quel periodo, Lisymache (Lewis 1955), il che significherebbe che il protagonista è una persona particolarmente legata al rito del sacrificio animale. </p>
                    <p> Dal punto di vista dello studio di questo rituale, tuttavia, ciò non ha un particolare significato, trascurando il fatto, forse degno di nota, che lo svolgimento di una funzione di culto forniva alla donna una posizione eccezionalmente elevata, proprio quella di cui la comica Lisymache sembra realmente godere.</p>
                    <p>
                        <emph>Schema della trama</emph>: Lisistrata convoca una riunione
                        segreta di donne di varie poleis di Atene per elaborare e giurare insieme un
                        piano per portare la pace. Il mezzo per questo fine è uno "sciopero del
                        letto", cioè negare agli uomini la soddisfazione sessuale finché fanno la
                        guerra. Allo stesso tempo, le donne anziane catturano l'Acropoli con il suo
                        tesoro. La parte femminile della comunità dell'Attica vi si trasferisce.
                        Dopo un periodo di difficile lotta con la loro natura stereotipata, le donne
                        riescono a portare alla riconciliazione tra Atene e Sparta. La commedia si
                        conclude con una festa universale.</p>
                    <p>Dal punto di vista della ricerca sul sacrificio di sangue, il testo è interessante per diverse brevi menzioni di questo rituale, e anche per la scena dell'obiezione, durante la quale - invece di un animale - viene macellato un vaso di vino.</p>
                    <p>  Il testo è citato dall'edizione Henderson (1987).</p>
                </div>
                <div type="textpart" n="commentary">
                    <div type="textpart" n="Lysistrata_78-84">
                        <head>Lisistrata 78-84</head>
                        <div type="textpart" n="78-84_intro">
                            <p>All'incontro segreto delle mogli partecipa la ragazza spartana Lampito, caratterizzata nel testo in modo stereotipato. A differenza di Atene, le ragazze lacedemoni praticavano esercizi fisici all'aria aperta (una delle forme tipiche era la danza del calcio dei glutei menzionata dall'eroina), quindi erano forti e abbronzate. </p>
                            <p>Il passus è significativo per il paragone che appare nel numero di Lampito, che afferma che le ragazze ateniesi la esaminano come un animale sacrificale.</p>
                            
                            <quote>
                                <lb/><emph>Λυσιστράτη</emph>
                                <lb/>ὦ φιλτάτη Λάκαινα χαῖρε Λαμπιτοῖ. 
                                <lb/>οἷον τὸ κάλλος γλυκυτάτη σου φαίνεται. 
                                <lb n="80"/>ὡς δ᾽ εὐχροεῖς, ὡς δὲ σφριγᾷ τὸ σῶμά σου. 
                                <lb/>κἂν ταῦρον ἄγχοις.
                                <lb/><emph>Λαμπιτώ</emph>
                                <lb/>μάλα γ᾽ οἰῶ ναὶ τὼ σιώ:
                                <lb/>γυμνάδδομαι γὰρ καὶ ποτὶ πυγὰν ἅλλομαι.
                                <lb/><emph>Καλονίκη</emph>
                                <lb/>ὡς δὴ καλὸν τὸ χρῆμα τιτθίων ἔχεις. 
                                <lb/><emph>Λαμπιτώ</emph>
                                <lb/>ᾇπερ ἱερεῖόν τοί μ᾽ ὑποψαλάσσετε. 
                            </quote>
                            
                            <quote><emph>Tr.:</emph> LISISTRATA: Lampito, caro spartano, benvenuto! Come
                                brilla, mio dolce, la tua bellezza! Come è sano e sodo il tuo corpo!
                                Potresti strangolare un toro! LAMPITO: E i Dioscuri? Finisco per
                                esercitarmi e fare balli di culo. CALONIKE: Che seni incredibili che
                                hai! LA.: Mi stai macellando come un animale sacrificale! </quote>
                        </div>
                        <div type="textpart" n="commentary">
                            <p> ὑποψαλάσσετε - 'tu che brancoli'; il verbo ὑπο-ψαλάσσω è certamente un hapax legomenon, ma la sua struttura e il contesto d'uso qui permettono di capire a cosa si riferisce. La forma senza prefisso (ψαλάσσω) significa toccare qualcosa, come le corde di uno strumento mentre si suona. Il prefisso ὑπο può avere sfumature rilassanti o riferirsi alla categoria spaziale "sotto". Entrambi i significati in questo contesto hanno un buon senso: "mi maceri delicatamente [solletico?]" o "mi maceri dal basso". </p>                  
                            <p> Questo secondo aspetto del significato potrebbe essersi riflesso in modo interessante nello strato performativo dell'opera. Aristofane ha certamente fatto pieno uso dell'effetto comico della commedia ambigua, in cui un uomo (attore) vestito da donna palpeggia un altro uomo, indossando attributi iperbolici della femminilità. Naturalmente, questo strato dell'opera ci rimane completamente inaccessibile.</p> 
                            <p>I commentatori moderni del passus (Sommerstein 1990: ad loc. , Henderson 1987: ad loc. ) spiegano il confronto indicando i passus che si riferiscono al sacrificio di un animale quando è abbastanza grasso da fornire una buona carne per il banchetto (Ar. Eq. 1135--1140; Philem. Fr. 155). </p>                
                            <p> Lo scholiasta (ad loc. ) interpreta il luogo in modo simile: τὰ γὰρ ἱερεῖα μέλλοντες θύειν ψηλαφῶσιν, εἰ λιπαρά ἐστι ("perché gli animali che dovevano essere sacrificati venivano palpati per vedere se erano grassi"). A prescindere da questi motivi pratici e forse anche edonistici, la necessità di sottoporre un animale all'ispezione era dettata da fattori puramente religiosi (per un approfondimento si veda Feyel 2006; ad Ar. Ach. 784).</p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <div type="textpart" n="Lysistrata_177-179">
                        <head>Lisistrata 177-179</head>
                        <div type="textpart" n="177-179">
                            <p>Come parte del piano comico di Lisistrata, le donne più giovani devono influenzare i loro mariti colpendo nelle loro camere da letto. Alle più anziane, che non possono svolgere un tale ruolo, è stato dato il compito di controllare la posizione strategica sull'Acropoli. </p>                     
                            <p>Il passus non contiene alcuna informazione assolutamente chiara sul sacrificio di sangue, tuttavia c'è un prezioso suggerimento in esso. Vale a dire, qualcosa di ovvio per gli ateniesi deve essere stata la presenza di donne anziane sull'Acropoli nelle prime ore del mattino (quando l'azione del lavoro), legata all'attività cultuale. </p>
                            <p>La parola θύειν usata nel testo può significare fare un sacrificio di sangue o un'altra forma di culto. Non è chiaro se il passus si riferisce a qualche particolare attività cultuale svolta dalle donne anziane sull'Acropoli. È possibile che si tratti di uno stereotipo (probabilmente giustificato dalla realtà ateniese), secondo il quale le donne anziane sono un gruppo sociale particolarmente incline alla devozione. </p>
                            <p>  In questo caso, il passaggio potrebbe riferirsi a sacrifici spontanei, auto-iniziati dalle donne anziane.</p>
                            
                            <quote>
                                <lb/><emph>Λυσιστράτη</emph>
                                <lb/> Ταῖς πρεσβυτάταις γὰρ προστέτακται τοῦτο δρᾶν,  
                                <lb/> ἕως ἂν ἡμεῖς ταῦτα συντιθώμεθα,
                                <lb/> θύειν δοκούσαις καταλαβεῖν τὴν ἀκρόπολιν.    
                            </quote>
                            
                            <quote><emph>Tr.: </emph>LISISTRATA: È toccato alle donne più anziane
                                andare ad occupare l'Acropoli mentre noi siamo qui a frequentare,
                                con la scusa di fare delle offerte. </quote>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <div type="textpart" n="Lysistrata_181-239">
                        <head>Lisistrata 181-239</head>
                        <div type="textpart" n="181-239">
                            <p>Il passus contiene una scena comica di giuramento. A differenza del rituale paragmatico di tipo thysia, il sacrificio, che di solito era coronato da una festa gioiosa, la cerimonia del giuramento era piuttosto cupa, poiché erano ancora presenti terribili sanzioni per il mancato rispetto degli obblighi. L'animale macellato non veniva mangiato. </p>
                            <p>La scena di Aristofane contiene elementi contrastanti; la serietà cede qui il passo alla pagliacciata. Le donne, invece di macellare l'animale, aprono la brocca e al posto del sangue scorre il vino, alludendo allo stereotipo comico che le donne ateniesi erano ghiotte della bevanda, che bevevano non mescolata con l'acqua di nascosto dai loro mariti.</p>
                            <quote>
                                <lb/><emph>Λυσιστράτη</emph>
                                <lb/>τί δῆτα ταῦτ᾽ οὐχ ὡς τάχιστ᾽ ὦ Λαμπιτοῖ 
                                <lb/>ξυνωμόσαμεν, ὅπως ἂν ἀρρήκτως ἔχῃ; 
                                <lb/><emph>Λαμπιτώ</emph>
                                <lb/>πάρφαινε μὰν τὸν ὅρκον, ὡς ὀμιόμεθα. 
                                <lb/><emph>Λυσιστράτη</emph>
                                <lb/>καλῶς λέγεις. ποῦ 'σθ᾽ ἡ Σκύθαινα; ποῖ βλέπεις; 
                                <lb n="185"/>θὲς ἐς τὸ πρόσθεν ὑπτίαν τὴν ἀσπίδα, 
                                <lb/>καί μοι δότω τὰ τόμιά τις. 
                                <lb/><emph>Καλονίκη</emph>
                                <lb/>Λυσιστράτη
                                <lb/>τίν᾽ ὅρκον ὁρκώσεις ποθ᾽ ἡμᾶς; 
                                <lb/><emph>Λυσιστράτη</emph> 
                                <lb/>ὅντινα;
                                <lb/>εἰς ἀσπίδ᾽, ὥσπερ φάσ᾽ ἐν Αἰσχύλῳ ποτέ,
                                <lb/>μηλοσφαγούσας.  
                                <lb/><emph>Καλονίκη</emph>      
                                <lb/>μὴ σύ γ᾽ ὦ Λυσιστράτη
                                <lb n="190"/>εἰς ἀσπίδ᾽ ὀμόσῃς μηδὲν εἰρήνης πέρι.
                                <lb/><emph>Λυσιστράτη</emph>
                                <lb/>τίς ἂν οὖν γένοιτ᾽ ἂν ὅρκος; 
                                <lb/><emph>Καλονίκη</emph>
                                <lb/>εἰ λευκόν ποθεν
                                <lb/>ἵππον λαβοῦσαι τόμιον ἐντεμοίμεθα.
                                <lb/><emph>Λυσιστράτη</emph>
                                <lb/>ποῖ λευκὸν ἵππον; 
                                <lb/><emph>Καλονίκη</emph>
                                <lb/>ἀλλὰ πῶς ὀμούμεθα
                                <lb/>ἡμεῖς;
                                <lb/><emph>Λυσιστράτη</emph>
                                <lb/>ἐγώ σοι νὴ Δί᾽, ἢν βούλῃ, φράσω.
                                <lb n="195"/>θεῖσαι μέλαιναν κύλικα μεγάλην ὑπτίαν,
                                <lb/>μηλοσφαγοῦσαι Θάσιον οἴνου σταμνίον
                                <lb/>ὀμόσωμεν ἐς τὴν κύλικα μὴ 'πιχεῖν ὕδωρ.
                                <lb/><emph>Λαμπιτώ</emph>
                                <lb/>φεῦ δᾶ τὸν ὅρκον ἄφατον ὡς ἐπαινίω. 
                                <lb/><emph>Λυσιστράτη</emph>
                                <lb/>φερέτω κύλικά τις ἔνδοθεν καὶ σταμνίον. 
                                <lb/><emph>Μυρρίνη</emph>
                                <lb/>ὦ φίλταται γυναῖκες, <add>ὁ</add> κεραμεὼν ὅσος. 
                                <lb/><emph>Καλονίκη</emph>
                                <lb/>ταύτην μὲν ἄν τις εὐθὺς ἡσθείη λαβών. 
                                <lb/><emph>Λυσιστράτη</emph>
                                <lb/>καταθεῖσα ταύτην προσλαβοῦ μοι τοῦ κάπρου. 
                                <lb/>δέσποινα Πειθοῖ καὶ κύλιξ φιλοτησία, 
                                <lb/>τὰ σφάγια δέξαι ταῖς γυναιξὶν εὐμενής. 
                                <lb/><emph>Καλονίκη</emph>
                                <lb/>εὔχρων γε θαἶμα κἀποπυτίζει καλῶς. 
                                <lb/><emph>Λαμπιτώ</emph>
                                <lb/>καὶ μὰν ποτόδδει γ᾽ ἁδὺ ναὶ τὸν Κάστορα. 
                                <lb/><emph>Μυρρίνη</emph>
                                <lb/>ἐᾶτε πρώτην μ᾽ ὦ γυναῖκες ὀμνύναι. 
                                <lb/><emph>Καλονίκη</emph>
                                <lb/>μὰ τὴν Ἀφροδίτην οὔκ, ἐάν γε μὴ λάχῃς. 
                                <lb/><emph>Λυσιστράτη</emph>
                                <lb/>λάζυσθε πᾶσαι τῆς κύλικος ὦ Λαμπιτοῖ: 
                                <lb n="210"/>λεγέτω δ᾽ ὑπὲρ ὑμῶν μί᾽ ἅπερ ἂν κἀγὼ λέγω:
                                <lb/>ὑμεῖς δ᾽ ἐπομεῖσθε ταὐτὰ κἀμπεδώσετε. 
                                <lb/>οὐκ ἔστιν οὐδεὶς οὔτε μοιχὸς οὔτ᾽ ἀνήρ—   
                                <lb/><emph>Καλονίκη</emph>
                                <lb/>οὐκ ἔστιν οὐδεὶς οὔτε μοιχὸς οὔτ᾽ ἀνήρ— 
                                <lb/>[...]
                                <lb/><emph>Λυσιστράτη</emph>
                                <lb/>ταῦτ᾽ ἐμπεδοῦσα μὲν πίοιμ᾽ ἐντευθενί: 
                                <lb/><emph>Καλονίκη</emph>
                                <lb/>ταῦτ᾽ ἐμπεδοῦσα μὲν πίοιμ᾽ ἐντευθενί: 
                                <lb/><emph>Λυσιστράτη</emph>
                                <lb/>εἰ δὲ παραβαίην, ὕδατος ἐμπλῇθ᾽ ἡ κύλιξ. 
                                <lb/><emph>Καλονίκη</emph>
                                <lb/>εἰ δὲ παραβαίην, ὕδατος ἐμπλῇθ᾽ ἡ κύλιξ. 
                                <lb/><emph>Λυσιστράτη</emph>
                                <lb/>συνεπόμνυθ᾽ ὑμεῖς ταῦτα πᾶσαι; 
                                <lb/><emph>Πᾶσαι</emph>
                                <lb/>νὴ Δία.
                                <lb/><emph>Λυσιστράτη</emph>
                                <lb/>φέρ᾽ ἐγὼ καθαγίσω τήνδε. 
                                <lb/><emph>Καλονίκη</emph>
                                <lb/>τὸ μέρος γ᾽ ὦ φίλη,
                                <lb/>ὅπως ἂν ὦμεν εὐθὺς ἀλλήλων φίλαι.
                            </quote>
                            <quote><emph>Tr.:</emph> LISISTRATA: Perché allora, Lampito, non
                                facciamo subito un giuramento per rendere indissolubile l'accordo?
                                LAMPITO: Quindi presenta le sue parole in modo che possiamo giurare.
                                LY..: Giusto. Dov'è Scythian? Cosa stai guardando? [Date questa
                                parte di catrame concava verso l'alto. Che qualcuno passi l'offerta
                                a fette. CALONIKE: Lisistrato, che giuramento vuoi, avremmo legato?
                                LY.:Quale?Come si dice che Eschilo abbia una volta predetto,
                                macellando una pecora su uno scudo. KA.:Solo [190] non sopra lo
                                scudo, visto che si tratta di pace. LY.: Allora cosa dovremmo
                                giurare? KA.:Perché non prendiamo un gatto bianco da qualche parte,
                                lo tagliamo a pezzi e ci giuriamo sopra?LY...: Da dove viene il
                                cavallo bianco? KA.:Allora come possiamo giurare? LY.: Se vuoi, te
                                lo dirò, per Zeus. [195] Prendi un grande incantesimo nero e mettilo
                                a macinare una brocca di vino di Taso, e giura di non versare mai
                                acqua in quell'incantesimo. LA.: In verità, raccomando questo
                                straordinario tipo di giuramento. LY.: Allora che qualcuno porti un
                                incantesimo e una brocca. MYRRINE: [200] Care donne, una brocca così
                                grande! KA.: Basta prendere questo incantesimo nelle tue mani per
                                provare piacere. LY..: Mettila giù e tieni il cinghiale. O Peitho,
                                sovrano, e tu, maga dell'amicizia, accetta questa offerta, o donna
                                benevola. KA.: [205] Bello è il colore di questo sangue, e sgorga
                                magnificamente. LA.: E, per Kastor, ha un odore delizioso. NOI..:
                                Lasciatemi essere il primo a giurare. KA: Su Afrodite, non c'è modo,
                                a meno che non tiri fuori un destino. LY.: Lampito, prendi tutto
                                l'incantesimo. [210] Che uno a nome di tutti ripeta dopo di me, e
                                che gli altri lo approvino con un giuramento. "Nessun amante o
                                marito.... KA.: "Nessun amante o marito... [...] LY..: [233] ...se
                                tengo questo, posso bere da esso.... KA.: ...se tengo questo,
                                lasciami bere da esso... LY..: [235] ...e se non mantengo la fede,
                                che la coppa sia riempita d'acqua. KA..: e se non mantengo la fede,
                                che la coppa sia riempita d'acqua. Giurate tutti. DONNA: Per Zeus!
                                LY.: Ora compirò un atto di sacrificio. KA.:Solo un po', mia cara,
                                per poter essere subito amici. </quote>
                        </div>
                        <div type="textpart" n="commentary">
                            <p>Il sacrificio legato al giuramento è una categoria che interessa dal punto di vista tipologico. Sembra che nella visione "emica", fosse qualcosa di completamente diverso dalla thysia, come evidenziato dal vocabolario stesso usato nel passaggio. Il sostantivo τὰ σφάγια appare qui come sinonimo, denotando sacrifici cruenti, che non vengono mangiati. L'azione compiuta dall'eroina, o una delle azioni, è a sua volta denotata dal verbo καθαγίζω, 'distruggere ritualmente'. Questo suggerisce che abbiamo a che fare con un rituale il cui obiettivo primario non è quello di conquistare forze amiche, ma di scacciare quelle ostili (Parker 2011: 141 - l'opposizione tra sacrifici congiuntivi e disgiuntivi è una variante della divisione più consolidata nella letteratura in sacrifici olim-pici e ctonici, cfr. Scullion 1994). Nonostante queste indicazioni lessicali, il passus in questione contiene non pochi dati che suggeriscono che la distinzione tra tipi di rituali non era abbastanza rigorosa.</p>
                            <p>La struttura del rituale, visibile sotto lo strato di distorsione comica, è analoga a quella dei thysia: le eroine portano l'"animale" e segue una preghiera (203-204). Vale la pena notare che essa contiene una richiesta alla dea di accettare il sacrificio (τὰ σφάγια δέξαι). La stessa destinataria è descritta come ταῖς γυναιξὶν εὐμενής ("benevola con le donne"), che è un tipico espediente retorico nella preghiera, che comporta l'identificazione di una divinità con un epiteto contenente una proiezione della sua relazione desiderata con il devoto. Il luogo suggerisce che il sacrificio (τὰ σφάγια) può essere trattato come l'equivalente di un dono, qualcosa il cui dare, da un lato, e il cui ricevere, dall'altro, apre un tipo di relazione benevola. Ciò che è caratteristico dei riti di tipo sphagia, l'accento cade sul "sangue". Nel caso della thysia, esso fluirebbe nella ciotola dello sphageion, una piccola parte verrebbe usata per ungere l'altare, e il resto verrebbe usato per le frattaglie (Ekroth 2005). Nel rituale in discussione, il sangue veniva raccolto in un recipiente (la cui scelta aveva chiaramente un significato simbolico) per essere utilizzato in qualche modo.</p>
                            <p>La distorsione del comico e la vaghezza del testo senza didascalie rendono difficile dire cosa sia effettivamente successo in scena in quel luogo e a quale tipo di comportamento corrispondesse nella realtà rituale. Tuttavia, sembra caratteristico che la fine del rituale sia qui connessa con il piacere di banchettare insieme, similmente a Thysia, dove la macellazione era coronata dalla degustazione delle interiora arrostite. Le associazioni della festa non sono forse tanto il risultato di una distorsione comica quanto un segno dei tempi.</p>
                            <p>Infatti, è chiaro da Pausania (5.24.10-11) che mentre c'era un'usanza tra gli eroi omerici di scartare l'intera carcassa degli animali (cfr. Il. 19.266-8) su cui giuravano, i suoi contemporanei (II secolo d.C.) non sempre, se mai, osservavano questa ingiunzione. Come nota Parker (2011: 157-158; 1996: 105; Stengel 1920: 137-138), il cambiamento (se si può davvero parlare di cambiamento, trattando Omero come una fonte che riflette autorevolmente la realtà sociale) può essere avvenuto molto presto. Si sa che già nel periodo classico si mangiava la carne di un animale sul quale si era fatto un giuramento durante l'Apaturia (per un'ampia base di fonti vedi: Parker 1996: 105). Per saperne di più sui giuramenti: Sommerstein, Bayliss (2013) e Sommerstein, Torrance (2014).</p>
                            <p>184: ἡ Σκύθαινα"Sciti"; ad Atene le truppe d'ordine venivano reclutate tra gli Sciti, che indossavano un caratteristico abito straniero. La loro immagine nella commedia indica l'esistenza di stereotipi negativi su di loro. La presenza di una controparte femminile della Scizia nella scena indica paradossalmente che la scena è una parodia di un tipico rito ateniese eseguito in pubblico, assistito da un tutore dell'ordine.</p>
                            <p>186/192: τὰ τόμια - sacrificio a fette / τόμιον ἐντεμοίμεθα - "taglieremo a pezzi"; la pratica di una persona che presta giuramento stando in piedi su o toccando qualcosa descritto come τόμια è ben attestata (e.D. 23.68; Arist. Ath. 55.5; Antipho 5.12; Aesch. 1.114; Lycurg. 1.20). Il contesto, l'etimologia della frase, così come la formula τόμιον ἐντεμοίμεθα (cfr. Aesch. 2.87: τἐμνοντα τὰ τόμια) non lasciano dubbi sul fatto che ciò che si intende siano parti di un animale tagliate, escisse o tritate (la formula omerica, ad es. in Il. in Il. 2.124 ὅρκια πιστὰ ταμόντες - "aver tagliato = aver stretto un patto inviolabile"). </p>
                            <p>I dettagli rimangono purtroppo oggetto di congetture. Stengel (1910: 80-85), Stengel (1920: 137), cf. Burkert (2011: 378), Burkert (1985: 251), Burkert (1983: 36) ha espresso una congettura audace che possa trattarsi di nuclei (tagliati), ma come nota Faraone (1993: 68), non ci sono forti indicazioni a sostegno di ciò, che non si trattasse di visceri (σπλάγχνα tagliati e affettati) o di carne tagliata (cfr. Ekroth 2014: 164-165; Casabona 1966: 220-225). È anche possibile che il tipo di oggetti che venivano usati come τόμια variasse e dipendesse da fattori per noi sfuggenti (oltre alla cronologia e alla geografia, il contenuto dei giuramenti, il loro carattere pubblico o privato, ecc.).</p>
                            <p>185-90: i versi contengono un riferimento esplicativo a un luogo dei Sette contro Tebe di Eschilo (42-48; parole dell'esploratore): ("Poiché, ecco, sette uomini, audaci condottieri,/ scannarono un toro, raccogliendone il sangue in uno scudo dai bordi neri/ e con le mani toccarono il sangue del toro,/ su Ares, Enyo e Grosha, avidi di sangue/ fecero un giuramento che o avrebbero portato distruzione alla città/ e l'avrebbero distrutta con la forza, / o morendo avrebbero mescolato il proprio sangue con questa terra"). </p>
                            <p>Ovviamente, questa immagine suggestiva deve essere affrontata con la stessa cautela del grottesco aristofanico. Perché queste parole si riferiscono al comportamento dei violatori iperbolici del passato mitico. Vale la pena notare, tuttavia, che l'esistenza di una tale pratica rituale è ampiamente confermata da Senofonte (An. 2.2.9), che descrive come tre animali (un toro, un cinghiale e un ariete) furono macellati, il loro sangue fu raccolto in uno scudo, dopo di che i Greci e i loro alleati vi immersero le loro spade e lance e giurarono un'alleanza. Sembra significativo che Eschilo sottolinei la connessione simbolica tra il sangue animale versato e il sangue umano. È presente nel soprannome della personificazione Phobos - il sostantivo, trattato come il nome di una divinità, definisce "paura in preda al panico". Nel quadro della tecnica di guerra dei tempi di Eschilo, questo stesso fenomeno portava alla rottura della formazione, alla fuga disordinata e al massacro dei guerrieri. Il sangue menzionato qui è anche quello dei sette capi che giurano di morire se non catturano la città. Così, il poeta tratta chiaramente l'atto di violenza contro l'animale come una rappresentazione di ciò che è l'oggetto della promessa del boia: compiere un atto di violenza.</p>
                            <p>È sorprendente che l'idea di Lisistrata di ripetere il gesto conosciuto da Eschilo si scontri con un violento rifiuto. Le donne di Aristofane si occupano di pace, quindi l'intero rituale, piuttosto che il sangue come rappresentazione materiale dell'oggetto del giuramento, invocherà il vino, un liquido che dà piacere alla donna ateniese stereotipata e che probabilmente era abbastanza comunemente associato alla pace (cfr. Ar. Pax: sparsim; E. Ba 417-433; Il. 6.264-268).</p>
                            <p>189: μηλοσφαγούσας - "macellare una pecora"; in Eschilo (Th. 186) compare la parola ταυροσφαγοῦντες, "macellare un toro", come si dovrebbe dedurre dalla struttura del compositum e dal fatto che nel verso successivo si parla di sangue di toro. Va notato, tuttavia, che al tempo di Aristofane, sebbene la struttura di questi due composti fosse ancora evidente, essi persero chiaramente il loro significato originale ("macellare una pecora/toro") a favore di uno più generale: "macellare qualsiasi animale". (cf. schol. ad loc. ). È difficile resistere all'impressione che il poeta abbia voluto qui fare uno scherzo, sostituendo la parola associata a una vittima più prestigiosa con una che si riferisce a una più comune. Una tale interpretazione, tuttavia, sembra eccessivamente sottile, poiché richiederebbe al pubblico di memorizzare il testo di Eschilo in modo molto preciso. Da un punto di vista sintattico, è interessante notare il comportamento del verbo μηλο-/ ταυρο-σφαγέω, che nei luoghi discussi ricorre con la circostanza εἰς ἀσπίδα / ἐς σάκος, 'tarif' (dove due sostantivi diversi nominano due tipi di scudi). Il punto, ovviamente, è che il sangue dell'animale macellato, che è l'oggetto di interesse prosessuale durante il rito, deve fluire in un tale recipiente improvvisato.</p>
                            <p>191-2: λευκὸν ἵππον - "un cavallo bianco"; il luogo non è chiaro. Scholiasta vede qui o uno scherzo osceno o un'allusione ai costumi delle Amazzoni, che, scrive, sacrificavano cavalli bianchi (λευκοὺς ἵππους ἔθυον). La prima di queste ipotesi, come al solito con il testo di Aristofane, sembra attraente. Poiché non sappiamo cosa accadde sulla scena, non si può escludere che l'arguzia qui contenuta fosse non solo piccante ma anche perfettamente leggibile,grazie al gesto che accompagna le parole. </p>
                            <p>D'altra parte, il fatto che Scholiast fornisca una variante alternativa della spiegazione indica che egli stesso non aveva dati sufficienti sullo strato performativo per affermare qualcosa di certo sul contenuto del passus. La seconda interpretazione che dà sembra tanto meno convincente in quanto nulla si sa da altre fonti sui sacrifici che si presume siano stati fatti dalle Amazzoni. Erodoto (7.113) menziona l'uccisione rituale di cavalli bianchi da parte dei magi persiani, e Lukian (Scyth. 3) menziona il sacrificio sulla tomba di una rosa scita. Questi due passaggi si collegano con i costumi delle Amazzoni nel migliore dei casi indirettamente. Inoltre non contengono nulla che sarebbe ovviamente associato al luogo in questione in Aristofane. Poiché il passus era ovviamente destinato a suscitare il riso, si può sospettare che l'allusione in esso contenuta fosse ben leggibile, e quindi si riferisse a qualcosa di ben noto al pubblico. Presumibilmente, quindi, le spiegazioni speculative dello studioso ci allontanano solo dal cogliere l'essenza della battuta, che poteva riguardare qualcosa di molto attuale all'epoca in cui la commedia fu rappresentata. È con una distanza simile che dobbiamo considerare la proposta di Fletcher (2012: 228), che ha indicato come parallelo il giuramento fatto dai pretendenti di Elena. In questo rituale, secondo Pausania (3.20.9), veniva utilizzato un tom di cavallo (non sappiamo di che razza), ma è difficile dire se questa tradizione fosse nota al pubblico di Aristofane.</p>
                            <p>196: μηλοσφαγοῦσαι Θάσιον οἴνου σταμνίον - 'macellare una brocca di vino di Taso'. Lisistrata (qui e coerentemente più avanti) usa il linguaggio tecnico del sacrificio di sangue, applicandolo ad azioni che non sono sacrifici (μηλοσφαγέω - cfr. 189). Non sono nemmeno libagioni sensu stricto (come Henderson 1987: ad loc.), perché il vino qui non è versato a terra, ma in un recipiente. Il vino di Taso era famoso per la sua qualità, quindi chiaramente, come al solito nella commedia, la dimensione edonistica del rito parodiato viene in primo piano. Il sacrificio di un recipiente di vino anche in: Ar. Th. 686-762.</p>
                            <p>202: προσλαβοῦ μοι τοῦ κάπρου - "tenere il cinghiale". Henderson (1987: ad loc. ), nel suo commento al passus, fa notare che l'imposizione delle mani sull'animale prima di macellarlo aveva un importante significato simbolico. Suppongo che si tratti solo di un equivoco, perché lo studioso si riferisce al passus (cit. ad 185-190) di Eschilo (Th. 42), che parla di immergere le mani nel sangue già dopo la macellazione, e al luogo di Stengel (1920: 136), dove si tratta di tagliare ciocche di capelli alle vittime (in Iliade 3.273-274) e consegnarle ai capi degli Achei e dei Troiani. Quest'ultimo gesto (cfr. Eustathius: ad loc.) aveva chiaramente un significato analogo a quello di dare ai giuranti le interiora o pezzi dell'animale macellato e probabilmente non aveva nulla a che fare con il mettere le mani su di esso prima di ucciderlo. Per questo motivo, si può supporre che l'espressione data da Lisistrata nei passaggi discussi imiti il comportamento legato alla routine sacrificale di carattere puramente pragmatico e sia priva di un profondo simbolismo. Poiché le eroine erano così preoccupate per il calice, la leader ha dovuto richiamarle all'ordine, ordinando loro di aiutare a tenere l'animale, mentre lei stessa (apparentemente) intendeva sferrare un colpo. Perché il testo faccia riferimento a un cinghiale (κάπρος) rimane una questione di dibattito. </p>
                            <p>Anche se i commentatori (Henderson 1987: ad loc.; Sommerstein 1990 ad loc.) suggeriscono che può essere influenzato da una scena analoga nell'Iliade (19.249-268), in cui Agamennone macella un simile animale, è difficile dire perché questo luogo dovrebbe essere più significativo di, per esempio, un passus dal libro III dell'Iliade (271-323), in cui l'eroe macella due pecore. Dato che i dati disponibili non indicano che i maiali siano particolarmente legati al contesto della storia, forse dovremmo supporre una sorta di gioco di parole qui. Scholiast (ad loc. ) nota che la parola per cinghiale è usata qui da Aristofane nel senso di "genitali", il che sembra essere un suggerimento attraente, purtroppo non confermato dal materiale lessicale. Naturalmente, invece di un cinghiale, le eroine "macellano" una brocca di vino.</p>
                            <p>203-204: una preghiera molto breve che contiene un'invocazione a due dee (una delle quali è puramente una personificazione comica), una richiesta di accettare un'offerta (al singolare, ma credo che siano entrambe le dee). L'epiteto rivela che lo scopo del rituale è quello di conquistare gli immortali (questa volta, però, si riferisce probabilmente solo alla seconda dea menzionata).</p>
                            <p>205: εὔχρων γε θαἶμα κἀποπυτίζει καλῶς - "bello è il colore di questo sangue e sgorga magnificamente". Un'altra di una serie di battute basate sul doppio senso: vino/sangue. Gli Scholia (ad loc.) contengono la spiegazione che il boia qui imita un indovino o un sacerdote (θυοσκόος). Questo ci porta a supporre che il flusso di sangue fosse sottoposto a una lettura per ottenere dei segni. Anche se non ci fosse un sofisticato sistema di semiosi delle petecchie, sarebbe effettivamente strano se non funzionasse la categoria di base dell'opposizione binaria: "giusto/sbagliato". Il luogo della Pace (1054-1055) indica l'adeguatezza in tale contesto dell'avverbio καλῶς.</p>
                            <p>207: ἐᾶτε πρώτην μ', ὦ γυναῖκες, ὀμνύναι - "lasciami essere la prima a giurare"; l'eroina ovviamente non può aspettare il suo turno alla coppa. Sotto lo strato di uno scherzo si può scorgere una pratica rituale: il giuramento richiede un contatto fisico con l'animale macellato, i suoi pezzi o il sangue.</p>
                            <p>235-236: εἰ δὲ παραβαίην, ὕδατος ἐμπλῆιθ' ἡ κύλιξ - "e se non mantengo la fede, che la coppa sia riempita di acqua". I testi di giuramento di solito contengono una sanzione esplicitamente espressa. Caratteristicamente, il materiale greco indica che essa era il più delle volte collegata all'oggetto su cui il giuramento veniva fatto. Faraone (1993), con tutta la distanza che conserva dal concetto di Frazer, definisce probabilmente a ragione tale comportamento come una sorta di magia simpatica, in cui - condizionatamente, perché nella situazione di rottura della parola - chi giura porta su di sé il destino che incontra qualcos'altro - un animale macellato e tagliato, sangue o vino versato, cera fusa (es. 3.292-301; Paroemioraphi Graeci 126 (Gaisford); SEG IX 4; cfr. Fletcher 2012: 214, 230). La descrizione del giuramento dai Sette contro Tebe di Eschilo (42-48), citata sopra (ad 185-9), rientra perfettamente in questo schema.</p>
                            <p>238: ἐγὼ καθαγίσω τήνδε - "compirò un atto di sacrificio"; il verbo καθαγίζω denota l'atto di offrire qualcosa mediante distruzione completa, di solito con il fuoco (cfr. Ar. Av. 566). Nel luogo in discussione, tuttavia, si tratta chiaramente di "distruggere" il vino in un modo che sia piacevole per la persona che lo distrugge, cioè di berlo. Chiaramente, quindi, ciò che era al centro dell'interesse di chi usava il termine non era l'uso del fuoco, ma il fatto di annientare un oggetto, o, come probabilmente Svenbro (2005) fa notare giustamente, di toglierlo dalla sfera umana e in una forma alterata (per esempio il fumo) trasferirlo agli esseri soprannaturali. Considerando la funzione dell'oggetto su cui si è giurato, con il cui destino si è identificato il destino di chi giura sulla croce (cfr. ad 235,6), a questo punto ci si aspetterebbe un trattamento brutale del vino. Ciò è perfettamente sottolineato dalla natura comica del passus, in cui Lisistrata intende chiaramente bere avidamente l'intero contenuto del grande incantesimo.</p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <div type="textpart" n="Lysistrata_1128–1134">
                        <head>Lisistrata 1128–1134</head>
                        <div type="textpart" n="1128-1134">
                            <p>Lisistrata esprime la critica degli uomini delle varie poleis greche coinvolte nella guerra del Peloponneso. Il passus è interessante per l'ideologia panellenica che porta alla ribalta, il cui prezioso punto di riferimento è lo "straniero, il barbaro". A causa della menzione di un esercito di potenziali nemici esterni, possiamo indovinare che se era in qualche modo specificato quali stranieri si intendevano, la fonte della paura che portava i Greci alla solidarietà doveva essere soprattutto la Persia. Oltre alla minaccia esterna - reale o immaginaria - i santuari comuni erano un fattore unificante a livello ideologico. Nei passaggi citati l'attenzione si concentra sul gesto di lavarsi le mani. </p>
                            <p>È difficile dire se si tratta solo di una figura retorica. In ogni caso, era chiaramente un momento molto importante nel processo rituale.</p>
                            
                            <quote>
                                <lb/><emph>Λυσιστράτη</emph>
                                <lb/>λαβοῦσα δ᾽ ὑμᾶς λοιδορῆσαι βούλομαι
                                <lb/>κοινῇ δικαίως, οἳ μιᾶς ἐκ χέρνιβος
                                <lb n="1130"/>βωμοὺς περιρραίνοντες ὥσπερ ξυγγενεῖς
                                <lb/>Ὀλυμπίασιν, ἐν Πύλαις, Πυθοῖ （πόσους
                                <lb/>εἴποιμ᾽ ἂν ἄλλους, εἴ με μηκύνειν δέοι;）
                                <lb/>ἐχθρῶν παρόντων βαρβάρων στρατεύματι
                                <lb/>Ἕλληνας ἄνδρας καὶ πόλεις ἀπόλλυτε.
                            </quote>
                            
                            <quote>Poiché vi ho riuniti qui, desidero esprimere una giusta critica
                                a tutti coloro che da un solo recipiente spruzzano acqua sugli
                                altari, come i fratelli - a Olimpia, a Pylaia, a Pytho.... quanti
                                altri potrei enumerare, se dovessi parlare più a lungo? Sebbene
                                l'esercito barbaro sia così vicino, tu distruggi le città e gli
                                uomini greci.</quote>
                        </div>
                        <div type="textpart" n="commentary">
                            <p>1129: μιᾶς ἐκ χέρνιβος - "da un solo recipiente"; il sostantivo
                                χέρνιψ originariamente significava acqua per lavarsi le mani - prima
                                del sacrificio, così come altre attività come un pasto. Nel luogo in
                                questione, Aristofane usa la frase preposizionale ἐκ χέρνιβος ("dai
                                chernips"), il che può indicare che all'epoca veniva già usato anche
                                in senso metonimico: "un recipiente per lavare l'acqua" (cfr. Ar.
                                Av. 850 con commento). Una scena della Pace di Aristofane (960-961)
                                contiene una preziosa menzione del passaggio di una tale ciotola di
                                mano in mano durante i riti preliminari che precedono il sacrificio.
                                È possibile che Lisistrata alluda a tale lavaggio collettivo,
                                sottolineando l'unità del gruppo di partecipanti al rito.</p>
                            <p>È interessante notare, tuttavia, che nei dipinti su vaso il chernips è quasi sempre posto nelle mani di una persona più giovane, che lo consegna al sacrificatore principale, un uomo più anziano di status chiaramente superiore (van Straten 1995: fig. 30-36). Il luogo in questione si riferisce a un modo leggermente diverso di usare il chernips: βωμοὺς περιρραίνοντες: "spruzzare gli altari". Il verbo περιρραίνω qui usato, la cui sola base derivazionale: ῥαίνω esprime la semantica di "spruzzare", intensifica questo significato con il prefisso περι-, "da ogni dove". Evidentemente, quindi, ciò che si intende è un rituale preliminare che consiste in una pulizia simbolica dell'altare, probabilmente eseguita mentre l'altare viene percorso (in senso antiorario ἐπιδεξιά), con l'aiuto di una billetta o di un ramoscello immerso nel chernips. Più ampiamente su questo argomento: ad Ar. Pax 956-61; Av. 850, 958.Rispetto o mancanza di esso per il chernips come un segno di osservanza o di violazione delle norme rituali: Th. 4.97.3; S. O.T. 240; Lys. 6.52; D. 20.158 (citando dopo Henderson 1987: ad loc.; nel caso del primo luogo citato non sono sicuro che l'autore intendesse veramente chernips come figura; gli altri passi non sollevano le mie obiezioni).</p>
                            <p>1131-1132: Lisistrata afferma retoricamente che potrebbe nominare più santuari panellenici dei tre che elenca. Infatti, è difficile dimenticare Isthmia, Nemea, Delo, Eleusi, Dodon o anche Atene, che organizzando i giochi panatenaici, rivendicava il ruolo di centro del culto panellenico. Tanto più nel contesto della stessa dichiarazione dell'oratrice, la sua scelta dovrebbe apparire sconcertante. Mentre Olympia e Delfi, probabilmente i più famosi santuari dell'antichità, sembrano ovviamente degni di menzione, la menzione di Pylaia sembra insolita. Questo luogo, meglio conosciuto come Thermopylai è un istmo in posizione strategica, che fornisce un passaggio facilmente difendibile da mezzanotte alla Grecia centrale. Almeno dal periodo arcaico nelle sue vicinanze c'era un santuario di Demetra in Anthelia, la sede originale di un'organizzazione panellenica chiamata l'Anfiteatro di Pylaean, più tardi (dato che controllava anche Delfi) - l'Anfiteatro di Delfi. </p>
                            <p>Questa istituzione religiosa svolgeva un importante ruolo politico. Forse fu ispirato da questa istituzione che il primo luogo di resistenza contro Serse da parte dei Greci fu vicino alla sua sede durante la famosa battaglia delle Termopili (cfr. Stählin 1934). Dato il contesto, questo è probabilmente ciò a cui Aristofane si riferisce quando invita gli Ateniesi a riconciliarsi con gli Spartani e ad unire le forze contro i loro comuni nemici. Il riferimento all'ideologia formata durante le guerre persiane è una caratteristica tipica del suo programma politico.</p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>
            
            <div type="edition" xml:lang="en">
                <div type="textpart" n="intro"> 
                    <p>A comedy probably staged at Lenaeus in 411 BC. Its content refers to the very difficult military, economic and demographic situation of Athens after the defeat of the Sicilian expedition. When there were already many indications that the Peloponnesian war, which had been going on for twenty years, could only end in defeat, Aristophanes proposed a comedic vision of making peace not as a result of one of the sides giving up, but thanks to the mediation of women.</p>
                    <p> <emph>Plot Outline: </emph>Lysistrata convenes a secret meeting of women from various poleis in Athens to work out and swear together a plan to bring peace. The means to this end is to be a "bed strike", i.e. denying men sexual satisfaction as long as they wage war. At the same time, the older women capture the Acropolis with its treasury. The female part of the Attica community moves there. After a period of difficult struggle with their stereotyped nature, the women manage to bring about a reconciliation between Athens and Sparta. The comedy ends with a universal feast.</p>
                    <p> From the point of view of research on blood sacrifice, the text is interesting because of several short mentions of this ritual, and also because of the obverse scene, during which - instead of an animal - a vessel of wine is butchered.</p>
                    <p> The text is quoted from the Henderson (1987) edition.  </p>
                </div>
                <div type="textpart" n="commentary">
                    <div type="textpart" n="Lysistrata_78-84">
                        <head>Lysistrata 78-84</head>
                        <div type="textpart" n="78-84_intro">
                            <p>The secret meeting of wives is attended by the Spartan girl Lampito, characterized in the text in a stereotypical way. Unlike in Athens, Lacedemonian girls practiced physical exercises in the open air (one of the typical forms was the buttock-kicking dance mentioned by the heroine), so they were strong and tanned. </p>
                            <p>The passus is significant because of the comparison that appears in the issue of Lampito, who states that the Athenian girls examine her like a sacrificial animal.</p>
                            
                            <quote>
                                <lb/><emph>Λυσιστράτη</emph>
                                <lb/>ὦ φιλτάτη Λάκαινα χαῖρε Λαμπιτοῖ. 
                                <lb/>οἷον τὸ κάλλος γλυκυτάτη σου φαίνεται. 
                                <lb n="80"/>ὡς δ᾽ εὐχροεῖς, ὡς δὲ σφριγᾷ τὸ σῶμά σου. 
                                <lb/>κἂν ταῦρον ἄγχοις.
                                <lb/><emph>Λαμπιτώ</emph>
                                <lb/>μάλα γ᾽ οἰῶ ναὶ τὼ σιώ:
                                <lb/>γυμνάδδομαι γὰρ καὶ ποτὶ πυγὰν ἅλλομαι.
                                <lb/><emph>Καλονίκη</emph>
                                <lb/>ὡς δὴ καλὸν τὸ χρῆμα τιτθίων ἔχεις. 
                                <lb/><emph>Λαμπιτώ</emph>
                                <lb/>ᾇπερ ἱερεῖόν τοί μ᾽ ὑποψαλάσσετε. 
                            </quote>
                            
                            <quote><emph>Tr.:</emph> LYSISTRATA:
                                Lampito, dear Spartan, welcome! How shines, my sweet, your beauty! How healthy and firm your body! You could strangle a bull!
                                LAMPITO:
                                How about the Dioscurs?   I end up practicing and doing butt-kicking dances.
                                CALONIKE:
                                What amazing breasts you have!
                                LA.: You're macing me like a sacrificial animal!
                            </quote>
                        </div>
                        <div type="textpart" n="commentary">
                            <p> ὑποψαλάσσετε - 'you groping'; the verb ὑπο-ψαλάσσω is admittedly a hapax legomenon, but its structure and context of use here make it possible to understand what it refers to. The form without the prefix (ψαλάσσω) means to touch something, such as the strings of an instrument while playing. The prefix ὑπο may have soothing overtones or refer to the spatial category 'below'. Both meanings in this context make good sense: "you macerate me gently [tickle?]" or "you macerate me from below". This second aspect of meaning may have been interestingly reflected in the performative layer of the work. Aristophanes certainly made full use of the comic effect of the ambiguous play, in which a man (actor) dressed as a woman gropes another man, wearing hyperbolic attributes of femininity. Of course, this layer of the work remains completely inaccessible to us.</p>                  
                            <p> Modern commentators on the passus (Sommerstein 1990: ad loc. , Henderson 1987: ad loc. ) explain the comparison by pointing to passus that refer to sacrificing an animal when it is fat enough to provide good meat for the feast (Ar. Eq. 1135–
                                -1140; Philem. Fr. 155). The scholiasta (ad loc. ) interpreted the place in a similar way: τὰ γὰρ ἱερεῖα μέλλοντες θύειν ψηλαφῶσιν, εἰ λιπαρά ἐστι ("for the animals that were to be sacrificed were groped to see if they were fat"). Regardless of these practical and perhaps even hedonistic motives, the necessity of subjecting an animal to inspection was dictated by purely religious factors (for more on this see Feyel 2006; ad Ar. Ach. 784).</p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <div type="textpart" n="Lysistrata_177-179">
                        <head>Lysistrata 177-179</head>
                        <div type="textpart" n="177-179">
                            <p>As part of Lysistrata's comical plan, the younger women are to influence their husbands by striking in their bedrooms. The older ones, who cannot play such a role, were given the task of controlling the strategic position on the Acropolis. The passus does not contain any absolutely clear information about the blood sacrifice, however there is a valuable suggestion in it. Namely, something obvious for Athenians must have been the presence of elderly women on the Acropolis in the early morning hours (when the The action of the work), related to cultic activity. </p>
                            <p>The word θύειν used in the text may mean making a blood sacrifice or another form of worship. It is not clear whether the passus refers to any particular cultic activities performed by old women on the Acropolis. It is possible that we are dealing here with a stereotype (probably justified by the Athenian reality), according to which old women are a social group particularly prone to devotion. In this case, the passage could refer to spontaneous, self-initiated sacrifices made by old women. </p>
                            <quote>
                                <lb/><emph>Λυσιστράτη</emph>
                                <lb/> Ταῖς πρεσβυτάταις γὰρ προστέτακται τοῦτο δρᾶν,  
                                <lb/> ἕως ἂν ἡμεῖς ταῦτα συντιθώμεθα,
                                <lb/> θύειν δοκούσαις καταλαβεῖν τὴν ἀκρόπολιν.    
                            </quote>
                            
                            <quote><emph>Tr.: </emph>LYSISTRATA:  It fell to the older women to go and occupy the Acropolis while we are dating here, under the guise of making offerings.
                            </quote>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <div type="textpart" n="Lysistrata_181-239">
                        <head>Lisistrata 181-239</head>
                        <div type="textpart" n="181-239">
                            <p>The passus contains a comical oath scene. Unlike the paragmatic ritual of the thysia type, the sacrifice, which was usually crowned with a joyful feast, the oath ceremony was rather gloomy, as there were still present terrible sanctions for failure to keep the obligations. The slaughtered animal was not eaten. The scene in Aristophanes contains contrasting elements; seriousness gives way here to clownishness. </p>
                            <p>The women, instead of slaughtering the animal, open the jug and instead of blood the wine flows, alluding to the comedic stereotype that Athenian women were fond of the drink, which they drank unmixed with water in secret from their husbands.</p>
                            <quote>
                                <lb/><emph>Λυσιστράτη</emph>
                                <lb/>τί δῆτα ταῦτ᾽ οὐχ ὡς τάχιστ᾽ ὦ Λαμπιτοῖ 
                                <lb/>ξυνωμόσαμεν, ὅπως ἂν ἀρρήκτως ἔχῃ; 
                                <lb/><emph>Λαμπιτώ</emph>
                                <lb/>πάρφαινε μὰν τὸν ὅρκον, ὡς ὀμιόμεθα. 
                                <lb/><emph>Λυσιστράτη</emph>
                                <lb/>καλῶς λέγεις. ποῦ 'σθ᾽ ἡ Σκύθαινα; ποῖ βλέπεις; 
                                <lb n="185"/>θὲς ἐς τὸ πρόσθεν ὑπτίαν τὴν ἀσπίδα, 
                                <lb/>καί μοι δότω τὰ τόμιά τις. 
                                <lb/><emph>Καλονίκη</emph>
                                <lb/>Λυσιστράτη
                                <lb/>τίν᾽ ὅρκον ὁρκώσεις ποθ᾽ ἡμᾶς; 
                                <lb/><emph>Λυσιστράτη</emph> 
                                <lb/>ὅντινα;
                                <lb/>εἰς ἀσπίδ᾽, ὥσπερ φάσ᾽ ἐν Αἰσχύλῳ ποτέ,
                                <lb/>μηλοσφαγούσας.  
                                <lb/><emph>Καλονίκη</emph>      
                                <lb/>μὴ σύ γ᾽ ὦ Λυσιστράτη
                                <lb n="190"/>εἰς ἀσπίδ᾽ ὀμόσῃς μηδὲν εἰρήνης πέρι.
                                <lb/><emph>Λυσιστράτη</emph>
                                <lb/>τίς ἂν οὖν γένοιτ᾽ ἂν ὅρκος; 
                                <lb/><emph>Καλονίκη</emph>
                                <lb/>εἰ λευκόν ποθεν
                                <lb/>ἵππον λαβοῦσαι τόμιον ἐντεμοίμεθα.
                                <lb/><emph>Λυσιστράτη</emph>
                                <lb/>ποῖ λευκὸν ἵππον; 
                                <lb/><emph>Καλονίκη</emph>
                                <lb/>ἀλλὰ πῶς ὀμούμεθα
                                <lb/>ἡμεῖς;
                                <lb/><emph>Λυσιστράτη</emph>
                                <lb/>ἐγώ σοι νὴ Δί᾽, ἢν βούλῃ, φράσω.
                                <lb n="195"/>θεῖσαι μέλαιναν κύλικα μεγάλην ὑπτίαν,
                                <lb/>μηλοσφαγοῦσαι Θάσιον οἴνου σταμνίον
                                <lb/>ὀμόσωμεν ἐς τὴν κύλικα μὴ 'πιχεῖν ὕδωρ.
                                <lb/><emph>Λαμπιτώ</emph>
                                <lb/>φεῦ δᾶ τὸν ὅρκον ἄφατον ὡς ἐπαινίω. 
                                <lb/><emph>Λυσιστράτη</emph>
                                <lb/>φερέτω κύλικά τις ἔνδοθεν καὶ σταμνίον. 
                                <lb/><emph>Μυρρίνη</emph>
                                <lb/>ὦ φίλταται γυναῖκες, <add>ὁ</add> κεραμεὼν ὅσος. 
                                <lb/><emph>Καλονίκη</emph>
                                <lb/>ταύτην μὲν ἄν τις εὐθὺς ἡσθείη λαβών. 
                                <lb/><emph>Λυσιστράτη</emph>
                                <lb/>καταθεῖσα ταύτην προσλαβοῦ μοι τοῦ κάπρου. 
                                <lb/>δέσποινα Πειθοῖ καὶ κύλιξ φιλοτησία, 
                                <lb/>τὰ σφάγια δέξαι ταῖς γυναιξὶν εὐμενής. 
                                <lb/><emph>Καλονίκη</emph>
                                <lb/>εὔχρων γε θαἶμα κἀποπυτίζει καλῶς. 
                                <lb/><emph>Λαμπιτώ</emph>
                                <lb/>καὶ μὰν ποτόδδει γ᾽ ἁδὺ ναὶ τὸν Κάστορα. 
                                <lb/><emph>Μυρρίνη</emph>
                                <lb/>ἐᾶτε πρώτην μ᾽ ὦ γυναῖκες ὀμνύναι. 
                                <lb/><emph>Καλονίκη</emph>
                                <lb/>μὰ τὴν Ἀφροδίτην οὔκ, ἐάν γε μὴ λάχῃς. 
                                <lb/><emph>Λυσιστράτη</emph>
                                <lb/>λάζυσθε πᾶσαι τῆς κύλικος ὦ Λαμπιτοῖ: 
                                <lb n="210"/>λεγέτω δ᾽ ὑπὲρ ὑμῶν μί᾽ ἅπερ ἂν κἀγὼ λέγω:
                                <lb/>ὑμεῖς δ᾽ ἐπομεῖσθε ταὐτὰ κἀμπεδώσετε. 
                                <lb/>οὐκ ἔστιν οὐδεὶς οὔτε μοιχὸς οὔτ᾽ ἀνήρ—   
                                <lb/><emph>Καλονίκη</emph>
                                <lb/>οὐκ ἔστιν οὐδεὶς οὔτε μοιχὸς οὔτ᾽ ἀνήρ— 
                                <lb/>[...]
                                <lb/><emph>Λυσιστράτη</emph>
                                <lb/>ταῦτ᾽ ἐμπεδοῦσα μὲν πίοιμ᾽ ἐντευθενί: 
                                <lb/><emph>Καλονίκη</emph>
                                <lb/>ταῦτ᾽ ἐμπεδοῦσα μὲν πίοιμ᾽ ἐντευθενί: 
                                <lb/><emph>Λυσιστράτη</emph>
                                <lb/>εἰ δὲ παραβαίην, ὕδατος ἐμπλῇθ᾽ ἡ κύλιξ. 
                                <lb/><emph>Καλονίκη</emph>
                                <lb/>εἰ δὲ παραβαίην, ὕδατος ἐμπλῇθ᾽ ἡ κύλιξ. 
                                <lb/><emph>Λυσιστράτη</emph>
                                <lb/>συνεπόμνυθ᾽ ὑμεῖς ταῦτα πᾶσαι; 
                                <lb/><emph>Πᾶσαι</emph>
                                <lb/>νὴ Δία.
                                <lb/><emph>Λυσιστράτη</emph>
                                <lb/>φέρ᾽ ἐγὼ καθαγίσω τήνδε. 
                                <lb/><emph>Καλονίκη</emph>
                                <lb/>τὸ μέρος γ᾽ ὦ φίλη,
                                <lb/>ὅπως ἂν ὦμεν εὐθὺς ἀλλήλων φίλαι.
                            </quote>
                            <quote><emph>Tr.:</emph> 
                                LYSISTRATA:
                                Why then, Lampito, do we not take an oath at once to make the arrangement indissoluble?
                                LAMPITO:
                                So present her words so we can swear.
                                LY..: Right. Where's Scythian? What are you looking at? [185] Give this tarpart concave side up. Let someone pass the sliced offering.
                                CALONIKE:
                                Lysistrato, what oath you want,
                                would we bond?
                                LY.:Which one? Such as Aeschylus is said to have once fated, slaughtering a sheep over a shield.
                                KA.:Just [190] not over the shield,
                                since this is about peace.
                                LY.: Then what should we swear to?
                                KA.:Why don't we get a white cat from somewhere, cut it into pieces and swear over it?
                                LY..: Where did the white horse come from?
                                KA.:Then how do we swear?
                                LY.: If you will, I will tell you, by Zeus. [195] Take a large black spell and set it to butcher a jug of wine from Thasos, and swear never to pour water into that spell.
                                LA.: Verily, I commend this extraordinary kind of oath. LY.: Then let someone bring a spell and a pitcher.
                                MYRRINE:
                                [200] Dear women, such a big jug!
                                KA.: Just take this spell in your hands to experience pleasure.
                                LY..: Put her down and hold the boar. O Peitho, ruler, and you, sorceress of friendship, accept this offering, O benevolent woman.
                                KA.: [205] Beautiful is the color of this blood, and it gushes forth magnificently. LA.: And, by Kastor, it smells delightful.
                                WE..: Let me be the first to swear.
                                KA: On Aphrodite, no way, unless you pull a fate.
                                LY.: Lampito, catch all the spell. [210] Let one in the name of all repeat after me, and let the others approve it with an oath. "No lover or husband....
                                KA.: "No lover or husband...
                                [...]
                                LY..: [233] ...if I keep this, may I drink from it....
                                KA.: ...if I keep this, let me drink from it...
                                LY..: [235] ...and if I do not keep the faith, let the cup be filled with water.
                                KA..:	and if I do not keep the faith, let the cup be filled with water.
                                LY..: You all swear. WOMAN:
                                By Zeus! LY.: I will now perform an act of sacrifice.
                                KA.:Just a little, my dear,
                                so we could be friends right away.
                            </quote>
                        </div>
                        <div type="textpart" n="commentary">
                            <p>The oath-related sacrifice is a category of concern from a typological point of view. It seems that in the "emic" view, it was something entirely different from thysia, as evidenced by Perhaps the very vocabulary used in the passage. </p>
                            <p>   The noun τὰ σφάγια appears here as a synonym, denoting bloody sacrifices, which are not eaten. The action performed by the heroine, or one of the actions, is in turn denoted by the verb καθαγίζω, 'to ritually destroy'. This suggests that we are dealing with a ritual whose primary goal is not to win over friendly forces, but to drive away hostile ones (Parker 2011: 141 - the opposition between conjunctive and disjunctive sacrifices is a variant of the more established in scholarship division into olimpic and chthonic sacrifices, cf. Scullion 1994). In spite of these lexical indications, the passus in question contains quite a few data suggesting that the distinction between types of rituals was not strict enough. </p> 
                            <p>     The structure of the ritual, visible under the layer of comic distortion, is analogous to that in thysia: the heroines bring in the "animal" and a prayer follows (203-204). It is worth noting that it contains a request to the goddess to accept the sacrifice (τὰ σφάγια δέξαι). The addressee herself is described as ταῖς γυναιξὶν εὐμενής ('benevolent to women'), which is a typical rhetorical device in prayer, involving the identification of a deity with an epithet containing a projection of his desired relationship with the worshipper. The place suggests that the sacrifice (τὰ σφάγια) may be treated as the equivalent of a gift, something the giving of which, on the one hand, and the receiving of which, on the other, opens up a type of benevolent relationship. What is characteristic of sphagia-type rites, the accent falls on "blood." In the case of thysia, it would flow into the sphageion bowl, a small part of it would be used to anoint the altar, and the rest would be used for offal (Ekroth 2005). In the ritual under discussion, the blood was collected into a vessel (the choice of which clearly had symbolic significance) to be used in some way. The comic distortion and vagueness of the text without dideliquaries make it difficult to say what actually happened on stage at that place and what kind of behaviour it corresponded to in the ritual reality. However, it seems characteristic that the end of the ritual is connected here with the pleasure of feasting together, similarly to Thysia, where the slaughter was crowned with tasting the roasted entrails. The feast associations are perhaps not so much the result of a comic distortion as a sign of the times.</p>
                            <p> Indeed, it is clear from Pausanias (5.24.10-11) that while there was a custom among Homeric heroes to discard the entire carcass of animals (cf. Il. 19.266-8) over which they swore, his contemporaries (2nd century AD) did not always, if ever, observe this injunction. As Parker (2011: 157-158; 1996: 105; Stengel 1920: 137-138) notes, change (if one can indeed speak of change, treating Homera as a source authoritatively reflecting social reality) may have occurred very early on. It is known that already in the classical period the flesh of an animal over which an oath was taken during Apaturia was eaten (for an extensive source base see: Parker 1996: 105). More on oaths: Sommerstein, Bayliss (2013) and Sommerstein, Torrance (2014).</p>
                            <p>184: ἡ Σκύθαινα - "Scythian"; in Athens the troops of order were recruited from among the Scythians, who wore a characteristic foreign dress. Their image in the comedy indicates the existence of negative stereo-types about them. The presence of a female counterpart of Scythia in the scene paradoxically indicates that the scene is a parody of a typical Athenian ritual performed in public, assisted by a guardian of order.</p>
                            <p>186/192: τὰ τόμια - sliced sacrifice / τόμιον ἐντεμοίμεθα - "we will cut into pieces"; the practice of a person taking an oath by standing on or touching something described as τόμια is well attested (e.g. D. 23.68; Arist. Ath. 55.5; Antipho 5.12; Aesch. 1.114; Lycurg. 1.20). The context, the etymology of the phrase, as well as the formula τόμιον ἐντεμοίμεθα (cf. Aesch. 2.87: τἐμνοντα τὰ τόμια) leave no doubt that what is meant is parts of an animal cut off, excised or chopped (the Homeric formula, e.g. in Il. in Il. 2.124 ὅρκια πιστὰ ταμόντες - "having cut = having made an inviolable covenant"). The details unfortunately remain a matter of conjecture. Stengel (1910: 80-85), Stengel (1920: 137), cf. Bur-kert (2011: 378), Burkert (1985: 251), Burkert (1983: 36) has expressed a bold conjecture that it may be about nuclei (cut off), but as Faraone (1993: 68) notes, there are no strong indications to support this, that it was not viscera (cut and sliced σπλάγχνα) or cut meat (cf. Ekroth 2014: 164-165; Casabona 1966: 220-225). It is also possible that the type of objects which were used as τόμια varied and depended on factors which are elusive for us (apart from chronology and geography, the content of oaths, their public or private character, etc.). </p>  
                            <p>>185-90: the verses contain an explicative reference to a place in Aeschylus' Seven against Thebes (42-48; words of the scout): ἄνδρες γὰρ ἑπτά, θούριοι λοχαγέται, / ταυροσφαγοῦντες ἐς μελάνδετον σάκος / καὶ θιγγάνοντες χερσὶ ταυρείου φόνου, / Ἄρη τ', ᾿Ενυώ, καὶ φιλαίματον Φόβον / ὡρκωμότησαν ἢ πόλει κατασκαφὰς / θέντες λαπάξειν ἄστυ Καδμείων βίαι, / ἢ γῆν θανόντες τήνδε φυράσειν φόνωι ("For, behold, seven men, bold commanders,/ slaughtered a bull, collecting the blood into a shield with black edges/ and with their hands they touched the bull's blood,/ on Ares, Enyo and Grosha, greedy for blood/ they took an oath that either they would bring destruction to the city/ and destroy it by force, / or dying, they would mix their own blood with this land" - transl. K. Bielawski). Obviously, this suggestive image should be approached with equal caution as the Aristophanic grotesque. For these words refer to the behavior of hyperbolic violators from the mythical past. It is worth noting, however, that the existence of such a ritual practice is largely confirmed by Xenophon (An. 2.2.9), who describes how three animals (a bull, a boar and a ram) were slaughtered, their blood was collected in a shield, after which the Greeks and their allies dipped their swords and spears in it and swore an alliance. It seems significant that Aeschylus emphasises the symbolic connection between shed animal blood and human blood. It is present in the nickname of the personification Phobos - the noun, treated as the name of a deity, defines "panic-stricken fear". In the framework of the war technique of Aeschylus' times, this very phenomenon led to breaking formation, disorderly flight and the slaughter of warriors. The blood mentioned here is also that of the seven chiefs who swear to die if they do not capture the city. Thus, the poet clearly treats the act of violence against the animal as a representation of what is the object of the bohater's promise: to perform an act of violence. It should not in such a contextIt is surprising that <persName type="literary" key="Lysistrata">Lysistrata</persName>'s idea to repeat the gesture known from Aeschylus is met with violent rejection. Aristophanes' women are concerned with peace, so the entire ritual, rather than blood as a material representation of the object of the oath, will invoke wine, a liquid that gives pleasure to the stereotypical Athenian woman and which was probably quite commonly associated with peace (cf. Ar. Pax: sparsim; E. Ba 417-433; Il. 6.264-268)</p>
                            <p>189: μηλοσφαγούσας -'butchering a sheep'; in Aeschylus (Th. 186) the word ταυροσφαγοῦντες appears, 'butchering a bull', as one should infer from the structure of the compositum and from the fact that in the following verse bull's blood is mentioned. It should be noted, however, that in Aristophanes' time, although the structure of these two compounds was still obvious, they clearly lost their original meaning ("to slaughter a sheep/ bull") in favour of a more general one: "to slaughter any animal". (cf. schol. ad loc. ). It is hard to resist the impression that the poet wanted to make a joke here, replacing the word associated with a more prestigious victim with one that refers to a more common one. Such an interpretation, however, seems overly subtle, as it would require the audience to memorize Aeschylus' text very precisely. From a syntactic point of view, it is interesting to note the behaviour of the verb μηλο-/ ταυρο-σφαγέω, which in the places discussed occurs with the circumstance εἰς ἀσπίδα / ἐς σάκος, 'to tarif' (where two different nouns name two types of shields). The point, of course, is that the blood from the butchered animal, which is the prosessential object of interest during the ritual, is to flow into such an improvised vessel.</p>
                            <p>191-2: λευκὸν ἵππον -"a white horse"; the place unclear. Scholiasta sees here either an obscene joke or an allusion to the customs of the Amazons, who, he writes, sacrificed white horses (λευκοὺς ἵππους ἔθυον). The first of these hypotheses, as usual with Aristophanes' text, seems attractive. Since we do not know what happened on the stage, it cannot be ruled out that the wit contained here was not only piquant but also perfectly readable,   thanks to the gesture accompanying the words. </p>
                            <p>On the other hand, the fact that Scholiast gives an alternative variant of the explanation indicates that he himself did not have sufficient data concerning the performative layer to state anything certain about the content of the passus. The second interpretation he gives seems all the more unconvincing because nothing is known from other sources about the sacrifices allegedly made by the Amazons. Herodotus (7.113) mentions the ritual killing of white horses by Persian magi, and Lukian (Scyth. 3) mentions sacrificing them on the grave of a Scythian herosa. These two passages connect themselves with the customs of the Amazons at best indirectly. They also do not contain anything that would be obviously associated with the place in question in Aristophanes. Since the passus was obviously intended to evoke laughter, one can suspect that the allusion contained in it was well readable, and therefore referred to something well known to the audience. Presumably, therefore, the scholiast's speculative explanations only distance us from grasping the essence of the joke, which could have been about something very topical at the time the play was performed. It is with a similar distance that we should consider the proposal of Fletcher (2012: 228), who pointed to the oath taken by Helen's suitors as a parallel. In this ritual, according to Pausanias (3.20.9), a tom of a horse (we do not know what breed) was used, but it is difficult to say whether this tradition was known to Aristophanes' audience.</p>
                            <p>196: μηλοσφαγοῦσαι Θάσιον οἴνου σταμνίον -'to butcher a jug of wine from Thasos'. Lysistrata (here and consistently further on) uses the technical language of blood sacrifice, applying it to actions that are not sacrifices (μηλοσφαγέω - cf. 189). They are also not libations sensu stricto (as Henderson 1987: ad loc.), because wine is not poured on the ground here, but into a vessel. Wine from Thasos was famous for its quality, so clearly, as usual in comedy, the hedonistic dimension of the parodied ritual comes to the fore. The sacrifice of a vessel of wine also in: Ar. Th. 686-762.</p>
                            <p>202: προσλαβοῦ μοι τοῦ κάπρου - 'hold the boar'. Henderson (1987: ad loc. ), in his commentary on the passus, points out that laying hands on the animal before butchering it had important symbolic significance. I suppose that this is just a misunderstanding, because the scholar refers to the passus (cit. ad 185-190) from Aeschylus (Th. 42), which speaks of immersing hands in blood already after the slaughter, and to the place in Stengel (1920: 136), where it is about cutting off strands of hair from the victims (in Iliad 3.273-274) and handing them over to the leaders of the Achaeans and Trojans. This last gesture (cf. Eustathius: ad loc.) clearly had a meaning analogous to giving the oath-takers entrails or pieces of the slaughtered animal and probably had nothing to do with putting hands on it before killing it. For this reason, it can be assumed that the expression given by Lysistrata in the discussed passages imitates the behaviour connected with the sacrificial routine of a purely pragmatic character and is devoid of deep symbolism. Because the heroines were so preoccupied with the chalice, the leader had to call them to order, ordering them to help hold the animal, while she herself (apparently) intended to strike a blow. Why the text refers to a boar (κάπρος) remains a matter of debate. Although commentators (Henderson 1987: ad loc.; Sommerstein 1990 ad loc.) suggest that it may be influenced by an analogous scene in the Iliad (19.249-268), in which Agamemnon slaughters such an animal, it is difficult to say why this place should be more significant than, for example, a passus from book III of the Iliad (271-323), in which the hero slaughters two sheep. Since the available data do not indicate that the pigs are particularly connected with the context of the story, perhaps we should suppose some kind of wordplay here. Scholiast (ad loc. ) notes that the word for boar is used here by Aristophanes in the sense of 'genitalia', which seems to be an attractive suggestion, unfortunately not confirmed by the lexical material. Of course, instead of a boar, the heroines "butcher" a jug of wine.</p>
                            <p>203-204: a very short prayer containing an invocation to two goddesses (one of whom is purely a comic personification), a request to accept an offering (in the singular, but I think both goddesses). The epithet reveals that the aim of the ritual is to win over immortals (this time, however, it probably refers only to the second goddess mentioned).</p>
                            <p>205: εὔχρων γε θαἶμα κἀποπυτίζει καλῶς -"beautiful is the colour of this blood and it gushes forth magnificently". Another in a series of jokes based on double-meaning: wine/blood. Scholia (ad loc.) contain an explanation that the bohater here imitates a soothsayer or priest (θυοσκόος). This leads us to suppose that the stream of blood was subjected to a reading in order to obtain signs. Even if there was no sophisticated system of semiosis of the petechiae, it would actually be strange if the basic category of binary opposition did not function: "right/wrong". The place in Peace (1054-1055) points to the appropriateness in such a context of the adverb καλῶς.</p>
                            <p>207: ἐᾶτε πρώτην μ', ὦ γυναῖκες, ὀμνύναι - "let me be the first to swear"; the heroine obviously cannot wait her turn at the cup. Under the layer of a joke one can discern a ritualistic practice: the oath requires physical contact with the slaughtered animal, its pieces or blood.</p>
                            <p>235-236: εἰ δὲ παραβαίην, ὕδατος ἐμπλῆιθ' ἡ κύλιξ - "and if I do not keep the faith, let the cup be filled with water". Texts of oaths usually contain an explicitely expressed sanction. Characteristically, the Greek material indicates that it was most often connected with the object on which the oath was taken. Faraone (1993), with all the distance he retains from Frazer's concept, probably rightly defines such behaviour as a kind of sympathetic magic, in which - conditionally, because in the situation of breaking the word - the swearer brings upon himself the fate that meets something else - a slaughtered and cut animal, spilled blood or wine, melted wax (e.g. : Il. 3.292-301; Paroemioraphi Graeci 126 (Gaisford); SEG IX 4; cf. Fletcher 2012: 214, 230). The description of the oath from Aeschylus' Seven against Thebes (42-48), quoted above (ad 185-9), fits perfectly into this schema.</p>
                            <p>238: ἐγὼ καθαγίσω τήνδε - "I will perform an act of sacrifice"; the verb καθαγίζω denotes the act of offering something by complete destruction, usually by fire (cf. Ar. Av. 566). In the place under discussion, however, it is clearly a matter of 'destroying' wine in a way that is pleasant for the person who destroys it, that is, drinking it. Clearly, then, what was in the centre of interest of those who used the term was not the use of fire, but the fact of annihilating an object, or, as Svenbro (2005) probably rightly points out, removing it from the human sphere and in an altered form (e.g. smoke) transferring it to supernatural beings. Considering the function of the object on which one has sworn, with whose fate one has identified the fate of the crossswearer (cf. ad 235,6), at this point a brutal treatment of wine would be expected. This is perfectly underscored by the comical nature of the passus, in which Lysistrata clearly intends to drink greedily the entire contents of the great spell.</p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <div type="textpart" n="Lysistrata_1128–1134">
                        <head>Lysistrata 1128–1134</head>
                        <div type="textpart" n="1128-1134">
                            <p>Lysistrata expresses criticism of men from various Greek poleis involved in the Peloponnesian War. The passus is interesting because of the Panhellenic ideology it brings to the fore, whose invaluable reference point is the "stranger, the barbarian". Because of the mention of an army of potential external enemies, we can guess that if it was in any way specified which foreigners were meant, the source of the fear that led the Greeks to solidarity had to be above all Persia. In addition to external - real or imagined - threat, common sanctuaries were a unifying factor at the ideological level. In the quoted passages attention is focused on the gesture of washing hands. It is difficult to say whether this is merely a rhetorical figure.</p>
                            <p>Either way, it was clearly a very important moment in the ritual process.</p>
                            
                            <quote>
                                <lb/><emph>Λυσιστράτη</emph>
                                <lb/>λαβοῦσα δ᾽ ὑμᾶς λοιδορῆσαι βούλομαι
                                <lb/>κοινῇ δικαίως, οἳ μιᾶς ἐκ χέρνιβος
                                <lb n="1130"/>βωμοὺς περιρραίνοντες ὥσπερ ξυγγενεῖς
                                <lb/>Ὀλυμπίασιν, ἐν Πύλαις, Πυθοῖ （πόσους
                                <lb/>εἴποιμ᾽ ἂν ἄλλους, εἴ με μηκύνειν δέοι;）
                                <lb/>ἐχθρῶν παρόντων βαρβάρων στρατεύματι
                                <lb/>Ἕλληνας ἄνδρας καὶ πόλεις ἀπόλλυτε.
                            </quote>
                            
                            <quote>Since I have gathered you here, I wish to express a just criticism of all those who from one vessel [1130] spray water on the altars, like the brothers - in Olympia, Pylaia, Pytho.... how many more could I enumerate, if I were to speak longer? Though the barbarian army is so near, you destroy Greek cities and men.</quote>
                        </div>
                        <div type="textpart" n="commentary">
                            <p>1129: μιᾶς ἐκ χέρνιβος - 'from one vessel'; the noun χέρνιψ originally meant water for washing hands - before the sacrifice, as well as other activities such as a meal. In the place in question, Aristophanes uses the prepositional phrase ἐκ χέρνιβος ("from the chernips"), which may indicate that at the time it was also already being used in a metonymic sense: "a vessel for washing water" (cf. Ar. Av. 850 with commentary). A scene in the Peace of Aristophanes (960-961) contains a valuable mention of passing such a bowl from hand to hand during the preliminary rites preceding the sacrifice. It is possible that Lysistrata alludes to such a collective washing, emphasizing the unity of the group of participants in the ritual. Interestingly, however, in vase paintings chernips is almost always placed in the hands of a younger person, who hands it to the main sacrificer, an older man of clearly higher status (van Straten 1995: fig. 30-36). The place in question refers to a slightly different way of using chernips: βωμοὺς περιρραίνοντες: "spraying the altars". The verb περιρραίνω used here, whose derivational base alone: ῥαίνω expresses the semantics of 'to spray', intensifies this meaning with the prefix περι-, 'from everywhere'. Evidently, therefore, what is meant is a preliminary ritual consisting in a symbolic cleansing of the altar, probably performed while the altar is being walked around (counterclockwise ἐπιδεξιά), with the help of a billet or twig immersed in the chernips. More extensively on this subject: ad Ar. Pax 956-61; Av. 850, 958.</p>
                            <p>  A sign of observance or violation of ritual norms: Th. 4.97.3; S. O.T. 240; Lys. 6.52; D. 20.158 (quoting after Henderson 1987: ad loc.; in the case of the first mentioned place I am not sure that the author really meant chernips as a figure; the other passages do not raise my objections).</p>
                            <p>1131-1132:Lysistrata rhetorically asserts that she could name more Panhellenic sanctuaries than the three she lists. Indeed, it is difficult to forget Isthmia, Nemea, Delos, Eleusis, Dodon or even Athens, which by organizing the Panathenaic Games, claimed the role of the centre of the Panhellenic cult. All the more so in the context of the speaker's own declaration, her choice should seem puzzling. While Olympia and Delfy, probably the most famous sanctuaries of antiquity, seem obviously worthy of mention, the mention of Pylaia seems unusual. This place, better known as Thermopylai is a strategically located isthmus, providing an easily defensible passage from midnight to central Greece. At least from the archaic period in its vicinity there was a sanctuary of Demeter in Anthelia, the original seat of a pan-Hellenic organisation called the Pylaean Amphiction, later (as it controlled also Delphi) - the Delphic Amphiction. This religious institution played an important political role. Perhaps it was inspired by this institution that the first place of resistance against Xerxes by the Greeks was near its seat during the famous battle of Thermopylae (cf. Stählin 1934). Given the context, this is probably what Aristophanes refers to when he calls on the Athenians to reconcile with the Spartans and join forces against their common enemies. Referring to the ideology shaped during the Persian wars is a typical feature of his political programme.</p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>
            
            <div type="edition" xml:lang="pl">
                <div type="textpart" n="intro"> 
                    <p>Komedia wystawiona prawdopodobnie na Lenajach w 411 r. p.n.e. Jej treść nawiązuje do bardzo trudnej sytuacji militarnej, gospodarczej i demograficznej Aten po klęsce wyprawy sycylijskiej. Gdy już wiele wskazywało na to, że trwająca od dwudziestu lat wojna peloponeska może się skończyć wyłącznie klęską, Arystofanes zaproponował komediową wizję zawarcia pokoju nie wskutek ustąpienia jednej ze stron, ale dzięki mediacji kobiet.</p>
                    <p> Imię tytułowej bohaterki oznacza „rozwiązująca wojsko” (stąd koncepcje spolszczenia S. Srebrnego: Bojomira i E. Cięglewicza Gromiwoja). Być może nawiązuje ono do imienia pełniącej wówczas swój urząd kapłanki Ateny Polias, Lisymache (Lewis 1955) – to oznaczałoby, że protagonistka jest osobą w sposób szczególny związaną z rytuałem ofiary zwierzęcej. Z punktu widzenia badań nad tym rytuałem nie ma to jednak szczególnego znaczenia, pomijając może godny zaznaczenia fakt, że sprawowanie funkcji kultowej zapewniało kobiecie wyjątkowo wysoką pozycję, właśnie taką, jaką komediowa Lizystrata rzeczywiście zdaje się cieszyć.</p>
                    <p> <emph>Zarys fabuły:</emph> Lizystrata zwołuje w Atenach tajne zebranie kobiet z różnych poleis, by wspólnie z nimi dopracować i zaprzysiąc plan przywrócenia pokoju. Środkiem do tego celu ma być „strajk łóżkowy”, czyli odmawianie mężczyznom satysfakcji seksualnej tak długo, jak długo będą oni prowadzić wojnę. Jednocześnie starsze kobiety opanowują Akropol wraz ze skarbcem. Tam przenosi się żeńska część społeczności Attyki. Po okresie trudnych dla wszystkich zmagań ze swoją stereotypowo wyobrażoną naturą, kobietom udaje się doprowadzić do pojednania Aten ze Spartą. Komedia kończy się powszechnym świętem.
                        Z punktu widzenia badań nad ofiarą krwawą tekst jest interesujący ze względu na kilka krótkich wzmianek o tym rytuale, a także na obszerną scenę przysięgi, w czasie której – zamiast zwierzęcia – zarżnięte zostaje naczynie wina.
                    </p>
                    <p> Tekst cytuję za wydaniem Henderson (1987).</p>
                </div>
                <div type="textpart" n="commentary">
                    <div type="textpart" n="Lysistrata_78-84">
                        <head>Lysistrata 78-84</head>
                        <div type="textpart" n="78-84_intro">
                            <p>                   Na tajne zebranie żon przybywa Spartanka Lampito, scharakteryzowana w tekście w sposób stereotypowy. Inaczej niż w Atenach, dziewczęta lacedemońskie uprawiały ćwiczenia fizyczne na świeżym powietrzu (jedną z typowych form był wspomniany przez bohaterkę taniec z kopaniem pośladków), były więc silne i opalone. Passus jest istotny ze względu na porównanie pojawiające się w kwestii Lampito, która stwierdza, że Atenki badają ją jak zwierzę ofiarne.</p>                 
                            <quote>
                                <lb/><emph>Λυσιστράτη</emph>
                                <lb/>ὦ φιλτάτη Λάκαινα χαῖρε Λαμπιτοῖ. 
                                <lb/>οἷον τὸ κάλλος γλυκυτάτη σου φαίνεται. 
                                <lb n="80"/>ὡς δ᾽ εὐχροεῖς, ὡς δὲ σφριγᾷ τὸ σῶμά σου. 
                                <lb/>κἂν ταῦρον ἄγχοις.
                                <lb/><emph>Λαμπιτώ</emph>
                                <lb/>μάλα γ᾽ οἰῶ ναὶ τὼ σιώ:
                                <lb/>γυμνάδδομαι γὰρ καὶ ποτὶ πυγὰν ἅλλομαι.
                                <lb/><emph>Καλονίκη</emph>
                                <lb/>ὡς δὴ καλὸν τὸ χρῆμα τιτθίων ἔχεις. 
                                <lb/><emph>Λαμπιτώ</emph>
                                <lb/>ᾇπερ ἱερεῖόν τοί μ᾽ ὑποψαλάσσετε. 
                            </quote>
                            
                            <quote><emph>Tr.:</emph> LYSISTRATA:
                                Lampito, kochana Spartanko, witaj! Jak lśni, moja słodka, twoje piękno! Jak zdrowe i jędrne masz ciało! Byka mogłabyś zadusić!
                                LAMPITO:
                                A jakże,   na   Dioskurów?   W końcu   ćwiczę i uprawiam tańce z kopaniem pośladków.
                                KALONIKE:
                                Jakie masz niesamowite piersi!
                                LA.: Macacie mnie jak zwierzę ofiarne!
                            </quote>
                        </div>
                        <div type="textpart" n="commentary">
                            <p> ὑποψαλάσσετε – „obmacujecie”; czasownik ὑπο-ψαλάσσω jest wprawdzie hapax legomenon, jednak jego struktura i kontekst użycia w tym miejscu pozwalają zrozumieć, do czego się odnosi. Forma bez prefiksu (ψαλάσσω) oznacza dotykanie czegoś, np. strun instrumentu w czasie gry. Przedrostek ὑπο może mieć wydźwięk łagodzący lub odwoływać się do kategorii przestrzennej „poniżej”. Oba znaczenia w tym kontekście mają niezły sens: „macacie mnie delikatnie [łaskoczecie?]” lub „macacie mnie od spodu”. Ten drugi aspekt znaczenia mógł znajdować ciekawe odzwierciedlenie w warstwie performatywnej dzieła. Arystofanes bowiem z pewnością wykorzystał w pełni efekt komiczny niejednoznacznej gry, w ramach której mężczyzna (aktor) przebrany za kobietę obmacuje innego mężczyznę, noszącego hiperboliczne atrybuty kobiecości. Rzecz jasna, ta warstwa dzieła pozostaje dla nas całkowicie niedostępna.</p>
                            <p>Współcześni komentatorzy passusu (Sommerstein 1990: ad loc., Henderson 1987: ad loc.) wyjaśniają porównanie, wskazując na passusy, w których mowa o składaniu zwierzęcia w ofierze w chwili, gdy jest ono na tyle tłuste, by zapewnić dobre mięso na ucztę (Ar. Eq. 1135––1140; Philem. fr. 155). </p>
                            <p>Podobnie zresztą zinterpretował miejsce scholiasta (ad loc.): τὰ γὰρ ἱερεῖα μέλλοντες θύειν ψηλαφῶσιν, εἰ λιπαρά ἐστι („bo zwierzęta, które miały zostać złożone w ofierze, obmacywano, by sprawdzić, czy są tłuste”). Niezależnie od tych praktycznych, a może wręcz hedonistycznych motywów, konieczność poddania zwierzęcia oględzinom dyktowały czynniki czysto religijne (szerzej na ten temat: Feyel 2006; ad Ar. Ach. 784).</p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <div type="textpart" n="Lysistrata_177-179">
                        <head>Lysistrata 177-179</head>
                        <div type="textpart" n="177-179">
                            <p>W ramach komicznego planu Lizystraty młodsze kobiety mają wywrzeć wpływ na swych mężów poprzez strajk w sypialniach. Starszym, które tego rodzaju roli nie mogą odegrać, przypadło w udziale opanowanie strategicznej pozycji na Akropolu. Passus nie zawiera żadnej całkowicie jasnej informacji na temat ofiary krwawej, jednak pojawia się w nim cenna sugestia. Mianowicie czymś oczywistym dla Ateńczyków musiała być obecność starszych kobiet na Akropolu we wczesnych godzinach porannych (kiedy rozgrywa się
                                akcja utworu), związana z działalnością kultową. </p>
                            <p>Użyte w tekście słowo θύειν może oznaczać składanie ofiary krwawej lub inną formę czci. Nie jest jasne, czy w passusie chodzi o jakieś konkretne czynności kultowe, których wykonawczyniami na Akropolu były stare kobiety. Niewykluczone, że mamy tu do czynienia ze stereotypowym ujęciem (znajdującym pewnie uzasadnienie w rzeczywistości ateńskiej), zgodnie z którym wiekowe kobiety stanowią grupę społeczną szczególnie skłonną do dewocji. W takim razie w passusie mogłoby chodzić o spontanicznie, z własnej inicjatywy podejmowane przez staruszki ofiary.
                            </p>
                            
                            <quote>
                                <lb/><emph>Λυσιστράτη</emph>
                                <lb/> Ταῖς πρεσβυτάταις γὰρ προστέτακται τοῦτο δρᾶν,  
                                <lb/> ἕως ἂν ἡμεῖς ταῦτα συντιθώμεθα,
                                <lb/> θύειν δοκούσαις καταλαβεῖν τὴν ἀκρόπολιν.    
                            </quote>
                            
                            <quote><emph>Tr.: </emph>LYSISTRATA:
                                Starszym kobietom przypadło w udziale, by w czasie gdy my tutaj się umawiamy, poszły zająć Akropol pod pozorem składania ofiar.
                            </quote>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <div type="textpart" n="Lysistrata_181-239">
                        <head>Lysistrata 181-239</head>
                        <div type="textpart" n="181-239">
                            <p>Passus zawiera komiczną scenę przysięgi. W odróżnieniu od paradygmatycznego rytuału typu thysia, ofiary, którą najczęściej wieńczyła radosna uczta, obrzęd przysięgi był raczej ponury, jako że wirtualnie wciąż obecne tu były straszliwe sankcje za niedotrzymanie zobowiązań. Zarzynanego zwierzęcia nie zjadano. Scena u Arystofanesa zawiera elementy kontrastowe; powaga ustępuje tu miejsca błazenadzie. Kobiety, zamiast zarżnąć zwierzę, otworzą bukłak, zamiast krwi popłynie wino, w nawiązaniu do komediowego stereotypu, zgodnie z którym Atenki lubowały się w trunku, który niezmieszany z wodą pijały w tajemnicy przed mężami.</p>
                            <quote>
                                <lb/><emph>Λυσιστράτη</emph>
                                <lb/>τί δῆτα ταῦτ᾽ οὐχ ὡς τάχιστ᾽ ὦ Λαμπιτοῖ 
                                <lb/>ξυνωμόσαμεν, ὅπως ἂν ἀρρήκτως ἔχῃ; 
                                <lb/><emph>Λαμπιτώ</emph>
                                <lb/>πάρφαινε μὰν τὸν ὅρκον, ὡς ὀμιόμεθα. 
                                <lb/><emph>Λυσιστράτη</emph>
                                <lb/>καλῶς λέγεις. ποῦ 'σθ᾽ ἡ Σκύθαινα; ποῖ βλέπεις; 
                                <lb n="185"/>θὲς ἐς τὸ πρόσθεν ὑπτίαν τὴν ἀσπίδα, 
                                <lb/>καί μοι δότω τὰ τόμιά τις. 
                                <lb/><emph>Καλονίκη</emph>
                                <lb/>Λυσιστράτη
                                <lb/>τίν᾽ ὅρκον ὁρκώσεις ποθ᾽ ἡμᾶς; 
                                <lb/><emph>Λυσιστράτη</emph> 
                                <lb/>ὅντινα;
                                <lb/>εἰς ἀσπίδ᾽, ὥσπερ φάσ᾽ ἐν Αἰσχύλῳ ποτέ,
                                <lb/>μηλοσφαγούσας.  
                                <lb/><emph>Καλονίκη</emph>      
                                <lb/>μὴ σύ γ᾽ ὦ Λυσιστράτη
                                <lb n="190"/>εἰς ἀσπίδ᾽ ὀμόσῃς μηδὲν εἰρήνης πέρι.
                                <lb/><emph>Λυσιστράτη</emph>
                                <lb/>τίς ἂν οὖν γένοιτ᾽ ἂν ὅρκος; 
                                <lb/><emph>Καλονίκη</emph>
                                <lb/>εἰ λευκόν ποθεν
                                <lb/>ἵππον λαβοῦσαι τόμιον ἐντεμοίμεθα.
                                <lb/><emph>Λυσιστράτη</emph>
                                <lb/>ποῖ λευκὸν ἵππον; 
                                <lb/><emph>Καλονίκη</emph>
                                <lb/>ἀλλὰ πῶς ὀμούμεθα
                                <lb/>ἡμεῖς;
                                <lb/><emph>Λυσιστράτη</emph>
                                <lb/>ἐγώ σοι νὴ Δί᾽, ἢν βούλῃ, φράσω.
                                <lb n="195"/>θεῖσαι μέλαιναν κύλικα μεγάλην ὑπτίαν,
                                <lb/>μηλοσφαγοῦσαι Θάσιον οἴνου σταμνίον
                                <lb/>ὀμόσωμεν ἐς τὴν κύλικα μὴ 'πιχεῖν ὕδωρ.
                                <lb/><emph>Λαμπιτώ</emph>
                                <lb/>φεῦ δᾶ τὸν ὅρκον ἄφατον ὡς ἐπαινίω. 
                                <lb/><emph>Λυσιστράτη</emph>
                                <lb/>φερέτω κύλικά τις ἔνδοθεν καὶ σταμνίον. 
                                <lb/><emph>Μυρρίνη</emph>
                                <lb/>ὦ φίλταται γυναῖκες, <add>ὁ</add> κεραμεὼν ὅσος. 
                                <lb/><emph>Καλονίκη</emph>
                                <lb/>ταύτην μὲν ἄν τις εὐθὺς ἡσθείη λαβών. 
                                <lb/><emph>Λυσιστράτη</emph>
                                <lb/>καταθεῖσα ταύτην προσλαβοῦ μοι τοῦ κάπρου. 
                                <lb/>δέσποινα Πειθοῖ καὶ κύλιξ φιλοτησία, 
                                <lb/>τὰ σφάγια δέξαι ταῖς γυναιξὶν εὐμενής. 
                                <lb/><emph>Καλονίκη</emph>
                                <lb/>εὔχρων γε θαἶμα κἀποπυτίζει καλῶς. 
                                <lb/><emph>Λαμπιτώ</emph>
                                <lb/>καὶ μὰν ποτόδδει γ᾽ ἁδὺ ναὶ τὸν Κάστορα. 
                                <lb/><emph>Μυρρίνη</emph>
                                <lb/>ἐᾶτε πρώτην μ᾽ ὦ γυναῖκες ὀμνύναι. 
                                <lb/><emph>Καλονίκη</emph>
                                <lb/>μὰ τὴν Ἀφροδίτην οὔκ, ἐάν γε μὴ λάχῃς. 
                                <lb/><emph>Λυσιστράτη</emph>
                                <lb/>λάζυσθε πᾶσαι τῆς κύλικος ὦ Λαμπιτοῖ: 
                                <lb n="210"/>λεγέτω δ᾽ ὑπὲρ ὑμῶν μί᾽ ἅπερ ἂν κἀγὼ λέγω:
                                <lb/>ὑμεῖς δ᾽ ἐπομεῖσθε ταὐτὰ κἀμπεδώσετε. 
                                <lb/>οὐκ ἔστιν οὐδεὶς οὔτε μοιχὸς οὔτ᾽ ἀνήρ—   
                                <lb/><emph>Καλονίκη</emph>
                                <lb/>οὐκ ἔστιν οὐδεὶς οὔτε μοιχὸς οὔτ᾽ ἀνήρ— 
                                <lb/>[...]
                                <lb/><emph>Λυσιστράτη</emph>
                                <lb/>ταῦτ᾽ ἐμπεδοῦσα μὲν πίοιμ᾽ ἐντευθενί: 
                                <lb/><emph>Καλονίκη</emph>
                                <lb/>ταῦτ᾽ ἐμπεδοῦσα μὲν πίοιμ᾽ ἐντευθενί: 
                                <lb/><emph>Λυσιστράτη</emph>
                                <lb/>εἰ δὲ παραβαίην, ὕδατος ἐμπλῇθ᾽ ἡ κύλιξ. 
                                <lb/><emph>Καλονίκη</emph>
                                <lb/>εἰ δὲ παραβαίην, ὕδατος ἐμπλῇθ᾽ ἡ κύλιξ. 
                                <lb/><emph>Λυσιστράτη</emph>
                                <lb/>συνεπόμνυθ᾽ ὑμεῖς ταῦτα πᾶσαι; 
                                <lb/><emph>Πᾶσαι</emph>
                                <lb/>νὴ Δία.
                                <lb/><emph>Λυσιστράτη</emph>
                                <lb/>φέρ᾽ ἐγὼ καθαγίσω τήνδε. 
                                <lb/><emph>Καλονίκη</emph>
                                <lb/>τὸ μέρος γ᾽ ὦ φίλη,
                                <lb/>ὅπως ἂν ὦμεν εὐθὺς ἀλλήλων φίλαι.
                            </quote>
                            <quote><emph>Tr.:</emph>LYSISTRATA:
                                Dlaczego zatem, Lampito, nie złożymy czym prędzej przysięgi, by układ stał się nierozerwalny?
                                LAMPITO:
                                Więc przedstaw jej słowa, żebyśmy mogły przysiąc.
                                LY.: Słusznie. Gdzie jest Scytyjka? Na co się gapisz? [185] Daj tę tarczę wklęsłą stroną do góry. Niech ktoś poda pokrojoną ofiarę.
                                KALONIKE:
                                Lysistrato, jaką przysięgą chcesz,
                                byśmy się związały?
                                LY.:		Jaką? Taką, jak podobno niegdyś Ajschylos, zarzynając owcę nad tarczą.
                                KA.:	Byle [190] nie nad tarczą,
                                skoro tu chodzi o pokój.
                                LY.: To na co mamy przysięgać?
                                KA.:		Może skądś weźmiemy białego konia, pokroimy na kawałki i nad nim przysięgniemy?
                                
                                
                                LY.: Skąd białego konia?
                                KA.:	To jak mamy przysięgać?
                                LY.: Jeśli chcecie, powiem wam, na Zeusa. [195] Wziąć należy wielką czarną czarę i ustawić ją, by zarżnąć dzban wina z Thasos, a przysięgniemy nigdy do tej czary nie wlewać wody.
                                LA.: Zaprawdę, pochwalam ten nadzwyczajny rodzaj przysięgi. LY.: Niech więc ktoś przyniesie czarę i dzban.
                                MYRRINE:
                                [200] Drogie kobiety, taki wielki dzban!
                                KA.: Wystarczy tę czarę wziąć do rąk, by zaznać rozkoszy.
                                LY.: Odłóż ją i przytrzymaj knura. O Peitho, władczyni i ty, czaro przyjaźni, przyjmij tę ofiarę, o życzliwa kobietom.
                                KA.: [205] Piękny ma kolor ta krew i tryska wspaniale. LA.: I, na Kastora, pachnie rozkosznie.
                                MY.: Pozwólcie, że ja jako pierwsza przysięgnę.
                                KA.: Na Afrodytę, nie ma mowy, chyba że wyciągniesz los.
                                LY.: Lampito, złapcie wszystkie czarę. [210] Niech jedna w imieniu wszystkich powtarza za mną, a pozostałe niech to zatwierdzą przysięgą. „Żaden kochanek ani mąż....
                                KA.: „Żaden kochanek ani mąż...
                                [...]
                                LY.: [233] ...jeśli tego dotrzymam, niech piję z tego...
                                KA.: ...jeśli tego dotrzymam, niech piję z tego...
                                LY.: [235] ...a jeśli nie dochowam wiary, niech czara wypełni się wodą.
                                KA.:	a jeśli nie dochowam wiary, niech czara wypełni się wodą.
                                LY.: Przysięgacie wszystkie. KOBIETY:
                                Na Zeusa! LY.: Teraz dokonam aktu poświęcenia.
                                KA.:	Tylko trochę, moja droga,
                                żebyśmy od razu mogły zostać przyjaciółkami.
                            </quote>
                        </div>
                        <div type="textpart" n="commentary">
                            <p>Ofiara związana z przysięgą stanowi kategorię niepokojącą z typologicznego punktu widzenia. Wygląda na to, że w ujęciu „emicznym”, była ona czymś całkowicie odmiennym niż thysia, o czym świadczyć
                                może samo użyte w passusie słownictwo. </p>
                            <p>Jako synonim pojawia się tu rzeczownik τὰ σφάγια, określający ofiary krwawe, których nie zjadano. Czynność dokonywaną przez bohaterkę, lub jedną z czynności, nazywa z kolei czasownik καθαγίζω, „rytualnie zniszczyć”. To sugeruje, że mamy do czynienia z rytuałem, którego zasadniczym celem nie jest zjednanie sobie przyjaznych sił, lecz odepchnięcie wrogich (Parker 2011: 141 – opozycja pomiędzy conjunctive i disjunctive sacrifices jest to wariant bardziej utrwalonego w nauce podziału na ofiary typu olimpijskiego i chtonicznego, cf. Scullion 1994). Pomimo tych leksykalnych przesłanek omawiany passus zawiera sporo danych przemawiających za tym, że rozgraniczenie pomiędzy typami rytuałów nie było doskonale ścisłe. Wyraźna pod warstwą komicznego zniekształcenia struktura obrzędu jest analogiczna do tej, która uwidaczniała się w thysia: bohaterki sprowadzają „zwierzę”, następuje modlitwa (203–204). Warto zaznaczyć, że zawiera ona prośbę do bogini o przyjęcie ofiary (τὰ σφάγια δέξαι). Sama adresatka określona jest jako ταῖς γυναιξὶν εὐμενής („życzliwa kobietom”), co stanowi typowy zabieg retoryczny w modlitwie, polegający na określaniu bóstwa przydomkiem zawierającym projekcję pożądanej relacji jego z wyznawcą. Miejsce sugeruje, że ofiara (τὰ σφάγια) może być traktowana jako odpowiednik daru, coś, czego przekazanie z jednej strony, a przyjęcie – z drugiej, otwiera typ życzliwej relacji. Co charakterystyczne dla rytów typu sphagia, akcent pada na „krew”. W przypadku thysia, spłynęłaby ona do misy typu sphageion, niewielką jej część wykorzystano by do pomazania ołtarza, a resztę przeznaczono na podroby (Ekroth 2005). W ramach omawianego rytuału krew zebrano do naczynia (którego wybór ewidentnie miał znaczenie symboliczne), by wykorzystać ją w jakiś sposób. Komiczne zniekształcenie i niejasność tekstu pozbawionego didaskaliów sprawiają, że trudno powiedzieć, co rzeczywiście stało się w tym miejscu na scenie i jakiemu zachowaniu odpowiadało to w rzeczywistości rytualnej. Charakterystyczne wydaje się jednak to, że zakończenie obrzędu wiąże się tu z przyjemnością wspólnego ucztowania, podobnie jak w przypadku thysia, gdzie ubój wieńczyło kosztowanie pieczonych wnętrzności. Skojarzenia biesiadne są być może nie tyle wynikiem komicznego zniekształcenia, ile znakiem czasu. Ze stwierdzenia
                                Pauzaniasza (5.24.10–11) wynika bowiem, że o ile wśród bohaterów homeryckich istniał zwyczaj wyrzucania całości zwłok zwierząt (cf. Il. 19.266–8), nad którymi przysięgano, o tyle jego współcześni (II w. n.e) nie zawsze, jeśli w ogóle kiedykolwiek, przestrzegali tego nakazu. Jak zauważa Parker (2011: 157–158; 1996: 105; Stengel 1920: 137–138), zmiana (jeśli rzeczywiście można mówić o zmianie, traktując Homera jako źródło miarodajnie oddające rzeczywistość społeczną) mogła się dokonać bardzo wcześnie. Wiadomo bowiem, że już w okresie klasycznym zjadano mięso zwierzęcia, nad którym składano przysięgę w czasie Apaturii (obszerna baza źródłowa w: Parker 1996: 105). Szerzej na temat przysiąg: Sommerstein, Bayliss (2013) i Sommerstein, Torrance (2014).
                            </p>
                            <p>184: ἡ Σκύθαινα – „Scytyjka”; w Atenach oddziały porządkowe rekrutowano spośród Scytów, którzy nosili charakterystyczny, obcy strój. Ich obraz w komedii wskazuje na istnienie negatywnych stereotypów na ich temat. Obecność żeńskiego odpowiednika Scyty w omawianym miejscu paradoksalnie wskazuje na to, że scena jest parodią typowo ateńskiego publicznie spełnianego obrzędu, w którym asystuje stróż porządku.</p>
                            <p>186/192: τὰ τόμια – pokrojoną ofiarę / τόμιον ἐντεμοίμεθα – „pokroimy na kawałki”; praktyka składania przysięgi przez osobę, która stała na czymś, co określano jako τόμια, lub dotykała tego rodzaju przedmiotów, jest dobrze poświadczona (e.g. D. 23.68; Arist. Ath. 55.5; Antipho 5.12; Aesch. 1.114; Lycurg. 1.20). Kontekst, etymologia wyrazu, a także formuła τόμιον ἐντεμοίμεθα (cf. Aesch. 2.87: τἐμνοντα τὰ τόμια) nie pozostawiają wątpliwości, że chodzi o części zwierzęcia odcięte, wycięte lub posiekane (nie bez znaczenia jest i homerycka formuła np. w Il. 2.124 ὅρκια πιστὰ ταμόντες – „przeciąwszy = zawarłszy nienaruszalne przymierze”). Szczegóły niestety pozostają kwestią domysłów. Stengel (1910: 80–85), Stengel (1920: 137), cf. Bur-
                                kert (2011: 378), Burkert (1985: 251), Burkert (1983: 36) wyraził śmiałe przypuszczenie, że może chodzić o jądra (odcięte), jak jednak zauważa Faraone (1993: 68), nie istnieją silne przesłanki przemawiające za tym,
                                
                                
                                że nie chodzi o wnętrzności (wycięte i pokrojone σπλάγχνα), czy pocięte mięso (cf. Ekroth 2014: 164–165; Casabona 1966: 220–225). Możliwe zresztą, że rodzaj obiektów, jakie wykorzystywano w charakterze τόμια, bywał różny i zależał od nieuchwytnych dla nas czynników (poza chronologią i geografią liczyć się mogła np. treść przysiąg, ich publiczny bądź prywatny charakter itp.).
                            </p>
                            <p>185-90:wersy zawierają eksplicytne odwołanie do miejsca w Siedmiu przeciw Tebom Ajschylosa (42–48; słowa zwiadowcy): ἄνδρες γὰρ ἑπτά, θούριοι λοχαγέται, / ταυροσφαγοῦντες ἐς μελάνδετον σάκος / καὶ θιγγάνοντες χερσὶ ταυρείου φόνου, / Ἄρη τ’, ᾿Ενυώ, καὶ φιλαίματον Φόβον / ὡρκωμότησαν ἢ πόλει κατασκαφὰς / θέντες λαπάξειν ἄστυ Καδμείων βίαι, / ἢ γῆν θανόντες τήνδε φυράσειν φόνωι („Bo oto siedmiu mężów, zuchwałych dowódców,/ zaszlachtowało byka, krew zbierając do tarczy o czarnych brzegach/ i rękoma dotknęli byczej krwi,/ na Aresa, Enyo i Grozę chciwą krwi/ złożyli przysięgę, że albo miastu zgubę/ przynosząc, zniszczą miasto Kadmejczyków siłą,/ albo ginąc, własną krew zmieszają z tą ziemią” – przeł. K. Bielawski). Rzecz jasna, do tego sugestywnego obrazu należy podejść z równą ostrożnością, jak do arystofanejskiej groteski. Słowa te bowiem odnoszą się do zachowania hiperbolicznych gwałtowników z mitycznej przeszłości. Warto jednak zaznaczyć, że istnienie takiej praktyki rytualnej w dużej mierze potwierdza Ksenofont (An. 2.2.9), który opisuje, jak zarżnięto trzy zwierzęta (byka, knura i barana), zebrano ich krew do tarczy, po czym Grecy i ich sprzymierzeńcy zanurzali w niej miecze i włócznie, poprzysięgając sojusz. Wydaje się znaczące, że Ajschylos kładzie nacisk na symboliczny związek pomiędzy przelaną krwią zwierzęcia a krwią ludzką. Uobecnia się ona w przydomku personifikacji Phobos – rzeczownik, potraktowany jako imię bóstwa, określa „paniczny strach”. W ramach techniki wojennej czasów Ajschylosa właśnie to zjawisko prowadziło do przełamania szyków, bezładnej ucieczki i rzezi wojowników. Wymieniona tu krew to także krew siedmiu wodzów, którzy przysięgają zginąć, jeśli nie zdobędą miasta. Poeta wyraźnie zatem traktuje akt przemocy wobec zwierzęcia jako odwzorowanie tego, co jest przedmiotem obietnicy bohaterów: dokonanie aktu przemocy. Nie powinno w takim kontekście dziwić, że pomysł Lizystraty, by powtórzyć gest znany z Ajschylosa, spotyka się z gwałtownym odrzuceniem. Arystofanejskim kobietom zależy na pokoju, dlatego też całość rytuału, zamiast do krwi jako materialnego odzwierciedlenia przedmiotu przysięgi, odwoła się do wina, płynu, który sprawia rozkosz stereotypowej kobiecie ateńskiej i który chyba dość powszechnie kojarzono z pokojem (cf. Ar. Pax: sparsim; E. Ba 417–433; Il. 6.264–268).
                            </p>
                            <p>189: μηλοσφαγούσας – „zarzynając owcę”; u Ajschylosa (Th. 186) pojawia się wyraz ταυροσφαγοῦντες, „zarzynający byka”, jak należałoby wnosić ze struktury compositum i z tego, że w kolejnym wersie jest mowa o byczej krwi. Należy jednak zaznaczyć, że w czasach Arystofanesa, choć budowa tych dwóch złożeń w dalszym ciągu wydawała się oczywista, wyraźnie zatraciły one swoje pierwotne znaczenie („zarżnąć owcę/ byka”) na rzecz bardziej ogólnego: „zarżnąć dowolne zwierzę” (cf. schol. ad loc.). Trudno się oprzeć wrażeniu, że poeta chciał w tym miejscu zażartować, zastępując wyraz kojarzący się z ofiarą bardziej prestiżową, takim, który odwołuje się do bardziej pospolitej. Taka interpretacja wydaje się jednak przesadnie subtelna, wymagałaby bowiem od publiczności bardzo dokładnego zapamiętania tekstu Ajschylosa. Z punktu widzenia syntaktycznego ciekawe jest zachowanie czasownika μηλο-/ ταυρο-σφαγέω, który w omawianych miejscach występuje z okolicznikiem εἰς ἀσπίδα / ἐς σάκος, „do tarczy” (gdzie dwa różne rzeczowniki nazywają dwa typy tarcz). Rzecz jasna chodzi o to, że krew z zarżniętego zwierzęcia, która stanowi zasadniczy przedmiot zainteresowania w czasie rytuału, ma spłynąć do takiego zaimprowizowanego naczynia.</p>
                            <p>191-192: λευκὸν ἵππον – „białego konia”; miejsce niejasne. Scholiasta dopatruje się tu albo obscenicznego żartu, albo aluzji do zwyczajów Amazonek, które, jak pisze, składały w ofierze białe konie (λευκοὺς ἵππους ἔθυον). Pierwsza spośród wymienionych hipotez, jak zwykle w przypadku tekstu Arystofanesa, wydaje się atrakcyjna. Ponieważ nie wiemy, co działo się na scenie, nie można wykluczyć, że zawarty w tym miejscu dowcip nie tylko był pikantny, ale i doskonale czytelny,dzięki towarzyszącemu słowom gestowi. Z drugiej strony fakt, że scholiasta podaje alternatywny wariant wyjaśnienia, wskazuje na to, że on sam nie miał dostatecznych danych dotyczących warstwy performatywnej, by stwierdzić cokolwiek pewnego na temat zawartości passusu. Druga spośród podanych przez niego interpretacji wydaje się o tyle mało przekonująca, że z innych źródeł niczego nie wiadomo na temat ofiar rzekomo składanych przez Amazonki. Herodot (7.113) wspomina o rytualnym zabijaniu białych koni przez perskich magów, a Lukian (Scyth. 3) o składaniu ich w ofierze na grobie scytyjskiego herosa. Te dwa passusy łączą się z obyczajami Amazonek w najlepszym razie pośrednio. Nie zawierają też niczego, co w sposób oczywisty kojarzyłoby się z omawianym miejscem u Arystofanesa. Ponieważ passus ewidentnie obliczony był na wywołanie śmiechu, można podejrzewać, że zawarta w nim aluzja była dobrze czytelna, odwoływała się zatem do czegoś doskonale znanego publiczności. Przypuszczalnie zatem oparte na domysłach wyjaśnienia scholiasty wyłącznie oddalają nas od uchwycenia istoty żartu, który dotyczyć mógł czegoś bardzo aktualnego w czasie wystawienia sztuki. Z podobnym dystansem należy się odnieść do propozycji Fletcher (2012: 228), która jako paralelę wskazała przysięgę składaną przez zalotników Heleny. W rytuale tym, według Pauzaniasza (3.20.9), wykorzystano tomia konia (nie wiemy, jakiej maści), jednak trudno powiedzieć, czy tradycja ta była znana publiczności Arystofanesa.
                            </p>
                            <p>196: μηλοσφαγοῦσαι Θάσιον οἴνου σταμνίον – „zarżnąć dzban wina z Thasos”. Lizystrata (tu i konsekwentnie dalej) posługuje się językiem technicznym ofiary krwawej, stosując go do czynności, które ofiarą nie są (μηλοσφαγέω – cf. 189). Nie są też libacją sensu stricto (jak zauważa Henderson 1987: ad loc.), jako że wino nie leje się tu na ziemię, lecz do naczynia. Wino z Thasos słynęło ze swej jakości, wyraźnie zatem, jak zwykle w komedii, na pierwszy plan wysuwa się hedonistyczny wymiar parodiowanego rytuału. Ofiara z naczynia wina także w: Ar. Th. 686–762.</p>
                            <p>202: προσλαβοῦ μοι τοῦ κάπρου – „przytrzymaj knura”. Henderson (1987: ad loc.) w komentarzu do passusu zaznacza, że kładzenie rąk na zwierzęciu przed zarżnięciem miało istotne znaczenie symboliczne. Przypuszczam, że to zwykłe nieporozumienie, ponieważ uczony powołuje się na passus (cit. ad 185–190) z Ajschylosa (Th. 42), w którym mowa o nurzaniu dłoni we krwi już po uboju i na miejsce u Stengla (1920: 136), gdzie chodzi o obcięcie ofiarom kosmyków sierści (w Iliadzie 3.273–274) i przekazanie ich przywódcom Achajów i Trojan. Ten ostatni gest (cf. Eustathius: ad loc.) wyraźnie miał znaczenie analogiczne do podawania przysięgającym wnętrzności czy kawałków zarżniętego zwierzęcia i nie miał chyba nic wspólnego z kładzeniem na nim rąk przed zabiciem go. Z tego powodu można przypuszczać, że komenda, jaką w omawianym passusie wydaje Lizystrata, naśladuje zachowanie związane z ofiarniczą rutyną o charakterze czysto pragmatycznym i pozbawiona jest głębokiej symboliki. Ponieważ bohaterki bardzo przejęte były kielichem, przywódczyni musiała przywołać je do porządku, nakazując pomoc w trzymaniu zwierzęcia, podczas gdy ona sama (najwyraźniej) zamierzała wymierzyć mu cios. Kwestią zagadkową pozostaje, dlaczego w tekście mowa o knurze (κάπρος). Komentatorzy (Henderson 1987: ad loc.; Sommerstein 1990 ad loc.) zaznaczają wprawdzie, że może to być wpływ analogicznej sceny w Iliadzie (19.249–268), w której Agamemnon zarzyna takie zwierzę, jednak trudno powiedzieć, dlaczego owo miejsce miałoby mieć większe znaczenie niż np. passus z księgi III Iliady (271–323), w którym bohater zarzyna dwie owce. Ponieważ dostępne nam dane nie wskazują na to, by świnie w sposób szczególny związane były z kontekstem przysiąg, być może należy domyślać się w tym miejscu jakiegoś rodzaju gry słów. Scholiasta (ad loc.) zaznacza, że słowa oznaczającego knura Arystofanes używa tu w znaczeniu „genitalia”, co wydaje się atrakcyjną propozycją, niestety niepotwierdzoną w materiale leksykalnym. Oczywiście, zamiast knura, bohaterki „zarżną” dzban wina.</p>
                            <p>203–204: bardzo krótka modlitwa zawierająca inwokację do dwóch bogiń (z których jedna jest wyłącznie komiczną personifikacją), prośbę o przyjęcie ofiary (w liczbie pojedynczej, jednak chyba obie boginie są
                                adresatkami, przy czym jedna czara ma otrzymać płyn w sensie najbardziej dosłownym) i epitet zdradzający, że celem rytuału jest zjednanie sobie nieśmiertelnych (tym razem jednak chyba odnosi się on wyłącznie do drugiej z wymienionych bogiń).
                            </p>
                            <p>205: εὔχρων γε θαἶμα κἀποπυτίζει καλῶς – „piękny ma kolor ta krew i tryska wspaniale”. Kolejny z serii żartów opartych na dwuznaczności: wino/ krew. Scholia (ad loc.) zawierają wyjaśnienie, że bohaterka naśladuje w tym miejscu wieszczka lub kapłana (θυοσκόος). To pozwala przypuszczać, że strumień krwi poddawano lekturze w celu uzyskania znaków. Nawet jeśli nie istniał żaden wyrafinowany system semiozy wybroczyn, właściwie byłoby dziwne, gdyby nie funkcjonowała podstawowa kategoria opozycji binarnej: „jak należy/ źle”. Miejsce w Pokoju (1054–1055) wskazuje na adekwatność w takim kontekście przysłówka καλῶς.</p>                             <p>207: ἐᾶτε πρώτην μ', ὦ γυναῖκες, ὀμνύναι - "lasciami essere la prima a giurare"; l'eroina ovviamente non può aspettare il suo turno alla coppa. Sotto lo strato di uno scherzo si può scorgere una pratica rituale: il giuramento richiede un contatto fisico con l'animale macellato, i suoi pezzi o il sangue.</p>
                            <p>207: ἐᾶτε πρώτην μ’, ὦ γυναῖκες, ὀμνύναι – „pozwólcie, że ja jako pierwsza przysięgnę”; bohaterka oczywiście nie może się doczekać swojej kolejki przy kielichu. Pod warstwą żartu dostrzec można praktykę rytualną: przysięga wymaga wejścia w fizyczny kontakt z zarżniętym zwierzęciem, jego kawałkami lub krwią.</p>                            
                            <p>235–236: εἰ δὲ παραβαίην, ὕδατος ἐμπλῆιθ' ἡ κύλιξ – „a jeśli nie dochowam wiary, niech czara wypełni się wodą”. Teksty przysiąg zwykle zawierają eksplicytnie wyrażoną sankcję. Co charakterystyczne, materiał grecki wskazuje na to, że najczęściej była ona związana z przedmiotem, na który przysięgano. Faraone (1993) przy całym dystansie, jaki zachowuje w stosunku do koncepcji Frazera, chyba słusznie określa takie postępowanie rodzajem magii sympatycznej, w której – warunkowo, bo w sytuacji złamania słowa – przysięgający ściąga na siebie los, jaki spotyka coś innego – zarżnięte i pokrojone zwierzę, rozlaną krew lub wino, stopiony wosk (e.g.: Il. 3.292–301; Paroemioraphi Graeci 126 (Gaisford); SEG IX 4; cf. Fletcher 2012: 214, 230). W ten schemat doskonale wpisuje się cytowany powyżej (ad 185–9) opis przysięgi z Siedmiu przeciw Tebom Ajschylosa (42–48).</p>
                            <p>238: ἐγὼ καθαγίσω τήνδε – „dokonam aktu poświęcenia”; czasownik καθαγίζω oznacza czynność ofiarowania czegoś poprzez całkowite zniszczenie, najczęściej przy pomocy ognia (cf. Ar. Av. 566). W omawianym miejscu wyraźnie jednak chodzi o „zniszczenie” wina w sposób przyjemny dla niszczącej je osoby, to znaczy o wypicie. Wyraźnie zatem to, co znajdowało się w centrum zainteresowania osób posługujących się terminem, to nie użycie ognia, lecz fakt unicestwiania przedmiotu, czy też, jak chyba słusznie zaznacza Svenbro (2005), usunięcie go ze sfery ludzkiej i w zmienionej postaci (np. dymu) przekazanie go istotom nadprzyrodzonym. Zważywszy na funkcję przedmiotu, na który przysięgano, z którego losem utożsamiano los krzywoprzysięzcy (cf. ad 235,6), w tym momencie czymś oczekiwanym byłoby brutalne potraktowanie wina. Doskonale podkreśla to komizm passusu, w którym Lizystrata wyraźnie zamierza łapczywie wypić całą zawartość wielkiej czary.</p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <div type="textpart" n="Lysistrata_1128–1134">
                        <head>Lysistrata 1128–1134</head>
                        <div type="textpart" n="1128-1134">
                            <p>Lizystrata wyraża krytykę mężczyzn z różnych poleis greckich zaangażowanych w wojnę peloponeską. Passus jest interesujący ze względu na dochodzącą w nim do głosu ideologię panhelleńską, której bezcennym punktem odniesienia jest „obcy, barbarzyńca”. Ze względu na wzmiankę o wojsku potencjalnych zewnętrznych wrogów możemy się domyślać, że jeśli w jakikolwiek sposób konkretyzowano, o jakich cudzoziemców chodzi, źródłem lęku skłaniającego Greków do solidarności musiała być przede wszystkim Persja. Oprócz zewnętrznego – rzeczywistego bądź urojonego – zagrożenia czynnikiem jednoczącym na poziomie ideologicznym były wspólne sanktuaria. W przytoczonym passusie uwaga sfokalizowana jest na geście obmywania rąk. Trudno powiedzieć, czy to wyłącznie figura retoryczna. Tak czy inaczej, wyraźnie był to bardzo ważny moment procesu rytualnego..</p>
                            
                            <quote>
                                <lb/><emph>Λυσιστράτη</emph>
                                <lb/>λαβοῦσα δ᾽ ὑμᾶς λοιδορῆσαι βούλομαι
                                <lb/>κοινῇ δικαίως, οἳ μιᾶς ἐκ χέρνιβος
                                <lb n="1130"/>βωμοὺς περιρραίνοντες ὥσπερ ξυγγενεῖς
                                <lb/>Ὀλυμπίασιν, ἐν Πύλαις, Πυθοῖ （πόσους
                                <lb/>εἴποιμ᾽ ἂν ἄλλους, εἴ με μηκύνειν δέοι;）
                                <lb/>ἐχθρῶν παρόντων βαρβάρων στρατεύματι
                                <lb/>Ἕλληνας ἄνδρας καὶ πόλεις ἀπόλλυτε.
                            </quote>
                            
                            <quote>Skoro was tu zebrałam, pragnę wyrazić słuszną krytykę wszystkich, którzy z jednego naczynia [1130] opryskujecie wodą ołtarze, jak bracia – w Olimpii, Pylai, Pytho... ileż bym ich mogła jeszcze wyliczyć, gdybym miała dłużej mówić? Choć wojsko barbarzyńskie jest tak blisko, wy niszczycie greckie miasta i mężów.</quote>
                        </div>
                        <div type="textpart" n="commentary">
                            <p>1129: μιᾶς ἐκ χέρνιβος – „z jednego naczynia”; rzeczownik χέρνιψ pierwotnie oznaczał wodę do mycia rąk – przed przystąpieniem do ofiary, a także innych czynności, np. posiłku. W omawianym miejscu Arystofanes posługuje się wyrażeniem przyimkowym ἐκ χέρνιβος („z chernipsu”), co może wskazywać na to, że w owym okresie wyraz był już także używany w znaczeniu metonimicznym: „naczynie na wodę do mycia” (cf. Ar. Av. 850 wraz z komentarzem). Scena w Pokoju Arystofanesa (960–961) zawiera cenną wzmiankę o przekazywaniu z rąk do rąk takiej miski w czasie wstępnych rytów poprzedzających ofiarę. Być może właśnie do takiego kolektywnego obmycia, podkreślającego jedność grupy uczestników obrzędu, nawiązuje tu Lizystrata. Co ciekawe jednak, w malarstwie wazowym chernips niemal zawsze znajduje się w rękach osoby młodszej, która podaje go głównemu ofiarnikowi, mężczyźnie starszemu o wyraźnie wyższym statusie (van Straten 1995: fig. 30–36). W omawianym miejscu mowa o nieco innym sposobie zastosowania chernips: βωμοὺς περιρραίνοντες: „spryskując ołtarze”. Użyty tu czasownik περιρραίνω, którego sama podstawa derywacyjna: ῥαίνω wyraża semantykę „opryskiwać”, intensyfikuje to znaczenie prefiksem περι-, „zewsząd”. Ewidentnie zatem chodzi o wstępny ryt, polegający na symbolicznym oczyszczeniu ołtarza, prawdopodobnie dokonywany w czasie obchodzenia go (w kierunku przeciwnym do wskazówek zegara ἐπιδεξιά), przy pomocy zanurzanego w chernips polana lub gałązki. Obszerniej na ten temat: ad <ref type="lit">Ar. Pax 956–61</ref>; Av. 850, 958. Poszanowanie lub jego brak wobec chernips jako
                                znak przestrzegania lub łamania norm rytualnych: Th. 4.97.3; S. O.T. 240; Lys. 6.52; D. 20.158 (cytuję za Henderson 1987: ad loc.; w przypadku pierwszego z wymienionych miejsc nie jestem pewien, czy autor rzeczywiście miał na myśli chernips jako figurę; pozostałe passusy nie budzą moich zastrzeżeń).
                            </p>
                            <p>1131-1132: Lizystrata retorycznie zapewnia, że mogłaby wymienić więcej panhelleńskich sanktuariów niż te trzy, które wylicza. Rzeczywiście, trudno zapomnieć choćby o Istmii, Nemei, Delos, Eleusis, Dodonie czy choćby Atenach, które organizując igrzyska panatenajskie, pretendowały do roli ośrodka kultu panhelleńskiego. Tym bardziej w kontekście deklaracji samej przemawiającej zastanawiający powinien się wydać dokonany przez nią wybór. O ile bowiem Olimpia i Delfy, najsłynniejsze chyba sanktuaria starożytności, wydają się w sposób oczywisty godne wzmianki, o tyle nietypowe wydaje się wskazanie Pylai. Miejsce to, bardziej znane pod nazwą Thermopylai to strategicznie położony przesmyk, zapewniający łatwe do obrony przejście z północy do centralnej Grecji. Przynajmniej od okresu archaicznego w jego pobliżu znajdowało się sanktuarium <persName type="divine" key="Demeter">Demeter</persName> w Antheli, pierwotna siedziba organizacji panhelleńskiej zwanej Amfiktionią Pylajską, później (jako że kontrolowała ona między innymi Delfy) – Amfiktionią Delficką. Ta instytucja o charakterze religijnym odgrywała ważną rolę polityczną. Być może właśnie z jej inspiracji pierwszym miejscem oporu stawionego Kserksesowi przez Greków były okolice jej siedziby w czasie słynnej bitwy pod Termopilami (cf. Stählin 1934). Zważywszy na kontekst, prawdopodobnie do tego nawiązuje <persName key="Aristophanes">Arystofanes</persName>, wzywając Ateńczyków do pogodzenia się ze Spartanami i połączenie sił przeciw wspólnym wrogom. Odwoływanie się do ideologii ukształtowanej w czasie wojen perskich stanowi zresztą typowy rys jego programu politycznego.</p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
