<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title xml:lang="it">Iliade, canto I</title>
                <title xml:lang="en">Iliad, book I</title>
                <title xml:lang="pl">Iliada, pieśń I</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher><ref target="https://site.unibo.it/lares/">LARES Project</ref></publisher>
                <date when="2021"/>
                <idno type="filename">hom_01_ilias_i</idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p><title>Iliada, pieśń I</title>, in Lech Trzcionkowski, <title>Ofiara krwawa w Grecji starożytnej w świetle danych filologicznych. 
                    Homer</title>, Warszawa 2017, pp. 3-32</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change when="2022-02-10" who="Gaetano Spampinato">encoded document in XML</change>
                <change when="2017" who="Lech Trzcionkowski">Lech Trzcionkowski created document contents</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            
            <div type="edition" xml:lang="it">
              <div type="textpart" n="intro">
                  <p>L'Iliade è la storia dell'ira fatale (mēnis) di Achille, insultato da Agamennone, che privò l'eroe della sua prigioniera Briseis - il dono d'onore (geras) degli Achei, un segno visibile dell'onore dovutogli (timē). Privato dell'onore, Achille si ritirò dalla battaglia e fece richiesta a sua madre, la dea Teti, di vendicare l'insulto. L'esaudimento della richiesta di Teti da parte di Zeus stabilisce la trama vera e propria dell'epopea: la sconfitta degli Achei. 
                      La trama si basa quindi su eventi che si svolgono su due piani, quello umano e quello divino. A livello degli attori mortali, le azioni formano una catena: violazione di una norma (offesa) - reazione (rabbia) - ripristino della norma (riconciliazione). L'azione che viola la norma è la presa/sequestro della ragazza o il rifiuto di restituirla in cambio di un riscatto (apoina), e la riconciliazione richiede la restituzione della rapita. Nel caso di attori immortali (gli dei), un'analoga sequenza di azioni (insulto - rabbia vendicativa - restauro) può essere la risposta a una richiesta contenuta nella preghiera di un mortale insultato che presenta il suo danno (violazione della norma) e invoca la charis, il principio di reciprocità che regola i rapporti tra gli dei e gli umani. L'ira della divinità può essere alleviata facendo un'azione rituale appropriata - facendo un sacrificio. Così, per mantenere relazioni adeguate con gli immortali, si offrono sacrifici appropriati sugli altari appartenenti agli dei. Sono intesi come doni - segni del dovuto onore agli dei. Pertanto, le preghiere invocano i sacrifici offerti in passato o predicono i sacrifici da offrire in futuro, e trascurare i sacrifici può provocare l'ira del dio. Il ruolo del sacrificio in questa controversia può essere illustrato dal seguente diagramma (basato su Hitch 2009). 
                  </p><p>1-7 Invocazione alle Muse. Riassunto dell'argomento.</p>
                  <p>8-32 Insulto di Crise da parte di Agamennone - rifiuto della richiesta di consegnare Crise in cambio di un riscatto (apoina).</p>
                  <p> 33-42 Preghiera di Crise: richiesta di vendetta sostenuta dal ricordo dei sacrifici fatti in passato [Testo 1].</p>
                  <p> 43-52 Apollon punisce gli Achei - peste.</p>
                  <p>  [53–305]	Assemblea degli Achei.</p>
                  <p> 59-67 Discorso di Achille: richiesta di diagnosi: trascurata la catomba come possibile causa dell'ira di Apollo [testo 2].
                  </p><p> 92-100 'Diagnosi trascendentale': l'indovino Kalchas dichiara che non è la trascurata hecatomb la causa, ma l'insulto del sacerdote: la devozione di Crisippo e la deposizione della hecatomb possono vincere il dio [testo 3].
                  </p> <p> 121-139 Inizio della disputa di Achille con Agamennone.</p>
                  <p> 140-147 Agamennone decide di inviare un emissario con la catomba e Crisippo [testo 4].</p>
                  <p> 148-305 Agamennone annuncia la riconquista di Briseis.</p>
                  <p> 306-307 Achille si ritira nelle tende.</p>
                  <p> 308-311 Agamennone naviga con una nave a catasta verso Chryza [testo 5a].</p>
                  <p>311-317 L'ordine di Agamennone: lavare l'esercito dalle contaminazioni; deporre la catomba [testo 5b].</p>
                  <p>318-356 La presa di Briseis dalla tenda di Achille.</p>
                  <p>357-430a Conversazione tra Achille e Teti. La richiesta di Achille di vendicare l'insulto.</p>
                  <p>384-390 La resa di Crisippo e l'invio di doni (offerte) ad Apollo implicano la presa di un dono dovuto (Briseis) da Achille [testo 6].</p>
                  <p> 423-425 [Zeus a una festa con gli Etiopi] [testo 7].</p>
                  <p> 430a-474 Consegna di Crisippo a Crisippo e offerta della catomba ad Apollo in Crisippo - sacrificio di riconciliazione accettato [testo 8].</p>
                  <p> 475-487 Ritorno dei messaggeri al campo degli Achei.</p>
                  <p> 488-492 Achille sopraffatto dalla rabbia (mēnis) rimane nella sua tenda.</p>
                  <p>È stato sottolineato che l'intero episodio assomiglia nella struttura all'inno omerico ad Apollo il Delfico, in cui la parte narrativa si conclude con un sacrificio e l'istituzione del culto. Christopher Faraone ha avanzato l'ipotesi che la fonte dell'inizio del poema possa essere l'inno ad Apollon Smintejski (Faraone 2015). Se questo fosse davvero il caso, le origini narrative dell'inno andrebbero cercate nel Canto anatolico della liberazione, che, secondo Mary Bachvarova, sottende l'episodio (Bachvarova 2016). Accettare questa ipotesi ci permette di rispondere alla domanda perché il tema principale, cioè la rabbia di Achille scatenata dalla sua disputa con Agamennone, precede l'insulto di Agamennone al sacerdote di Apollo, Crise. Crise arriva all'accampamento degli Achei con una supplica per la restituzione di sua figlia rapita da Agamennone; Agamennone rifiuta e caccia via il supplicante. L'offeso Crise prega Apollo Sminteus di vendicare l'ingiustizia, ricordando il ricordo dei sacrifici che ha fatto. Il dio arrabbiato, accogliendo la richiesta del sacerdote, manda una peste, provocando una crisi nel campo degli Achei. Achille, parlando a un'assemblea dell'esercito, esprime la sua ipotesi che la causa dell'ira del dio possa essere una catomba trascurata o un voto non rispettato. La vera ragione è rivelata dall'indovino che, facendo una diagnosi trascendente, indica il colpevole (Agamennone) e presenta un possibile modo di propiziare il dio: l'ira di Apollo, provocata da Agamennone, può essere placata dando la Criside a Crise e offrendo una catomba ad Apollon. L'intero episodio si conclude con un rituale di un giorno, non annunciato in anticipo, durante il quale i giovani achei ballano e cantano il pajan propiziatorio. L'appagamento dell'ira del dio si intreccia con l'infiammazione dell'ira dell'eroe.</p>
              </div>
                <div type="textpart" n="Iliad_1.33-43">
                    <head>Iliade 1.33–43:</head>
                    <p>Il passus contiene la preghiera di un sacerdote di Apollo, Chryses, che è venuto al campo degli Achei con la richiesta di consegnare sua figlia Chryses, prigioniera di Agamennone. Scacciato da Agamennone, prega Apollo sulla riva del mare, invocando vendetta per le sofferenze subite. L'ubicazione della scena sulla riva del mare enfatizza la disperazione e la solitudine di Crise (es. Il. 1.327, 350, 23-59, 24.12, cfr. Edwards 1980: 8). L'adempimento della richiesta da parte del dio diventerà la causa della disputa di Achille con Agamennone, che susciterà l'ira di Achille (mēnis) - il tema principale dell'epica. Sulla preghiera di Crise si veda Aubriot-Sévin 1992: 219, 281-283, 304; Ausfeld 1903: 505 ss; Chapot, Laurot 2001: 31-32 (G1); Pulleyn 1997: 16; Pulleyn 2000: 132-136; Citron 1965: 88-89; Edwards 1980: 8-9; Lateiner 1997: 241 ss; Morrison 1991; Mueller 1976; Rabel 1988: 473 ss. ; Servais 1967: 415 ff; Thornton 1984, per la funzione del motivo di Crise nella costruzione dell'Iliade nel suo complesso, si veda Rabel 1988. Gli effetti della preghiera di Crise cesseranno quando Crise si arrenderà a suo padre e propizierà Apollon con una hecatomb, ma la sua ulteriore conseguenza sarà l'ira di Achille, si veda Wilson 2002: 40-53.</p>
                    <quote>
                        <lb/>Ὣς ἔφατ’, ἔδεισεν δ’ ὃ γέρων καὶ ἐπείθετο μύθῳ· 				
                        <lb/>βῆ δ’ ἀκέων παρὰ θῖνα πολυφλοίσβοιο θαλάσσης·
                        <lb/>πολλὰ δ’ ἔπειτ’ ἀπάνευθε κιὼν ἠρᾶθ’ ὃ γεραιὸς   	
                        <lb/>    Ἀπόλλωνι ἄνακτι, τὸν ἠΰκομος τέκε Λητώ· 					
                        <lb/>    κλῦθί μευ ἀργυρότοξ᾽, ὃς Χρύσην ἀμφιβέβηκας 
                        <lb/>     Κίλλάν τε ζαθέην Τενέδοιό τε ἶφι ἀνάσσεις,  
                        <lb/>     Σμινθεῦ εἴ ποτέ τοι χαρίεντ᾽ ἐπὶ νηὸν ἔρεψα, 
                        <lb/>     ἢ εἰ δή ποτέ τοι κατὰ πίονα μηρί᾽ ἔκηα 						
                        <lb/>      ταύρων ἠδ᾽ αἰγῶν, τὸ δέ μοι κρήηνον ἐέλδωρ· 
                        <lb/>     τίσειαν Δαναοὶ ἐμὰ δάκρυα σοῖσι βέλεσσιν.  
                    </quote>
                    <quote>
                        <lb/>Tak rzekł. Przestraszył się starzec i posłuchał rozkazu;
                        <lb/>   kroczył w milczeniu brzegiem rozgłośnego morza;
                        <lb/>   wówczas idąc samotnie wzniósł gorliwie błagania stary: 
                        <lb/>   „Apollonie, Panie, którego porodziła pięknowłosa Leto!				
                        <lb/>   Usłysz mnie, Srebnołuki, co troszczysz się o Chryzę,
                        <lb/>   i przenajświętszą Killę, i panujesz z mocą nad Tenedosem,
                        <lb/>   Sminteusie, jeżeli ci kiedyś miłą przykryłem dachem świątynię
                        <lb/>   lub jeżelim Ci kiedyś spalił tłuste udźce						
                        <lb/>   byków i kozłów – mego błagania teraz wysłuchaj:
                        <lb/>   pomścij na Danajach moje łzy swoimi strzałami”.
                    </quote>
                    <p>36: 	Ἀπόλλωνι ἄνακτι, τὸν ἠΰκομος τέκε Λητώ – "Apollon, o Signore, che la bella Leto ha partorito!"; la preghiera di Crise è un esempio di una struttura di preghiera in tre parti: 1) invocazione al dio o alla dea, con aggiunta di epiteti e/o genealogia; 2) argomentazione (giustificazione della richiesta) che indica la base della charis attesa; 3) richiesta (Aubriot-Sévin 1992: 218 ss.; Muellner 1976: 27-28); si apre con un esametro solenne che invoca Apollon, con una formale invocazione della genealogia (cfr. Il. 19.413; h.h.Apol. 178).</p>
                    <p>37-38: Crise, invece di evocare Apollo con una serie di epiteti (cfr. la preghiera di Achille a Zeus, Il. 16.233-235), sottolinea il suo legame con specifici luoghi di culto in Troade.</p>
                    <p>39-40:	εἴ ποτέ τοι... τοι χαρίεντ᾽ ἐπὶ νηὸν ἔρεψα / ἢ... κατὰ πίονα μηρί᾽ ἔκηα - "se una volta ho coperto piacevolmente un tempio con un tetto a voi o Ho bruciato le grasse zampe posteriori"; nella parte centrale dello schema di preghiera Chryses usa la tipica formula εἴ ποτέ τοι ("se io una volta..."): si tratta di ricordare atti indicativi della riverenza mostrata alla divinità nel passato, che dovrebbero ora indurla ad accogliere la richiesta (Aubriot-Sévin 1992; Pulleyn 1997). Chryses cita due tipi di azioni umane: la copertura del tempio e l'offerta di sacrifici. In entrambi i casi, si tratta di azioni che - in quanto gradite a Dio - conquistano la sua benevolenza, graziosità, favore, cioè charis. È indicato dall'aggettivo χαρίεντα che definisce il tempio come "dotato di charis" - "gentilezza conquistatrice, piacevole". (χαρίεντα... νηὸν). Si può supporre che i sacrifici animali fossero percepiti in modo analogo. Una connessione diretta tra il concetto di charis e le zampe posteriori bruciate sugli altari si trova in Od. 19.397 ("belle gambe posteriori", κεχαρισμένα μηρία, cfr. Ar. Pax 386) e Od. 16.184 ("belle offerte", κεχαρισμένα ... ἱρὰ). Non si tratta di un semplice scambio basato sul principio del do ut des, ma di una relazione permanente di reciprocità generalizzata (reciprocità generalizzata, termine di M. Sahlins, vedi Sahlins 1972, cap. 5), cioè una relazione basata su uno scambio permanente in cui si dà qualche bene o servizio a un'altra persona senza ricevere nulla immediatamente in cambio. Questo perché ci si aspetta che il ricevente ricambi più tardi (sulla charis, Parker 2011; più estesamente: Loew 1908; Latacz 1966: 78-98; Moussy 1966: 411-415; de Lamberterie 1978-79: 31-39). 
                        ἐπὶ νηὸν ἔρεψα - 'Ho coperto il tempio con un tetto'; secondo Walter Burkert, la formulazione potrebbe implicare una ripetizione di entrambe le azioni, il che suggerirebbe che Crise ha coperto il tempio con un tetto molte volte, forse ogni volta che ha fatto i sacrifici menzionati nella preghiera; questo si riferirebbe quindi a una capanna di fortuna eretta allo scopo della festa (Burkert 2011 [1992]: 262). Alexander Ainan Mazarakis, invece, ritiene che, comunque, il verbo ἐρέφω qui significhi 'coprire con piastrelle' e usa la preghiera di Crise per datare il testo dell'epopea, poiché i più antichi esempi di piastrelle di ceramica in Grecia risalgono all'inizio del VII secolo a.C. (il tempio di Apollo a Corinto, vedi Robinson 1984: 55-56; cfr. Ainan Mazarakis 2000: 113, nota 302). Tuttavia, sembra che ἐρέφω significhi semplicemente 'coprire, tetto', non necessariamente con tegole. Gli edifici templari che appaiono già nell'ottavo secolo esprimono la necessità di dotare una divinità di una casa in cui la divinità, simboleggiata dalla statua di culto, troverà rifugio (cfr. Coldstream 1977: 321). Sul significato simbolico dell'idea di protezione e riparo nell'Iliade, vedi Lynn-George 1993: 197-221.
                        κατὰ πίονα μηρί᾽ ἔκηα - 'Ho bruciato le grasse cerve'; nelle preghiere, la menzione del rogo delle cerve (→ μηρία) è un'evocazione metonimica di sacrifici compiuti in passato (cfr. Il. 8.240; Il. 15.373; Od. 4.764; Od. 17.241). Il loro ricordo è legato a una richiesta rivolta a un essere soprannaturale nel quadro di una relazione reciproca. Crise ricorda i sacrifici che egli stesso fece un tempo (analogamente Agamennone in Il. 8.240: ἀλλ᾽ ἐπὶ πᾶσι βοῶν δημὸν καὶ μηρί᾽ ἔκηα - 'ma su tutti (gli altari) del grasso di bue e dei femori ho bruciato'; e Il. 15.373-374: ἢ βοὸς ἢ οἰὸς κατὰ πίονα μηρία καίων / εὔχετο νοστῆσαι - "[se] ho pregato per il ritorno a casa delle cosce grasse di bue o pecora bruciandole"). Nel caso in cui un personaggio che occupa una posizione sociale inferiore, come Eumaeus e Penelope, prega, egli invoca i sacrifici fatti in passato dall'ospite legittimo (in entrambi i casi Odysseus): Od. 17.240-242 (Eumaios); Od. 4,763-765 (Penelope). Caratteristicamente, in tutti i casi le gambe bruciate sono descritte come grasso (πίονα μηρία) o, nel caso della preghiera di Eumaeus, si sottolinea il fatto che sono nascoste nel grasso (καλύψας πίονι δημῷ). La combustione (→ καίω) di femori avvolti nel grasso (→ κνῖσα, meno frequentemente: → δημός) produceva un fumo denso e fragrante (→ κνῖσα).
                    </p>
                    <p>41: 	ταύρων ἠδ᾽ αἰγῶν – "tori o capre"; la costruzione μηρία + NOME DELL'ANIMALE è abbastanza frequente nell'epica, l'analisi mostra una tendenza ad associare specifici animali sacrificali al dio a cui sono sacrificati; la scelta non è quindi del tutto casuale, ma si inserisce in uno schema. È da notare che anche Agamennone offrirà più tardi ad Apollo il propiziatorio τεληέσσας ἑκατόμβας / ταύρων ἠδ᾽ αἰγῶν - 'una perfetta catomba di tori e capri' (Il. 1.315). 	
                        ταύρων - "tori"; parola → ταῦρος "toro" (non castrato), 'toro' può suggerire un sacrificio di particolare valore, dato che i tori castrati venivano solitamente sacrificati. 	
                        αἰγῶν - "capre"; è difficile identificare chiaramente il sesso delle capre, poiché il sostantivo αἴξ può significare capra e caprone (nelle iscrizioni attiche - castrato, → αἴξ; capra non castrata, cap, → τράγος non si verifica nell'Iliade, e nell'Odissea appare solo una volta: Od. 9.239). Tuttavia, poiché era la norma sacrificare individui maschi a divinità maschili, la traduzione più appropriata è "capre".
                    </p>
                </div>
                
                <div type="textpart" n="Iliad_1.62–67">
                    <head>Iliade 1.62–67</head>
                    <p>La situazione di crisi (peste) che affliggeva l'esercito acheo richiede contromisure. La procedura prevede la realizzazione di una "diagnosi trascendentale" (termine di W. Burkert) da uno specialista rituale, un esperto-mediatore, cioè un indovino (mantis), che, sulla base dell'interpretazione di segni e conoscenze, determina i rimedi appropriati e come applicarli (Burkert 1996: 103-128). La richiesta di una diagnosi trascendentale è fatta all'assemblea da Achille. Da come lo formula, sembra che la causa più probabile della crisi possa essere un errore rituale, un mancato adempimento di un obbligo verso gli dei (un voto, → εὐχωλή) o la trascuratezza di un sacrificio di sangue (una hecatomb, → ἑκατόμβη), e che il rinnovo di un corretto rapporto con gli dei debba essere compiuto compiendo un sacrificio adeguato (Casevitz 1992: 3-5).</p>
                    <quote>
                        <lb/>ἀλλ᾽ ἄγε δή τινα μάντιν ἐρείομεν ἢ ἱερῆα, 						
                        <lb/>ἢ καὶ ὀνειροπόλον, καὶ γάρ τ᾽ ὄναρ ἐκ  Διός ἐστιν, 
                        <lb/> ὅς κ᾽ εἴποι ὅ τι τόσσον ἐχώσατο  Φοῖβος  Ἀπόλλων, 
                        <lb n="65"/> εἴ ταρ ὅ γ᾽ εὐχωλῆς ἐπιμέμφεται ἠδ᾽ ἑκατόμβης,
                        <lb/>    αἴ κέν πως ἀρνῶν κνίσης αἰγῶν τε τελείων 
                        <lb/>  βούλεται ἀντιάσας ἡμῖν ἀπὸ λοιγὸν ἀμῦναι.
                    </quote>
                    <quote>
                        <lb/>Chiediamo a qualche indovino o prete,				
                        <lb/> o un interprete di sogni - perché da Zeus un sogno - 
                        <lb/> che poteva dire perché Phoebos Apollon era così arrabbiato.
                        <lb n="65"/> Ci trova forse da ridire per la mancata esecuzione di un voto o di una catomba? 
                        <lb/> Forse avendo accettato il grasso fumo sacrificale dei montoni o delle capre scelte 
                        <lb/> decide di evitare l'annientamento da parte nostra.
                    </quote>
                    <p>62-63: τινα μάντιν ἐρείομεν ἢ ἱερῆα, / ἢ καὶ ὀνειροπόλον - "qualche indovino chiediamo o a un prete, / o a un interprete di sogni"; una diagnosi trascendentale può essere fatta da uno specialista rituale appartenente a una delle tre (o due, vedi sotto) categorie: → mantis ('indovino, indovino'), → hiereus ('sacerdote'), → oneiropolos ('interprete di sogni'). Il versetto 63 ha sollevato dubbi tra i filologi alessandrini. Il primo capo della Biblioteca, Zenodotos (c. 325 - c. 260 a.C.) lo ateizza (rimuove), probabilmente considerando l'interprete di sogni come una categoria separata di specialista religioso, non direttamente collegata alla necessità di diagnosticare le cause della crisi (cfr. Kirk, ad loc.). Aristarco (216 - 144 a.C.), invece, mette un due punti (virgola) dopo ἐρείομεν, 'chiediamo', che cambia il significato della frase: "chiediamo a qualche indovino: un sacerdote o un interprete di sogni" - secondo questa interpretazione, l'indovino (mantis) è il nome di una categoria generale, "uno specialista rituale impegnato nella lettura dei segni", mentre il sacerdote (hiereus) e l'interprete di sogni (oneiropolos) sono sottocategorie, specialisti che leggono segni che appaiono durante i sacrifici o i sogni. Si noti, tuttavia, che hiereus denota un ruolo sociale indipendente (Chaniotis 2008) e non un tipo di indovino (Pulleyn 2000: 142), sebbene i due termini (plurale) siano giustapposti nell'epica (Il. 24.224). Michel Casevitz ha recentemente sostenuto che la parola (mantis) è legata al verbo μηνύω, 'rivelare ciò che è nascosto; rivelare' (Casevitz 1992). Se accettiamo questa ipotesi, si potrebbe sostenere che anche la radice indica che la funzione originaria e primaria della manteis era quella di rivelare le cause nascoste delle situazioni critiche e quindi di fare una diagnosi trascendentale. Sulla funzione dei manteis nell'epica, vedi Bremmer 1993, 171-6; Casevitz 1992; di Sacco 2000. L'uso di sacerdoti specializzati nell'interpretazione dei sogni per risolvere i problemi indicando il rituale necessario per risolverli ha paralleli nel sistema religioso babilonese, vedi West (2008 [1996]) 88-89.</p>
                    <p>64: ὅ τι τόσσον ἐχώσατο Φοῖβος Ἀπόλλων - "perché Phoebos Apollon era così arrabbiato": la domanda corretta da fare quando si effettua una diagnosi trascendentale. Il verbo χώομαι, "sono arrabbiato, sono collerico" si riferisce, naturalmente, ai segni percepiti dalla gente - la peste è causata dall'ira del dio, e il rovesciamento del male è possibile solo a condizione di scoprire la causa dell'ira. Le emozioni associate alla rabbia sono in assoluta opposizione alle emozioni associate al concetto di χάρις, "grazia, gentilezza, benevolenza".</p>
                    <p>65: 	εὐχωλῆς ἐπιμέμφεται ἠδ᾽ ἑκατόμβης – "sia che egli trovi colpa in noi a causa del mancato adempimento di una promessa o di una catomba"; poiché il verbo ἐπιμέμφεται + gen. rei significa "biasimare, rimproverare a causa della mancanza o del fallimento di qualcosa, lamentarsi a causa di qualcosa" (Il. 2.225, cfr. 226 ss., ph. 229), possiamo supporre che Achille si stia chiedendo se l'ira del dio sia stata scatenata da qualche fallimento nella sfera della comunicazione con gli dei. Il verbo ἐπιμέμφεται in questo contesto è spesso tradotto come uno stato emotivo ("essere arrabbiato"), ma è piuttosto un verbo con una sfumatura giuridica, che significa un'ampia accusa di mancato adempimento di qualche obbligo legittimo. Per l'ira degli dei causata da un sacrificio trascurato (Il. 5.177) cfr. Latacz, Nünlist, Stoevesandt 2009: 52-3. 	
                        εὐχωλή - 'voto'; la parola → εὐχωλή significa un impegno ad alta voce, pronunciato solennemente, verso un dio in cambio dell'aiuto atteso (Benveniste 1969). Poiché tale impegno veniva generalmente preso durante la preghiera, la parola può essere tradotta come "voto, promessa, promessa" o "preghiera". In questo caso, sembra che non si tratti di una richiesta mal posta nella preghiera, ma di una mancata realizzazione della promessa (Corlu 1966: 157-158). Un'interessante alternativa a "voto" nella traduzione polacca è la parola "promessa", che, sebbene nel polacco moderno non abbia connotazioni sacrali, si dovrebbe ricordare che è legata all'antico nome di "sacrificio" - obiata. Nel vecchio polacco "promessa" era usato per esprimere un voto religioso.	
                        ἑκατόμβη - "hekatomba"; la parola → ἑκατόμβη è solitamente spiegata come un sacrificio "(fatto) di cento buoi, cento lupi" (cfr. Omero, scholia vetera, ed. Erbse: ἑκατόμβη δὲ ἀπὸ τοῦ ἑκατὸν καὶ τοῦ βοῦς - "hekatomba: formato da "cento" (hekaton) e "bue" (bous)"), ma nell'epica la parola si è ormai lessicalizzata a significare "un grande sacrificio di valore" indipendentemente dal numero o dalla specie degli animali (LfgrE s.v. ἑκατόμβη), e può quindi significare sia un sacrificio di pecore e capre, sia cinquanta animali (Il. 23.146-8), o anche solo dodici giovenche (Il. 6.93, cfr. 6.115). Il fatto che, nonostante la sua chiara struttura, la parola non significhi necessariamente un sacrificio di cento buoi era già stato sottolineato dai commentatori antichi e bizantini (Eustathios, ad Il. 1.65, spiega: θυσία ἐξ ἑκατὸν δηλονότι κυρίως βοῶν, καταχρησιτκῶς μέντοι καὶ ἡ ἐξ ἑκατὸν ζώων - "un sacrificio, in senso stretto, di cento buoi, ma in senso lato anche di cento animali"; Gli scholia aggiungono che ἑκατόμβη significa "sacrifici perfetti, τελείας θυσίας"). Paul Thieme ha avanzato l'ipotesi che la parola significasse originariamente un atto volto a conquistare il favore degli dei per ricevere cento buoi (Thieme 1952: 62-76; cfr. Pulleyn 2000: 143). Indipendentemente dall'accettazione di questa ipotesi che si riferisce allo stato preistorico, nel linguaggio omerico si riferisce a un sacrificio combinato di molti animali, particolarmente prezioso dal punto di vista economico e quindi gradito al dio, il che fa apparire la parola principalmente nel contesto di sacrifici di voto o di richiamo di riti già compiuti (dettagli → ἑκατόμβη). Quale ἑκατόμβη trascurata potrebbe essere in questione qui? André Corlu suggerisce che si tratta di un sacrificio impegnato in un voto, e quindi la parola sarebbe il complemento di εὐχωλή, "voto", ma la sintassi della frase greca non autorizza questa proposta. Dal punto di vista della narrazione epica, è importante notare che il motivo dell'hecatomb qui introdotto sarà ripreso da Kalchas, l'indovino degli Achei, che, dopo aver indicato la vera causa della crisi (l'insulto di Crise, sacerdote di Apollo), ordina che Crise sia rimandato da suo padre e che una hecatomb sia inviata con lei come forma di propiziazione rituale al dio (Il. 1.100). Il canto I dell'Iliade è l'unico posto in Omero dove l'hecatombe appare nella narrazione principale; è spesso riferito nelle dichiarazioni dei personaggi come un sacrificio promesso alla divinità in futuro (Il. 4.102, 120; 6.115, cfr. 6.93, 274; 23.146-8). 
                    </p>
                    <p>66:	ἀρνῶν κνίσης αἰγῶν τε τελείων… ἀντιάσας – "avendo accettato ... il grasso fumo sacrificale di montoni o capri maturi"; ἀντιάσας (part. aor. act.), letteralmente "essendo uscito per incontrare il fumo sacrificale"; il verbo → ἀντιάω, significa "uscire per incontrare", in riferimento agli dei è talvolta usato nel senso di "uscire per incontrare il fumo sacrificale, il sacrificio, l'hecatomb" > "accettare il sacrificio", Od. 1,25; 3,436 con commento, cfr. LfgrE, s.v. Traduzione di K. Jeżewska: "onorato con il sacrificio dei montoni e dei capri scelti" sposta l'accento sull'intenzione del popolo (adorare il dio), mentre il greco si concentra sulla risposta divina al segno dato dai mortali. 	
                        κνίση - "fumo grasso"; il sostantivo → κνίση significa sia "grasso" che "grasso (scil. fumo denso) e profumato" emanato dalla parte destinata agli dei bruciata sull'altare; in senso stretto, è la membrana grassa del peritoneo in cui venivano avvolti i femori come parte destinata agli dei e bruciata sull'altare (Ekroth 2007; Forstenpointner, Galik, Weissengruber 2013); metonimicamente, come → μηρία, può significare 'sacrificio' (→ κνίση). Sul significato di grasso come sostanza di vita (life-stuff) con citazione di versi omerici, vedi Onians (1951) 279 ff.
                    </p>
                </div>
                
              
                
                <div type="textpart" n="Iliad_1.92–100 ">
                    <head>Iliade 1.92–100 </head>
                    <p>Il bardo Kalchas fa una diagnosi per spiegare le cause del presente stato di cose, per rispondere alla domanda di cosa Apollon incolpa (ἐπιμέμφεται) gli Achei. Kalchas come mantide "conosce ciò che era, ciò che è e ciò che sarà" (ὃς ᾔδη τά τ᾽ ἐόντα τά τ᾽ ἐσσόμενα πρό τ᾽ ἐόντα, Il. 1. 69), riconosce quindi lo stato presente, rivela la causa passata della rabbia di Apollo (94: ἕνεκ᾽ ἀρητῆρος ὃν ἠτίμησ᾽ Ἀγαμέμνων, "a causa del sacerdote che Agamennone non ha onorato") e dà un possibile futuro: o gli Achei onorano il sacerdote e il dio, o Apollon continuerà a mandare sofferenza. E anche se la causa dell'ira del dio non era la trascuratezza dei sacrifici, il suo rovesciamento richiede una catomba. Vedi Kaufman (1979) 44-45."</p>
                    <quote>οὔτ ἄρ᾽ ὅ γ᾽ εὐχωλῆς ἐπιμέμφεται οὐδ᾽ ἑκατόμβης,			
                       <lb/> ἀλλ᾽ ἕνεκ᾽ ἀρητῆρος ὃν ἠτίμησ᾽ Ἀγαμέμνων, 
                        <lb n="95"/>  οὐδ᾽ ἀπέλυσε θύγατρα καὶ οὐκ ἀπεδέξατ᾽ ἄποινα,
                        <lb/>  τοὔνεκ᾽ ἄρ᾽ ἄλγε᾽ ἔδωκεν ἑκηβόλος ἠδ᾽ ἔτι δώσει· 
                        <lb/>   οὐδ᾽ ὅ γε πρὶν Δαναοῖσιν ἀεικέα λοιγὸν ἀπώσει 
                        <lb/>   πρίν γ᾽ ἀπὸ πατρὶ φίλῳ δόμεναι ἑλικώπιδα κούρην 
                        <lb/>    ἀπριάτην ἀνάποινον, ἄγειν θ᾽ ἱερὴν ἑκατόμβην 
                        <lb n="100"/>   ἐς Χρύσην· τότε κέν μιν ἱλασσάμενοι πεπίθοιμεν.
                        <p>App. crit.
                        εὐχωλῆς ἐπιμέμφεται schol. A., Eusth. Mazon: εὐχωλῆς ἔπι μέμθεται Leuman (1950) 71 i nast.</p>
                    </quote>
                    <quote>
                        <lb/>Non ci incolpa per il matrimonio o per la catomba, 			 
                        <lb n="95"/> ma a causa del sacerdote che Agamennone insultò, sua figlia non lo liberò, né accettò il riscatto,
                        <lb/> per questo Trafnostic ci ha dato tormento e continuerà a dare:
                        <lb/> e dal vergognoso destino dei danesi non si libererà prima,
                        <lb/> finché non diamo la ragazza dagli occhi scuri a suo padre
                        <lb/> libero, senza riscatto, e una catomba manderemo
                        <lb n="100"/> santo a Chryza. Con questo forse lo conquisteremo - lo propizieremo.
                    </quote>
                    <p>93:	οὔτ ἄρ᾽ ὅ γ᾽ εὐχωλῆς ἐπιμέμφεται οὐδ᾽ ἑκατόμβης / ἀλλ᾽ ἕνεκ᾽ ἀρητῆρος - "non ci rimprovera per le nozze o per la catomba, / ma per il prete ... Kalchas risponde alla domanda posta da Achille (v. 65), riprendendo esattamente le sue parole, tranne che per la sostituzione del participio interrogativo con un negativo. Indicando la causa specifica delle sofferenze inviate dal dio, l'indovino non parla più di una possibile negligenza o svista (espressa dal genitivo), ma di una colpa specifica che è il risultato dell'atto di Agamennone, così che la costruzione ἐπιμέμφεται + gen. rei nella domanda si completa con ἕνεκα, "perché" > "ci incolpa, ci accusa a causa di" (vedi Pulleyn 2000: 150).</p>
                    <p>94:	ἀλλ᾽ ἕνεκ᾽ ἀρητῆρος ὃν ἠτίμησ᾽ Ἀγαμέμνων - "ma a causa del sacerdote che Agamennone insultò"; L'insulto per non aver mostrato la dovuta riverenza al sacerdote di Apollo provoca una reazione del dio simile a quella che sarebbe la causa della disgrazia se il dio stesso fosse insultato (per negligenza). La giusta relazione tra gli esseri umani è basata sul mostrare la dovuta riverenza (τιμή); anche gli dei hanno la loro τιμαί connessa con la distribuzione tra loro dei loro propri campi d'azione (cfr. Il. 15.189, h.Dem. 86; h.Aphr. 37, Hes.Th. 73, 112, 393, 425-6, 885), e il popolo, offrendo sacrifici, gli fa → γέρας, un dono postumo, espressione materiale del culto (Il. 4.49-50, cfr. Il. 9.498; Od. 5.335). Su τιμή e γέρας, vedi Benveniste 1969 [2011]: 127-133, Rudhardt 1959: 57.</p>
                    <p>96: ἑκηβόλος - "Aptly-shot"; un epiteto di Apollon, nell'antichità inteso come "da-distanza-da-tiro" (ἑκάς "lontano" + "lanciare, scagliare, sparare"). I linguisti moderni spiegano la prima parte del composto con ἑκών, 'a volontà', e quindi dovrebbe essere tradotto come 'a volontà' > 'sparare accuratamente', che sottolinea l'inevitabilità di colpire il bersaglio scelto dalla divinità. Vedi Beekes EDG, s.v.  Cfr. Cook 1925: 1042-1043 e Chantraine, DEG, s.v.</p>
                    <p>99-100:	ἄγειν θ᾽ ἱερὴν ἑκατόμβην / ἐς Χρύσην - "(prima che) l'hecatomb sia inviato / sacro a Chryza"; dopo aver presentato una "diagnosi trascendentale" (Apollon manda la sofferenza sugli Achei a causa dell'insulto di Agamennone al sacerdote del dio), la mantide Kalchas presenta un piano per radunare il dio, per convincerlo a desistere da ulteriori vendette. Il ripristino di una relazione basata sulla charis richiede la resa della ragazza senza accettare un riscatto (poine) e il sacrificio di → hekatombe sull'altare del dio in Chrissae. L'hekatombe funziona quindi come un sacrificio propiziatorio. Il motivo dell'offerta di una hekatombe propiziatoria ad Apollo sarà uno dei temi principali del Canto I, il che fa sì che solo in questa parte dell'epica l'hekatombe appaia nella narrazione del narratore principale (Hitch 2009: 100-1). L'intero processo rituale, dalla selezione degli animali sacrificali al banchetto, sarà descritto su due piani narrativi: da un lato, ci saranno le dichiarazioni dei personaggi che ordinano la preparazione del sacrificio o annunciano l'intenzione di offrirlo, e dall'altro, la descrizione delle azioni presentate dal narratore principale, l'aojda. </p>
                    <p>100b: τότε κέν μιν ἱλασσάμενοι πεπίθοιμεν - "con questo possiamo conquistarlo - propiziarlo": il verbo → ἱλάσκομαι, 'alleviare sforzarsi di ottenere favore, gentilezza', indica la natura propiziatoria della catomba, come sottolineato dalla sua ripetizione in tutto il primo canto ogni volta che viene menzionata l'intenzione del sacrificio ad Apollon (Il. 1.100; 147; 386; 444; 472). Il verbo deriva da i.e. *si-sḷh2-sḱe/o- (reduplicato inchoate), "lottare per il favore del dio, per la riconciliazione" > "offrire una preghiera" (Orm. alač'em, "prego"), vedi Klingenschmitt 1970: 75-88. Nell'epica omerica il complemento è sempre la divinità (Il. 1.100; 147; 386; 444; 472; 6.380; 385; Od. 3.419; cfr. Hes. Op. 338), che sembra corrispondere al significato religioso arcaico conservato in armeno alač'em, 'prego' (cioè * sḷh2-sḱe/o-). </p>
                    
                </div>
                
                <div type="textpart" n="Iliad_1.141–147">
                    <head>Iliade 1.141–147</head>
                    <p>Agamennone, come comandante di tutti gli Achei, ordina, in accordo con la sentenza di Kalchas, la deposizione della catomba e la resa di Crisippo. Agamennone traduce la raccomandazione generale del bardo in ordini dati in prima persona plurale (subiectivus hortativus). I verbi sono disposti in due coppie, la prima delle quali inizia gli esametri dopo la cesura (spingiamo giù - raccogliamo, ἐρύσσομεν - ἀγείρομεν), la seconda gli esametri successivi (poniamo - entriamo, θείομεν - βήσομεν). Procede poi a scegliere il capitano della nave e il capo del pellegrinaggio, il che è espresso dall'uso del modo imperativo di terza persona ("lasciatelo stare", ἔστω). Alla fine Agamennone si rivolge ad Achille stesso: "o tu Pelida [...], che ci rendi un tiratore preciso offrendo sacrifici".</p>
                    <quote>.
                        <lb/>νῦν δ᾽ ἄγε νῆα μέλαιναν ἐρύσσομεν εἰς ἅλα δῖαν, 				
                        <lb/>ἐν δ᾽ ἐρέτας ἐπιτηδὲς ἀγείρομεν, ἐς δ᾽ ἑκατόμβην 
                        <lb/> θείομεν, ἂν δ᾽ αὐτὴν Χρυσηΐδα καλλιπάρῃον 
                        <lb/>  βήσομεν· εἷς δέ τις ἀρχὸς ἀνὴρ βουληφόρος ἔστω, 
                        <lb n="145"/>    ἢ Αἴας ἢ Ἰδομενεὺς ἢ δῖος Ὀδυσσεὺς
                        <lb/>   ἠὲ σὺ Πηλεΐδη πάντων ἐκπαγλότατ᾽ ἀνδρῶν, 
                        <lb/>  ὄφρ᾽ ἥμιν ἑκάεργον ἱλάσσεαι ἱερὰ ῥέξας.
                    </quote>
                    <quote>
                        <lb/>  Ora spingiamo la nave nera verso il mare splendente, 			
                        <lb/> raduniamo tutti i marinai di cui abbiamo bisogno e facciamo una catomba
                        <lb/> mettiamo a bordo, e infine, portiamo la stessa Criseide
                        <lb/> portiamo dentro. Che un marito seduto in consiglio diventi comandante:
                        <lb n="145"/> Ayas o Idomeneo, o il divino Odisseo,
                        <lb/> o, tu Pelido, tra tutti gli uomini il più terribile,
                        <lb/> in modo che tu ci possa sovrastare con un sacrificio.
                    </quote>
                    <p>142-3: ἐς δ᾽ ἑκατόμβην / θείομεν - "hecatomb / mettiamo (a bordo)"; Agamennone, come comandante in capo degli eserciti achei, ordina di mettere a bordo l'hecatomb. Il poeta non presta attenzione alla scelta degli animali sacrificali (specie, numero), il che sembra suggerire che il comandante o l'esercito abbia a disposizione delle mandrie, dalle quali può in qualsiasi momento scegliere un gruppo adatto al sacrificio. Date le dimensioni della nave, la catomba scelta per Apollon non poteva essere composta da un grande gregge.</p>
                    <p>144: εἷς δέ τις ἀρχὸς ἀνὴρ βουληφόρος ἔστω - 'lascia che un uomo seduto in consiglio diventi comandante'; Agamennone rimarrà nell'accampamento, e delega la sua autorità di 'signore dei sacrifici' al comandante scelto della spedizione Crisa (Hitch 2010: 169-170). Odisseo, arrivando a Chryza, sottolineerà che viene mandato da Agamennone (Il. 1.442). Il leader dovrebbe essere un marito "che serve con consiglio" (βουληφόρος, letteralmente "portare consiglio"), che sottolinea la natura conciliante e politica del messaggio. L'epiteto denota i membri dell'élite che prendono decisioni durante le discussioni del consiglio, compreso il capo (Il. 2.24; 61). </p>
                    <p>147: ὄφρ᾽ ἥμιν ἑκάεργον ἱλάσσεαι ἱερὰ ῥέξας - "affinché tu faccia offerte propiziatorie a noi del Diletto"; di nuovo, il verbo ἱλάσκομαι (vedi sopra, commento al verso 100) indica la natura propiziatoria della catasta.
                        ἱερὰ ῥέξας - 'aver fatto un sacrificio'; una frase chiave nella terminologia sacrificale omerica (Casabona 1966: 6-7; 39-58). Nella prima epica, un aggettivo di genere neutro → ἱερὰ, "sacrificio (letteralmente, "ciò che è sacro, consacrato") come complemento del verbo → ἔρδω, "fare, fare", appare un totale di 16 volte, di cui 4 nell'Iliade (Il. 1.147; 9.357; 11.307, 327) e 10 nell'Odissea (Od. 1.61; 3.5, 159; 4.473; 5.102; 7.191; 11.130; 23.277). Qui deve essere inteso come una serie di azioni che compongono il rituale del sacrificio animale, il che permette di tradurlo con 'fare un sacrificio' (Casabona 1966: 50). Nell'ulteriore sviluppo della lingua, il verbo ἔρδω arrivò a significare "fare un sacrificio" indipendentemente dall'uso del complemento ἱερὰ. 
                    </p>
                    
                </div>
                
              
                
                <div type="textpart" n="Iliad_1.308–317 ">
                    <head>Iliade 1.308–317 </head>
                    <p>Quando la disputa di Achille con Agamennone si conclude con il ritiro di Achille dalla battaglia, Agamennone procede ad attuare le risoluzioni prese in assemblea. La narrazione del narratore principale ripete le formulazioni di Agamennone dai vv. 141-147 con trasformazioni significative. Nei vv. 141-147, in cui parla Agamennone stesso, i comandi erano espressi in 1os. Qui, presentando l'attuazione di questi comandi, il poeta usa costantemente la terza persona singolare, che sottolinea l'autorità di Agamennone come leader e sacrificatore. Mentre in precedenza Agamennone lasciava aperta la questione del numero di marinai e del loro comandante ("raduniamo tanti marinai quanti ce ne servono", "che un uomo abile nelle decisioni sia il comandante"), ora la scelta è stata fatta: l'hecatomb e la Criseide saranno portate alla Criseide da venti rematori scelti, e il loro comandante sarà Ulisse. </p>
                    <quote>
                        <lb/>    Ἀτρεΐδης δ᾽ ἄρα νῆα θοὴν ἅλα δὲ προέρυσσεν, 				
                        <lb/>    ἐν δ᾽ ἐρέτας ἔκρινεν ἐείκοσιν, ἐς δ᾽ ἑκατόμβην 
                        <lb n="310"/>    βῆσε θεῷ, ἀνὰ δὲ Χρυσηΐδα καλλιπάρῃον
                        <lb/>    εἷσεν ἄγων· ἐν δ᾽ ἀρχὸς ἔβη πολύμητις Ὀδυσσεύς.   
                        <lb/>       Οἳ μὲν ἔπειτ᾽ ἀναβάντες ἐπέπλεον ὑγρὰ κέλευθα, 
                        <lb/>    λαοὺς δ᾽ Ἀτρεΐδης ἀπολυμαίνεσθαι ἄνωγεν· 
                        <lb/>    οἳ δ᾽ ἀπελυμαίνοντο καὶ εἰς ἅλα λύματα βάλλον, 
                        <lb n="315"/>    ἕρδον δ᾽ Ἀπόλλωνι τεληέσσας ἑκατόμβας
                        <lb/>    ταύρων ἠδ᾽ αἰγῶν παρὰ θῖν᾽ ἁλὸς ἀτρυγέτοιο· 
                        <lb/>    κνίση δ᾽ οὐρανὸν ἷκεν ἑλισσομένη περὶ καπνῷ.
                    </quote>
                    <quote>
                        <lb/>    Atreides, invece, ha spinto la nave instabile in mare,					
                        <lb/> ha scelto venti canottieri e ha catombato
                        <lb n="310"/> per il dio, e poi Chryside la bella
                        <lb/> ha portato. L'astuto Odisseo salì (sulla nave) come comandante.
                        <lb/> Quando questi, dopo essersi imbarcati, navigarono lungo la rotta umida.
                        <lb/> Atreides ordinò al popolo di lavarsi (della macchia):
                        <lb/> questi si sono lavati, nel mare hanno gettato la loro sporcizia,
                        <lb n="315"/> e ad Apollon offrirono perfette hecatombies
                        <lb/> di tori e capre sulle rive del mare sterile.
                        <lb/> L'odore del grasso raggiunse il cielo arricciando il fumo del sacrificio.
                    </quote>
                  <p>     309:	ἐς δ᾽ ἑκατόμβην / βῆσε θεῷ - '[Agamennone] hecatomb introdotto per il dio'; cfr. ἐς δ᾽ ἑκατόμβην / θείομεν - 'hecatomb / luogo'. (a bordo), Il. 1.143-4. Agamennone, come comandante in capo degli Achei, sorveglia personalmente l'imbarco dell'equipaggio, del carico e della Criseide. A differenza dei rematori, il cui numero è specificato, il numero di animali che compongono l'hekatombe non è specificato. La parola è hekatombe qui usata in funzione di colettivo, cioè un termine che denota una collezione, un insieme composto da parti, in questo caso un gruppo di animali destinati a un sacrificio cerimoniale.</p>
                  <p>      313: λαοὺς δ᾽ Ἀτρεΐδης ἀπολυμαίνεσθαι ἄνωγεν - "Atreides ordinò all'esercito di lavarsi"; gli studiosi si chiedono se questo si riferisca a un rito speciale di pulizia dalla macchia religiosa causata dalla peste, o a un normale lavaggio rituale prima del rito del sacrificio. Tuttavia, il rituale del sacrificio iniziava con il lavaggio delle mani, che era denotato dal termine tecnico χερνίπτομαι. Nel frattempo, Agamennone ordina a tutto l'esercito di lavarsi, il che indica la gravità della macchia e la necessità di misure speciali. L'epica non descrive rituali di purificazione per rimuovere la macchia, ma in situazioni eccezionali gli eroi si lavano dalla sporcizia del campo di battaglia prima di procedere al rito (Ettore, Il. 6.266-8). L'ipotesi di speciali rituali di purificazione è supportata anche da paralleli del Vicino Oriente, come sottolineato da Burkert 1997: 62. R. Parker sostiene erroneamente che il rituale di purificazione fu ordinato da Kalchas come indovino (guaritore-servo), vedi Parker 1983: 210. L'ordine è dato da Agamennone stesso, che è apparentemente dotato della conoscenza della necessità della purificazione prima del rito, ma non ha bisogno di fare riferimento alla competenza di un indovino specializzato. Sul ruolo di Agamennone, vedi Hitch 2009: 78. Paradossalmente, il capo del popolo, la cui azione ha portato alla rovina, è il primo a ordinare al popolo di fare purificazioni (Haubold 2000: 51-52).
                        314: οἳ δ᾽ ἀπελυμαίνοντο καὶ εἰς ἅλα λύματα βάλλον - "questi si lavarono, nel mare gettarono sporcizia"; gettando sporcizia (λύματα - acqua sporca? vestiti sporchi?) nel mare sembra avere le sue controparti nei rituali del Vicino Oriente (Burkert 1992: 62; West 2008 [1996]: 97) e anticipare le successive pratiche di purificazione greche, vedi Morb. Sacr. 148.43-6: "I resti delle purificazioni li nascondono poi nella terra, li gettano in mare, o li portano sulle montagne, dove nessuno li tocca o li calpesta (traduzione di Przemyslaw Biernat)". La parola τὸ λῦμα (τὰ λύματα) significa "tutto ciò che può essere lavato via con acqua (o altro liquido)", "acqua dei piatti", "sporco". E' usato in una varietà di contesti, inclusi quelli in cui non si tratta certamente di alcuna macchia rituale (Il. 14.171).In un contesto rituale, si tratta di una macchia che può essere rimossa da pratiche rituali appropriate. "In contrasto con l'appannamento (μίασμα), che è il risultato del crimine, un disturbo dell'ordine divino (ὅσιον) e corrisponde - in un'altra dimensione psicologica - all'azione nociva della potenza divina (ἄγος), τὸ λῦμα è il risultato di azioni che sono in accordo con questo ordine ma che deteriorano lo stato di purezza (ἁγνεία)" (Rudhardt 1958: 48).
                        315-6: ἕρδον δ᾽ Ἀπόλλωνι τεληέσσας ἑκατόμβας / ταύρων ἠδ᾽ αἰγῶν παρὰ θῖν᾽ ἁλὸς ἀτρυγέτοιο - "e ad Apollon offrirono in perfetto hecatomb / di tori e capri sulla riva del mare sterile"; il sacrificio offerto da Agamennone, a differenza dell'hecatomb inviato a Chryza, non fu annunciato all'assemblea. Agamennone agisce quindi come un capo dotato di autorità religiosa, che si manifesta nel suo potere di decidere se eseguire i riti appropriati. Tuttavia, l'offerta del sacrificio ad Apollo prima che Odisseo raggiunga Chryza e la resa di Chryseis preoccupa gli interpreti (vedi Kirk, comm. ad loc.). F.S. Naiden sottolinea la mancanza di menzione dell'accettazione di questo sacrificio da parte del dio (Naiden 2013: 111). 	
                            ἕρδον [...] τεληέσσας ἑκατόμβας - 'deposero in perfetta hecatomb'; la frase ἔρδω + ἡκατόμβην, 'deporre in hecatomb', compare 23 volte nell'epica omerica: 11 volte nell'Iliade (1.315; 444; 2.306; 4.102; 120; 8.550; 9.535-6; 23. 146, 206, 864, 873) e 12 volte nell'Odissea (3.144; 4.352, 478, 582, 5.102, 7.202; 11.132, 12.344; 13.350; 17.51, 60; 23.279), cfr. Casabona 1966: 52. Ciò significa che ἡκατόμβην è il complemento più frequente del verbo ἔρδω, che in totale era usato in senso religioso in 47 luoghi. Su hekatombe, vedi sopra (commento a Il. 1.33-43). 
                            ταύρων ἠδ᾽ αἰγῶν - "di tori e capre"; vedi sopra, commento al v. 41.</p>
                        
                    <p>        317: 	κνίση δ᾽ οὐρανὸν ἷκεν ἑλισσομένη περὶ καπνῷ – 'il fumo grasso raggiunse il cielo turbinando intorno al fumo del sacrificio'; il verso rappresenta vividamente il momento chiave del rituale, la combustione della parte divina sull'altare - intorno al fumo che sale al cielo (presumibilmente dai ceppi bruciati) turbina κνίση, l'odore del grasso (e delle ossa) bruciate per il dio (cfr. Il. 1.66).Come per i sacrifici menzionati dai personaggi dell'epica, il rituale è definito metonimicamente in questa descrizione dalla combustione di grasse zampe posteriori, e il narratore si concentra sull'invio spettacolare di un segno visibile al dio - il fumo derivante dalle zampe posteriori bruciate avvolte in una membrana peritoneale grassa
                        Altrove nell'Iliade il fumo è portato via dal vento (8.549), vedi Naiden 2013: 111-112. </p>
                </div>
                
                <div type="textpart" n="Iliad_1.384–390 ">
                    <head>Iliade 1.384–390 </head>
                    <p>Su ordine di Agamennone gli eroi presero Briseis dalla tenda di Achille. Privato del suo dono d'onore, l'insultato Achille si allontanò dai suoi compagni e chiamò la sua madre divina, Teti, sulla riva del mare. Quando lei emerse dagli abissi e chiese la causa delle sue lacrime, Achille raccontò la storia di aver fatto prigioniera Crisippa, di averla data ad Agamennone durante la divisione del bottino, di aver respinto la supplica di Crisippa per la restituzione di sua figlia e della peste inviata da Apollon. Poi raccontò a sua madre gli eventi del giorno in cui ebbe una disputa con Agamennone. Questo lungo riassunto degli eventi raccontati in dettaglio nei versi precedenti dal narratore principale può essere una sorpresa. Presumibilmente questo è ciò che Aristarco pensava quando atetizzò l'intero passus 366-92 (cfr. Kirk 1984: 91). Tuttavia, la ripetizione è giustificata perché gli eventi chiave di Achille che legano la trama dell'Iliade dalla prospettiva di un attore di eventi, che si riflette in trasformazioni specifiche della narrazione.</p>
                    <quote>
                        <lb/>      ἄμμι δὲ μάντις 
                        <lb n="385"/>      εὖ εἰδὼς ἀγόρευε θεοπροπίας ἑκάτοιο. 					
                        <lb/>      αὐτίκ᾽ ἐγὼ πρῶτος κελόμην θεὸν ἱλάσκεσθαι· 
                        <lb/>      Ἀτρεΐωνα δ᾽ ἔπειτα χόλος λάβεν, αἶψα δ᾽ ἀναστὰς 
                      <lb/>  ἠπείλησεν μῦθον ὃ δὴ τετελεσμένος ἐστί·  
                        <lb/>      τὴν μὲν γὰρ σὺν νηῒ θοῇ ἑλίκωπες Ἀχαιοὶ
                        <lb n="390"/>       ἐς Χρύσην πέμπουσιν, ἄγουσι δὲ δῶρα ἄνακτι·				
                        <lb/>       τὴν δὲ νέον κλισίηθεν ἔβαν κήρυκες ἄγοντες 
                        <lb/>       κούρην Βρισῆος τήν μοι δόσαν υἷες Ἀχαιῶν.  
                    </quote>
                    <quote>
                        <lb/>Wieszczek
                        <lb n="385"/> il benefattore ha annunciato i verdetti nel caso Trafnostrzelny.		
                        <lb/> Poi sono stato il primo a chiamare per propiziare il dio.
                        <lb/> Allora il figlio di Atreo fu preso dall'ira e si alzò violentemente
                        <lb/> Ha incluso le minacce nel comando, che in effetti è adempiuto.
                        <lb/> Perché lì gli astuti achei su una nave volatile
                        <lb n="390"/> mandano a Chryza, portando doni per il Signore.					
                        <lb/> Con questo gli eredi sono appena partiti dalla mia tenda, avendo rapito
                        <lb/> la figlia di Bryzes, che i figli degli Achei mi avevano dato.
                    </quote>
                    <p>385: ἀγόρευε θεοπροπίας ἑκάτοιο - "pronunciò oracoli in materia di Tracia"; la parola θεοπροπίας riecheggia la frase εἰπὲ θεοπρόπιον ὅ τι οἶσθα, "dì l'oracolo che conosci", detta da Achille a Kalchas (Il. 1.85). Il sostantivo θεοπροπία (r.s.) significa probabilmente 'oracolo', anche se la sua etimologia è contestata. Il primo elemento, θεο-, significa divinità, e originariamente si riferiva a un'esperienza miracolosa, straordinaria, un'epifania estatica o profetica (cfr. Burkert 1997). L'elemento -προπ- è molto probabilmente legato al verbo πρέπω "apparire chiaramente", "diventare prominente", "spiccare" "essere visibile", "apparire". È quindi un gruppo di parole che denota la rivelazione delle cause divine e nascoste degli eventi e dei fenomeni.  Secondo un'altra ipotesi, meno probabile, l'elemento -προπ- deriva dalla radice *pre/ok "una richiesta rivolta agli dei per ricevere un dono indicato" ed è legato al latino precor, "chiedere", "fare richiesta", "rivolgersi" (nella preghiera), "pregare", Pol. La forma originale *θεοπροκος avrebbe dovuto subire un'assimilazione progressiva (trasformando la 'k' in 'p'), cfr. Pulleyn 2000: 147. </p>
                    <p>386: αὐτίκ᾽ ἐγὼ πρῶτος κελόμην θεὸν ἱλάσκεσθαι - 'allora fui io il primo a chiamare per propiziare il dio'; la rappresentazione della sequenza degli eventi non è esatta - Achille ammise di aver parlato per primo e di aver chiamato per chiedere al bardo la causa della rabbia di Apollon (v. 62-5) e si offrì di fare un sacrificio per scongiurarlo (v. 66-7), ma fu Kalchas a presentare una via d'uscita dalla crisi, il ritorno di Crisippo e il sacrificio di una hecatomb che potesse propiziare (→ ἱλάσκομαι) il dio e indurre la fine della peste (vv. 97-100), e la diagnosi del bardo fu approvata da Agamennone; inoltre, prima che scoppiasse la disputa, Agamennone identificò Achille come un potenziale comandante di una nave che portava animali sacrificali per il dio (v. 147). Achille omette così interamente il suo duro discorso contro Agamennone, dando l'impressione che la rabbia di Agamennone sia stata provocata da una chiamata per propiziare Apollo. </p>
                    <p>390: ἄγουσι δὲ δῶρα ἄνακτι - "portano doni al Signore"; la hecatomb menzionata in precedenza (v. 99, 142, 309) è stata descritta come "doni (→ δῶρα)" al dio.</p>
                    
                </div>
                
                <div type="textpart" n="Iliad_1.423–425 ">
                    <head>Iliade 1.423–425 </head>
                    <p>Teti non può presentare immediatamente la richiesta a Zeus perché il dio si trova con gli Etiopi ad una festa. Il motivo della permanenza del dio presso gli Etiopi come spiegazione della sua assenza dall'Olimpo appare anche all'inizio dell'Odissea (1,22-25, cfr. Il. 23,205-7). Su questo motivo nella prima canzone, vedi Scodel 2007.</p>
                    <quote>
                        <lb/>Ζεὺς γὰρ ἐς Ὠκεανὸν μετ᾽ ἀμύμονας Αἰθιοπῆας
                        <lb/>χθιζὸς ἔβη κατὰ δαῖτα, θεοὶ δ᾽ ἅμα πάντες ἕποντο· 
                        <lb/>  δωδεκάτῃ δέ τοι αὖτις ἐλεύσεται Οὔλυμπονδέ
                    </quote>
                    <quote>
                        <lb/>Per Zeus su Okeanos agli Etiopi senza macchia
                        <lb/>Ieri è andato a una festa e tutti gli dei lo hanno seguito;
                        <lb/> il dodicesimo giorno verrà di nuovo sull'Olimpo
                    </quote>
                    
                    <p>423-4: Ζεὺς γὰρ ἐς Ὠκεανὸν... ἔβη κατὰ δαῖτα - "Poiché Zeus sopra Okeanos... andò a banchettare"; sullo scudo di Achille, Efesto raffigurò Okeanos come un fiume che circonda la terra piatta e raggiunge la volta celeste (Il. 18.607-8). Nell'immaginario arcaico del mondo, Okeanos era anche il dio del fiume cosmico che dava vita a tutto ciò che esiste; risiedeva ai confini della terra con sua moglie, Teti (Il. 14.201, 246, 302). L'assenza di Zeus sull'Olimpo significa che le sue richieste non lo raggiungono (nel caso di Teti - lei non può andare dal dio in persona). Sembra che il popolo utopico degli Etiopi banchetti con gli dei, come l'umanità nei tempi prima della sua separazione dagli dei immortali. Il sacrificio è una forma di comunicazione con gli dei quando la comunione diretta è diventata impossibile. 
                        μετ᾽ ἀμύμονας Αἰθιοπῆας - "agli Etiopi senza macchia"; gli Etiopi si trovano solitamente nelle zone orientali di confine della terra (cfr. Mimnermos, fr. 12.9 West; Aesch. Prom. 809). Il re degli Etiopi, Memnon era il figlio della dea dell'alba, Eos (Hes. Theog. 984-5). Il primo autore a collocarli a sud dell'Egitto è Ecataios (FGrHist 1 F 325-8 con commento di F. Jacoby).
                    </p>
                   
                </div>
                
                <div type="textpart" n="Iliad_1.430–431,436–474 ">
                    <head>Iliade 1.430–431, 436–474 </head>
                    <p>L'offerta dell'hecatomb ha lo scopo di porre fine alla peste causata da Apollon come vendetta per l'insulto al sacerdote Chryses. Il ripristino del corretto rapporto degli Achei con il dio richiede la restituzione della figlia di Crise al sacerdote e l'offerta del sacrificio prescritto, durante il quale il sacerdote revoca la sua precedente richiesta. La sposa e gli animali vengono portati su delle navi dagli inviati dell'esercito acheo guidato da Odisseo. Nel rituale stesso il ruolo del sacrificatore (sacrificante) è svolto da Crise, i sacrificatori per conto dei quali il sacrificio sarà offerto sono gli Achei. Cfr. Hitch 2009: 80-81; Muellner 1976: 32-33 (preghiera di Crise).
                        
                    </p>
                    <quote>
                        <lb n="430"/>αὐτὰρ Ὀδυσσεὺς						
                        <lb/>    ἐς Χρύσην ἵκανεν ἄγων ἱερὴν ἑκατόμβην. 
                        <lb/>    [...]
                        <lb/>    ἐκ δ᾽ εὐνὰς ἔβαλον, κατὰ δὲ πρυμνήσι᾽ ἔδησαν· 			
                        <lb/>      ἐκ δὲ καὶ αὐτοὶ βαῖνον ἐπὶ ῥηγμῖνι θαλάσσης, 
                        <lb/>       ἐκ δ᾽ ἑκατόμβην βῆσαν ἑκηβόλῳ Ἀπόλλωνι· 
                        <lb/>       ἐκ δὲ Χρυσηῒς νηὸς βῆ ποντοπόροιο.    
                        <lb n="440"/>       τὴν μὲν ἔπειτ᾽ ἐπὶ βωμὸν ἄγων πολύμητις Ὀδυσσεὺς 		
                        <lb/>      πατρὶ φίλῳ ἐν χερσὶ τίθει καί μιν προσέειπεν· 
                        <lb/>      ὦ Χρύση, πρό μ᾽ ἔπεμψεν ἄναξ ἀνδρῶν Ἀγαμέμνων 
                        <lb/>      παῖδά τε σοὶ ἀγέμεν, Φοίβῳ θ᾽ ἱερὴν ἑκατόμβην 
                        <lb/>      ῥέξαι ὑπὲρ Δαναῶν ὄφρ᾽ ἱλασόμεσθα ἄνακτα, 
                        <lb n="445"/>      ὃς νῦν Ἀργείοισι πολύστονα κήδε᾽ ἐφῆκεν.   			
                        <lb/>      Ὣς εἰπὼν ἐν χερσὶ τίθει, ὃ δὲ δέξατο χαίρων 
                        <lb/>      παῖδα φίλην· τοὶ δ᾽ ὦκα θεῷ ἱερὴν ἑκατόμβην  
                        <lb/>      ἑξείης ἔστησαν ἐΰδμητον περὶ βωμόν, 
                        <lb/>    χερνίψαντο δ᾽ ἔπειτα καὶ οὐλοχύτας ἀνέλοντο. 
                        <lb n="450"/>    τοῖσιν δὲ Χρύσης μεγάλ᾽ εὔχετο χεῖρας ἀνασχών· 			
                        <lb/>       κλῦθί μευ ἀργυρότοξ᾽, ὃς Χρύσην ἀμφιβέβηκας 
                        <lb/>      Κίλλάν τε ζαθέην  Τενέδοιό τε ἶφι ἀνάσσεις· 
                        <lb/>        ἦ μὲν δή ποτ᾽ ἐμεῦ πάρος ἔκλυες εὐξαμένοιο, 
                        <lb/>         τίμησας μὲν ἐμέ, μέγα δ᾽ ἴψαο λαὸν Ἀχαιῶν· 
                        <lb n="455"/>        ἠδ᾽ ἔτι καὶ νῦν μοι τόδ᾽ ἐπικρήηνον ἐέλδωρ· 			
                        <lb/>        ἤδη νῦν Δαναοῖσιν ἀεικέα λοιγὸν ἄμυνον.
                        <lb/>        Ὣς ἔφατ᾽ εὐχόμενος, τοῦ δ᾽ ἔκλυε Φοῖβος Ἀπόλλων. 
                        <lb/>        αὐτὰρ ἐπεί ῥ᾽ εὔξαντο καὶ οὐλοχύτας προβάλοντο, 
                        <lb/>        αὐέρυσαν μὲν πρῶτα καὶ ἔσφαξαν καὶ ἔδειραν, 
                        <lb n="460"/>        μηρούς τ᾽ ἐξέταμον κατά τε κνίσῃ ἐκάλυψαν 			
                        <lb/>         δίπτυχα ποιήσαντες, ἐπ᾽ αὐτῶν δ᾽ ὠμοθέτησαν· 
                        <lb/>         καῖε δ᾽ ἐπὶ σχίζῃς ὁ γέρων, ἐπὶ δ᾽ αἴθοπα οἶνον 
                        <lb/>            λεῖβε· νέοι δὲ παρ᾽ αὐτὸν ἔχον πεμπώβολα χερσίν. 
                        <lb/>         αὐτὰρ ἐπεὶ κατὰ μῆρε κάη καὶ σπλάγχνα πάσαντο, 
                        <lb n="465"/>           μίστυλλόν τ᾽ ἄρα τἆλλα καὶ ἀμφ᾽ ὀβελοῖσιν ἔπειραν,  		
                        <lb/>         ὤπτησάν τε περιφραδέως, ἐρύσαντό τε πάντα. 
                        <lb/>          αὐτὰρ ἐπεὶ παύσαντο πόνου τετύκοντό τε δαῖτα 
                        <lb/>          δαίνυντ᾽, οὐδέ τι θυμὸς ἐδεύετο δαιτὸς ἐΐσης. 
                        <lb/>        αὐτὰρ ἐπεὶ πόσιος καὶ ἐδητύος ἐξ ἔρον ἕντο, 
                        <lb n="470"/>       κοῦροι μὲν κρητῆρας ἐπεστέψαντο ποτοῖο,				
                        <lb/>    νώμησαν δ᾽ ἄρα πᾶσιν ἐπαρξάμενοι δεπάεσσιν· 
                   <lb/>     οἳ δὲ πανημέριοι μολπῇ θεὸν ἱλάσκοντο 
                        <lb/>     καλὸν ἀείδοντες παιήονα κοῦροι  Ἀχαιῶν 
                        <lb/>μέλποντες ἑκάεργον· ὃ δὲ φρένα τέρπετ᾽ ἀκούων.  
                        
                        <p>App. crit. 
                        ἱερὴν Zen Ar cf. [99] P.S.I.13 (Pack2 608 s. V); [431] P.Berol. inv. 7507 (Pack2 871; s. I: 11, 101–6)</p>
                    </quote>
                    <quote>
                        <lb/>Nel frattempo, Odisseo 430
                        <lb/> ha raggiunto Chryza, conducendo una santa hecatomb.
                        <lb/> [...]
                        <lb/> Hanno gettato le pietre dell'ancora e hanno legato gli ormeggi di poppa,  	
                        <lb/> E scesero sulla riva del mare,
                        <lb/> Hanno atterrato una hecatomb per l'Apollonio,
                        <lb/> Finalmente la Crisalide uscì dalla nave che navigava
                        <lb n="440"/> Poi conducendola verso l'altare, il pensieroso Odisseo, 
                        <lb/> la diede nelle braccia del suo caro padre, e così gli disse:
                        <lb/> "Crise, sono stato mandato qui dal signore degli uomini Agamennone,
                        <lb/> per portarti un bambino, e a Febo una sacra hecatomb
                        <lb/> di fare per i danesi, per vincere il Signore, 
                        <lb n="445"/> che ora affligge gli Argivi con terribili calamità".		
                        <lb/>Così disse, e nelle mani di suo padre diede la ragazza. Con gioia
                        <lb/> Ha ricevuto la figlia amata. Fecero presto una santa catomba 
                        <lb/> Intorno all'altare ben costruito misero in ordine il dio.
                        <lb/> Quando si lavarono le mani e presero l'orzo sacrificale,
                        <lb n="450"/> Per loro Chryses pregò ad alta voce, alzando le braccia:	
                        <lb/> "Ascoltami, argentiere, cosa ti importa di Crisi,
                        <lb/> e il trascendente Killa, e regnare con potenza su Tenedos!
                        <lb/> Se tu hai prima ascoltato la mia supplica, per la grazia
                        <lb/> mi hai mostrato tanto distruggendo le tribù degli Achei,
                        <lb n="455"/> ora ascolta anche me ed esaudisci la mia supplica:			
                        <lb/> scongiura già ora la vergognosa condanna del popolo di Danay".
                        <lb/> Così parlò, supplicando. Fojbos Apollon lo ascoltò.
                        <lb/> Dopo aver pregato e gettato l'orzo sacrificale,
                        <lb/> prima hanno deviato (le gole) e l'hanno macellato e scuoiato,
                        <lb n="460"/> hanno tagliato le gambe e le hanno coperte di grasso (della membrana peritoneale) 
                        <lb/> avvolto su entrambi i lati, su questi hanno messo pezzi di carne cruda.
                        <lb/> Il vecchio li bruciò su un ceppo e con vino scuro
                        <lb/> lo cosparse, e i giovani accanto a lui tenevano in mano uno spiedo con cinque lame
                        <lb/> Quando le gambe furono bruciate e le viscere assaggiate,
                        <lb n="465"/> hanno tritato il resto e l'hanno infilato negli spiedini, 
                        <lb/> Li arrostivano con cura e poi li toglievano dagli spiedi.
                        <lb/> Quando si erano riposati dopo la loro fatica e avevano preparato un banchetto,
                        <lb/> hanno banchettato, e nulla mancava al cuore di un banchetto uguale.
                        <lb/> Quando ebbero placato la loro sete con le bevande e la loro fame con il cibo
                        <lb n="470"/> i giovani riempirono le mescite fino all'orlo di bevande, 
                        <lb/> e dopo aver versato la libagione, la versarono in tutti i vasi.
                        <lb/> E tutto il giorno con un canto di preghiera cercavano di vincere il dio
                        <lb/> cantano splendidamente i pajan, i giovani achei,
                        <lb/> lodando il trace, ed egli si rallegrò nell'ascoltare.
                    </quote>
                    <p>430–6:	navigare verso Chryza. Dal punto di vista del linguaggio poetico, la descrizione dell'arrivo di Odisseo a Crisa è caratterizzata dalla tipicità delle scene e dei motivi oltre che dalla formularità (cfr. Schipp 1972: 296 ss.; Kirk 1985, ad loc.). La navigazione di Odisseo con la catomba a Crisa è unica rispetto all'ambientazione terrestre dell'azione dell'Iliade, il che fa sì che le formule usate per descriverla trovino i loro equivalenti nel linguaggio dell'Odissea (es. Il. 1.432 = Od. 16.324). La frase introduttiva dell'episodio inizia a metà dell'esametro (... αὐτὰρ Ὀδυσσεὺς) e si concentra sul trasporto delle hekatombe (ἄγων ἱερὴν ἑκατόμβην), omettendo in partenza la presenza a bordo dei Crisidi. </p>
                    <p>436-9: scendere a terra e sbarcare gli animali sacrificali. Il quadruplice uso enfatico di ἐκ all'inizio degli esametri successivi è un'epanafora che crea uno stato d'animo di spostamento frettoloso del carico della nave pur mantenendo l'ordine (Kirk 1985: 100): lo sbarco dell'equipaggio, lo spostamento degli animali sacrificali (ἐκ δ᾽ ἑκατόμβην βῆσαν) e lo sbarco del Criside formano una sorta di processione diretta all'altare di Apollo. </p>
                    <p>440: 	τὴν μὲν ἔπειτ᾽ ἐπὶ βωμὸν ἄγων πολύμητις Ὀδυσσεὺς - "poi conducendola verso l'altare, pensieroso Odisseo"; poiché l'hecatomb è depositata nel recinto sacro di Apollon Sminteus, il narratore menziona costantemente l'altare (cfr. w. 448). Nella seconda scena estesa tipica dell'Iliade (2,402-432), quando il sacrificio viene offerto da Agamennone nel campo degli Achei, il narratore tace sull'altare. </p>
                    <p>442: πρό μ᾽ ἔπεμψεν ἄναξ ἀνδρῶν Ἀγαμέμνων; il poeta sottolinea costantemente il ruolo di Agamennone come sacrificatore, signore del sacrificio nella terminologia della scienza tedesca (Opferherr). Nel discorso di Odisseo, la sua autorità è sottolineata dalla formula epica ἄναξ ἀνδρῶν Ἀγαμέμνων (vedi Hitch 2009: 81; 141 ss.).</p>
                    <p>442-443:	Φοίβῳ θ᾽ ἱερὴν ἑκατόμβην / ῥέξαι ὑπὲρ Δαναῶν ὄφρ᾽ ἱλασόμεσθα ἄνακτα - "e a Phoebos la sacra hecatomb / per fare riguardo ai Danayani, che possiamo vincere il signore"; per l'espressione ἔρδω + ἑκατόμβην, vedi. Casabona 1966: 52. </p>
                    <p>447-468: scena tipica - sacrificio di sangue. La descrizione più estesa del sacrificio animale nell'Iliade è una scena tipo elaborata che contiene quasi tutti gli elementi rituali inclusi nelle elaborate rappresentazioni di scene di sacrificio nella narrazione principale dell'epica. Le varianti che appaiono in ogni scena tipo sono giustificate dal contesto narrativo. L'hekatombe sacrificata per Apollo è un rituale eseguito sull'altare del tempio, con il sacerdote come sacrestano e gli Achei come sacrificatori</p>
                    <p>447-448: θεῶι κλειτὴν ἑκατόμβην... ἔστησαν ἐΰδμητον περὶ βωμόν - 'posero il dio attorno ad un altare ben costruito una famosa hecatomb'; la posa in un cerchio di animali sacrificali appare in scene tipiche, cfr. Il. 2.410a: βοῦν δὲ περιστήσαντο - "hanno messo in giro i buoi"; Od. 356a: τὰς δὲ περιστήσαντο. Cfr. la variante nella descrizione del sacrificio di maiale offerto da Eumayos, dove invece di un altare abbiamo ἔσχαρη, "focolare, fuoco", e un solo animale rende impossibile l'ambientazione: τὸν μὲν ἔπειτ᾽ ἔστησαν ἐπ᾽ ἐσχάρῃ - "lo misero vicino al fuoco" (Od. 14.420). I due avverbi sottolineano che una volta portati al luogo del sacrificio, gli animali sacrificali sono sistemati rapidamente (ὦκα) e "nel giusto ordine" (ἑξείης), presumibilmente per evitare confusione, tumulto all'altare. La giustapposizione della morte violenta sul campo di battaglia con la violenza ordinata e controllata del sacrificio è uno dei tratti distintivi della visione epica del mondo, vedi Seaford 1993. 
                        ἐΰδμητον περὶ βωμόν - 'intorno a un altare ben costruito'; per l'espressione cfr. Od. 7.100 (fuori dal contesto sacrificale). 
                  </p>
                    <p>449:	χερνίψαντο δ᾽ ἔπειτα καὶ οὐλοχύτας ἀνέλοντο – "quando si furono lavati le mani e presero l'orzo sacrificale"; verso formulare (= Il. 2.410); vi compaiono termini tecnici arcaici del vocabolario sacrificale: χερνίπτομαι e οὐλόχυται. 
                        χερνίψαντο - 'si lavarono le mani'; verbo → χερνίπτομαι, un termine tecnico formato dal sostantivo → χέρνιψ, 'acqua per lavarsi le mani', che nel contesto del sacrificio e della preghiera appare anche nella descrizione del sacrificio da parte di Nestore (Od. 3.440 e 445). Il lavaggio delle mani, come forma di pulizia rituale, era una condizione necessaria prima dei riti del sangue e del sacrificio liquido (Il. 6.266-8). Nell'Odissea, quando i nuovi arrivati si uniscono ai banchetti, vengono date loro interiora da assaggiare, vengono versate libagioni e si prega, ma non si fa menzione del lavaggio delle mani (vedi Od. 3.5 e seguenti). Fuori dal contesto sacrificale χέρνιψ significa acqua per lavarsi le mani (prima di un pasto: Od. 1.136; 4.52). Le pitture vascolari raffigurano il χέρνιψ come una ciotola con i vizi, cfr. la discussione in Athenaeus (Ath. 408b-9b, 9.75-6). Le ciotole fisse di purificazione in pietra appaiono nei santuari alla fine del VII secolo a.C. (Parker, 1983: 19-20). Sui rituali di apertura, vedi Ginouvès 1968: 313-4; Moulinier 1950 71-74; van Straten 1995: 31-40. </p>
                    <p>449b: καὶ οὐλοχύτας ἀνέλοντο - 'presero briciole/grano d'orzo'; verso formulare (= Il. 2.410b). Sebbene nell'Iliade non si faccia menzione del cesto in cui il grano veniva portato nel luogo in cui si svolgeva il rito, il verbo ἀνέλοντο - 'andarono a prendere' suggerisce l'esistenza di un contenitore in cui il grano veniva conservato; il grano sarà gettato sull'animale dopo che la preghiera ad Apollon è stata detta (v. 458). La parola → οὐλόχυται è un composto in cui il secondo elemento è l'aggettivo -χυτός, "versato, versato sopra" formato dal verbo χέω, "versare" (sui solidi), "versare", "ammassare", "spargere". J. Casabona lo vede come un aggettivo che denota → κριθαί - 'orzo'. Il significato dell'elemento οὐλο- è più difficile da stabilire; per analogia con, ad esempio, τεῖχος ἀμφίχυτον, si può supporre che esso specificasse il modo, lo scopo o il destinatario del gesto di spargere grani (Casabona 1966: 283). In Od. 3.441 e le fonti pohomeriche è stato sostituito dal sostantivo οὐλαί. Od. 3.444-5 collega direttamente l'uso dell'acqua per la purificazione e la presa dei chicchi d'orzo con l'inizio del rito sacrificale sull'altare (γέρων δ᾽ ἱππηλάτα Νέστωρ / χέρνιβά τ᾽ οὐλοχύτας τε κατήρχετο - "il vecchio, il cavaliere Nestore / cominciò con l'acqua e l'orzo"). I compagni di Odisseo, quando dovevano fare un sacrificio in un luogo dove non avevano accesso al grano, usano foglie di quercia invece di orzo (Od. 3.357-8: φύλλα δρεψάμενοι τέρενα δρυὸς ὑψικόμοιο- / οὐ γὰρ ἔχον κρῖ λευκὸν ἐϋσσέλμου ἐπὶ νηός, vedi comm. ad loc.). </p>
                    <p>450: τοῖσιν δὲ Χρύσης μεγάλ᾽ εὔχετο χεῖρας ἀνασχών - "e per loro Crise pregava ad alta voce alzando le braccia"; l'uso qui della costruzione εὔχομαι + dat. indica che Crise innalza una preghiera per gli Achei, revocando così una richiesta ad Apollo di punirli a causa di sua figlia (Pulleyn 2002). Nel verso 458 il verbo εὔχομαι è usato al plurale, suggerendo che la preghiera, anche se sollevata da un individuo, può essere stata vista come un atto collettivo, come altre azioni rituali. </p>
                    <p>458-469: La preghiera è seguita da versi formulari che saranno ripetuti nella scena di Il.2.421-432, che raffigura il sacrificio fatto da Agamennone, tranne i versi di Il.1.462-463, che si allontanano dallo schema comune in Il.2.425-426 ma ritornano nella scena del sacrificio di Nestore nell'Odissea (3.459-460). </p>
                    <p>458: αὐτὰρ ἐπεί ῥ᾽ εὔξαντο καὶ οὐλοχύτας προβάλοντο - 'quando avevano pregato e gettato l'orzo'; un verso formula che riassume i riti introduttivi che accompagnano la preghiera (= Il. 2.421 = Od. 3.447; cfr. variante in Od.12.359: αὐτὰρ ἐπεί ῥ᾽ εὔξαντο καὶ ἔσφαξαν καὶ ἔδειραν). Il formulare emistico αὐτὰρ ἐπεί ῥ᾽ εὔξαντο è usato solo in un contesto sacro in scene tipiche - il sacrificio animale - il che esclude l'interpretazione laica del verbo εὔχομαι, che qui non significa semplicemente "pronunciare ad alta voce parole solenni" ma più specificamente "pregare, elevare una preghiera". Su questo verbo si veda Benveniste 1968; Muellner 1976 (il luogo in questione è analizzato alle pp. 31-37).	οὐλοχύτας προβάλοντο - "gettarono orzo"; in Od. 3.446 il lavaggio delle mani, la dispersione dell'orzo e la bruciatura dei capelli tagliati sono indicati come riti primordiali, azioni che precedono la macellazione rituale. Nelle fonti successive, i partecipanti al rito gettano l'orzo nel fuoco acceso sull'altare, sull'animale sacrificale o sui partecipanti al rito. W. Burkert (1972: 5) ha interpretato il lancio di grani contro un animale come un gesto di aggressione, indicando rituali in cui si lanciavano pietre invece di grani. F. Graf, d'altra parte, ha richiamato l'attenzione sulla specie di grano utilizzata - l'orzo era considerato un cereale coltivato dall'uomo nei tempi primitivi (Graf 2002: 121). </p>
                    <p>459a: αὐέρυσαν μὲν πρῶτα - "prima hanno deviato" (la gola dell'animale); (verso formula = Il. 2.422a) dopo che i riti preliminari sono stati compiuti, i partecipanti al rito procedono alla macellazione rituale. Nelle descrizioni epiche della macellazione dell'animale sacrificale c'è una sequenza fissa di azioni, ma le singole scene focalizzano l'attenzione su elementi selezionati. La sequenza nella sua forma più completa sarebbe: "(1) stordimento dell'animale, (2) macellazione, (3) scuoiatura, (4) rifilatura, (5) lavorazione della carne". Anche se è un elemento costante delle scene di macellazione nell'epopea, tutti i suoi elementi non appaiono mai in un unico luogo. L'elemento (1) dello stordimento dell'animale, che si verifica nell'Odissea dando un colpo al collo dell'animale con un'ascia (bestiame) o una billetta (gregge), non appare nell'Iliade. Qui sono presenti tre elementi: (2), (3). Una sequenza più completa, composta da tre elementi: (2) macellare, (3) scuoiare e (5) fare la carne, è presente in Il. 24.622 e si ripete quasi alla lettera in Il. 7.314-316. Nella scena della macellazione e della preparazione della cena in Il. 18.559 (scudo di Achille) compaiono gli elementi (1) e (3); mentre in Il. 23.167 (2) e (3) a, Od. 8.61, 19.421 Questo non dovrebbe essere attribuito a differenze di rituale, ma al desiderio di Omero di essere breve nella descrizione. Il significato del verbo αὐέρυσαν è spiegato da Apollonio il Sofista (Lex. Hom.): εἰς τοὐπίσω εἵλκυσαν, 'hanno piegato all'indietro (il collo)' per tagliare la gola.
                        καὶ ἔσφαξαν - "e macellato"; verso formulare (= Il. 2.422). Il verbo → σφάζω appartiene al linguaggio tecnico del sacrificio. Come per la preghiera, il plurale non indica necessariamente il taglio della gola dell'animale da parte di un numero maggiore di partecipanti al rito. È possibile, tuttavia, che il plurale sottolinei la complicità di più persone nell'uccisione dell'animale. In Od. 3.454 la gola della mucca viene tagliata da Pejsistratos, ma la rappresentazione di un sacrificio privato, incentrato sulla complicità dei membri della famiglia di entrambi i sessi, ha reso necessario un maggiore dettaglio nella descrizione, vedi commento ad loc.  
                        καὶ ἔδειραν - "e scuoiarono"; l'epica omerica non menziona esplicitamente l'ulteriore destino della pelle estratta dall'animale, ma possiamo supporre che fu usata come materiale da ridistribuire ulteriormente. Cfr. fig. 23.144-151 con commento.
                    </p>
                    <p>460-461a: μηρούς τ᾽ ἐξέταμον κατά τε κνίσῃ ἐκάλυψαν/ δίπτυχα ποιήσαντες - "tagliarono le gambe e le nascosero nel grasso (membrane peritoneali) / su due lati avvolgenti"; versi formulari (= Il. 2, 427 = Od. 12, 364). Dopo aver scuoiato la carcassa dell'animale, i sacrificatori preparano la parte dedicata agli dei. L'espressione μηρούς τ᾽ ἐξέταμον - "hanno tagliato le gambe" (cfr. ἐκ μηρία τάμνον, con tesi, Od. 3.456), che ricorre solo in scene di tipo esteso, può essere tradotto come "tagliarono le gambe" (= ossa della coscia) dalla carne che le ricopre, o "tagliarono le gambe" (dal corpo). Si apre in scene tipiche con una disposizione ripetitiva di versi che descrivono la procedura di preparazione delle zampe posteriori (μηρούς) per il rogo (3x: Il. 1.464-5 = Il. 2.427-8 = Od. 12. 364-5): μηρούς τ᾽ ἐξέταμον κατά τε κνίσῃ ἐκάλυψαν / δίπτυχα ποιήσαντες, ἐπ᾽ αὐτῶν δ᾽ ὠμοθέτησαν, cf. la variante nella descrizione di Nestore dell'offerta ad Atena (Od. 3.456b-457, vedi commento ad. loc.): ἄφαρ δ᾽ ἐκ μηρία τάμνον / πάντα κατὰ μοῖραν, κατά τε κνίσῃ ἐκάλυψαν. Su κνίση vedi sopra, 1.60 con commento.</p>
                    <p>461b: ἐπ᾽ αὐτῶν δ᾽ ὠμοθέτησαν - "su di loro posarono pezzi di carne cruda"; (= Il. 2.424 = Od. 3.458 = Od. 12.424); verbo → ὠμοθετέω, composto dall'aggettivo ὠμός, "crudo", "non arrostito" (sulla carne) e θετέω, "disporre" (SlG.-P.: "deporre pezzi di carne sacrificale cruda sull'altare"). Il rituale è descritto in dettaglio in Od.14.427-8: ὁ δ᾽ ὠμοθετεῖτο συβώτης, / πάντων ἀρχόμενος μελέων, ἐς πίονα δημόν - "il porcaro depose i pezzi di carne cruda sulla sella grassa, offrendo un sacrificio primordiale di tutti i membri". Il significato del rituale non è chiaro. Secondo Karl Meuli (Meuli 1946: 306) e Walter Burkert (Burkert 1983: 6, 16), il rituale continua la tradizione dei cacciatori paleolitici che, offrendo particelle di prede uccise, assicuravano la sopravvivenza delle mandrie animali come risposta al senso di colpa. </p>
                    <p>462-4: Dopo aver preparato le parti per gli dei, il sacrificatore le brucia sull'altare, allo stesso tempo il giovane arrostisce → σπλάγχνα - 'viscere'. La divisione dei ruoli è chiaramente marcata: il vecchio sacerdote Chryses (ὁ γέρων) supervisiona il rogo dei femori avvolti nella membrana grassa del peritoneo e versa il vino sul fuoco, mentre i giovani arrostiscono sullo stesso fuoco d'altare le interiora rimosse dal peritoneo e il cuore, al posto del quale venivano inserite le ossa. </p>
                    <p>462:	καῖε δ᾽ ἐπὶ σχίζῃς – "bruciato su una lastra"; sostantivo → σχίζα, "lastra", "billetta", "legna da ardere"; poiché un altare è stato menzionato prima (448), possiamo supporre che le billette siano state usate metonimicamente qui al posto di altare (βωμός); cf. l'espressione πολλὰ δὲ μηρί᾽ ἔκηε θεῶν ἱεροῖσ᾽ ἐπὶ βωμοὶς - "numerosi femori ho bruciato sugli altari sacri degli dei", Od. 3.273. ὁ γέρων, ἐπὶ δ᾽ αἴθοπα οἶνον / λεῖβε - "bruciato il vecchio su una lastra, versato con vino frizzante". </p>
                    <p>463: νέοι δὲ παρ᾽ αὐτὸν ἔχον πεμπώβολα χερσίν - "e i giovani presso di lui tenevano in mano uno spiedo con cinque lame"; verso formulare (= Od. 3. 460); quando il sacrificatore cosparge la porzione bruciata destinata all'essere soprannaturale con un'offerta liquida di vino, i giovani partecipanti al rito abbrustoliscono nello stesso fuoco gli organi interni dell'animale impalati su spiedini a cinque lame, → πεμπώβολα. Alcuni commentatori suggeriscono che l'oggetto descritto da Omero era simile alla forchetta dentata trovata al santuario di Apollo a Dendra, che misura 11,2 cm di lunghezza per 7,5 cm di larghezza. Cfr. Bruns, Archaeologia Homerica, vol. Q: 39, vedi anche Od. 3.460, West comm. ad loc.</p>
                    <p>464-6: versi formulari che descrivono le azioni che seguono il rogo rituale della parte destinata all'essere soprannaturale, il versamento di libagioni e la degustazione di pezzi di organi interni da parte dei partecipanti al rito. Nelle descrizioni omeriche del sacrificio animale combinato con un banchetto, l'attenzione del poeta si concentra sulla preparazione della parte dedicata agli dei e delle interiora, seguita dalla carne mangiata dagli umani. Queste descrizioni consistono in versi formulari, ma permettono un certo numero di varianti adattate al contesto e ai bisogni della narrazione, mentre la festa stessa è menzionata in versi formulari piuttosto stereotipati. Sulla preparazione di un pasto di carne dai sacrifici animali, vedi van Straten 1995: 144-153. </p>
                    <p>466: αὐτὰρ ἐπεὶ κατὰ μῆρ' ἐκάη καὶ σπλάγχνα πάσαντο - 'quando le gambe furono bruciate e assaggiarono le interiora'; un verso formulare (= Il. 2.427 = Od. 3.461 = Od. 12.364) che riassume la prima parte del rito. Il soggetto del verbo κατὰ... ἐκάη nella 3a persona ind. aor. passare. 3 sg. sono → μῆρα, un sostantivo collettivo arcaico usato come termine per i femori bruciati per gli dei, che può indicare un'origine antica della formula.
                        σπλάγχνα πάσαντο - 'assaggiarono le viscere'; il sostantivo collettivo σπλάγχνα, come μῆρα, è un termine tecnico usato nel contesto del rito del sacrificio animale (cfr. ἔγκατα, plurale tantum, cfr. pol. 'viscere'), che si spiega con la volontà di inquadrare le viscere come un insieme inseparabile di organi interni rimossi da un animale macellato. Sembra che questa simmetria non sia casuale: nella prima parte dei rituali che seguono la macellazione dell'animale, gli dei ricevono μῆρα e gli umani σπλάγχνα. Abbiamo visto che la combustione agli dei della porzione loro dovuta, la sua trasformazione in fumo (κνίση) è l'essenza del sacrificio inteso come un atto di comunicazione tra gli uomini e gli dei, significando metonimicamente il rito sacrificale stesso. Il rituale si svolge su un altare. Usando lo stesso fuoco, in cui il fumo dei tronchi bruciati si mescola a quello denso delle ossa e del grasso bruciati, il popolo prepara le parti dell'animale da mangiare sul posto, sull'altare stesso (fonti successive sottolineano che ancora caldo). Non c'è nessuna descrizione nell'epica che descriva in dettaglio gli organi inclusi nella σπλάγχνα. Aristotele nel suo trattato Sulle parti degli animali distingue: cuore, polmoni, fegato, milza e reni (De partibus animalium 664b-672b). Su σπλάγχνα, vedi Stengel 1910 [1970]: 73-78; Rudhardt 1958: 262, nota 8; Detienne 1977: 174-179; Durand 1979: 133-166 (specialmente 139-150); Berthiaume 1982: 60-61; van Straten 1995: 131-41 (specialmente 131-3); Ekroth 2008: 87-111 (specialmente 93-95).
                    </p>
                    <p>465–6:	μίστυλλόν τ᾽ ἄρα τἆλλα καὶ ἀμφ᾽ ὀβελοῖσιν ἔπειραν / ὤπτησάν τε περιφραδέως, ἐρύσαντό τε πάντα – "Tagliarono il resto e lo misero sugli spiedi, / Lo arrostirono con cura, e poi lo tirarono via tutto dagli spiedi": verso formulare (= Il. 2.428 = Il. 7.317 = Il. 24.623 = Od. 3.462 = Od. 12.365 = Od. 14.430). Nelle descrizioni omeriche, il pasto destinato agli umani consiste in pezzi di carne finemente tritati e abbrustoliti su spiedini, assomigliando così a degli spiedini (souvlaki). Nelle fonti successive, la carne viene anche preparata in calderoni come uno stufato. Appare poi un'opposizione tra splanchna arrostita e sarks bollita, vedi Detienne 1977: 174.</p>
                    <p>467: αὐτὰρ ἐπεὶ παύσαντο πόνου τετύκοντό τε δαῖτα - 'quando si erano riposati dopo la fatica e avevano preparato un banchetto': verso formulare (Il. 1.467 = Il. 2.430 = Il. 7.319, cfr. οἱ δ᾽ ἐπεὶ οὖν παύσαντο πόνου τετύκοντό τε δαῖτα, Od. 16.478 = 24.384).</p>
                    <p>468: δαίνυντ᾽, οὐδέ τι θυμὸς ἐδεύετο δαιτὸς ἐΐσης - "banchettarono, e nulla mancò al cuore di un uguale banchetto": verso formulaico (Il. 1.468 = Il. 1.602 = Il. 2.431 = Il. 7.320 = Il. 23.56 = Od. 16,479 = Od. 19.425; cfr. Il. 4.48 = Il. 24.69).</p>
                    <p>469: αὐτὰρ ἐπεὶ πόσιος καὶ ἐδητύος ἐξ ἔρον ἕντο - 'quando con la bevanda avevano sete e con il cibo saziavano la fame'; verso formulare (Il. 1.469 = Il. 2.432 = Il. 7.323 = Il. 9.92 = Il. 9.222 = Il. 13.638 = Il. 23.57 = Il. 24.227 = Il. 24.628; Od. 1,150 = Od. 3,67 = Od. 3,473 = Da. 4.68 = Da. 8.72 = Da. 8,485 = Da. 12.308 = Da. 14.454 = Da. 15.143 = Da. 15.303 = Da. 15.501 = Da. 16.55 = Da. 17.99 = Da. 24.489). Questa formula di chiusura molto frequente (Abschlussformel) segna la fine della prima parte della festa eroica, durante la quale i partecipanti alla festa soddisfano la loro sete e fame. Sembra che l'organizzazione del banchetto eroico presupponesse la simultaneità del mangiare e del bere. Chiudere il corso dell'intera festa soddisfacendo i bisogni biologici con una formula breve permette di concentrarsi su altre attività dei festeggiati, cfr. Arend 1933: 69-78 (soprattutto 70); Węcowski 2011: 184-5.</p>
                    <p>470: κοῦροι μὲν κρητῆρας ἐπεστέψαντο ποτοῖο - "i giovani riempirono i miscelatori fino all'orlo di bevande"; il vino veniva versato nei crateri (miscelatori) da giovani uomini (κοῦροι), membri dell'elite sociale piuttosto che giovani schiavi (cfr. Il. 9.175; Od. 1.148; Od. 3.339; Od. 21.271).</p>
                    <p>471: νώμησαν δ᾽ ἄρα πᾶσιν ἐπαρξάμενοι δεπάεσσιν - "e dopo che le libagioni furono versate in tutti i vasi": il significato di questa formula è stato spiegato da Paul Mazon (1937). Dopo la preparazione del cratere, i giovani, che fungevano da servitori, versavano alcune gocce di vino nella ciotola di ogni partecipante alla festa, che venivano poi, presumibilmente simultaneamente, versate come libagione dando inizio al bere insieme. Cfr. Węcowski 2011: 189.</p>
                    <p>472-5: il sacrificio e la successiva festa aristocratica non esauriscono le attività della giornata. Poiché il sacrificio procedette immediatamente dopo l'arrivo dei messaggeri, si può legittimamente chiedere il significato del pajan cantato e presumibilmente ballato dai giovani achei. Altrettanto sorprendente è l'uso del verbo ἱλάσκομαι, che era stato precedentemente associato all'offerta di una hecatomb. Ora, sebbene la catomba propiziatoria sia già stata accettata, il giovane acheo erige un inno propiziatorio, vedi Faraone 2015.</p>
                    <p>472: οἳ δὲ πανημέριοι μολπῇ θεὸν ἱλάσκοντο - e tutto il giorno con il canto di preghiera cercavano di vincere il dio: sia l'uso dell'aggettivo πανημέριοι, "lavorare tutto il giorno", sia il verbo ἱλάσκοντο nell'indicativus imperfecti che esprime la durata dell'azione, sottolineano la durata del canto rituale propiziatorio.  </p>
                    
                </div>
            </div>
            
            
            <div type="edition" xml:lang="en">
                <div type="textpart" n="intro">
                    <p>The Iliad is the story of the fatal anger (mēnis) of Achilles, insulted by Agamemnon, who deprived the hero of his bride Briseis - the gift of honour (geras) of the Achaeans, a visible sign of the honour due him (timē). Deprived of honour, Achilles withdrew from the battle and made a request to his mother, the goddess Thetis, to avenge the insult. Zeus' fulfilment of Thetis' request sets up the actual plot of the epic - the defeat of the Achaeans. 
                        The plot is thus based on events taking place on two planes - human and divine. At the level of mortal actors, the actions form a chain: violation of a norm (offence) - reaction (anger) - restoration of the norm (reconciliation). The action that violates the norm is the taking/abduction of the girl or the refusal to return her for ransom (apoina) , and reconciliation requires the return of the kidnapped. In the case of immortal actors (gods), an analogous sequence of actions (insult - vindictive anger - restoration) may be the response to a request contained in the prayer of an insulted mortal who presents his or her harm (violation of the norm) and invokes charis, the principle of reciprocity governing the relations of gods and humans. The wrath of the deity can be relieved by taking appropriate ritual action - making a sacrifice. Thus, in order to maintain proper relations with the immortals, appropriate sacrifices are offered on the altars belonging to the gods. They are understood as gifts - signs of due honour to the gods. Therefore, the prayers invoke the sacrifices offered in the past or foretell the sacrifices to be offered in the future, and neglecting the sacrifices may provoke the god's anger. The role of sacrifice in this dispute can be illustrated by the following diagram (based on Hitch 2009). 
                    </p><p>1-7 Invocation to the Muses. Summary of theme.</p>
                    <p>8-32 Insult of Chryses by Agamemnon - refusal of request to give up Chryses in exchange for ransom (apoina).</p>
                    <p> 33-42 Prayer of Chryses: request for vengeance supported by memory of past sacrifices made [Text 1].</p>
                    <p> 43-52 Apollon punishes the Achaeans - plague.</p>
                    <p> [53-305] Assembly of the Achaeans.</p>
                    <p> 59-67 Speech of Achilles: request for diagnosis: neglected hecatomb as possible cause of Apollon's wrath [Text 2].
                    </p><p> 92-100 'Transcendental diagnosis': the soothsayer Kalchas declares that it is not the neglected hecatomb that is the cause, but the insult of the priest: the devotion of Chrysippus and the laying down of the hecatomb can win over the god [Text 3].
                    </p> <p> 121-139 Beginning of Achilles' dispute with Agamemnon.</p>
                    <p> 140-147 Agamemnon decides to send an emissary with the hecatomb and Chrysippus [Text 4].</p>
                    <p> 148-305 Agamemnon announces the recapture of Briseis.</p>
                    <p> 306-307 Achilles retreats to the tents.</p>
                    <p> 308-311 Agamemnon sails a hecatomb ship to Chryza [Text 5a].</p>
                    <p>311-317 Agamemnon's order: washing the army of defilement; laying up the hecatomb [Text 5b].</p>
                    <p>318-356 The taking of Briseis from the tent of Achilles.</p>
                    <p>357-430a Conversation between Achilles and Thetis. Achilles' request to avenge the insult.</p>
                    <p>384-390 The surrender of Chrysippus and the sending of gifts (offerings) to Apollo involve the taking of a due gift (Briseis) from Achilles [Text 6].</p>
                    <p> 423-425 [Zeus at a feast with the Ethiopians] [Text 7].</p>
                    <p> 430a-474 Surrender of Chryseis to Chrysippus and offering of the hecatomb to Apollon in Chryseis - reconciliation sacrifice accepted [Text 8].</p>
                    <p> 475-487 Return of the messengers to the camp of the Achaeans.</p>
                    <p> 488-492 Achilles overwhelmed with anger (mēnis) remains in his tent.</p>
                    <p>It has been pointed out that the whole episode resembles in structure the Homeric hymn to Apollon the Delphic, in which the narrative part ends with the sacrifice and the establishment of worship. Christopher Faraone has put forward the hypothesis that the source of the beginning of the poem may be the hymn to Apollon Smintejski (Faraone 2015). If this was indeed the case, the narrative origins of the hymn should be sought in the Anatolian Song of Deliverance, which, according to Mary Bachvarova, underlies the episode (Bachvarova 2016). Accepting this hypothesis allows us to answer the question why the main theme, i.e. Achilles' anger triggered by his dispute with Agamemnon, precedes Agamemnon's insult of Apollo's priest, Chryses. Chryses arrives at the camp of the Achaeans with a plea for the return of his daughter abducted by Agamemnon; Agamemnon refuses and chases the supplicant away. The offended Chryses prays to Apollo Sminteus to avenge the injustice, recalling the memory of the sacrifices he made. The angry god, granting the priest's request, sends a plague, causing a crisis in the camp of the Achaeans. Achilles, speaking at an assembly of the army, expresses his assumption that the cause of the god's anger may be a neglected hecatomb or an unfulfilled vow. The real reason is revealed by the soothsayer who, making a transcendent diagnosis, points to the guilty party (Agamemnon) and presents a possible way of propitiating the god: the wrath of Apollon, provoked by Agamemnon, can be appeased by giving the Chryside to Chryses and offering the hecatomb to Apollon. The whole episode ends with a day-long ritual, unannounced beforehand, during which the Achaean youths dance and sing the propitiatory pajan. The appeasement of the god's anger is intertwined with the inflaming of the hero's anger.</p>
                    
                    
                 
                </div>
               
                  <div type="textpart" n="Iliad_1.33-43">
                    <head>Iliad 1.33–43 (modlitwa Chryzesa):</head>
                      <p>Passus contains the prayer of Apollon's priest, Chryses, who has come to the camp of the Achaeans with a request to hand over his daughter Chryses, Agamemnon's captive. Driven away by Agamemnon, he prays to Apollo on the seashore, crying out for vengeance for the suffering he has suffered. The location of the scene on the seashore emphasises Chryses' despair and loneliness (e.g. Il. 1.327, 350, 23-59, 24.12, cf. Edwards 1980: 8). The god's fulfilment of the request will become the cause of Achilles' dispute with Agamemnon, which will arouse Achilles' anger (mēnis) - the main theme of the epic. On Chryses' prayer see Aubriot-Sévin 1992: 219, 281-283, 304; Ausfeld 1903: 505 ff; Chapot, Laurot 2001: 31-32 (G1); Pulleyn 1997: 16; Pulleyn 2000: 132-136; Citron 1965: 88-89; Edwards 1980: 8-9; Lateiner 1997: 241 ff; Morrison 1991; Mueller 1976; Rabel 1988: 473 ff. ; Servais 1967: 415 ff; Thornton 1984, for the function of the Chryses motif in the construction of the Iliad as a whole, see Rabel 1988. The effects of Chryses' prayer will cease when Chryses surrenders to his father and propitiates Apollon with a hecatomb, but its further consequence will be the wrath of Achilles, see Wilson 2002: 40-53.</p>
                      
                       <quote>
                        <lb/>Ὣς ἔφατ’, ἔδεισεν δ’ ὃ γέρων καὶ ἐπείθετο μύθῳ· 				
                        <lb/>βῆ δ’ ἀκέων παρὰ θῖνα πολυφλοίσβοιο θαλάσσης·
                        <lb/>πολλὰ δ’ ἔπειτ’ ἀπάνευθε κιὼν ἠρᾶθ’ ὃ γεραιὸς   	
                        <lb/>    Ἀπόλλωνι ἄνακτι, τὸν ἠΰκομος τέκε Λητώ· 					
                        <lb/>    κλῦθί μευ ἀργυρότοξ᾽, ὃς Χρύσην ἀμφιβέβηκας 
                        <lb/>     Κίλλάν τε ζαθέην Τενέδοιό τε ἶφι ἀνάσσεις,  
                        <lb/>     Σμινθεῦ εἴ ποτέ τοι χαρίεντ᾽ ἐπὶ νηὸν ἔρεψα, 
                        <lb/>     ἢ εἰ δή ποτέ τοι κατὰ πίονα μηρί᾽ ἔκηα 						
                        <lb/>      ταύρων ἠδ᾽ αἰγῶν, τὸ δέ μοι κρήηνον ἐέλδωρ· 
                        <lb/>     τίσειαν Δαναοὶ ἐμὰ δάκρυα σοῖσι βέλεσσιν.  
                    </quote>
                    <quote>
                        <lb/>So he said. The old man was frightened and obeyed the command;
                        <lb/> he walked in silence along the shore of the loud sea;
                        <lb/> then walking alone the old man made earnest supplication: 
                        <lb/> "Apollon, O Lord, whom the beautiful-haired Leto bore!				
                        <lb/> Hear me, O silver-haired one, what carest thou for Chrys,
                        <lb/> and the holy Killa, and reign with power over Tenedos,
                        <lb/> Sminteus, if I have once pleasantly covered thee with a temple roof
                        <lb/> or if I once burned thee fat legs						
                        <lb/> bulls and goats - hear my entreaty now:
                        <lb/> avenge on the Danayas my tears with your arrows".
                    </quote>
                      <p>36: Ἀπόλλωνι ἄνακτι, τὸν ἠΰκομος τέκε Λητώ - "Apollon, O Lord, whom the beautiful-haired Leto bore!"; Chryses' prayer is an example of a three-part prayer structure: 1) an invocation to the god or goddess with added epithets and/or genealogy; 2) an argumentation (justification for the request) indicating the basis for the expected charis; 3) a request (Aubriot-Sévin 1992: 218 ff.; Muellner 1976: 27-28); it opens with a solemn hexameter invoking Apollon, with a formal invocation of the genealogy (cf. Il. 19.413; h.h.Apol. 178).</p>
                      <p>37-38: Chryses, rather than summoning Apollo with a series of epithets (cf. Achilles' prayer to Zeus, Il. 16.233-235), emphasises his association with specific places of worship in Troad.</p>
                      <p>39-40:	εἴ ποτέ τοι... τοι χαρίεντ᾽ ἐπὶ νηὸν ἔρεψα / ἢ... κατὰ πίονα μηρί᾽ ἔκηα - "if I once loved you I covered the temple with a roof or.... I burned the fat hind legs"; in the middle part of the prayer scheme Chryses uses the typical formula εἴ ποτέ τοι ("if I once..."): it is a matter of recalling acts indicative of the reverence shown to the deity in the past, which should now induce it to grant the request (Aubriot-Sévin 1992; Pulleyn 1997). Chryses cites two types of human action: the roofing of the temple and the offering of sacrifices. In both cases it is about actions which - as pleasing to God - win his kindness, graciousness, favour, i.e. charis. It is indicated by the adjective χαρίεντα defining the temple as "endowed with charis" - "conquering kindness, nice". (χαρίεντα... νηὸν). It can be assumed that animal sacrifices were perceived analogously. A direct connection between the concept of charis and the hind legs burnt on the altars is found in Od. 19.397 ('nice hind legs', κεχαρισμένα μηρία, cf. Ar. Pax 386) and Od. 16.184 ('nice offerings', κεχαρισμένα ... ἱρὰ). It is not a simple exchange based on the principle of do ut des, but a permanent relationship of generalized reciprocity (generalized reciprocity, M. Sahlins' term, see Sahlins 1972, ch. 5), that is, a relationship based on a permanent exchange in which one gives some good or service to another person without receiving anything immediately in return. This is because the recipient is expected to reciprocate later (on charis, Parker 2011; more extensively: Loew 1908; Latacz 1966: 78-98; Moussy 1966: 411-415; de Lamberterie 1978-79: 31-39). 
                          ἐπὶ νηὸν ἔρεψα - 'I covered the temple with a roof'; according to Walter Burkert, the wording may imply a repetition of both actions, which would suggest that Chryses covered the temple with a roof many times, perhaps each time he made the sacrifices mentioned in the prayer; this would therefore refer to a makeshift hut erected for the purpose of the festival (Burkert 2011 [1992]: 262). Alexander Ainan Mazarakis, on the other hand, believes that, however, the verb ἐρέφω here means 'to cover with tile' and uses Chryses' prayer to date the text of the epic, since the oldest examples of ceramic tile in Greece date from the early seventh century BC. (the temple of Apollo in Corinth, see Robinson 1984: 55-56; cf. Ainan Mazarakis 2000: 113, note 302). However, it seems that ἐρέφω simply means 'to cover, roof', not necessarily with tiles. Temple buildings appearing as early as the eighth century express the need to endow a deity with a home in which the deity, symbolised by the cult statue, will find shelter (cf. Coldstream 1977: 321). On the symbolic significance of the idea of protection and shelter in the Iliad, see Lynn-George 1993: 197-221.
                          κατὰ πίονα μηρί᾽ ἔκηα - 'I burned the fat hinds'; in the prayers, the mention of the burning of the hinds (→ μηρία) is a metonymic evocation of sacrifices fulfilled in the past (cf. Il. 8.240; Il. 15.373; Od. 4.764; Od. 17.241). Their recollection is linked to a request addressed to a supernatural being within a reciprocal relationship. Chryses recalls the sacrifices he himself once made (similarly Agamemnon in Il. 8.240: ἀλλ᾽ ἐπὶ πᾶσι βοῶν δημὸν καὶ μηρί᾽ ἔκηα - 'but on all (the altars) of the oxen fat and femurs I burned'; and Il. 15.373-374: ἢ βοὸς ἢ οἰὸς κατὰ πίονα μηρία καίων / εὔχετο νοστῆσαι - '[if] I prayed for the return home of the ox or sheep fat thighbones by burning them'). In the case where a character- occupying a lower social position, such as Eumaeus and Penelope- prays, he invokes sacrifices made in the past by the rightful host (in both cases Odysseus): Od. 17.240-242 (Eumaios); Od. 4.763-765 (Penelope). Characteristically, in all cases the burnt legs are described as fat (πίονα μηρία) or, in the case of Eumaeus' prayer, the fact that they are hidden in fat (καλύψας πίονι δημῷ) is emphasised. The burning (→ καίω) of femurs wrapped in fat (→ κνῖσα, less frequently: → δημός) produced a thick, fragrant smoke (→ κνῖσα).
                      </p>
                      <p>41: ταύρων ἠδ᾽ αἰγῶν - "bulls or goats"; the construction μηρία + ANIMAL NAME is quite frequent in the epic, the analysis showing a tendency to associate specific sacrificial animals with the god to whom they are sacrificed; the choice is therefore not entirely random, but fits into a pattern. It is noteworthy that also Agamemnon will later offer to Apollon the propitiatory τεληέσσας ἑκατόμβας / ταύρων ἠδ᾽ αἰγῶν - 'a perfect hecatomb of bulls and goats' (Il. 1.315). 	
                          ταύρων - "bulls"; word → ταῦρος "bull" (uncastrated), 'bull' may suggest a particularly valuable sacrifice, as castrated bulls were usually sacrificed. 	
                          αἰγῶν - 'goats'; it is difficult to clearly identify the sex of the goats, since the noun αἴξ can mean goat and goat (in Attic inscriptions - castrated, → αἴξ; uncastrated goat, cap, → τράγος does not occur in the Iliad, and in the Odyssey it appears only once: Od. 9.239). However, since it was the norm to sacrifice male individuals to male deities, the most appropriate translation is 'goats'.
                      </p>
                </div>
                
                <div type="textpart" n="Iliad_1.62–67">
                    <head>Iliad 1.62–67</head>
                    <p>The crisis situation (plague) that afflicted the Achaean army requires countermeasures. The procedure provides for the making of a "transcendental diagnosis" (W. Burkert's term) by a ritual specialist, an expert-mediator, i.e. a soothsayer (mantis), who, on the basis of the interpretation of signs and knowledge, determines the appropriate remedies and how to apply them (Burkert 1996: 103-128). The request for a transcendental diagnosis is made at the assembly by Achilles. From the way he formulates it, it appears that the most likely cause of the crisis could be a ritual error, a failure to fulfil an obligation to the gods (a vow, → εὐχωλή) or a neglect of a blood sacrifice (a hecatomb, → ἑκατόμβη), and that the renewal of a correct relationship with the gods should be accomplished by making a proper sacrifice (Casevitz 1992: 3-5).</p>
                    <quote>
                        <lb/>ἀλλ᾽ ἄγε δή τινα μάντιν ἐρείομεν ἢ ἱερῆα, 						
                        <lb/>ἢ καὶ ὀνειροπόλον, καὶ γάρ τ᾽ ὄναρ ἐκ  Διός ἐστιν, 
                        <lb/> ὅς κ᾽ εἴποι ὅ τι τόσσον ἐχώσατο  Φοῖβος  Ἀπόλλων, 
                        <lb n="65"/> εἴ ταρ ὅ γ᾽ εὐχωλῆς ἐπιμέμφεται ἠδ᾽ ἑκατόμβης, 				
                        <lb/>    αἴ κέν πως ἀρνῶν κνίσης αἰγῶν τε τελείων 
                        <lb/>  βούλεται ἀντιάσας ἡμῖν ἀπὸ λοιγὸν ἀμῦναι.
                    </quote>
                    <quote>
                        <lb/>Let us ask some soothsayer or priest,				
                        <lb/> or a dream interpreter - for from Zeus a dream - 
                        <lb/> who could tell why Phoebos Apollon was so angry.
                        <lb n="65"/> Does he find fault in us because of the failure to perform a vow or a hecatomb? 	
                        <lb/> Perhaps having accepted the fatty sacrificial smoke of the chosen rams or goats 
                        <lb/> decides to avert annihilation from us.
                    </quote>
                    <p>62-63: τινα μάντιν ἐρείομεν ἢ ἱερῆα, / ἢ καὶ ὀνειροπόλον - "some soothsayer let us ask either a priest, / or and interpreter of dreams"; a transcendental diagnosis can be made by a ritual specialist belonging to one of three (or two, see below) categories: → mantis ('diviner, soothsayer'), → hiereus ('priest'), → oneiropolos ('dream interpreter'). Verse 63 raised doubts among Alexandrian philologists. The first head of the Library, Zenodotos (c. 325 - c. 260 BC) athetizes (removes) it, probably considering the dream interpreter as a separate category of religious specialist, not directly related to the need to diagnose the causes of the crisis (cf. Kirk, ad loc.). Aristarchus (216 - 144 BC), on the other hand, puts a colon (comma) after ἐρείομεν, 'let us ask', which changes the meaning of the sentence: "let us ask some soothsayer: a priest or a dream interpreter" - according to this interpretation, the soothsayer (mantis) is the name of a general category, "a ritual specialist engaged in reading signs", while the priest (hiereus) and the dream interpreter (oneiropolos) are subcategories, specialists who read signs appearing during sacrifices or dreams. Note, however, that hiereus denotes an independent social role (Chaniotis 2008) and not a type of soothsayer (Pulleyn 2000: 142), although the two terms (plural) are juxtaposed in the epic (Il. 24.224). Michel Casevitz has recently argued that the word (mantis) is related to the verb μηνύω, 'to reveal what is hidden; to reveal' (Casevitz 1992). If we accept this hypothesis, it could be argued that also the root indicates that the original and primary function of manteis was to reveal the hidden causes of critical situations and thus to make a transcendental diagnosis. On the function of manteis in the epic, see Bremmer 1993, 171-6; Casevitz 1992; di Sacco 2000. The use of priests specialized in dream interpretation to solve problems by indicating the ritual necessary to solve them has parallels in the Babylonian religious system, see West (2008 [1996]) 88-89.</p>
                    <p>64:	ὅ τι τόσσον ἐχώσατο  Φοῖβος  Ἀπόλλων – "Why was Phoebos Apollon so angry": the right question to ask when carrying out a transcendental diagnosis. The verb χώομαι, "I am angry, I am wrathful" refers, of course, to the signs perceived by people - the plague is caused by the god's wrath, and the reversal of evil is possible only on the condition of discovering the cause of the anger. The emotions associated with anger are in absolute opposition to the emotions associated with the term χάρις, "grace, kindness, benevolence".</p>
                    <p>65: εὐχωλῆς ἐπιμέμφεται ἠδ᾽ ἑκατόμβης - "whether he finds fault with us because of the failure to fulfill a promise or a hecatomb"; since the verb ἐπιμέμφεται + gen. rei means "to blame, rebuke because of the lack or failure of something, to complain because of something" (Il. 2.225, cf. 226 ff., ph. 229), we can assume that Achilles is wondering whether the god's wrath was triggered by some failure in the sphere of communication with the gods. The verb ἐπιμέμφεται in this context is often translated as an emotional state ('to be angry'), but it is rather a verb with a legal tinge, which means a broad accusation of failure to fulfil some legitimate obligation. For the anger of the gods caused by a neglected sacrifice (Il. 5.177) cf. Latacz, Nünlist, Stoevesandt 2009: 52-3. 	
                        εὐχωλή - 'vow'; the word → εὐχωλή means a loud, solemnly spoken commitment to a god in return for expected help (Benveniste 1969). Since such a commitment was generally made during prayer, the word can be translated as 'vow, vow, pledge, promise' or 'prayer'. In this case, it seems that it is not an ill-formed request in prayer, but a failure to fulfil a promise (Corlu 1966: 157-158). An interesting alternative to "vow" in the Polish translation is the word "promise", which, although in modern Polish does not have sacral connotations, one should remember that it is related to the old name of "sacrifice" - obiata. In Old Polish "promise" was used to express a religious vow.	
                        ἑκατόμβη - "hekatomba"; the word → ἑκατόμβη is usually explained as a sacrifice "(made) of a hundred oxen, a hundredwolves" (cf. Homer, scholia vetera, ed. Erbse: ἑκατόμβη δὲ ἀπὸ τοῦ ἑκατὸν καὶ τοῦ βοῦς - "hekatomba: formed from "hundred" (hekaton) and "ox" (bous)"), but in the epic the word has now become lexicalised to mean "a large, valuable sacrifice" regardless of the number or species of animals (LfgrE s.v. ἑκατόμβη), and can therefore mean both a sacrifice of sheep and goats, fifty animals (Il. 23.146-8), or even just twelve heifers (Il. 6.93, cf. 6.115). The fact that, despite its clear structure, the word does not necessarily mean a sacrifice of a hundred oxen was already pointed out by ancient and Byzantine commentators (Eustathios, ad Il. 1.65, explains: θυσία ἐξ ἑκατὸν δηλονότι κυρίως βοῶν, καταχρησιτκῶς μέντοι καὶ ἡ ἐξ ἑκατὸν ζώων - 'a sacrifice, strictly speaking, of a hundred oxen, but in a wider sense also of a hundred animals'; The scholia add that ἑκατόμβη means "perfect sacrifices, τελείας θυσίας"). Paul Thieme put forward the hypothesis that the word originally meant an act aimed at winning the favour of the gods in order to obtain a hundred oxen (Thieme 1952: 62-76; cf. Pulleyn 2000: 143). Irrespective of the acceptance of this hypothesis referring to the prehistoric state, in Homeric language it refers to a feast-combined sacrifice of many animals, particularly economically valuable and thus pleasing to the god, which makes the word appear primarily in the context of vowing sacrifices or recalling rites already performed (details → ἑκατόμβη). What neglected ἑκατόμβη might be at issue here? André Corlu suggests that it is about a sacrifice pledged in a vow, and thus the word would be the complement of εὐχωλή, 'vow', but the syntax of the Greek sentence does not authorise this proposal. From the point of view of the epic narrative, it is important to note that the hecatomb motif introduced here will be taken up by Kalchas, the soothsayer of the Achaeans, who, after pointing out the real cause of the crisis (the insult of Chryses, priest of Apollo), orders Chryses to be sent back to his father and to send a hecatomb with her as a form of ritual propitiation to the god (Il. 1.100). Song I of the Iliad is the only place in Homer where the hekatomba appears in the main narrative; it is often referred to in character statements as a sacrifice promised to the deity in the future (Il. 4.102, 120; 6.115, cf. 6.93, 274; 23.146-8). 
                    </p>
                    <p>66:	ἀρνῶν κνίσης αἰγῶν τε τελείων… ἀντιάσας – "having accepted ... the fatty sacrificial smoke of rams or ripe goats"; ἀντιάσας (part. aor. act.), literally "having gone out to meet the sacrificial smoke"; the verb → ἀντιάω, means "to go out to meet", in reference to the gods it is sometimes used in the sense of "to go out to meet the sacrificial smoke, the sacrifice, the hecatomb" > "to accept the sacrifice", Od. 1.25; 3.436 with commentary, cf. LfgrE, s.v. Translation by K. Jeżewska: "honoured with the sacrifice of the chosen rams and goats" shifts the emphasis to the intention of the people (to worship the god), while the Greek focuses on the divine response to the sign given by mortals. 	
                        κνίση - "greasy smoke"; the noun → κνίση means both "fat" and "greasy (scil. dense) and fragrant smoke" emanating from the part intended for the gods burnt on the altar; strictly speaking, it is the fatty membrane of the peritoneum in which the femurs were wrapped as the part intended for the gods and burnt on the altar (Ekroth 2007; Forstenpointner, Galik, Weissengruber 2013); metonymically, like → μηρία, it can mean 'sacrifice' (→ κνίση). On the meaning of fat as a substance of life (life-stuff) with citation of Homeric verses, see Onians (1951) 279 ff.
                    </p>
                </div>
                
              
                
                <div type="textpart" n="Iliad_1.92–100 ">
                    <head>Iliad 1.92–100 </head>
                    <p>The bard Kalchas offers a diagnosis to explain the causes of the current state of affairs, to answer the question of what Apollon blames (ἐπιμέμφεται) the Achaeans for. Kalchas as mantis "knows what was, what is, and what will be" (ὃς ᾔδη τά τ᾽ ἐόντα τά τ᾽ ἐσσόμενα πρό τ᾽ ἐόντα, Il. 1. 69), therefore recognizes the present state, reveals the past cause of Apollon's anger (94: ἕνεκ᾽ ἀρητῆρος ὃν ἠτίμησ᾽ Ἀγαμέμνων, "because of the priest whom Agamemnon did not honour") and gives a possible future: either the Achaeans honour the priest and the god, or Apollon will continue to send suffering. And although the cause of the god's wrath was not the neglect of the sacrifices, its reversal requires a hecatomb. See Kaufman (1979) 44-45."</p>
                    <quote>οὔτ ἄρ᾽ ὅ γ᾽ εὐχωλῆς ἐπιμέμφεται οὐδ᾽ ἑκατόμβης,			
                       <lb/> ἀλλ᾽ ἕνεκ᾽ ἀρητῆρος ὃν ἠτίμησ᾽ Ἀγαμέμνων, 
                        <lb n="95"/>  οὐδ᾽ ἀπέλυσε θύγατρα καὶ οὐκ ἀπεδέξατ᾽ ἄποινα, 			
                        <lb/>  τοὔνεκ᾽ ἄρ᾽ ἄλγε᾽ ἔδωκεν ἑκηβόλος ἠδ᾽ ἔτι δώσει· 
                        <lb/>   οὐδ᾽ ὅ γε πρὶν Δαναοῖσιν ἀεικέα λοιγὸν ἀπώσει 
                        <lb/>   πρίν γ᾽ ἀπὸ πατρὶ φίλῳ δόμεναι ἑλικώπιδα κούρην 
                        <lb/>    ἀπριάτην ἀνάποινον, ἄγειν θ᾽ ἱερὴν ἑκατόμβην 
                        <lb n="100"/>   ἐς Χρύσην· τότε κέν μιν ἱλασσάμενοι πεπίθοιμεν.  			
                        <p>App. crit.
                        εὐχωλῆς ἐπιμέμφεται schol. A., Eusth. Mazon: εὐχωλῆς ἔπι μέμθεται Leuman (1950) 71 i nast.</p>
                    </quote>
                    <quote>
                        <lb/>He blames us not because of the wedding or the hecatomb, 			 
                        <lb n="95"/> but because of the priest whom Agamemnon insulted, his daughter did not release to him, nor did he accept the ransom, 
                        <lb/> for this Trafnostic has given us torment and will continue to give:
                        <lb/> and from the shameful doom of the Danes he will not first deliver,
                        <lb/> until we give the dark-eyed girl to her father
                        <lb/> free, not taking a ransom, and a hecatomb we shall send
                        <lb n="100"/> holy to Chryza. With this, perhaps, winning him over, we will propitiate him.
                    </quote>
                    <p>93:	οὔτ ἄρ᾽ ὅ γ᾽ εὐχωλῆς ἐπιμέμφεται οὐδ᾽ ἑκατόμβης / ἀλλ᾽ ἕνεκ᾽ ἀρητῆρος – "He does not blame us because of the wedding or the hecatomb, / but because of the priest..."; Kalchas answers the question asked by Achilles (v. 65), exactly repeating his words except for the replacement of the interrogative participle with a negative. By pointing to the specific cause of the sufferings sent by the god, the soothsayer is no longer speaking of a possible negligence or oversight (expressed by the genitive), but of a specific fault that is the result of Agamemnon's act, so that the construction ἐπιμέμφεται + gen. rei in the question is completed by ἕνεκα, "because" > "he blames us for, accuses us because of" (see Pulleyn 2000: 150).</p>
                    <p>94:	ἀλλ᾽ ἕνεκ᾽ ἀρητῆρος ὃν ἠτίμησ᾽ Ἀγαμέμνων - "but because of the priest whom Agamemnon insulted"; The insult by failing to show due reverence to the priest of Apollo provokes a reaction from the god similar to that which would be the cause of misfortune if the god himself were insulted (by negligence). The proper relationship between human beings is based on the showing of due reverence (τιμή); the gods too have their τιμαί connected with the distribution among them of their proper fields of action (cf. Il. 15.189, h.Dem. 86; h.Aphr. 37, Hes.Th. 73, 112, 393, 425-6, 885), and the people, by offering sacrifices, give them → γέρας, a posthumous gift, a material expression of worship (Il. 4.49-50, cf. Il. 9.498; Od. 5.335). On τιμή and γέρας, see Benveniste 1969 [2011]: 127-133, Rudhardt 1959: 57.</p>
                    <p>96: ἑκηβόλος - "Aptly-shot"; an epithet of Apollon, in antiquity understood as "from-distance-against/shooting" (ἑκάς "far" + "to throw, hurl, shoot"). Modern linguists explain the first part of the compound by ἑκών, 'at will', and thus it should be translated as 'at will' > 'accurately shooting', which emphasises the inevitability of hitting the deity's chosen target. See Beekes EDG, s.v.  Cf. Cook 1925: 1042-1043 and Chantraine, DEG, s.v.</p>
                    <p>99-100:	ἄγειν θ᾽ ἱερὴν ἑκατόμβην / ἐς Χρύσην - '(before) the hecatomb is sent / sacred to Chryza'; after presenting a 'transcendental diagnosis' (Apollon sends suffering on the Achaeans because of Agamemnon's insult of the god's priest), the mantis Kalchas presents a plan to rally the god, to persuade him to desist from further vengeance. The restoration of a relationship based on charis requires the surrender of the girl without accepting a ransom (poine) and the sacrifice of → hekatombe on the altar of the god in Chrissae. The hekatombe thus functions as a propitiatory sacrifice. The motif of offering a propitiatory hekatombe to Apollo will be one of the main themes of Song I, which makes it only in this part of the epic that the hekatombe appears in the narrative of the main narrator (Hitch 2009: 100-1). The whole ritual process from the selection of sacrificial animals to the feast will be described on two narrative planes: on the one hand, there will be the statements of the characters ordering the preparation of the sacrifice or announcing the intention to offer it, and on the other hand, the description of the actions presented by the main narrator, the aojda. </p>
                    <p>100b: τότε κέν μιν ἱλασσάμενοι πεπίθοιμεν - "with this we may win him over - propitiate him": the verb → ἱλάσκομαι, 'to alleviate strive to obtain favour, kindness', indicates the propitiatory nature of the hecatomb, as emphasised by its repetition throughout the first song whenever the intention of the sacrifice to Apollon is mentioned (Il. 1.100; 147; 386; 444; 472). The verb is derived from i.e. *si-sḷh2-sḱe/o- (reduplicated inchoate), "to strive for the favor of the god, for reconciliation" > "to offer a prayer" (Orm. alač'em, "I pray"), see Klingenschmitt 1970: 75-88. In Homeric epic the complement is always the deity (Il. 1.100; 147; 386; 444; 472; 6.380; 385; Od. 3.419; cf. Hes. Op. 338), which seems to correspond to the archaic religious meaning preserved in Armenian alač'em, 'I pray' (i.e. * sḷh2-sḱe/o-). </p>
                    
                </div>
                
                <div type="textpart" n="Iliad_1.141–147">
                    <head>Iliad 1.141–147</head>
                    <p>Agamemnon, as commander of all the Achaeans, orders, in accordance with Kalchas's ruling, the laying down of the hecatomb and the surrender of Chrysippus. Agamemnon translates the bard's general recommendation into orders given in the first person plural (subiectivus hortativus). The verbs are arranged in two pairs, the first of which begins the hexameters after the caesura (let us push down - let us gather, ἐρύσσομεν - ἀγείρομεν), the second the subsequent hexameters (let us place - let us enter, θείομεν - βήσομεν). He then proceeds to choose the captain of the ship and the leader of the pilgrimage, which is expressed by the use of the 3rd person imperative mode ("let him stay", ἔστω). At the end Agamemnon addresses Achilles himself: "or thou Pelida [...], that thou mayest make us an accurate-shooter by offering sacrifice".</p>
                    <quote>
                        <lb/>νῦν δ᾽ ἄγε νῆα μέλαιναν ἐρύσσομεν εἰς ἅλα δῖαν, 				
                        <lb/>ἐν δ᾽ ἐρέτας ἐπιτηδὲς ἀγείρομεν, ἐς δ᾽ ἑκατόμβην 
                        <lb/> θείομεν, ἂν δ᾽ αὐτὴν Χρυσηΐδα καλλιπάρῃον 
                        <lb/>  βήσομεν· εἷς δέ τις ἀρχὸς ἀνὴρ βουληφόρος ἔστω, 
                        <lb n="145"/>    ἢ Αἴας ἢ Ἰδομενεὺς ἢ δῖος Ὀδυσσεὺς 					
                        <lb/>   ἠὲ σὺ Πηλεΐδη πάντων ἐκπαγλότατ᾽ ἀνδρῶν, 
                        <lb/>  ὄφρ᾽ ἥμιν ἑκάεργον ἱλάσσεαι ἱερὰ ῥέξας.
                    </quote>
                    <quote>
                        <lb/>  Now let us push the black ship to the shining sea, 			
                        <lb/> let us gather as many sailors as we need and hecatomb
                        <lb/> let's put on board, and at last, let's bring Chryseis herself
                        <lb/> let us bring in. Let one husband sitting in council become commander:
                        <lb n="145"/> Ayas or Idomeneus, or the divine Odysseus, 
                        <lb/> or, thou Pelido, of all men most terrible,
                        <lb/> so that thou mayest give us a sacrifice to the Thracian.
                    </quote>
                    <p>142–3:	ἐς δ᾽ ἑκατόμβην / θείομεν – "the hecatomb / let us place (on board)"; Agamemnon, as commander-in-chief of the Achaean army, orders the hecatomb to be brought on board. The poet pays no attention to the choice of sacrificial animals (species, number), which seems to imply that the commander or the army has herds at its disposal, from which it can at any time choose a suitable bunch for sacrifice. Given the size of the ship, the hecatomb chosen for Apollon could not have consisted of a large flock.</p>
                    <p>144: εἷς δέ τις ἀρχὸς ἀνὴρ βουληφόρος ἔστω - 'let one man sitting in council become commander'; Agamemnon will remain in camp, and delegates his authority as 'lord of the sacrifices' to the chosen commander of the Chryza expedition (Hitch 2010: 169-170). Odysseus, on arriving at Chryza, will emphasise that he is coming sent by Agamemnon (Il. 1.442). The leader should be a husband "serving with advice" (βουληφόρος, literally "bringing counsel"), which emphasises the conciliatory and political nature of the message. The epithet denotes the members of the elite who make decisions during the council discussions, including the leader (Il. 2.24; 61). </p>
                    <p>147: ὄφρ᾽ ἥμιν ἑκάεργον ἱλάσσεαι ἱερὰ ῥέξας - "that thou mayest make propitiatory offerings to us of the Delightful One"; again, the verb ἱλάσκομαι (see above, commentary on verse 100) indicates the propitiatory nature of the hecatomb.
                        ἱερὰ ῥέξας - 'having made a sacrifice'; a key phrase in Homeric sacrificial terminology (Casabona 1966: 6-7; 39-58). In the early epic, an adjective of the neuter gender → ἱερὰ, 'sacrifice' (literally, "that which is sacred, consecrated") as a complement of the verb → ἔρδω, "to do, to make", appears a total of 16 times, of which 4 in the Iliad (Il. 1.147; 9.357; 11.307, 327) and 10 in the Odyssey (Od. 1.61; 3.5, 159; 4.473; 5.102; 7.191; 11.130; 23.277). Here it should be understood as a series of actions that make up the ritual of animal sacrifice, which allows it to be translated by 'to make a sacrifice' (Casabona 1966: 50). In the further development of the language, the verb ἔρδω began to mean 'to offer a sacrifice' independently of the use of the complement ἱερὰ. 
                    </p>
                    
                </div>
                
              
                
                <div type="textpart" n="Iliad_1.308–317 ">
                    <head>Iliada 1.308–317 </head>
                    <p>Gdy spór Achillesa z Agamemnonem zakończył się wycofaniem się Achillesa z walki, Agamemnon przystępuje do realizacji postanowień podjętych podczas zgromadzenia. Opowiadanie narratora głównego powtarza sformułowania Agamemnona z ww. 141–147 ze znaczącymi przekształceniami. W ww. 141–147, w których przemawia sam Agamemnon,  polecenia zostały wyrażone w 1os. l.mn., tutaj, przedstawiając realizację tych poleceń, poeta konsekwentnie używa 3os. l.poj., co podkreśla autorytet Agamemnona jako wodza i ofiarnika. O ile poprzednio Agamemnon kwestię liczby żeglarzy oraz ich dowódcy pozostawiał otwartą („ilu potrzeba żeglarzy zgromadźmy”, „niech jeden mąż biegły w decyzjach zostanie dowódcą”), teraz wybór został dokonany: hekatombę i Chryzejdę zawiezie do Chryzy dwudziestu wybranych wioślarzy, a ich dowódcą zostanie Odyseusz.</p>
                    <quote>
                        <lb/>    Ἀτρεΐδης δ᾽ ἄρα νῆα θοὴν ἅλα δὲ προέρυσσεν, 				
                        <lb/>    ἐν δ᾽ ἐρέτας ἔκρινεν ἐείκοσιν, ἐς δ᾽ ἑκατόμβην 
                        <lb n="310"/>    βῆσε θεῷ, ἀνὰ δὲ Χρυσηΐδα καλλιπάρῃον 					
                        <lb/>    εἷσεν ἄγων· ἐν δ᾽ ἀρχὸς ἔβη πολύμητις Ὀδυσσεύς.   
                 <lb/>       Οἳ μὲν ἔπειτ᾽ ἀναβάντες ἐπέπλεον ὑγρὰ κέλευθα, 
                        <lb/>    λαοὺς δ᾽ Ἀτρεΐδης ἀπολυμαίνεσθαι ἄνωγεν· 
                        <lb/>    οἳ δ᾽ ἀπελυμαίνοντο καὶ εἰς ἅλα λύματα βάλλον, 
                        <lb n="315"/>    ἕρδον δ᾽ Ἀπόλλωνι τεληέσσας ἑκατόμβας 					
                        <lb/>    ταύρων ἠδ᾽ αἰγῶν παρὰ θῖν᾽ ἁλὸς ἀτρυγέτοιο· 
                        <lb/>    κνίση δ᾽ οὐρανὸν ἷκεν ἑλισσομένη περὶ καπνῷ.
                    </quote>
                    <quote>
                        <lb/>    Atryda zaś lotny okręt zepchnął na morze,					
                        <lb/>      wybrał dwudziestu wioślarzy i hekatombę wprowadził
                        <lb n="310"/>       dla boga, a potem Chryzejdę pięknolicą						
                        <lb/>       przywiódł. Jako dowódca wstąpił (na okręt) przebiegły Odyseus.
                        <lb/>       Gdy ci, wstąpiwszy na okręt, wilgotnym szlakiem popłynęli.
                        <lb/>       Atryda rozkazał ludowi obmywać się (ze zmazy):
                        <lb/>      ci obmywali się, do morza brudy wrzucali,
                        <lb n="315"/>      i Apollonowi złożyli doskonałe hekatomby					
                        <lb/>      z byków i kozłów nad brzegiem nieurodzajnego morza.
                        <lb/>        Zapach tłuszczu dosięgnął nieba kręcąc się wokół dymu ofiary.
                    </quote>
                    <p>When Achilles' dispute with Agamemnon ends with Achilles' withdrawal from the battle, Agamemnon proceeds to implement the resolutions made at the assembly. The narrative of the main narrator repeats Agamemnon's formulations from vv. 141-147 with significant transformations. In vv. 141-147, in which Agamemnon himself speaks, the commands were expressed in 1os. Here, presenting the implementation of these commands, the poet consistently uses the 3rd person singular, which emphasises Agamemnon's authority as a leader and sacrificer. While previously Agamemnon left the question of the number of sailors and their commander open ("let us gather as many sailors as we need", "let one man who is proficient in decisions be the commander"), now the choice has been made: the hecatomb and the Chryseis will be taken to the Chryseis by twenty chosen rowers, and their commander will be Odysseus.
                        
                    </p>
                    <p>317: 	κνίση δ᾽ οὐρανὸν ἷκεν ἑλισσομένη περὶ καπνῷ – "the fat smoke reached the sky swirling around the smoke of the sacrifice"; the verse vividly depicts the key moment of the ritual, the burning of the divine part on the altar - around the smoke rising to the sky (presumably from the burned logs) swirls κνίση, the smell of fat (and bones) burned for the god (cf. Il. 1.66). As in the case of the sacrifices mentioned by the epic's characters, in this description too the ritual is metonymically defined by the burning of fatty hind legs, and the narrator focuses on the spectacular sending of a visible sign to the god - the smoke arising from the burnt hind legs wrapped in a fatty membrane of peritoneum. Elsewhere in the Iliad the smoke is carried away by the wind (8.549), see Naiden 2013: 111-112.</p>
                    
                </div>
                
                <div type="textpart" n="Iliad_1.384–390 ">
                    <head>Iliad 1.384–390 </head>
                    <p>At Agamemnon's order the heroes took Briseis from Achilles' tent. Deprived of his gift of honour, the insulted Achilles distanced himself from his companions and called his divine mother, Thetis, to the sea shore. When she emerged from the depths and asked the cause of his tears, Achilles told the story of taking Chrysippa captive, giving her to Agamemnon during the division of the spoils, rejecting Chrysippa's plea for the return of her daughter and the plague sent by Apollon. He then recounted to his mother the events of the day when he got into a dispute with Agamemnon. This lengthy summary of events recounted in detail in the previous verses by the main narrator may come as a surprise. Presumably this is what Aristarchus was thinking when he athethised the entire passus 366-92 (cf. Kirk 1984: 91). However, the repetition is justified, since Achilles key events tying up the plot of the Iliad from the perspective of the actor of events, which is reflected in specific transformations of the narrative.</p>
                    <quote>
                        <lb/>      ἄμμι δὲ μάντις 
                        <lb n="385"/>      εὖ εἰδὼς ἀγόρευε θεοπροπίας ἑκάτοιο. 					
                        <lb/>      αὐτίκ᾽ ἐγὼ πρῶτος κελόμην θεὸν ἱλάσκεσθαι· 
                        <lb/>      Ἀτρεΐωνα δ᾽ ἔπειτα χόλος λάβεν, αἶψα δ᾽ ἀναστὰς 
                      <lb/>  ἠπείλησεν μῦθον ὃ δὴ τετελεσμένος ἐστί·  
                        <lb/>      τὴν μὲν γὰρ σὺν νηῒ θοῇ ἑλίκωπες Ἀχαιοὶ
                        <lb n="390"/>       ἐς Χρύσην πέμπουσιν, ἄγουσι δὲ δῶρα ἄνακτι·				
                        <lb/>       τὴν δὲ νέον κλισίηθεν ἔβαν κήρυκες ἄγοντες 
                        <lb/>       κούρην Βρισῆος τήν μοι δόσαν υἷες Ἀχαιῶν.  
                    </quote>
                    <quote>
                        <lb/>Wieszczek
                        <lb n="385"/> the well-wisher announced the verdicts in the Trafnostrzelny case.		
                        <lb/> Then I was the first to call to propitiate the god.
                        <lb/> Then the son of Atreus was seized with wrath, having risen violently
                        <lb/> He included threats in the command, which in fact is fulfilled.
                        <lb/> For there the astute Achaians on a volatile ship
                        <lb n="390"/> they send to Chryza, carrying gifts for the Lord.					
                        <lb/> With this one the herolds have just departed from my tent, having abducted
                        <lb/> the daughter of Bryzes, whom the sons of the Achaeans had given me.
                    </quote>
                    <p>385: ἀγόρευε θεοπροπίας  ἑκάτοιο – "he pronounced the oracles in the case of the Thracian"; the word θεοπροπίας echoes the phrase εἰπὲ θεοπρόπιον ὅ τι οἶσθα, "say the oracle you know", spoken by Achilles to Kalchas (Il. 1.85). The noun θεοπροπία (r.s.) probably means 'oracle', although its etymology is disputed. The first element, θεο-, means deity, and originally referred to a miraculous, extraordinary experience, an ecstatic or prophetic epiphany (cf. Burkert 1997). The element -προπ- is most probably related to the verb πρέπω 'to appear clearly', 'to become prominent', 'to stand out' 'to be visible', 'to appear'. It is therefore a group of words denoting the revelation of divine, hidden causes of events and phenomena.  According to another, less probable hypothesis, the element -προπ- derives from the stem *pre/ok "a request addressed to the gods to receive an indicated gift" and is related to Latin precor, "to ask", "to make request", "to turn" (in prayer), "to pray", Pol. The original form *θεοπροκος would have had to undergo progressive assimilation (turning 'k' into 'p'), cf. Pulleyn 2000: 147. </p>
                    <p>386: αὐτίκ᾽ ἐγὼ πρῶτος κελόμην θεὸν ἱλάσκεσθαι - 'then I was the first to call to propitiate the god'; the representation of the sequence of events is not accurate - Achilles admittedly spoke first and called to ask the bard the cause of Apollon's anger (v. 62-5) and offered to make a sacrifice to avert it (v. 66-7), but it was Kalchas who presented a way out of the crisis, the return of Chrysippus and the sacrifice of a hecatomb that could propitiate (→ ἱλάσκομαι) the god and induce an end to the plague (vv. 97-100), and the bard's diagnosis was endorsed by Agamemnon; moreover, before the dispute broke out, Agamemnon identified Achilles as a potential commander of a ship carrying sacrificial animals for the god (v. 147). Achilles thus omits entirely his harsh speech against Agamemnon, giving the impression that Agamemnon's anger was provoked by a call to propitiate Apollo. </p>
                    <p>390: ἄγουσι δὲ δῶρα ἄνακτι - "they carry gifts to the Lord"; the hecatomb mentioned earlier (v. 99, 142, 309) has been described as "gifts (→ δῶρα)" to the god.</p>
                   
                </div>
                
                <div type="textpart" n="Iliad_1.423–425 ">
                    <head>Iliad 1.423–425 </head>
                    <p>Thetis cannot immediately present the request to Zeus because the god is staying with the Ethiopians at a feast. The motif of the god staying with the Ethiopians as an explanation for his absence from Olympus also appears at the beginning of the Odyssey (1.22-25, cf. Il. 23.205-7). On this motif in song one, see Scodel 2007.</p>
                    <quote>
                        <lb/>Ζεὺς γὰρ ἐς Ὠκεανὸν μετ᾽ ἀμύμονας Αἰθιοπῆας
                        <lb/>χθιζὸς ἔβη κατὰ δαῖτα, θεοὶ δ᾽ ἅμα πάντες ἕποντο· 
                        <lb/>  δωδεκάτῃ δέ τοι αὖτις ἐλεύσεται Οὔλυμπονδέ
                    </quote>
                    <quote>
                        <lb/>For Zeus over Okeanos to the Ethiopians without blemish
                        <lb/>he went to a feast yesterday, and all the gods followed him;
                        <lb/> on the twelfth day he will come again to Olympus
                    </quote>
                    
                    <p>423–4:	Ζεὺς γὰρ ἐς Ὠκεανὸν… ἔβη κατὰ δαῖτα – "For Zeus over Okeanos ... went to a feast"; on the shield of Achilles, Hephaestus depicted Okeanos as a river circling the flat earth and reaching the celestial vault (Il. 18.607-8). In archaic world imagery, Okeanos was also the god of the cosmic river who gave birth to all that exists; he resided at the ends of the earth with his wife, Thetis (Il. 14.201, 246, 302). Zeus's absence on Olympus means that his requests do not reach him (in the case of Thetis - she cannot go to the god in person). It seems that the utopian people of the Ethiopians feast with the gods, like mankind in the times before its separation from the immortal gods. Sacrifice is a form of communication with the gods when direct fellowship has become impossible. 
                        μετ᾽ ἀμύμονας Αἰθιοπῆας - "to the Ethiopians without blemish"; the Ethiopians are usually located in the eastern borderlands of the land (cf. Mimnermos, fr. 12.9 West; Aesch. Prom. 809). The king of the Ethiopians, Memnon was the son of the dawn goddess, Eos (Hes. Theog. 984-5). The first author to place them south of Egypt is Hecataios (FGrHist 1 F 325-8 with commentary by F. Jacoby).
                    </p>
                   
                </div>
                
                <div type="textpart" n="Iliad_1.430–431,436–474 ">
                    <head>Iliad 1.430–431, 436–474 </head>
                    <p>The offering of the hecatomb is intended to end the plague caused by Apollon as revenge for the insult to the priest Chryses. The restoration of the Achaeans' proper relationship with the god requires the return of Chryses' daughter to the priest and the offering of the prescribed sacrifice, during which the priest revokes his earlier request. The bride and the animals are brought with them on ships by envoys of the Achaean army led by Odysseus. In the ritual itself the role of the sacrificer (sacrifiant) is played by Chryses, the sacrificers on whose behalf the sacrifice will be offered are the Achaeans. Cf. Hitch 2009: 80-81; Muellner 1976: 32-33 (Chryses' prayer).
                        
                    </p>
                    <quote>
                        <lb n="430"/>αὐτὰρ Ὀδυσσεὺς						
                        <lb/>    ἐς Χρύσην ἵκανεν ἄγων ἱερὴν ἑκατόμβην. 
                        <lb/>    [...]
                        <lb/>    ἐκ δ᾽ εὐνὰς ἔβαλον, κατὰ δὲ πρυμνήσι᾽ ἔδησαν· 			
                        <lb/>      ἐκ δὲ καὶ αὐτοὶ βαῖνον ἐπὶ ῥηγμῖνι θαλάσσης, 
                        <lb/>       ἐκ δ᾽ ἑκατόμβην βῆσαν ἑκηβόλῳ Ἀπόλλωνι· 
                        <lb/>       ἐκ δὲ Χρυσηῒς νηὸς βῆ ποντοπόροιο.    
                        <lb n="440"/>       τὴν μὲν ἔπειτ᾽ ἐπὶ βωμὸν ἄγων πολύμητις Ὀδυσσεὺς 		
                        <lb/>      πατρὶ φίλῳ ἐν χερσὶ τίθει καί μιν προσέειπεν· 
                        <lb/>      ὦ Χρύση, πρό μ᾽ ἔπεμψεν ἄναξ ἀνδρῶν Ἀγαμέμνων 
                        <lb/>      παῖδά τε σοὶ ἀγέμεν, Φοίβῳ θ᾽ ἱερὴν ἑκατόμβην 
                        <lb/>      ῥέξαι ὑπὲρ Δαναῶν ὄφρ᾽ ἱλασόμεσθα ἄνακτα, 
                        <lb n="445"/>      ὃς νῦν Ἀργείοισι πολύστονα κήδε᾽ ἐφῆκεν.   			
                        <lb/>      Ὣς εἰπὼν ἐν χερσὶ τίθει, ὃ δὲ δέξατο χαίρων 
                        <lb/>      παῖδα φίλην· τοὶ δ᾽ ὦκα θεῷ ἱερὴν ἑκατόμβην  
                        <lb/>      ἑξείης ἔστησαν ἐΰδμητον περὶ βωμόν, 
                        <lb/>    χερνίψαντο δ᾽ ἔπειτα καὶ οὐλοχύτας ἀνέλοντο. 
                        <lb n="450"/>    τοῖσιν δὲ Χρύσης μεγάλ᾽ εὔχετο χεῖρας ἀνασχών· 			
                        <lb/>       κλῦθί μευ ἀργυρότοξ᾽, ὃς Χρύσην ἀμφιβέβηκας 
                        <lb/>      Κίλλάν τε ζαθέην  Τενέδοιό τε ἶφι ἀνάσσεις· 
                        <lb/>        ἦ μὲν δή ποτ᾽ ἐμεῦ πάρος ἔκλυες εὐξαμένοιο, 
                        <lb/>         τίμησας μὲν ἐμέ, μέγα δ᾽ ἴψαο λαὸν Ἀχαιῶν· 
                        <lb n="455"/>        ἠδ᾽ ἔτι καὶ νῦν μοι τόδ᾽ ἐπικρήηνον ἐέλδωρ· 			
                        <lb/>        ἤδη νῦν Δαναοῖσιν ἀεικέα λοιγὸν ἄμυνον.
                        <lb/>        Ὣς ἔφατ᾽ εὐχόμενος, τοῦ δ᾽ ἔκλυε Φοῖβος Ἀπόλλων. 
                        <lb/>        αὐτὰρ ἐπεί ῥ᾽ εὔξαντο καὶ οὐλοχύτας προβάλοντο, 
                        <lb/>        αὐέρυσαν μὲν πρῶτα καὶ ἔσφαξαν καὶ ἔδειραν, 
                        <lb n="460"/>        μηρούς τ᾽ ἐξέταμον κατά τε κνίσῃ ἐκάλυψαν 			
                        <lb/>         δίπτυχα ποιήσαντες, ἐπ᾽ αὐτῶν δ᾽ ὠμοθέτησαν· 
                        <lb/>         καῖε δ᾽ ἐπὶ σχίζῃς ὁ γέρων, ἐπὶ δ᾽ αἴθοπα οἶνον 
                        <lb/>            λεῖβε· νέοι δὲ παρ᾽ αὐτὸν ἔχον πεμπώβολα χερσίν. 
                        <lb/>         αὐτὰρ ἐπεὶ κατὰ μῆρε κάη καὶ σπλάγχνα πάσαντο, 
                        <lb n="465"/>           μίστυλλόν τ᾽ ἄρα τἆλλα καὶ ἀμφ᾽ ὀβελοῖσιν ἔπειραν,  		
                        <lb/>         ὤπτησάν τε περιφραδέως, ἐρύσαντό τε πάντα. 
                        <lb/>          αὐτὰρ ἐπεὶ παύσαντο πόνου τετύκοντό τε δαῖτα 
                        <lb/>          δαίνυντ᾽, οὐδέ τι θυμὸς ἐδεύετο δαιτὸς ἐΐσης. 
                        <lb/>        αὐτὰρ ἐπεὶ πόσιος καὶ ἐδητύος ἐξ ἔρον ἕντο, 
                        <lb n="470"/>       κοῦροι μὲν κρητῆρας ἐπεστέψαντο ποτοῖο,				
                        <lb/>    νώμησαν δ᾽ ἄρα πᾶσιν ἐπαρξάμενοι δεπάεσσιν· 
                        <lb/>     οἳ δὲ πανημέριοι μολπῇ θεὸν ἱλάσκοντο 
                        <lb/>     καλὸν ἀείδοντες παιήονα κοῦροι  Ἀχαιῶν 
                        <lb/>μέλποντες ἑκάεργον· ὃ δὲ φρένα τέρπετ᾽ ἀκούων.  
                        
                        <p>App. crit. 
                        ἱερὴν Zen Ar cf. [99] P.S.I.13 (Pack2 608 s. V); [431] P.Berol. inv. 7507 (Pack2 871; s. I: 11, 101–6)</p>
                    </quote>
                    <quote>
                        <lb/>Meanwhile, Odysseus 430
                        <lb/> reached Chryza, leading a holy hecatomb.
                        <lb/> [...]
                        <lb/> They cast the anchor-stones and tied the stern moorings,  	
                        <lb/> And they went down to the seashore,
                        <lb/> They landed a hecatomb for the Apollonian,
                        <lb/> At last the Chryseis emerged from the sea-going ship
                        <lb n="440"/> Then leading her towards the altar, the thoughtful Odysseus, 
                        <lb/> gave her into the arms of her dear father, and thus said to him:
                        <lb/> "Chryses, I was sent here by the lord of men Agamemnon,
                        <lb/> to bring thee a child, and to Phoebus a sacred hecatomb
                        <lb/> to make for the Danes, that we may win the Lord, 
                        <lb n="445"/> who now afflicts the Argives with terrible calamities".		
                        <lb/>So he said, and into his father's hands he gave the girl. With joy
                        <lb/> He received the beloved daughter. They soon made a holy hecatomb 
                        <lb/> Around the well-built altar they set the god in order.
                        <lb/> When they had washed their hands and taken the sacrificial barley,
                        <lb n="450"/> For them Chryses prayed aloud, lifting up his arms:	
                        <lb/> "Hear me, Silversmith, what carest thou for Chryses,
                        <lb/> and the transcendent Killa, and reign with power over Tenedos!
                        <lb/> If thou hast first heard my supplication, by the grace
                        <lb/> you showed me so much by destroying the tribes of the Achaeans,
                        <lb n="455"/> now hear me also and grant my supplication:			
                        <lb/> avert already now the shameful doom from the people of Danay".
                        <lb/> Thus he spoke, pleading. Fojbos Apollon listened to him.
                        <lb/> When they had prayed and thrown the sacrificial barley,
                        <lb/> first they deflected (the throats) and butchered and skinned it,
                        <lb n="460"/> they cut out the legs and covered them with fat (of the peritoneal membrane) 
                        <lb/> wrapped on both sides, on these they placed pieces of raw meat.
                        <lb/> The old man burnt them on a log and with dark wine
                        <lb/> he sprinkled it, and the young men by him held in their hands a spit with five blades
                        <lb/> When the legs were burnt and the entrails tasted,
                        <lb n="465"/> they chopped the rest and stuffed it on the spits, 
                        <lb/> They roasted them carefully, and then they were taken off the spits.
                        <lb/> When they had rested after their toil and had prepared a feast,
                        <lb/> they feasted, and nothing was lacking in the heart from an equal feast.
                        <lb/> When they had quenched their thirst with drink, and their hunger with food
                        <lb n="470"/> the young men filled the mixers to the brim with drink, 
                        <lb/> and after pouring out the libation, they poured it into all the vessels.
                        <lb/> And all day long with prayer song they sought to win the god
                        <lb/> beautifully singing the pajan, the Achaean youths,
                        <lb/> praising the Thracian, and he rejoiced in listening.
                    </quote>
                    <p>430–6:	sailing to Chryza. From the point of view of poetic language, the description of Odysseus's arrival at Chryza is characterised by typicality of scenes and motifs as well as formality (see Schipp 1972: 296 ff.; Kirk 1985, ad loc.). The sailing of Odysseus with the hecatomb to Chryza is unique against the land setting of the action of the Iliad, which makes the formulas used to describe it find their equivalents in the language of the Odyssey (e.g. Il. 1.432 = Od. 16.324). The introductory sentence of the episode begins in the middle of the hexameter (... αὐτὰρ Ὀδυσσεὺς) and focuses on the transport of the hekatombe (ἄγων ἱερὴν ἑκατόμβην), omitting at the outset the presence on board of the Chrysidae. </p>
                    <p>436-9: going ashore and landing the sacrificial animals. The emphatic fourfold use of ἐκ at the beginning of successive hexameters is an epanaphora that creates a mood of hastily moving the ship's cargo out while maintaining order (Kirk 1985: 100): the disembarkation of the crew, the moving out of the sacrificial animals (ἐκ δ᾽ ἑκατόμβην βῆσαν) and the disembarkation of the Chryside form a kind of procession heading for the altar of Apollo. </p>
                    <p>440: 	τὴν μὲν ἔπειτ᾽ ἐπὶ βωμὸν ἄγων πολύμητις Ὀδυσσεὺς – "then leading her towards the altar, thoughtful Odysseus"; since the hecatomb is offered in the sacred precinct of Apollon Sminteus, the narrator consistently mentions the altar (cf. v. 448). In the second extensive scene typical in the Iliad (2.402-432), when the sacrifice is offered by Agamemnon in the camp of the Achaeans, the narrator is silent about the altar. </p>
                    <p>442: πρό μ᾽ ἔπεμψεν ἄναξ ἀνδρῶν Ἀγαμέμνων; the poet consistently emphasises Agamemnon's role as sacrificer, lord of the sacrifice in the terminology of German science (Opferherr). In Odysseus' speech, his authority is underlined by the epic formula ἄναξ ἀνδρῶν Ἀγαμέμνων (see Hitch 2009: 81; 141 ff.).</p>
                    <p>442-443:	Φοίβῳ θ᾽ ἱερὴν ἑκατόμβην / ῥέξαι ὑπὲρ Δαναῶν ὄφρ᾽ ἱλασόμεσθα ἄνακτα - "and to Phoebos the sacred hecatomb / to make concerning the Danayans, that we may win over the lord"; for the expression ἔρδω + ἑκατόμβην, see. Casabona 1966: 52. </p>
                    <p>447-468: typical scene - blood sacrifice. The most extensive description of animal sacrifice in the Iliad is an elaborate type scene that contains almost all the ritual elements included in the elaborate depictions of sacrifice scenes in the epic's main narrative. The variants that appear in each type scene are justified by the narrative context. The hekatombe sacrificed for Apollo is a ritual performed at the temple altar, with the priest as sacristan and the Achaeans as sacrificers</p>
                    <p>447–448: θεῶι κλειτὴν ἑκατόμβην… ἔστησαν ἐΰδμητον περὶ βωμόν – "they set the god around the well-built altar with a famous hecatomb"; the setting in a circle of sacrificial animals appears in typical scenes, see Il. 2.410a: βοῦν δὲ περιστήσαντο - "they set the oxen around"; Od. 356a: τὰς δὲ περιστήσαντο. Cf. the variant in the description of the hog sacrifice offered by Eumayos, where instead of an altar we have ἔσχαρη, "hearth, fire", and one animal makes it impossible to set around: τὸν μὲν ἔπειτ᾽ ἔστησαν ἐπ᾽ ἐσχάρῃ - "they set it by the fire" (Od. 14.420). The two adverbs emphasize that once brought to the place of sacrifice, the sacrificial animals are set up quickly (ὦκα) and "in the right order" (ἑξείης), presumably to prevent confusion, tumult at the altar. The juxtaposition of violent death on the battlefield with orderly and controlled violence at the sacrifice is one of the hallmarks of the epic worldview, see Seaford 1993. 
                        ἐΰδμητον περὶ βωμόν - 'around a well-built altar'; for the expression cf. Od. 7.100 (outside the sacrificial context). 
                    </p>
                    <p>449: χερνίψαντο δ᾽ ἔπειτα καὶ οὐλοχύτας ἀνέλοντο - "when they had washed their hands and collected the sacrificial barley"; formular verse (= Il. 2.410); archaic technical terms of sacrificial vocabulary appear: χερνίπτομαι and οὐλόχυται. 
                        χερνίψαντο - 'they washed their hands'; verb → χερνίπτομαι, a technical term formed from the noun → χέρνιψ, 'water for washing hands', which in the context of sacrifice and prayer also appears in Nestor's description of the sacrifice (Od. 3.440 and 445). The washing of the hands, as a form of ritual cleansing, was a necessary condition before the rituals of the blood and liquid sacrifice (Il. 6.266-8). In the Odyssey, when newcomers join the feasters, they are given entrails to taste, poured libations and prayed over, but there is no mention of washing hands (see Od. 3.5 ff.). Outside the sacrificial context χέρνιψ means water for washing hands (before a meal: Od. 1.136; 4.52). Vase paintings depict χέρνιψ as a bowl with vices, cf. the discussion in Athenaeus (Ath. 408b-9b, 9.75-6). Fixed stone purification bowls appear in sanctuaries in the late seventh century BC. (Parker, 1983: 19-20). On opening rituals, see Ginouvès 1968: 313-4; Moulinier 1950 71-74; van Straten 1995: 31-40. </p>
                    <p>449b: καὶ οὐλοχύτας ἀνέλοντο - 'they took crumbs/barley grain'; formular verse (= Il. 2.410b). Although there is no mention in the Iliad of the basket in which the grain was brought to the place where the ritual was performed, the verb ἀνέλοντο - 'they fetched' suggests the existence of a container in which the grain was stored; the grain will be thrown on the animal after the prayer to Apollon is said (v. 458). The word → οὐλόχυται is a compound in which the second element is the adjective -χυτός, "poured out, poured over" formed from the verb χέω, "to pour out" (about solids), "to pour", "to pile up", "to scatter". J. Casabona sees it as an adjective denoting → κριθαί - 'barley'. The meaning of the element οὐλο- is more difficult to determine; by analogy with, for example, τεῖχος ἀμφίχυτον, it can be assumed that it specified the manner, purpose or addressee of the gesture of scattering grains (Casabona 1966: 283). In Od. 3.441 and the Pohomeric sources it has been replaced by the noun οὐλαί. Od. 3.444-5 directly links the use of water for purification and the taking of barley grains with the beginning of the sacrificial ritual at the altar (γέρων δ᾽ ἱππηλάτα Νέστωρ / χέρνιβά τ᾽ οὐλοχύτας τε κατήρχετο - 'the old man, the horseman Nestor / began with water and barley'). Odysseus' companions, when they had to make a sacrifice in a place where they had no access to grain, use oak leaves instead of barley (Od. 3.357-8: φύλλα δρεψάμενοι τέρενα δρυὸς ὑψικόμοιο- / οὐ γὰρ ἔχον κρῖ λευκὸν ἐϋσσέλμου ἐπὶ νηός, see comm. ad loc.). </p>
                    <p>450:	τοῖσιν δὲ Χρύσης μεγάλ᾽ εὔχετο χεῖρας ἀνασχών – "but for them Chryses prayed aloud lifting up his arms"; the use of the εὔχομαι + dat. construction here indicates that Chryses is raising a prayer for the Achaeans, thus revoking a request to Apollo to punish them because of his daughter (Pulleyn 2002). In verse 458 the verb εὔχομαι is used in the plural, suggesting that the prayer, even if raised by an individual, may have been seen as a collective act, like other ritual actions. </p>
                    <p>458-469: The prayer is followed by formular verses that will be repeated in the scene of Il.2.421-432, which depicts the sacrifice made by Agamemnon, except for the verses of Il.1.462-463, which depart from the common pattern in Il.2.425-426 but return in the scene of Nestor's sacrifice in the Odyssey (3.459-460). </p>
                    <p>458: αὐτὰρ ἐπεί ῥ᾽ εὔξαντο καὶ οὐλοχύτας προβάλοντο - 'when they had prayed and thrown the barley'; a formulaic verse summarising the introductory rites accompanying the prayer (= Il. 2.421 = Od. 3.447; cf. variant in Od.12.359: αὐτὰρ ἐπεί ῥ᾽ εὔξαντο καὶ ἔσφαξαν καὶ ἔδειραν). The haemistic formular αὐτὰρ ἐπεί ῥ᾽ εὔξαντο is only used in a sacred context in typical scenes - animal sacrifice - which excludes the secular interpretation of the verb εὔχομαι, which here does not simply mean "to utter aloud solemn words" but more specifically "to pray, to raise a prayer". On this verb see Benveniste 1968; Muellner 1976 (the place in question is analysed on pp. 31-37).	οὐλοχύτας προβάλοντο - "they threw barley"; in Od. 3.446 the washing of the hands, the scattering of the barley and the burning of the cut hair are referred to as primal rites, actions preceding ritual slaughter. In later sources, participants in the ritual throw barley into the fire lit on the altar, on the sacrificial animal or on the participants in the ritual. W. Burkert (1972: 5) interpreted throwing grains at an animal as a gesture of aggression, pointing to rituals in which stones were thrown instead of grains. F. Graf, on the other hand, drew attention to the species of grain used - barley was considered a cereal grown by humans in primitive times (Graf 2002: 121). </p>
                    <p>459a: αὐέρυσαν μὲν πρῶτα - "first they deflected" (the animal's throat); (formulaic verse = Il. 2.422a) after the preliminary rites have been fulfilled, the participants in the ritual proceed to the ritual slaughter. In the epic descriptions of the slaughter of the sacrificial animal there is a fixed sequence of actions, but individual scenes focus attention on selected elements. The sequence in its fullest form would be: "(1) stunning the animal, (2) butchering, (3) skinning, (4) trimming, (5) making meat". Although it is a constant element of slaughter scenes in the epic, all its elements never appear in one place. The element (1) of stunning the animal, which occurs in the Odyssey by dealing a blow to the animal's neck with an axe (cattle) or a billet (flock), does not appear in the Iliad. Here three elements are present: (2), (3). A fuller sequence, consisting of three elements: (2) butchering, (3) skinning and (5) making meat, is present in Il. 24.622 and is almost verbatim repeated in Il. 7.314-316. In the slaughter and supper preparation scene in Il. 18.559 (Achilles' shield) the elements (1) and (3) appear; while in Il. 23.167 (2) and (3) at, Od. 8.61, 19.421 This should not be attributed to differences of ritual, but to Homer's desire for brevity of description. The meaning of the verb αὐέρυσαν is explained by Apollonios the Sophist (Lex. Hom.): εἰς τοὐπίσω εἵλκυσαν, 'they bent backwards (the neck)' in order to cut the throat.
                        καὶ ἔσφαξαν - "and butchered"; formular verse (= Il. 2.422). The verb → σφάζω belongs to the technical language of sacrifice. As with the prayer, the plural does not necessarily indicate the slitting of the animal's throat by a larger number of participants in the ritual. It is possible, however, that the plural emphasizes the complicity of several persons in the killing of the animal. In Od. 3.454 the cow's throat is cut by Pejsistratos, but the depiction of a private sacrifice, centred on the complicity of family members of both sexes, necessitated greater detail in the description, see comment ad loc.  
                        καὶ ἔδειραν - 'and they skinned'; the Homeric epic does not explicitly mention the further fate of the skin pulled from the animal, but we can assume that it was used as material to be further redistributed. Cf. Il. 23.144-151 with commentary.
                    </p>
                    <p>460–461a:	μηρούς τ᾽ ἐξέταμον κατά τε κνίσῃ ἐκάλυψαν/ δίπτυχα ποιήσαντες – "they cut the legs and hid them in fat (peritoneal membranes) / on two sides wrapping"; formular verses (= Il. 2, 427 = Od. 12, 364). After skinning the carcass of the animal, the sacrificers prepare the portion dedicated to the gods. The expression μηρούς τ᾽ ἐξέταμον - "they cut the legs" (cf. ἐκ μηρία τάμνον, with the thesis, Od. 3.456), which occurs only in extended type scenes, can be translated as "they cut the legs" (= thighbones) from the flesh covering them, or "they cut off the legs" (from the body). It opens in typical scenes with a repetitive arrangement of verses describing the procedure for preparing the hind legs (μηρούς) for burning (3x: Il. 1.464-5 = Il. 2.427-8 = Od. 12. 364-5): μηρούς τ᾽ ἐξέταμον κατά τε κνίσῃ ἐκάλυψαν / δίπτυχα ποιήσαντες, ἐπ᾽ αὐτῶν δ᾽ ὠμοθέτησαν, cf. the variant in Nestor's description of the offering to Athena (Od. 3.456b-457, see comment ad. loc.): ἄφαρ δ᾽ ἐκ μηρία τάμνον / πάντα κατὰ μοῖραν, κατά τε κνίσῃ ἐκάλυψαν. On κνίση see above, 1.60 with commentary.</p>
                    <p>461b: ἐπ᾽ αὐτῶν δ᾽ ὠμοθέτησαν - "on them they laid pieces of raw meat"; (= Il. 2.424 = Od. 3.458 = Od. 12.424); verb → ὠμοθετέω, composed of the adjective ὠμός, "raw", "not roasted" (about meat) and θετέω, "to arrange" (SlG.-P.: "to lay pieces of raw sacrificial meat on the altar"). The ritual is described in detail in Od.14.427-8: ὁ δ᾽ ὠμοθετεῖτο συβώτης, / πάντων ἀρχόμενος μελέων, ἐς πίονα δημόν - "the swineherd laid the raw pieces of meat on the fat saddle, offering a primal sacrifice of all the members". The meaning of the ritual is not clear. According to Karl Meuli (Meuli 1946: 306) and Walter Burkert (Burkert 1983: 6, 16), the ritual continues the tradition of Palaeolithic hunters who, by offering particles of slain prey, ensured the survival of animal herds as a response to guilt. </p>
                    <p>462-4: After preparing the parts for the gods, the sacrificer burns them on the altar, at the same time the youth roasts → σπλάγχνα - 'entrails'. The division of roles is clearly marked: the old priest Chryses (ὁ γέρων) supervises the burning of the femurs wrapped in the fatty membrane of the peritoneum and pours wine on the fire, while the youths roast on the same altar fire the entrails removed from the peritoneum and the heart, in place of which the bones were inserted. </p>
                    <p>462: καῖε δ᾽ ἐπὶ σχίζῃς - 'burned on a slab'; noun → σχίζα, 'slab', 'log', 'firewood'; since an altar was mentioned earlier (448), we may suppose that the logs were used metonymically here in place of the altar (βωμός); cf. the expression πολλὰ δὲ μηρί᾽ ἔκηε θεῶν ἱεροῖσ᾽ ἐπὶ βωμοὶς - 'numerous femurs I burned on the sacred altars of the gods', Od. 3.273. ὁ γέρων, ἐπὶ δ᾽ αἴθοπα οἶνον / λεῖβε - "burned the old man on a slab, poured with sparkling wine". </p>
                    <p>463: νέοι δὲ παρ᾽ αὐτὸν ἔχον πεμπώβολα χερσίν - "and the young ones by him held in their hands a spit with five blades"; formular verse (= Od. 3. 460); when the sacrificer sprinkles the burnt portion intended for the supernatural being with a liquid wine offering, the young participants in the ritual toast the animal's internal organs impaled on spits with five blades, → πεμπώβολα, in the same fire. Some commentators suggest that the object described by Homer was similar to the toothed fork found at the sanctuary of Apollo at Dendra, measuring 11.2 cm long by 7.5 cm wide. Cf. Bruns, Archaeologia Homerica, vol. Q: 39, see also Od. 3.460, West comm. ad loc.</p>
                    <p>464-6: Formular verses describing the actions following the ritual burning of the part intended for the supernatural being, the pouring out of libations and the tasting of pieces of internal organs by the participants in the ritual. In Homeric descriptions of animal sacrifice combined with a feast, the poet's attention is focused on the preparation of the part dedicated to the gods and the entrails, followed by the meat eaten by humans. These descriptions consist of formular verses, but allow for a number of variants adapted to the context and needs of the narrative, while the feast itself is mentioned in rather stereotyped formular verses. On the preparation of a meat meal from animal sacrifices, see van Straten 1995: 144-153. </p>
                    <p>466:	αὐτὰρ ἐπεὶ κατὰ μῆρ’ ἐκάη καὶ σπλάγχνα πάσαντο – "when the legs were burnt and they tasted the entrails"; a formular verse (= Il. 2.427 = Od. 3.461 = Od. 12.364) summarizing the first part of the rite. The subject of the verb κατὰ... ἐκάη in the 3rd person ind. aor. pass. 3 sg. are → μῆρα, an archaic collective noun used as a term for femurs burned for the gods, which may indicate an early origin of the formula.
                        σπλάγχνα πάσαντο - 'they tasted the entrails'; the collective noun σπλάγχνα, like μῆρα, is a technical term used in the context of the ritual of animal sacrifice (cf. ἔγκατα, plurale tantum, cf. pol. 'entrails'), which may be explained by the desire to frame the entrails as an inseparable collection of internal organs removed from the slaughtered animal. It seems that this symmetry is not accidental: in the first part of the rituals following the slaughter of the animal, the gods receive μῆρα and the humans receive σπλάγχνα. We have seen that the burning to the gods of the portion due to them, its transformation into smoke (κνίση) is the essence of sacrifice understood as an act of communication between humans and gods, metonymically signifying the sacrificial rite itself. The ritual takes place on an altar. Using the same fire, in which the smoke of burnt logs mingles with the thick smoke of burnt bones and fat, the people prepare the parts of the animal to be eaten on the spot, at the altar itself (later sources emphasise that still hot). There is no description in the epic detailing the organs included in the σπλάγχνα. Aristotle in his treatise On the Parts of Animals distinguishes: heart, lungs, liver, spleen and kidneys (De partibus animalium 664b-672b). On σπλάγχνα, see Stengel 1910 [1970]: 73-78; Rudhardt 1958: 262, note 8; Detienne 1977: 174-179; Durand 1979: 133-166 (especially 139-150); Berthiaume 1982: 60-61; van Straten 1995: 131-41 (especially 131-3); Ekroth 2008: 87-111 (especially 93-95).
                    </p>
                    <p>465-6:	μίστυλλόν τ᾽ ἄρα τἆλλα καὶ ἀμφ᾽ ὀβελοῖσιν ἔπειραν / ὤπτησάν τε περιφραδέως, ἐρύσαντό τε πάντα - "they chopped up the rest and on the spits they stuffed them, / they toasted them carefully, and then they pulled them all off the spits": Formular verse (= Il. 2.428 = Il. 7.317 = Il. 24.623 = Od. 3.462 = Od. 12.365 = Od. 14.430). In Homeric descriptions, the meal intended for humans consists of finely chopped pieces of meat toasted on spits, thus resembling skewers (souvlaki). In later sources, meat is also prepared in cauldrons like a stew. An opposition then appears between roasted splanchna and cooked sarks, see Detienne 1977: 174.</p>
                    <p>467: αὐτὰρ ἐπεὶ παύσαντο πόνου τετύκοντό τε δαῖτα - 'when they had rested after their toil and prepared a feast': formular verse (Il. 1.467 = Il. 2.430 = Il. 7.319, cf. οἱ δ᾽ ἐπεὶ οὖν παύσαντο πόνου τετύκοντό τε δαῖτα, Od. 16.478 = 24.384).</p>
                    <p>468: δαίνυντ᾽, οὐδέ τι θυμὸς ἐδεύετο δαιτὸς ἐΐσης - "they feasted, and nothing was lacking to the heart from an equal feast": formulaic verse (Il. 1.468 = Il. 1.602 = Il. 2.431 = Il. 7.320 = Il. 23.56 = Od. 16.479 = Od. 19.425; cf. Il. 4.48 = Il. 24.69).</p>
                    <p>469:	αὐτὰρ ἐπεὶ πόσιος καὶ ἐδητύος ἐξ ἔρον ἕντο – "when with drink they quenched their thirst and ate their hunger"; formular verse (Il. 1.469 = Il. 2.432 = Il. 7.323 = Il. 9.92 = Il. 9.222 = Il. 13.638 = Il. 23.57 = Il. 24.227 = Il. 24.628; Od. 1.150 = Od. 3.67 = Od. 3.473 = From. 4.68 = From. 8.72 = From. 8.485 = From. 12.308 = From. 14.454 = From. 15.143 = From. 15.303 = From. 15.501 = From. 16.55 = From. 17.99 = From. 24.489). This very frequent closing formula (Abschlussformel) marks the end of the first part of the heroic feast, during which the participants of the feast satisfy their thirst and hunger. It seems that the organisation of the heroic feast assumed simultaneous eating and drinking. Closing the course of the whole feast satisfying biological needs with a short formula allows to focus on other activities of the feasters, cf. Arend 1933: 69-78 (especially 70); Węcowski 2011: 184-5.</p>
                    <p>470: κοῦροι μὲν κρητῆρας ἐπεστέψαντο ποτοῖο - 'the young men filled the mixers to the brim with drink'; the wine was poured into the craters (mixers) by young men (κοῦροι), members of the social elite rather than young slaves (cf. Il. 9.175; Od. 1.148; Od. 3.339; Od. 21.271).</p>
                    <p>471: νώμησαν δ᾽ ἄρα πᾶσιν ἐπαρξάμενοι δεπάεσσιν - "and after the libations were poured into all the vessels": the meaning of this formula has been explained by Paul Mazon (1937). After the preparation of the crater, the young men, acting as serving men, pour a few drops of wine into the spigot of each participant of the feast, which are then, probably simultaneously, poured as the libation beginning the drinking together. Cf. Węcowski 2011: 189.</p>
                    <p>472-5: the sacrifice and the subsequent aristocratic feast do not exhaust the activities of the day. Since the sacrifice proceeded immediately upon the arrival of the messengers, one may legitimately ask about the meaning of the pajan sung and presumably danced by the Achaean youths. Equally surprising is the use of the verb ἱλάσκομαι, which had previously been associated with the offering of a hecatomb. Now, although the propitiatory hecatomb has already been accepted, the Achaean youth erects a propitiatory paean, see Pharaoh 2015.</p>
                    <p>472: οἳ δὲ πανημέριοι μολπῇ θεὸν ἱλάσκοντο - and all day long with prayer song they sought to win over the god: both the use of the adjective πανημέριοι, 'working all day long', and the verb ἱλάσκοντο in the indicativus imperfecti expressing the duration of the action, emphasise the duration of the ritual propitiatory song.  </p>
                    
                </div>
         
            </div>
            
            <div type="edition" xml:lang="pl">
                <div type="textpart" n="intro">
                    <p>Iliada to opowieść o zgubnym gniewie (mēnis) Achillesa, znieważonego przez Agamemnona, który odebrał herosowi brankę Bryzejdę – dar zaszczytny (geras) Achajów, widomy znak należnej mu czci (timē). Pozbawiony czci Achilles wycofał się z walki i zaniósł prośbę do swojej matki, bogini Tetydy, o pomszczenie zniewagi. Spełnienie przez Zeusa prośby Tetydy zawiązuje właściwą akcję eposu – klęski Achajów. 
                        Fabuła jest oparta zatem na wydarzeniach rozgrywających się na dwóch planach –ludzkim i boskim. Na poziomie śmiertelnych aktorów działania tworzą łańcuch: naruszenie normy (obraza) – reakcja (gniew) – przywrócenie normy (pojednanie). Działaniem naruszającym normę jest odebranie/uprowadzenie dziewczyny lub odmowa zwrotu za okupem (apoina) , a pojednanie wymaga zwrotu porwanej. W przypadku aktorów nieśmiertelnych (bogów) analogiczny ciąg działań (obraza – mściwy gniew – przywrócenie) może być odpowiedzią na prośbę zawartą w modlitwie znieważonego śmiertelnika, który przedstawia swoją krzywdę (naruszenie normy) i powołuje się na charis, zasadę wzajemności regulującą relacje bogów i ludzi. Gniew bóstwa można uśmierzyć przez podjęcie właściwych działań rytualnych – złożenie ofiary. Utrzymaniu prawidłowych relacji z nieśmiertelnymi służy zatem składanie stosownych ofiar na ołtarzach należących do bogów. Są one rozumiane jako dary – znaki należnej bogom czci. Dlatego modlący się przywołują ofiary złożone w przeszłości lub zapowiadają złożenie ich w przyszłości, a zaniedbanie ofiar może wywołać gniew boga. Rolę ofiary w tym sporze można zilustrować następującym schematem (na podstawie Hitch 2009). 
                    </p><p>1–7	Inwokacja do Muz. Streszczenie tematu.</p>
                        <p>8–32	Znieważenie Chryzesa przez Agamemnona – odrzucenie prośby o oddanie Chryzejdy w zamian za okup (apoina).</p>
                       <p> 33–42	Modlitwa Chryzesa: prośba o pomstę wsparta wspomnieniem złożonych w przeszłości ofiar [Tekst 1].</p>
                       <p> 43–52		Apollon karze Achajów – zaraza.</p>
                      <p>  [53–305]	Zgromadzenie Achajów.</p>
             <p>           59–67	Mowa Achillesa: wniosek o postawienie diagnozy: zaniedbana hekatomba jako możliwa przyczyna gniewu Apollona [Tekst 2].
                 </p><p>       92–100 	„Diagnoza transcendentna”: wieszczek Kalchas oświadcza, że to nie zaniedbana hekatomba jest przyczyną, lecz znieważenie kapłana: oddanie Chryzejdy oraz złożenie hekatomby może zjednać boga [Tekst 3].
                   </p>   <p>  121–139	Początek sporu Achillesa z Agamemnonem.</p>
                      <p>  140–147	Agamemnon postanawia wysłać poselstwo z hekatombą i Chryzejdą [Tekst 4].</p>
                    <p>    148–305	Agamemnon zapowiada odebranie Bryzejdy.</p>
                       <p> 306–307	Achilles wycofuje się do namiotów.</p>
                    <p>    308–311	Agamemnon wyprawia okręt z hekatombą do Chryzy [Tekst 5a].</p>
                        <p>311–317	Rozkaz Agamemnona: obmycie wojska ze zmazy; złożenie hekatomby [Tekst 5b].</p>
                       <p> 318–356	Zabranie Bryzejdy z namiotu Achillesa.</p>
                        <p>357–430a	Rozmowa Achillesa i Thetis. Prośba Achillesa o pomszczenie zniewagi.</p>
                        <p>384–390	Oddanie Chryzejdy i wysłanie darów (ofiar) dla Apollona wiąże się z odebraniem należnego daru (Bryzejdy) Achillesowi [Tekst 6].</p>
                       <p> 423–425 	[Zeus na uczcie u Etiopów] [Tekst 7].</p>
                       <p> 430a–474	Oddanie Chryzejdy Chryzesowi i złożenie hekatomby Apollonowi w Chryzie – ofiara pojednania przyjęta [Tekst 8].</p>
                       <p> 475–487	Powrót do obozu poselstwa do obozu Achajów.</p>
              <p>          488–492	Achilles ogarnięty gniewem (mēnis) pozostaje w swoim namiocie.</p>
                    <p>Zwrócono uwagę, że cały epizod przypomina strukturą hymn homerycki do Apollona Delfickiego, w którym część narracyjna kończy się ofiarą i ustanowieniem kultu. Christopher Faraone wysunął hipotezę, że źródłem początku poematu może być hymn do Apollona Smintejskiego (Faraone 2015). Jeśli istotnie tak było, narracyjnych źródeł hymnu należy szukać w anatolijskiej Pieśni o uwolnieniu, która według Mary Bachvarovej leży u podstaw tego epizodu (Bachvarova 2016). Przyjęcie tej hipotezy pozwala udzielić odpowiedzi na pytanie, dlaczego temat główny, czyli gniew Achillesa wywołany sporem z Agamemnonem, poprzedza znieważenie przez Agamemnona kapłana Apollona, Chryzesa. Chryzes przybywa do obozu Achajów z błaganiem o zwrot uprowadzonej przez Agamemnona córki; Agamemnon odmawia i przepędza błagalnika. Obrażony Chryzes modli się do Apollona Sminteusa z prośbą o pomszczenie krzywdy, przywołując pamięć o złożonych przez siebie ofiarach. Zagniewany bóg, spełniając prośbę kapłana, zsyła zarazę, wywołując kryzys w obozie Achajów. Achilles, przemawiając na zgromadzeniu wojska, wyraża przypuszczenie, że przyczyną gniewu boga może być zaniedbana hekatomba lub niespełniony ślub. Rzeczywistą przyczynę objawia wieszczek, który stawiając diagnozę transcendentną wskazuje na winnego (Agamemnona) i przedstawia możliwy sposób przebłagania boga: wywołany przez Agamemnona gniew Apollona można uśmierzyć oddając Chryzejdę Chryzesowi i składając Apollonowi hekatombę. Całość epizodu kończą, niezapowiedziane wcześniej, całodzienne obrzędy, w czasie których młodzież achajska tańczy i śpiewa przebłagalny pajan. Uśmierzenie gniewu boga splata się z rozognieniem gniewu herosa.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="textpart" n="Iliad_1.33-43">
                    <head>Iliada 1.33–43 (modlitwa Chryzesa):</head>
                    <p>Passus zawiera modlitwę kapłana Apollona, Chryzesa, który przybył do obozu Achajów z prośbą o oddanie córki Chryzejdy, branki Agamemnona. Przepędzony przez Agamemnona, modli się nad brzegiem morza do Apollona, wołając o pomstę za doznane cierpienie. Umiejscowienie sceny na brzegu morza podkreśla rozpacz i osamotnienie Chryzesa (np. Il. 1.327, 350, 23–59, 24.12, por. Edwards 1980: 8). Spełnienie prośby przez boga stanie się przyczyną sporu Achillesa z Agamemnonem, który wzbudzi gniew (mēnis) Achillesa – główny temat eposu. Na temat modlitwy Chryzesa zob.: Aubriot-Sévin 1992: 219, 281–283, 304; Ausfeld 1903: 505 i nast.; Chapot, Laurot 2001: 31–32 (G1); Pulleyn 1997: 16; Pulleyn 2000: 132–136; Citron 1965: 88–89; Edwards 1980: 8–9; Lateiner 1997: 241 i nast.; Morrison 1991; Mueller 1976; Rabel 1988: 473 i nast.; Servais 1967: 415 i nast.; Thornton 1984, w sprawie funkcji motywu Chryzesa w konstrukcji całości Iliady zob. Rabel 1988. Skutki modlitwy Chryzesa ustaną z chwilą oddania Chryzejdy ojcu i przebłagania Apollona hekatombą, jednak jej dalszą konsekwencją będzie gniew Achillesa, zob. Wilson 2002: 40–53.</p>
                    <quote>
                        <lb/>Ὣς ἔφατ’, ἔδεισεν δ’ ὃ γέρων καὶ ἐπείθετο μύθῳ· 				
                        <lb/>βῆ δ’ ἀκέων παρὰ θῖνα πολυφλοίσβοιο θαλάσσης·
                        <lb/>πολλὰ δ’ ἔπειτ’ ἀπάνευθε κιὼν ἠρᾶθ’ ὃ γεραιὸς   	
                        <lb/>    Ἀπόλλωνι ἄνακτι, τὸν ἠΰκομος τέκε Λητώ· 					
                        <lb/>    κλῦθί μευ ἀργυρότοξ᾽, ὃς Χρύσην ἀμφιβέβηκας 
                        <lb/>     Κίλλάν τε ζαθέην Τενέδοιό τε ἶφι ἀνάσσεις,  
                        <lb/>     Σμινθεῦ εἴ ποτέ τοι χαρίεντ᾽ ἐπὶ νηὸν ἔρεψα, 
                        <lb/>     ἢ εἰ δή ποτέ τοι κατὰ πίονα μηρί᾽ ἔκηα 						
                        <lb/>      ταύρων ἠδ᾽ αἰγῶν, τὸ δέ μοι κρήηνον ἐέλδωρ· 
                        <lb/>     τίσειαν Δαναοὶ ἐμὰ δάκρυα σοῖσι βέλεσσιν.  
                    </quote>
                    <quote>
                        <lb/>Tak rzekł. Przestraszył się starzec i posłuchał rozkazu;
                        <lb/>   kroczył w milczeniu brzegiem rozgłośnego morza;
                        <lb/>   wówczas idąc samotnie wzniósł gorliwie błagania stary: 
                        <lb/>   „Apollonie, Panie, którego porodziła pięknowłosa Leto!				
                        <lb/>   Usłysz mnie, Srebnołuki, co troszczysz się o Chryzę,
                        <lb/>   i przenajświętszą Killę, i panujesz z mocą nad Tenedosem,
                        <lb/>   Sminteusie, jeżeli ci kiedyś miłą przykryłem dachem świątynię
                        <lb/>   lub jeżelim Ci kiedyś spalił tłuste udźce						
                        <lb/>   byków i kozłów – mego błagania teraz wysłuchaj:
                        <lb/>   pomścij na Danajach moje łzy swoimi strzałami”.
                    </quote>
                    <p>36: 	Ἀπόλλωνι ἄνακτι, τὸν ἠΰκομος τέκε Λητώ – „Apollonie, Panie, którego porodziła pięknowłosa Leto!”; modlitwa Chryzesa jest przykładem trzyczęściowej struktury modlitwy: 1) inwokacja do boga lub bogini z dodanymi epitetami i/lub genealogią; 2) argumentacja (uzasadnienie prośby) wskazująca na podstawy oczekiwanej charis; 3) prośba (Aubriot-Sévin 1992: 218 i nast.; Muellner 1976: 27–28); otwiera ją uroczysty heksametr wzywający Apollona, z formularnym przywołaniem genealogii (por. Il. 19.413; h.h.Apol. 178).</p>
                    <p>37–38:	Chryzes, zamiast wezwać Apollona szeregiem epitetów (por. modlitwę Achillesa do Zeusa, Il. 16.233–235), podkreśla jego związek z konkretnymi miejscami kultu w Troadzie.</p>
                    <p>39–40:	εἴ ποτέ τοι… τοι χαρίεντ᾽ ἐπὶ νηὸν ἔρεψα / ἢ… κατὰ πίονα μηρί᾽ ἔκηα – „jeżeli Ci kiedyś miłą przykryłem dachem świątynię lub… spaliłem tłuste udźce”; w środkowej części schematu modlitewnego Chryzes posługuje się typową formułą εἴ ποτέ τοι („jeśli ci kiedyś…”): chodzi o przypomnienie czynów świadczących o czci okazywanej w przeszłości bóstwu, które obecnie powinny skłonić je do spełnienia prośby (Aubriot-Sévin 1992; Pulleyn 1997). Chryzes przywołuje dwa rodzaje działań ludzkich: zadaszenie świątyni oraz składanie ofiar. W obu wypadkach chodzi o czyny, które – jako miłe bogu – zjednują, zaskarbiają jego życzliwość, łaskawość, przychylność, czyli charis. Wskazuje na to przymiotnik χαρίεντα określający świątynię „obdarzony charis” – „zjednujący życzliwość, miły” (χαρίεντα... νηὸν). Można przypuszczać, że ofiary zwierzęce były postrzegane analogiczne. Bezpośredni związek między pojęciem charis a udźcami spalanymi na ołtarzach znajdujemy w Od. 19.397 („miłe udźce”, κεχαρισμένα μηρία, por. Ar. Pax 386) oraz Od. 16.184 („miłe ofiary”, κεχαρισμένα… ἱρὰ). Nie chodzi o prostą wymianę opartą na zasadzie do ut des, lecz o stałą relację wzajemności zgeneralizowanej (generalized reciprocity, termin M. Sahlinsa, zob. Sahlins 1972, rozdz. 5), czyli związek oparty na stałej wymianie, w której przekazuje się jakieś dobro lub usługę innej osobie, nie otrzymując niczego od razu w zamian. Oczekuje się bowiem, że obdarowany odwzajemni się później (na temat charis, Parker 2011; szerzej: Loew 1908; Latacz 1966: 78–98; Moussy 1966: 411–415; de Lamberterie 1978–79: 31–39). 
                        ἐπὶ νηὸν ἔρεψα – „przykryłem dachem świątynię”; według Waltera Burkerta sformułowanie może oznaczać powtarzalność obu czynności, co miałoby sugerować, że Chryzes pokrywał dachem świątynię wielokrotnie, być może za każdym razem, gdy składał wspomniane w modlitwie ofiary; chodziłoby zatem o prowizoryczną chatę wznoszoną na potrzeby święta (Burkert 2011 [1992]: 262). Z kolei Aleksander Ainan Mazarakis uważa, że jednak czasownik ἐρέφω oznacza tutaj „przykryć dachówką” i wykorzystuje modlitwę Chryzesa do datowania tekstu eposu, gdyż najstarsze przykłady dachówki ceramicznej w Grecji pochodzą z początku VII w. p.n.e. (świątynia Apollona w Koryncie, zob. Robinson 1984: 55–56; por. Ainan Mazarakis 2000: 113, przyp. 302). Wydaje się jednak, że ἐρέφω oznacza po prostu „przykryć, zadaszyć”, niekoniecznie dachówką. Pojawiające się już w VIII w. budynki świątynne wyrażają potrzebę obdarzenia bóstwa domostwem, w którym bóstwo, symbolizowane przez posąg kultowy, znajdzie schronienie (por. Coldstream 1977: 321). O symbolicznym znaczeniu idei ochrony i schronienia w Iliadzie, zob. Lynn-George 1993: 197–221.
                        κατὰ πίονα μηρί᾽ ἔκηα – „spaliłem tłuste udźce”; w modlitwach wspomnienie spalania udźców (→ μηρία) jest metonimicznym przywołaniem ofiar spełnionych w przeszłości (por. Il. 8.240; Il. 15.373; Od. 4.764; Od. 17.241). Ich przypomnienie jest powiązane z prośbą skierowaną do istoty nadprzyrodzonej w ramach relacji wzajemności. Chryzes wspomina ofiary, które sam niegdyś złożył (podobnie Agamemnon w Il. 8.240: ἀλλ᾽ ἐπὶ πᾶσι βοῶν δημὸν καὶ μηρί᾽ ἔκηα – „lecz na wszystkich (ołtarzach) wołów tłuszcz i kości udowe spalałem”; oraz Il. 15.373–374: ἢ βοὸς ἢ οἰὸς κατὰ πίονα μηρία καίων / εὔχετο νοστῆσαι – „[jeśli] modliłem się o powrót do domu wołu lub owcy tłuste kości udowe spalając”). W przypadku gdy modli się postać- zajmująca niższą pozycję społeczną, jak Eumajos i Penelopa, przywołuje ona ofiary złożone w przeszłości przez prawowitego gospodarza (w obu wypadkach Odyseusza): Od. 17.240–242 (Eumajos); Od. 4.763–765 (Penelopa). Charakterystyczne, że we wszystkich przypadkach spalane udźce są określone jako tłuste (πίονα μηρία) lub – w przypadku modlitwy Eumajosa – podkreśla się fakt ukrycia ich w tłuszczu (καλύψας πίονι δημῷ). Spalanie (→ καίω) kości udowych owiniętych w tłuszcz (→ κνῖσα, rzadziej: → δημός) wytwarzało gęsty, wonny dym (→ κνῖσα).
                    </p>
                    <p>41: 	ταύρων ἠδ᾽ αἰγῶν – „byków lub kozłów”; konstrukcja μηρία + NAZWA ZWIERZĘCIAGEN jest dość częsta w eposie, analiza wykazuje tendencję do kojarzenia określonych zwierząt ofiarnych z bogiem, któremu składa się je w ofierze; wybór zatem nie jest całkowicie przypadkowy, lecz wpisuje się w pewien wzorzec. Warto zauważyć, że również Agamemnon złoży później Apollonowi przebłagalne τεληέσσας ἑκατόμβας / ταύρων ἠδ᾽ αἰγῶν – „doskonałe hekatomby z byków i kozłów” (Il. 1.315). 	
                        ταύρων – „byków”; słowo → ταῦρος „byk” (niekastrowany), „buhaj” może sugerować ofiarę szczególnie wartościową, gdyż zazwyczaj składano w ofierze byki kastrowane. 	
                        αἰγῶν – „kozłów”; trudno jednoznacznie określić płeć kóz, gdyż rzeczownik αἴξ może oznaczać kozę i kozła (w inskrypcjach attyckich – kastrowanego, → αἴξ; niekastrowany kozioł, cap, → τράγος nie występuje w Iliadzie, a w Odysei pojawia się tylko raz: Od. 9.239). Jednak ponieważ normą było składanie męskich osobników męskim bóstwom, najwłaściwszym tłumaczeniem jest „kozłów”.
                    </p>
                </div>
                
                <div type="textpart" n="Iliad_1.62–67">
                    <head>Iliada 1.62–67 (mowa Achillesa)</head>
                    <p>Sytuacja kryzysowa (zaraza), która dotknęła wojsko Achajów, wymaga zastosowania środków zaradczych. Procedura przewiduje postawienie „diagnozy transcendentnej” (termin W. Burkerta) przez specjalistę rytualnego, znawcę-mediatora, czyli wieszczka (mantis), który na podstawie interpretacji znaków i wiedzy określa właściwe środki zaradcze oraz sposób ich zastosowania (Burkert 1996: 103–128). Wniosek o przeprowadzenie diagnozy transcendentnej zgłasza na zgromadzeniu Achilles. Ze sposobu, w jaki go formułuje, wynika, że najbardziej prawdopodobną przyczyną kryzysu może być błąd rytualny, niedopełnienie zobowiązania wobec bogów (ślubu, → εὐχωλή) lub zaniedbanie ofiary krwawej (hekatomby, → ἑκατόμβη), a odnowienie prawidłowych relacji z bogami powinno dokonać się poprzez złożenie właściwej ofiary (Casevitz 1992: 3–5).</p>
                    <quote>
                        <lb/>ἀλλ᾽ ἄγε δή τινα μάντιν ἐρείομεν ἢ ἱερῆα, 						
                        <lb/>ἢ καὶ ὀνειροπόλον, καὶ γάρ τ᾽ ὄναρ ἐκ  Διός ἐστιν, 
                        <lb/> ὅς κ᾽ εἴποι ὅ τι τόσσον ἐχώσατο  Φοῖβος  Ἀπόλλων, 
                        <lb n="65"/> εἴ ταρ ὅ γ᾽ εὐχωλῆς ἐπιμέμφεται ἠδ᾽ ἑκατόμβης, 				
                        <lb/>    αἴ κέν πως ἀρνῶν κνίσης αἰγῶν τε τελείων 
                        <lb/>  βούλεται ἀντιάσας ἡμῖν ἀπὸ λοιγὸν ἀμῦναι.
                    </quote>
                    <quote>
                        <lb/>Nuże jakiegoś wieszczka spytajmy albo kapłana,				
                        <lb/> albo i snów tłumacza – od Zeusa bowiem marzenie senne – 
                        <lb/>  kto mógłby powiedzieć, dlaczego tak bardzo zagniewał się Fojbos Apollon.
                        <lb n="65"/>  Czy znajduje w nas winę z powodu niedopełnienia ślubu lub hekatomby? 	
                        <lb/>  Może przyjąwszy tłusty dym ofiarny z wybranych baranów lub kozłów 
                        <lb/>  postanowi odwrócić od nas zagładę.
                    </quote>
                    <p>62–63: τινα μάντιν ἐρείομεν ἢ ἱερῆα, / ἢ καὶ ὀνειροπόλον – „jakiegoś wieszczka spytajmy albo kapłana, / albo i snów tłumacza”; diagnozę transcendentną może postawić specjalista rytualny należący do jednej z trzech (lub dwóch, zob. niżej) kategorii: → mantis („wróżbita, wieszczek”), → hiereus („kapłan”), → oneiropolos („tłumacz snów”). Wers 63 budził wątpliwości wśród filologów aleksandryjskich. Pierwszy kierownik Biblioteki, Zenodotos (ok. 325 – ok. 260 p.n.e.) athetyzuje (usuwa) go, prawdopodobnie uznając tłumacza snów za odrębną kategorię specjalisty religijnego, niezwiązaną bezpośrednio z koniecznością zdiagnozowania przyczyn kryzysu (por. Kirk, ad loc.). Arystarch (216 – 144 p.n.e.) natomiast stawia dwukropek (comma) po ἐρείομεν, „spytajmy”, co zmienia sens zdania: „spytajmy jakiegoś wieszczka: kapłana albo tłumacza snów” – zgodnie z tą interpretacją wieszczek (mantis) jest nazwą kategorii ogólnej, „specjalisty rytualnego zajmującego się odczytywaniem znaków”, natomiast kapłan (hiereus) i tłumacz snów (oneiropolos) subkategoriami, specjalistami odczytującymi znaki pojawiające się podczas ofiar lub w czasie snów. Należy pamiętać jednak, że hiereus oznacza samodzielną rolę społeczną (Chaniotis 2008), a nie rodzaj wieszczków (Pulleyn 2000: 142), chociaż w eposie oba terminy (w liczbie mnogiej) są zestawiane (Il. 24.224). Michel Casevitz argumentował ostatnio, że słowo (mantis) jest związane z czasownikiem μηνύω, „ujawniać to, co ukryte; objawiać” (Casevitz 1992). Jeśli przyjmiemy tę hipotezę, możnaby stwierdzić, że również źródłosłów wskazuje na to, że pierwotną i podstawową funkcją manteis było objawianie ukrytych przyczyn krytycznych sytuacji, a zatem stawianie diagnozy transcendentnej. Na temat funkcji manteis w eposie, zob. Bremmer 1993, 171–6; Casevitz 1992; di Sacco 2000. Wykorzystywanie kapłanów wyspecjalizowanych w interpretacji snów do rozwiązywania problemów poprzez wskazania rytuału koniecznego do jego rozwiązania ma swoje paralele w babilońskim systemie religijnym, zob. West (2008 [1996]) 88–89.</p>
                    <p>64:	ὅ τι τόσσον ἐχώσατο  Φοῖβος  Ἀπόλλων – „dlaczego tak bardzo zagniewał się Fojbos Apollon”: właściwe pytanie, która należy postawić przeprowadzając diagnozę transcendentną. Czasownik χώομαι, „jestem zagniewany, gniewam się” odnosi się oczywiście do znaków spostrzeganych przez ludzi – zaraza jest spowodowana gniewem boga, a odwrócenie zła jest możliwe tylko pod warunkiem odkrycia przyczyny gniewu. Emocje związane z gniewem znajdują się w absolutnej opozycji do emocji związanych z pojęciem χάρις, „łaska, uprzejmość, życzliwość”.</p>
                    <p>65: 	εὐχωλῆς ἐπιμέμφεται ἠδ᾽ ἑκατόμβης – „czy znajduje w nas winę z powodu niedopełnienia obietnicy lub hekatomby”; ponieważ czasownik ἐπιμέμφεται + gen. rei oznacza „obwiniać, przyganiać z powodu braku lub niedopełnienia czegoś, skarżyć się z powodu czegoś” (Il. 2.225, por. 226 i nast., zw. 229), możemy przyjąć, że Achilles zastanawia się, czy gniew boga został wywołany jakimś uchybieniem w sferze komunikacji z bogami. Czasownik ἐπιμέμφεται w tym kontekście tłumaczy się często jako stan emocjonalny („gniewać się”), lecz chodzi raczej o czasownik o zabarwieniu prawnym, który oznacza szeroko pojmowane oskarżenie o niedopełnienie jakiegoś uzasadnionego zobowiązania. Gniew bogów wywołany zaniedbaną ofiarą (Il. 5.177) por. Latacz, Nünlist, Stoevesandt 2009: 52–3. 	
                        εὐχωλή – „ślub”; słowo → εὐχωλή oznacza głośno, uroczyście wypowiedziane zobowiązanie wobec boga w zamian za oczekiwaną pomoc (Benveniste 1969). Ponieważ zobowiązanie takie składano z reguły podczas modlitwy, słowo można tłumaczyć jako „ślubowanie, ślub, przyrzeczenie, obietnica” lub „modlitwa”. W tym wypadku zdaje się, że nie chodzi o źle sformułowaną prośbę w modlitwie, lecz o niespełnienie obietnicy (Corlu 1966: 157–158). Interesującą alternatywą dla „ślubowania” w polskim przekładzie jest słowo „obietnica”, które wprawdzie we współczesnej polszczyźnie nie ma konotacji sakralnych, należy jednak pamiętać, że jest spokrewnione z dawną nazwą „ofiary” – obiatą. W staropolszczyźnie „obietnica” była używana dla wyrażenia ślubowania o charakterze religijnym.	
                        ἑκατόμβη – „hekatomba”; słowo → ἑκατόμβη zazwyczaj jest wyjaśniane jako ofiara „(złożona) ze stu wołów, stuwola” (por. Homer, scholia vetera, ed. Erbse: ἑκατόμβη δὲ ἀπὸ τοῦ ἑκατὸν καὶ τοῦ βοῦς – „hekatomba: utworzone ze «sto» (hekaton) i «wołu» (bous)”), jednak w języku epickim słowo uległo już leksykalizacji i oznacza „dużą, wartościową ofiarę” niezależnie od liczby i gatunku zwierząt (LfgrE s.v. ἑκατόμβη), może zatem oznaczać zarówno ofiarę z owiec i kóz, pięćdziesięciu zwierząt (Il. 23.146–8), a nawet tylko dwunastu jałówek (Il. 6.93, por. 6.115). Na fakt, że mimo swej przejrzystej budowy słowo niekoniecznie oznacza ofiarę ze stu wołów, zwrócili uwagę już antyczni i bizantyjscy komentatorzy (Eustathios, ad Il. 1.65, wyjaśnia: θυσία ἐξ ἑκατὸν δηλονότι κυρίως βοῶν, καταχρησιτκῶς μέντοι καὶ ἡ ἐξ ἑκατὸν ζώων – „ofiara, ściśle rzecz biorąc, ze stu wołów, w szerszym znaczeniu natomiast także ze stu zwierząt”; scholia dopowiadają, że ἑκατόμβη oznacza „ofiary doskonałe, τελείας θυσίας”). Paul Thieme wysunął hipotezę, że słowo pierwotnie oznaczało akt zmierzający do zdobycia przychylności bogów, aby otrzymać sto wołów (Thieme 1952: 62-76; por. Pulleyn 2000: 143). Niezależnie od przyjęcia tej hipotezy odnoszącej się do stanu prehistorycznego, w języku Homera chodzi o połączoną z ucztą ofiarę z wielu zwierząt, szczególnie wartościową z ekonomicznego punktu widzenia, a przez to miłą bogu, co sprawia, że słowo pojawia się przede wszystkim w kontekście ślubowania ofiar lub wspomnienia obrzędów już odprawionych (szczegóły → ἑκατόμβη). O jaką zaniedbaną ἑκατόμβη może chodzić w tym miejscu? André Corlu sugeruje, że chodzi o ofiarę przyrzeczoną w ślubowaniu, a zatem słowo byłoby dopełnieniem εὐχωλή, „ślub”, jednak składnia zdania greckiego nie upoważnia do przyjęcia tej propozycji. Z punktu widzenia narracji epickiej ważne jest spostrzeżenie, że wprowadzony w tym miejscu motyw hekatomby zostanie podjęty przez Kalchasa, wieszczka Achajów, który po wskazaniu na rzeczywistą przyczynę kryzysu (znieważenie Chryzesa, kapłana Apollona) nakaże odesłanie Chryzejdy do ojca i posłanie z nią hekatomby jako formy rytualnego przebłagania boga (Il. 1.100). Pieśń I Iliady jest jedynym miejscem u Homera, gdzie hekatomba pojawia się w narracji głównej; często jest przywoływana w wypowiedziach postaci jako ofiara obiecana bóstwu w przyszłości (Il. 4.102, 120; 6.115, por. 6.93, 274; 23.146–8). 
                    </p>
                    <p>66:	ἀρνῶν κνίσης αἰγῶν τε τελείων… ἀντιάσας – „przyjąwszy… tłusty dym ofiarny z baranów lub dojrzałych kozłów”; ἀντιάσας (part. aor. act.), dosł. „wyszedłszy naprzeciw dymowi ofiarnemu”; czasownik → ἀντιάω, oznacza „wyjść naprzeciw”, w odniesieniu do bogów bywa używany w znaczeniu „wyjść naprzeciw dymowi ofiarnemu, ofierze, hekatombie” > „przyjąć ofiarę”, Od. 1.25; 3.436 z komentarzem, por. LfgrE, s.v. Tłumaczenie K. Jeżewskiej: „uczczony ofiarą z wybranych baranów i kozłów” przenosi akcent na intencje ludzi (oddanie czci bogu), tymczasem język grecki skupia się na boskiej odpowiedzi na znak przekazany przez śmiertelników. 	
                        κνίση – „tłusty dym”; rzeczownik → κνίση oznacza zarówno „tłuszcz”, jak i „tłusty (scil. gęsty) i wonny dym” wydobywający się z palonej na ołtarzu części przeznaczonej dla bogów; ściśle rzecz biorąc jest to tłusta błona otrzewnej, w którą zawijano kości udowe jako część przeznaczoną dla bogów i spalaną na ołtarzu (Ekroth 2007; Forstenpointner, Galik, Weissengruber 2013); metonimicznie, podobnie jak → μηρία, może oznaczać „ofiarę” (→ κνίση). Na temat znaczenia tłuszczu jako substancja życia (life-stuff) z przywołaniem wersów Homera, zob. Onians (1951) 279 i nast.
                    </p>
                </div>
                
              
                
                <div type="textpart" n="Iliad_1.92–100 ">
                    <head>Iliada 1.92–100 </head>
                    <p>Wieszczek Kalchas stawia diagnozę, która ma wyjaśnić przyczyny obecnego stanu rzeczy, odpowiedzieć na pytanie, o co Apollon obwinia (ἐπιμέμφεται) Achajów. Kalchas jako mantis „zna, co było, co jest i co będzie” (ὃς ᾔδη τά τ᾽ ἐόντα τά τ᾽ ἐσσόμενα πρό τ᾽ ἐόντα, Il. 1.69), dlatego rozpoznaje stan teraźniejszy, wyjawia przeszłą przyczynę gniewu Apollona (94: ἕνεκ᾽ ἀρητῆρος ὃν ἠτίμησ᾽ Ἀγαμέμνων, „z powodu kapłana, którego Agamemnon nie uczcił”) i podaje możliwą przyszłość: albo Achajowie uczczą kapłana i boga, albo Apollon będzie dalej zsyłał cierpienia. I chociaż przyczyną gniewu boga nie było zaniedbanie ofiar, jego odwrócenie wymaga złożenia hekatombe. Zob. Kaufman (1979) 44–45. </p>
                    <quote>οὔτ ἄρ᾽ ὅ γ᾽ εὐχωλῆς ἐπιμέμφεται οὐδ᾽ ἑκατόμβης,			
                       <lb/> ἀλλ᾽ ἕνεκ᾽ ἀρητῆρος ὃν ἠτίμησ᾽ Ἀγαμέμνων, 
                        <lb/>  οὐδ᾽ ἀπέλυσε θύγατρα καὶ οὐκ ἀπεδέξατ᾽ ἄποινα, 			
                        <lb n="95"/>  τοὔνεκ᾽ ἄρ᾽ ἄλγε᾽ ἔδωκεν ἑκηβόλος ἠδ᾽ ἔτι δώσει· 
                        <lb/>   οὐδ᾽ ὅ γε πρὶν Δαναοῖσιν ἀεικέα λοιγὸν ἀπώσει 
                        <lb/>   πρίν γ᾽ ἀπὸ πατρὶ φίλῳ δόμεναι ἑλικώπιδα κούρην 
                        <lb/>    ἀπριάτην ἀνάποινον, ἄγειν θ᾽ ἱερὴν ἑκατόμβην 
                        <lb n="100"/>   ἐς Χρύσην· τότε κέν μιν ἱλασσάμενοι πεπίθοιμεν.  			
                        <p>App. crit.
                        εὐχωλῆς ἐπιμέμφεται schol. A., Eusth. Mazon: εὐχωλῆς ἔπι μέμθεται Leuman (1950) 71 i nast.</p>
                    </quote>
                    <quote>
                        <lb/>Nie obwinia nas z powodu ślubu lub hekatomby, 			 
                        <lb n="95"/>  lecz z powodu kapłana, którego Agamemnon znieważył, córki mu nie uwolnił, ani nie przyjął okupu
                        <lb/>  za to Trafnostrzelny dał nam udręki i wciąż będzie dawał:
                        <lb/>   i od haniebnej zagłady Danajów wpierw nie wyzwoli,
                        <lb/>    aż ciemnoooką dziewczynę jej ojcu oddamy
                        <lb/>   darmo, nie biorąc okupu, i hekatombę poślemy
                        <lb n="100"/>   świętą do Chryzy. Tym może zjednując go – przebłagamy.
                    </quote>
                    <p>93:	οὔτ ἄρ᾽ ὅ γ᾽ εὐχωλῆς ἐπιμέμφεται οὐδ᾽ ἑκατόμβης / ἀλλ᾽ ἕνεκ᾽ ἀρητῆρος – „nie obwinia nas z powodu ślubu lub hekatomby, / lecz z powodu kapłana…”; Kalchas odpowiada na pytanie zadane przez Achillesa (w. 65), dokładnie powtarzając jego słowa z wyjątkiem zamiany partykuły pytajnej na przeczącą. Wskazując na konkretną przyczynę cierpień zsyłanych przez boga, wieszczek nie mówi już o możliwym zaniedbaniu lub niedopatrzeniu (wyrażanym genetiwem), lecz o konkretnej winie, która jest wynikiem czynu Agamemnona, dlatego konstrukcja ἐπιμέμφεται + gen. rei w pytaniu, została uzupełniona przez ἕνεκα, „ponieważ” > „wini nas za, oskarża nas z powodu” (zob. Pulleyn 2000: 150).</p>
                    <p>94:	ἀλλ᾽ ἕνεκ᾽ ἀρητῆρος ὃν ἠτίμησ᾽ Ἀγαμέμνων – „lecz z powodu kapłana, którego Agamemnon znieważył”; znieważenie poprzez nieokazanie należnej czci kapłanowi Apollona wywołuje reakcję boga podobną do tej, która mogłaby stać się przyczyną nieszczęścia, gdyby znieważono (przez zaniedbanie) samego boga. Prawidłowa relacja między ludźmi opiera się na okazywaniu należnej czci (τιμή); również bogowie mają swoje τιμαί związane z rozdzieleniem między nich właściwych dziedzin działania (por. Il. 15.189, h.Dem. 86; h.Aphr. 37, Hes.Th. 73, 112, 393, 425-6, 885), a ludzie, poprzez składanie ofiar, przekazują im → γέρας, dar poczesny, materialny wyraz czci (Il. 4.49–50, por. Il. 9.498; Od. 5.335). Na temat τιμή i γέρας, zob. Benveniste 1969 [2011]: 127-133, Rudhardt 1959: 57.</p>
                    <p>96:	ἑκηβόλος – „Trafnostrzelny”;  epitet Apollona, w starożytności rozumiany jako „z-dala-godzący/strzelający” (ἑκάς „daleko” + „miotać, ciskać, strzelać”). Współcześni językoznawcy wyjaśniają pierwszy człon złożenia przez ἑκών, „dowolnie”, a zatem należałoby go tłumaczyć jako „dowolnie” > „celnie strzelający”, co podkreśla niechybność trafiania wybranego przez bóstwo celu. Zob. Beekes EDG, s.v.  Por. Cook 1925: 1042–1043 i Chantraine, DEG, s.v.</p>
                    <p>99–100:	ἄγειν θ᾽ ἱερὴν ἑκατόμβην / ἐς Χρύσην – „(zanim) hekatombę poślemy / świętą do Chryzy”; po przedstawieniu „diagnozy transcendentnej” (Apollon zsyła cierpienia na Achajów z powodu znieważenia przez Agamemnona kapłana boga), mantis Kalchas przedstawia plan zjednania boga, nakłonienia go do zaniechania dalszej zemsty. Przywrócenie relacji opartej na charis wymaga oddania dziewczyny bez przyjmowania okupu (poine) oraz złożenia → hekatombe na ołtarzu boga w Chryzie. Hekatombe pełni zatem funkcję ofiary przebłagalnej. Motyw złożenia przebłagalnej hekatombe dla Apollona będzie jednym z głównych tematów pieśni I, co sprawia, że tylko w tej części eposu hekatombe pojawia się w narracji głównego narratora (Hitch 2009: 100–1). Cały proces rytualny od wyboru zwierząt ofiarnych po ucztę będzie opisywany na dwóch planach narracyjnych: z jednej strony będą to wypowiedzi postaci nakazujące przygotowanie ofiary lub oznajmujące intencję jej złożenia, z drugiej strony opis działań przedstawianych przez narratora głównego, aojdę. </p>
                    <p>100b: τότε κέν μιν ἱλασσάμενοι πεπίθοιμεν – „tym może zjednując go – przebłagamy”: czasownik → ἱλάσκομαι, „załagodzić dążyć do uzyskania przychylności, życzliwości”, wskazuje na przebłagalny charakter hekatomby, co zostało podkreślone jego powtarzaniem w całej pieśni pierwszej, ilekroć jest mowa o intencji ofiary złożonej Apollonowi (Il. 1.100; 147; 386; 444; 472). Czasownik pochodzi od i.e. *si-sḷh2-sḱe/o- (reduplikowane inchoatiwum), „dążyć do uzyskania przychylności boga, do pojednania” > „zanosić modlitwę” (orm. ałač’em, „modlę się”), zob. Klingenschmitt 1970: 75–88. W eposie homeryckim dopełnieniem jest zawsze bóstwo (Il. 1.100; 147; 386; 444; 472; 6.380; 385; Od. 3.419; por. Hes. Op. 338), co zdaje się odpowiadać archaicznemu znaczeniu religijnemu zachowanemu w ormiańskim ałač’em, „modlę się” (i.e. * sḷh2-sḱe/o-). </p>

                </div>
                
                <div type="textpart" n="Iliad_1.141–147">
                    <head>Iliada 1.141–147</head>
                    <p>Agamemnon jako dowódca wszystkich Achajów rozkazuje, zgodnie z orzeczeniem Kalchasa, złożenie hekatomby i oddanie Chryzejdy. Agamemnon przekłada ogólne zalecenie wieszczka na rozkazy wydane w pierwszej osoby liczby mnogiej (subiectivus hortativus). Czasowniki zostały ułożone w dwie pary, z których pierwsza rozpoczyna hemistychy po cezurze (zepchnijmy – zgromadźmy, ἐρύσσομεν – ἀγείρομεν), druga kolejne heksametry (umieśćmy – wprowadźmy, θείομεν – βήσομεν). Następnie przechodzi do wyboru kapitana okrętu i przywódcy pielgrzymki, co wyraża się użyciem 3 os. trybu rozkazującego („niech zostanie”, ἔστω). Na końcu Agamemnon zwraca się do samego Achillesa: „albo ty Pelido […], abyś nam Celnie-strzelny mógł przejednać złożywszy ofiarę”.</p>
                    <quote>
                        <lb/>νῦν δ᾽ ἄγε νῆα μέλαιναν ἐρύσσομεν εἰς ἅλα δῖαν, 				
                        <lb/>ἐν δ᾽ ἐρέτας ἐπιτηδὲς ἀγείρομεν, ἐς δ᾽ ἑκατόμβην 
                        <lb/> θείομεν, ἂν δ᾽ αὐτὴν Χρυσηΐδα καλλιπάρῃον 
                        <lb/>  βήσομεν· εἷς δέ τις ἀρχὸς ἀνὴρ βουληφόρος ἔστω, 
                        <lb n="145"/>    ἢ Αἴας ἢ Ἰδομενεὺς ἢ δῖος Ὀδυσσεὺς 					
                        <lb/>   ἠὲ σὺ Πηλεΐδη πάντων ἐκπαγλότατ᾽ ἀνδρῶν, 
                        <lb/>  ὄφρ᾽ ἥμιν ἑκάεργον ἱλάσσεαι ἱερὰ ῥέξας.
                    </quote>
                    <quote>
                        <lb/>  Teraz już czarny okręt zepchnijmy na morze lśniące, 			
                        <lb/>  ilu potrzeba żeglarzy zgromadźmy i hekatombę
                        <lb/>   umieśćmy na pokładzie, a wreszcie samą Chryzejdę pięknolicą
                        <lb/>    wprowadźmy. Niech jeden mąż zasiadający w radzie zostanie dowódcą:
                        <lb n="145"/>    Ajas lub Idomeneus, lub boski Odysej,					
                        <lb/>    albo, ty Pelido, z wszystkich mężów najstraszniejszy,
                        <lb/>    abyś nam Trafnostrzelnego mógł przejednać złożywszy ofiarę.
                    </quote>
                    <p>142–3:	ἐς δ᾽ ἑκατόμβην / θείομεν – „hekatombę / umieśćmy (na pokładzie)”; Agamemnon, jako głównodowodzący wojsk achajskich, rozkazuje wprowadzić na pokład hekatombę. Poeta nie poświęca uwagi wyborowi zwierząt ofiarnych (gatunek, liczba), co zdaje się sugerować, że wódz lub wojsko dysponuje stadami, z których w każdej chwili może wybrać odpowiednią gromadę przeznaczoną na ofiarę. Zważywszy na wielkość okrętu hekatomba wybrana dla Apollona nie mogła składać się z dużego stada.</p>
                    <p>144:	εἷς δέ τις ἀρχὸς ἀνὴρ βουληφόρος ἔστω – „niech jeden mąż zasiadający w radzie zostanie dowódcą”; Agamemnon pozostanie w obozie, a swoją władzę „pana ofiar” deleguje na wybranego dowódcę wyprawy do Chryzy (Hitch 2010: 169–170). Odyseusz, po przybyciu do Chryzy, podkreśli, że przybywa przysłany przez Agamemnona (Il. 1.442). Wodzem powinien zostać mąż „służący radami” (βουληφόρος, dosł. „przynoszący rady”), co podkreśla pojednawczy i polityczny charakter poselstwa. Epitet oznacza członków elity, którzy podejmują decyzje w czasie dyskusji na radzie, w tym również przywódcę (Il. 2.24; 61). </p>
                    <p>147: 	ὄφρ᾽ ἥμιν ἑκάεργον ἱλάσσεαι ἱερὰ ῥέξας – „abyś nam Celnie-godzącego przejednał złożywszy ofiarę”; ponownie czasownik ἱλάσκομαι (zob. powyżej, komentarz do wersu 100) wskazuje na przebłagalny charakter hekatomby.
                        ἱερὰ ῥέξας – „złożywszy ofiarę”; kluczowy zwrot homeryckiej terminologii ofiarniczej (Casabona 1966: 6–7; 39–58). We wczesnym eposie przymiotnik rodzaju nijakiego → ἱερὰ, „ofiary” (dosł. „to, co święte, poświęcone”) jako dopełnienie czasownika → ἔρδω, „czynić, robić”, pojawia się w sumie 16 razy, z czego 4 w Iliadzie (Il. 1.147; 9.357; 11.307, 327) oraz 10 w Odysei (Od. 1.61; 3.5, 159; 4.473; 5.102; 7.191; 11.130; 23.277). W tym miejscu należy go rozumieć jako szereg czynności, które składają się na rytuał ofiary zwierzęcej, co pozwala go tłumaczyć przez „złożyć ofiarę” (Casabona 1966: 50). W dalszym etapie rozwoju języka czasownik ἔρδω zaczął oznaczać „składać ofiarę” niezależnie od użycia dopełnienia ἱερὰ. 
                    </p>
                    
                </div>
                
              
                
                <div type="textpart" n="Iliad_1.308–317 ">
                    <head>Iliada 1.308–317 </head>
                    <p>Gdy spór Achillesa z Agamemnonem zakończył się wycofaniem się Achillesa z walki, Agamemnon przystępuje do realizacji postanowień podjętych podczas zgromadzenia. Opowiadanie narratora głównego powtarza sformułowania Agamemnona z ww. 141–147 ze znaczącymi przekształceniami. W ww. 141–147, w których przemawia sam Agamemnon,  polecenia zostały wyrażone w 1os. l.mn., tutaj, przedstawiając realizację tych poleceń, poeta konsekwentnie używa 3os. l.poj., co podkreśla autorytet Agamemnona jako wodza i ofiarnika. O ile poprzednio Agamemnon kwestię liczby żeglarzy oraz ich dowódcy pozostawiał otwartą („ilu potrzeba żeglarzy zgromadźmy”, „niech jeden mąż biegły w decyzjach zostanie dowódcą”), teraz wybór został dokonany: hekatombę i Chryzejdę zawiezie do Chryzy dwudziestu wybranych wioślarzy, a ich dowódcą zostanie Odyseusz.</p>
                    <quote>
                        <lb/>    Ἀτρεΐδης δ᾽ ἄρα νῆα θοὴν ἅλα δὲ προέρυσσεν, 				
                        <lb/>    ἐν δ᾽ ἐρέτας ἔκρινεν ἐείκοσιν, ἐς δ᾽ ἑκατόμβην 
                        <lb n="310"/>    βῆσε θεῷ, ἀνὰ δὲ Χρυσηΐδα καλλιπάρῃον 					
                        <lb/>    εἷσεν ἄγων· ἐν δ᾽ ἀρχὸς ἔβη πολύμητις Ὀδυσσεύς.   
                        <lb/>       Οἳ μὲν ἔπειτ᾽ ἀναβάντες ἐπέπλεον ὑγρὰ κέλευθα, 
                        <lb/>    λαοὺς δ᾽ Ἀτρεΐδης ἀπολυμαίνεσθαι ἄνωγεν· 
                        <lb/>    οἳ δ᾽ ἀπελυμαίνοντο καὶ εἰς ἅλα λύματα βάλλον, 
                        <lb n="315"/>    ἕρδον δ᾽ Ἀπόλλωνι τεληέσσας ἑκατόμβας 					
                        <lb/>    ταύρων ἠδ᾽ αἰγῶν παρὰ θῖν᾽ ἁλὸς ἀτρυγέτοιο· 
                        <lb/>    κνίση δ᾽ οὐρανὸν ἷκεν ἑλισσομένη περὶ καπνῷ.
                    </quote>
                    <quote>
                        <lb/>    Atryda zaś lotny okręt zepchnął na morze,					
                        <lb/>      wybrał dwudziestu wioślarzy i hekatombę wprowadził
                        <lb n="310"/>       dla boga, a potem Chryzejdę pięknolicą						
                        <lb/>       przywiódł. Jako dowódca wstąpił (na okręt) przebiegły Odyseus.
                        <lb/>       Gdy ci, wstąpiwszy na okręt, wilgotnym szlakiem popłynęli.
                        <lb/>       Atryda rozkazał ludowi obmywać się (ze zmazy):
                        <lb/>      ci obmywali się, do morza brudy wrzucali,
                        <lb n="315"/>      i Apollonowi złożyli doskonałe hekatomby					
                        <lb/>      z byków i kozłów nad brzegiem nieurodzajnego morza.
                        <lb/>        Zapach tłuszczu dosięgnął nieba kręcąc się wokół dymu ofiary.
                    </quote>
                    <p>309:	ἐς δ᾽ ἑκατόμβην / βῆσε θεῷ – „[Agamemnon] hekatombę wprowadził dla boga”; por. ἐς δ᾽ ἑκατόμβην / θείομεν – „hekatombę / umieśćmy” (na pokładzie), Il. 1.143–4. Agamemnon, jako głównodowodzący Achajów, osobiście nadzoruje zaokrętowanie załogi, ładunku i Chryzejdy. W przeciwieństwie do wioślarzy, których liczba została sprecyzowana, liczba zwierząt składających się na hekatombe nie została uściślona. Słowo jest hekatombe tutaj użyte w funkcji kolektiwum, to znaczy terminu, który oznacza zbiór, całość złożoną z części, w tym wypadku grupy zwierząt przeznaczonych na uroczystą ofiarę.</p>
                    <p>313:	λαοὺς δ᾽ Ἀτρεΐδης ἀπολυμαίνεσθαι ἄνωγεν – „Atryda rozkazał wojsku obmywać się”; uczeni zastanawiają się, czy chodzi o specjalny rytuał oczyszczenia ze zmazy religijnej wywołanej zarazą, czy o normalne rytualne obmycie przed przystąpieniem do obrzędu ofiary. Jednak rytuał ofiary rozpoczynał się od obmycia rąk, który oznaczano terminem technicznym χερνίπτομαι. Tymczasem Agamemnon rozkazuje obmyć się całemu wojsku, co świadczy o powadze zmazy i potrzebie zastosowania środków specjalnych. Epos nie opisuje obrzędów oczyszczalnych usuwających zmazę, jednak w wyjątkowych sytuacjach herosi przed przystąpieniem do obrzędu myją się z brudu pola bitewnego (Hektor, Il. 6.266–8). Za hipotezą specjalnych rytuałów oczyszczających przemawiają również paralele bliskowschodnie, na które wskazał Burkert 1997: 62. R. Parker błędnie twierdzi, że rytuał oczyszczenia został zarządzony przez Kalchasa jako wieszczka-uzdrawiacza (healer-seer), zob. Parker 1983: 210. Rozkaz wydaje sam Agamemnon, który najwyraźniej jest wyposażony w wiedzę o potrzebie dokonania oczyszczenia przed przystąpieniem do obrzędu, lecz nie musi odwoływać się do wiedzy specjalisty – wieszczka. Na temat roli Agamemnona zob. Hitch 2009: 78. Paradoksalnie przywódca ludu, którego czyn sprowadził zgubę, jest pierwszym, który nakazuje ludowi dokonać oczyszczeń (Haubold 2000: 51–52).</p>
                    <p>314:	οἳ δ᾽ ἀπελυμαίνοντο καὶ εἰς ἅλα λύματα βάλλον – „ci obmywali się, do morza brudy wrzucali”; wrzucenie brudów (λύματα – brudnej wody? brudnych ubrań?) do morza zdaje się mieć swoje odpowiedniki w rytuałach bliskowschodnich (Burkert 1992: 62; West 2008 [1996]: 97) i antycypować późniejsze greckie praktyki oczyszczalne, zob. Morb. Sacr. 148.43–6: „Pozostałości z oczyszczeń ukrywają następnie w ziemi, wrzucają do morza, albo zanoszą w góry, gdzie nikt ich nie dotknie ani na nie nie nadepnie (tłum. Przemysław Biernat)”. Słowo τὸ λῦμα (τὰ λύματα) oznacza „wszystko, co można zmyć wodą (lub innym płynem)”, „pomyje”, „brud”. Znajduje zastosowanie w różnych kontekstach, również w takich, gdzie z pewnością nie chodzi o jakąkolwiek zmazę rytualną (Il. 14.171).W kontekście rytualnym chodzi o zmazę, którą można usunąć za pomocą odpowiednich praktyk rytualnych. „W przeciwieństwie do zmazy (μίασμα), która jest wynikiem zbrodni, zakłóceniem boskiego porządku (ὅσιον) i odpowiada – w innym wymiarze psychologicznym – szkodliwemu działaniu boskiej mocy (ἄγος), τὸ λῦμα jest wynikiem działań zgodnych z tym porządkiem, lecz pogorszających stan czystości (ἁγνεία)” (Rudhardt 1958: 48).</p>
                    <p>315–6: ἕρδον δ᾽ Ἀπόλλωνι τεληέσσας ἑκατόμβας / ταύρων ἠδ᾽ αἰγῶν παρὰ θῖν᾽ ἁλὸς ἀτρυγέτοιο – „i Apollonowi złożyli w doskonałe hekatomby / z byków i kozłów nad brzegiem nieurodzajnego morza”; ofiara złożona przez Agamemnona, w przeciwieństwie do hekatomby wysłanej do Chryzy, nie została zapowiedziana na zgromadzeniu. Agamemnon działa zatem jako wódz obdarzony autorytetem religijnym, który przejawia się w jego uprawnieniu do podejmowaniu decyzji o odprawieniu właściwych obrzędów. Jednak złożenie ofiary Apollonowi przed dotarciem Odyseusza do Chryzy i oddaniem Chryzejdy sprawia kłopot interpretatorom (zob. Kirk, comm. ad loc.). F.S. Naiden podkreśla brak wzmianki o przyjęciu tej ofiary przez boga (Naiden 2013: 111). 	
                        ἕρδον […] τεληέσσας ἑκατόμβας – „złożyli w doskonałe hekatomby”; zwrot ἔρδω + ἡκατόμβην, „składać hekatombę”, pojawia się w eposie homeryckim 23 razy: 11 razy w Iliadzie (1.315; 444; 2.306; 4.102; 120; 8.550; 9.535–6; 23.146, 206, 864, 873) i 12 razy w Odysei (3.144; 4.352, 478, 582, 5.102, 7.202; 11.132, 12.344; 13.350; 17.51, 60; 23.279), por. Casabona 1966: 52. Oznacza to, że ἡκατόμβην jest najczęstszym dopełnieniem czasownika ἔρδω, który w sumie został użyty w znaczeniu religijnym w 47 miejscach. W sprawie hekatombe, zob. wyżej (komentarz do Il. 1.33–43). 
                        ταύρων ἠδ᾽ αἰγῶν – „z byków i kozłów”; zob. wyżej, komentarz do w. 41.
                    </p>
                    <p>317: 	κνίση δ᾽ οὐρανὸν ἷκεν ἑλισσομένη περὶ καπνῷ – „tłusty dym dosięgnął nieba kręcąc się wokół dymu ofiary”; wers obrazowo przedstawia kluczowy moment rytuału, spalenie części boskiej na ołtarzu – wokół unoszącego się do nieba dymu (najpewniej ze spalanych polan) wije się κνίση, zapach tłuszczu (i kości) spalanych dla boga (por. Il. 1.66). Podobnie jak w przypadku ofiar wspominanych przez postaci eposu, również i w tym opisie rytuał metonimicznie jest definiowany przez spalenie tłustych udźców, a narrator skupia się na spektakularnym przesłaniu bogu widzialnego znaku – dymu powstałego ze spalonych udźców owiniętych w tłustą błonę otrzewnej. W innym miejscu Iliady dym unosi wiatr (8.549), zob. Naiden 2013: 111–112.</p>
                    
                </div>
                
                <div type="textpart" n="Iliad_1.384–390 ">
                    <head>Iliada + 1.384–390 </head>
                    <p>Heroldzi zabrali na rozkaz Agamemnona z namiotu Achillesa Bryzejdę. Pozbawiony swego daru zaszczytnego, znieważony Achilles oddalił się od towarzyszy i nad brzeg morza wezwał swą boską matkę, Tetydę. Gdy ta wyłoniła się z toni i zapytała o przyczynę łez, Achilles odpowiedział historię wzięcia do niewoli Chryzejdy, oddania jej Agamemnonowi podczas podziału łupów, odrzucenia błagania Chryzesa o zwrot córki i zarazy zesłanej przez Apollona. Następnie przedstawił matce wydarzenia z dnia, w którym wdał się w spór z Agamemnonem. To długie streszczenie wydarzeń szczegółowo opowiedzianych w poprzednich wersach przez głównego narratora może zaskakiwać. Najpewniej tak myślał Arystarch, gdy athetyzował cały passus 366–92 (por. Kirk 1984: 91). Jednak powtórzenie jest uzasadnione, gdyż Achilles kluczowe wydarzenia zawiązujące fabułę Iliady z perspektywy aktora wydarzeń, co znajduje odzwierciedlenie w specyficznych przekształceniach narracji.</p>
                    <quote>
                        <lb/>      ἄμμι δὲ μάντις 
                        <lb n="385"/>      εὖ εἰδὼς ἀγόρευε θεοπροπίας ἑκάτοιο. 					
                        <lb/>      αὐτίκ᾽ ἐγὼ πρῶτος κελόμην θεὸν ἱλάσκεσθαι· 
                        <lb/>      Ἀτρεΐωνα δ᾽ ἔπειτα χόλος λάβεν, αἶψα δ᾽ ἀναστὰς 
                      <lb/>  ἠπείλησεν μῦθον ὃ δὴ τετελεσμένος ἐστί·  
                        <lb/>      τὴν μὲν γὰρ σὺν νηῒ θοῇ ἑλίκωπες Ἀχαιοὶ
                        <lb n="390"/>       ἐς Χρύσην πέμπουσιν, ἄγουσι δὲ δῶρα ἄνακτι·				
                        <lb/>       τὴν δὲ νέον κλισίηθεν ἔβαν κήρυκες ἄγοντες 
                        <lb/>       κούρην Βρισῆος τήν μοι δόσαν υἷες Ἀχαιῶν.  
                    </quote>
                    <quote>
                        <lb/>Wieszczek
                        <lb n="385"/> dobrze wiedzący ogłosił wyrocznie w sprawie Trafnostrzelnego.		
                        <lb/>      Wtedy ja jako pierwszy wezwałem, żeby przebłagać boga.
                        <lb/>      Wówczas syna Atreusa chwycił gniew, gwałtownie powstawszy
                        <lb/>      Zawarł groźby w rozkazie, który w istocie jest wypełniany.
                        <lb/>        Tamtą bowiem bystroocy Achajowie na lotnym okręcie
                        <lb n="390"/>     wysyłają do Chryzy, wiozą dary dla Pana.					
                        <lb/>     Z tą zaś dopiero co heroldzi odeszli z mojego namiotu, uprowadzając
                        <lb/>       córkę Bryzesa, którą mi dali synowie Achajów.
                    </quote>
                    <p>385: ἀγόρευε θεοπροπίας  ἑκάτοιο – „ogłosił wyrocznie w sprawie Trafnostrzelnego”; słowo θεοπροπίας  jest echem sformułowania εἰπὲ θεοπρόπιον ὅ τι οἶσθα, „powiedz wyrocznię, którą znasz”, wypowiedzianego przez Achillesa do Kalchasa (Il. 1.85). Rzeczownik θεοπροπία (r.ż.) oznacza zapewne „wyrocznię”, aczkolwiek jego etymologia jest przedmiotem sporu. Pierwszy element, θεο-, oznacza bóstwo, pierwotnie odnosił się do cudownego, nadzwyczajnego doświadczenia, ekstatycznej lub profetycznej epifanii (por. Burkert 1997). Element  –προπ– wiąże się najpewniej z czasownikiem πρέπω „wyraźnie występować”, „uwydatniać się”, „odznaczać się”  „być widocznym”, „ukazywać się”. Chodzi zatem o grupę słów oznaczających objawianie boskich, ukrytych przyczyn zdarzeń i zjawisk.  Zgodnie z inną hipotezą, mniej prawdopodobną, element –προπ–  wywodzi się z rdzenia *pre/ok „prośba skierowana do bogów o otrzymanie wskazanego daru” i jest spokrewniony łac. precor, „prosić”, „dopraszać się”, „zwracać się” (w modlitwie), „modlić się”, pol. prosić. Oryginalna forma *θεοπροκος musiałaby ulec progresywnej asymilacji (zamianie „k” w „p”), por. Pulleyn 2000: 147. </p>
                    <p>386:	αὐτίκ᾽ ἐγὼ πρῶτος κελόμην θεὸν ἱλάσκεσθαι – „wtedy ja jako pierwszy wezwałem, żeby przebłagać boga”; przedstawienie kolejności wydarzeń nie jest ścisłe – Achilles wprawdzie zabrał głos jako pierwszy i wezwał do zapytania wieszczka o przyczynę gniewu Apollona (w. 62–5) i zaproponował złożenie ofiary w celu jego odwrócenia (w. 66–7), lecz to Kalchas przedstawił drogę wyjścia z kryzysu, zwrócenie Chryzejdy i złożenie hekatomby, która mogłaby przebłagać (→ ἱλάσκομαι) boga i nakłonić do zakończenia zarazy (w. 97–100), a diagnozę wieszczka zatwierdził Agamemnon; co więcej, zanim wybuchł spór, Agamemnon wskazał Achillesa jako potencjalnego dowódcę okrętu wiozącego zwierzęta ofiarne dla boga (w. 147). Achilles pomija zatem całkowicie swoją hardą mowę przeciwko Agamemnonowi, sprawiając wrażenie, że gniew Agamemnona został wywołany wezwaniem do przebłagania Apollona. </p>
                    <p>390: 	ἄγουσι δὲ δῶρα ἄνακτι – „wiozą dary dla Pana”; wspomniana wcześniej hekatomba (w. 99, 142, 309) została określona jako „dary (→ δῶρα)” dla boga.</p>
                   
                </div>
                
                <div type="textpart" n="Iliad_1.423–425 ">
                    <head>Iliada + 1.423–425 </head>
                    <p>Tetyda nie może natychmiast przedstawić prośby Zeusowi, gdyż bóg przebywa u Etiopów na uczcie. Motyw pobytu boga u Etiopów jako wyjaśnienie jego nieobecności na Olimpie pojawia się również na początku Odysei (1.22–25, por. Il. 23.205–7). Na temat tego motywu w pieśni pierwszej, zob. Scodel 2007.</p>
                    <quote>
                        <lb/>Ζεὺς γὰρ ἐς Ὠκεανὸν μετ᾽ ἀμύμονας Αἰθιοπῆας
                        <lb/>χθιζὸς ἔβη κατὰ δαῖτα, θεοὶ δ᾽ ἅμα πάντες ἕποντο· 
                        <lb/>  δωδεκάτῃ δέ τοι αὖτις ἐλεύσεται Οὔλυμπονδέ
                    </quote>
                    <quote>
                        <lb/>Zeus bowiem nad Okeanos do Etiopów bez skazy
                        <lb/>udał się wczoraj na ucztę, a wszyscy bogowie podążyli za nim;
                        <lb/>  dwunastego dnia znowu przybędzie na Olimp
                    </quote>
                    
                    <p>423–4:	Ζεὺς γὰρ ἐς Ὠκεανὸν… ἔβη κατὰ δαῖτα – „Zeus bowiem nad Okeanos… udał się na ucztę”; na tarczy Achillesa, Hefajstos przedstawił Okeanos jako rzekę obiegającą płaską ziemię i sięgającą sklepienia niebieskiego (Il. 18.607–8). W archaicznym obrazie świata Okeanos był również bogiem kosmicznej rzeki, który zrodził wszystko, co istnieje; przebywał na krańcach ziemi ze swą małżonką, Tetydą (Il. 14.201, 246, 302). Nieobecność Zeusa na Olimpie sprawia, że nie docierają do niego prośby (w przypadku Tetydy – nie może ona udać się osobiście do boga). Wydaje się, że utopijny lud Etiopów biesiaduje z bogami, jak ludzkość w czasach przed oddzieleniem jej od nieśmiertelnych bogów. Ofiara jest formą komunikacji z bogami w sytuacji, gdy bezpośrednie współbiesiadowanie stało się niemożliwe. 
                        μετ᾽ ἀμύμονας Αἰθιοπῆας – „do Etiopów bez skazy”; Etiopowie są zazwyczaj lokalizowani na wschodnich kresach ziemi (por. Mimnermos, fr. 12.9 West; Aesch. Prom. 809). Król Etiopów, Memnon był synem bogini Jutrzenki, Eos (Hes. Theog. 984–5). Pierwszym autorem umieszczającym ich na południe od Egiptu jest Hekatajos (FGrHist 1 F 325–8 z komentarzem F. Jacoby’ego).
                    </p>
                   
                </div>
                
                <div type="textpart" n="Iliad_1.430–431,436–474 ">
                    <head>Iliada 1.430–431, 436–474 </head>
                    <p>Złożenie hekatomby ma zakończyć zarazę wywołaną przez Apollona jako zemsta za znieważenie kapłana Chryzesa. Przywrócenie właściwych relacji Achajów z bogiem wymaga zwrotu kapłanowi córki Chryzejdy oraz złożenia nakazanej ofiary, w czasie której kapłan odwoła swoją wcześniejszą prośbę. Brankę oraz zwierzęta przywożą ze sobą na okrętach wysłannicy wojska achajskiego, na czele których stoi Odyseusz. W samym obrzędzie rolę ofiarującego (sacrifiant) spełnia Chryses, ofiarnikami, w imieniu których ofiara będzie złożona, są Achajowie. Por. Hitch 2009: 80–81; Muellner 1976: 32–33 (modlitwa Chrysesa).
                        Tekst:
                    </p>
                    <quote>
                        <lb n="430"/>αὐτὰρ Ὀδυσσεὺς						
                        <lb/>    ἐς Χρύσην ἵκανεν ἄγων ἱερὴν ἑκατόμβην. 
                        <lb/>    [...]
                        <lb/>    ἐκ δ᾽ εὐνὰς ἔβαλον, κατὰ δὲ πρυμνήσι᾽ ἔδησαν· 			
                        <lb/>      ἐκ δὲ καὶ αὐτοὶ βαῖνον ἐπὶ ῥηγμῖνι θαλάσσης, 
                        <lb/>       ἐκ δ᾽ ἑκατόμβην βῆσαν ἑκηβόλῳ Ἀπόλλωνι· 
                        <lb/>       ἐκ δὲ Χρυσηῒς νηὸς βῆ ποντοπόροιο.    
                        <lb n="440"/>       τὴν μὲν ἔπειτ᾽ ἐπὶ βωμὸν ἄγων πολύμητις Ὀδυσσεὺς 		
                        <lb/>      πατρὶ φίλῳ ἐν χερσὶ τίθει καί μιν προσέειπεν· 
                        <lb/>      ὦ Χρύση, πρό μ᾽ ἔπεμψεν ἄναξ ἀνδρῶν Ἀγαμέμνων 
                        <lb/>      παῖδά τε σοὶ ἀγέμεν, Φοίβῳ θ᾽ ἱερὴν ἑκατόμβην 
                        <lb/>      ῥέξαι ὑπὲρ Δαναῶν ὄφρ᾽ ἱλασόμεσθα ἄνακτα, 
                        <lb n="445"/>      ὃς νῦν Ἀργείοισι πολύστονα κήδε᾽ ἐφῆκεν.   			
                        <lb/>      Ὣς εἰπὼν ἐν χερσὶ τίθει, ὃ δὲ δέξατο χαίρων 
                        <lb/>      παῖδα φίλην· τοὶ δ᾽ ὦκα θεῷ ἱερὴν ἑκατόμβην  
                        <lb/>      ἑξείης ἔστησαν ἐΰδμητον περὶ βωμόν, 
                        <lb/>    χερνίψαντο δ᾽ ἔπειτα καὶ οὐλοχύτας ἀνέλοντο. 
                        <lb n="450"/>    τοῖσιν δὲ Χρύσης μεγάλ᾽ εὔχετο χεῖρας ἀνασχών· 			
                        <lb/>       κλῦθί μευ ἀργυρότοξ᾽, ὃς Χρύσην ἀμφιβέβηκας 
                        <lb/>      Κίλλάν τε ζαθέην  Τενέδοιό τε ἶφι ἀνάσσεις· 
                        <lb/>        ἦ μὲν δή ποτ᾽ ἐμεῦ πάρος ἔκλυες εὐξαμένοιο, 
                        <lb/>         τίμησας μὲν ἐμέ, μέγα δ᾽ ἴψαο λαὸν Ἀχαιῶν· 
                        <lb n="455"/>        ἠδ᾽ ἔτι καὶ νῦν μοι τόδ᾽ ἐπικρήηνον ἐέλδωρ· 			
                        <lb/>        ἤδη νῦν Δαναοῖσιν ἀεικέα λοιγὸν ἄμυνον.
                        <lb/>        Ὣς ἔφατ᾽ εὐχόμενος, τοῦ δ᾽ ἔκλυε Φοῖβος Ἀπόλλων. 
                        <lb/>        αὐτὰρ ἐπεί ῥ᾽ εὔξαντο καὶ οὐλοχύτας προβάλοντο, 
                        <lb/>        αὐέρυσαν μὲν πρῶτα καὶ ἔσφαξαν καὶ ἔδειραν, 
                        <lb n="460"/>        μηρούς τ᾽ ἐξέταμον κατά τε κνίσῃ ἐκάλυψαν 			
                        <lb/>         δίπτυχα ποιήσαντες, ἐπ᾽ αὐτῶν δ᾽ ὠμοθέτησαν· 
                        <lb/>         καῖε δ᾽ ἐπὶ σχίζῃς ὁ γέρων, ἐπὶ δ᾽ αἴθοπα οἶνον 
                        <lb/>            λεῖβε· νέοι δὲ παρ᾽ αὐτὸν ἔχον πεμπώβολα χερσίν. 
                        <lb/>         αὐτὰρ ἐπεὶ κατὰ μῆρε κάη καὶ σπλάγχνα πάσαντο, 
                        <lb n="465"/>           μίστυλλόν τ᾽ ἄρα τἆλλα καὶ ἀμφ᾽ ὀβελοῖσιν ἔπειραν,  		
                        <lb/>         ὤπτησάν τε περιφραδέως, ἐρύσαντό τε πάντα. 
                        <lb/>          αὐτὰρ ἐπεὶ παύσαντο πόνου τετύκοντό τε δαῖτα 
                        <lb/>          δαίνυντ᾽, οὐδέ τι θυμὸς ἐδεύετο δαιτὸς ἐΐσης. 
                        <lb/>        αὐτὰρ ἐπεὶ πόσιος καὶ ἐδητύος ἐξ ἔρον ἕντο, 
                        <lb n="470"/>       κοῦροι μὲν κρητῆρας ἐπεστέψαντο ποτοῖο,				
                        <lb/>    νώμησαν δ᾽ ἄρα πᾶσιν ἐπαρξάμενοι δεπάεσσιν· 
                        <lb/>     οἳ δὲ πανημέριοι μολπῇ θεὸν ἱλάσκοντο 
                        <lb/>     καλὸν ἀείδοντες παιήονα κοῦροι  Ἀχαιῶν 
                        <lb/>μέλποντες ἑκάεργον· ὃ δὲ φρένα τέρπετ᾽ ἀκούων.  
                        
                        <p>App. crit. 
                        ἱερὴν Zen Ar cf. [99] P.S.I.13 (Pack2 608 s. V); [431] P.Berol. inv. 7507 (Pack2 871; s. I: 11, 101–6)</p>
                    </quote>
                    <quote>
                        <lb n="430"/>Tymczasem Odyseusz		
                        <lb/> dotarł do Chryzy, wiodąc świętą hekatombę.
                        <lb/>   [...]
                        <lb/>    Zarzucili kamienie kotwiczne i przywiązali cumy rufowe,  	
                        <lb/>     A sami zeszli na brzeg morza,
                        <lb/>    Wyładowali hekatombę dla Apollona Trafnostrzelnego,
                        <lb/>    Wyszła w końcu Chryzejda z morskospławnego okrętu
                        <lb n="440"/>    Wtedy prowadząc ją w stronę ołtarza, przemyślny Odyseusz,	
                        <lb/>   oddał w ramiona ojca drogiego, i tak doń powiedział:
                        <lb/>  „Chryzesie, wysłał mnie tutaj pan mężów Agamemnon,
                        <lb/>  żeby ci dziecko przywieść, a Fojbosowi świętą hekatombę
                        <lb/>    sprawić za Danajów, abyśmy zjednali Pana, 
                        <lb n="445"/>      który teraz Argiwów udręcza strasznymi klęskami”.		
                        <lb/>Tak rzekł i w ręce ojcowskie dziewczynę oddał. Z radością
                        <lb/>            przyjął ów córkę kochaną. Ci zaś wnet świętą hekatombę 
                        <lb/>        wokół dobrze zbudowanego ołtarza ustawili bogu we właściwym porządku.
                        <lb/>         Kiedy obmyli swe ręce i jęczmień ofiarny pobrali,
                        <lb n="450"/>         Za nich Chryzes głośno pomodlił się wznosząc w górę ramiona:	
                        <lb/>      „Usłysz mnie, Srebnołuki, co troszczysz się o Chryzę,
                        <lb/>         i przenajświętszą Killę, i panujesz z mocą nad Tenedosem!
                        <lb/>         Jeśli mojego błagania wpierw wysłuchałeś, przez łaskę
                        <lb/>         mnie okazaną tak bardzo niszcząc plemiona Achajów,
                        <lb n="455"/>         teraz mnie także wysłuchaj i spełnij moje błagania:			
                        <lb/>         odwróć już teraz haniebną zagładę od ludu Danajów”.
                        <lb/>         Tak przemawiał, błagając. Wysłuchał go Fojbos Apollon.
                        <lb/>         Gdy już się pomodlili i rzucili jęczmień ofiarny,
                        <lb/>         najpierw odchylili (gardła) i zarżnęli i oskórowali,
                        <lb n="460"/>         wycięli udźce i okryli tłuszczem (błony otrzewnej) 			
                        <lb/>         z dwóch stron obwijając, na nich położyli kawałki surowego mięsa.
                        <lb/>         Spalał je na szczapie starzec i ciemnym winem
                        <lb/>         spryskiwał, a młodzi przy nim trzymali w rękach rożny o pięciu ostrzach
                        <lb/>        Gdy spaliły się udźce i skosztowano wnętrzności,
                        <lb n="465"/>        posiekali resztę i na rożny nadziali, 					
                        <lb/>          opiekli starannie, a potem z rożnów je zdjęto.
                        <lb/>          Gdy odpoczęli po trudach i przygotowali ucztę,
                        <lb/>          ucztowali, i niczego nie brakowało sercu z równej uczty.
                        <lb/>          Gdy napojem pragnienie i jadłem głód nasycili,
                        <lb n="470"/>          młodzieńcy wypełnili napojem mieszalniki po brzegi, 		
                        <lb/>          i po ulaniu libacji, rozlewali do wszystkich naczyń.
                        <lb/>          I przez cały dzień pieśnią modlitewną starali się zjednać boga
                        <lb/>         piękny śpiewając pajan, młodzieńcy achajscy,
                        <lb/>         opiewając Trafnostrzelnego, on zaś radował się słuchając.
                    </quote>
                    <p>430–6:	żegluga do Chryzy. Z punktu widzenia języka poetyckiego opis przybycia Odyseusza do Chryzy cechuje typowość scen i motywów oraz formularność (zob. Schipp 1972: 296 i nast.; Kirk 1985, ad loc.). Żegluga Odyseusza z hekatombą do Chryzy jest wyjątkowa na tle lądowej scenerii akcji Iliady, co sprawia, że formuły użyte do jej opisu znajdują swoje odpowiedniki w języku Odysei (np. Il. 1.432 = Od. 16.324). Zdanie wprowadzające epizod zaczyna się w połowie heksametru (… αὐτὰρ Ὀδυσσεὺς) i skupia na przewiezieniu hekatombe (ἄγων ἱερὴν ἑκατόμβην), pomijając na wstępie obecność na pokładzie Chryzejdy. </p>
                    <p>436–9:	zejście na ląd i wyładunek zwierząt ofiarnych. Emfatyczne czterokrotne użycie ἐκ na początku kolejnych heksametrów jest epanaforą, która stwarza nastrój pośpiesznego wyprowadzania ładunku okrętu z jednoczesnym zachowaniem ładu (Kirk 1985: 100): wyjście na ląd załogi, wyprowadzenie zwierząt ofiarnych (ἐκ δ᾽ ἑκατόμβην βῆσαν) i zejście na ląd Chryzejdy tworzy rodzaj procesji zmierzającej do ołtarza Apollona. </p>
                    <p>440: 	τὴν μὲν ἔπειτ᾽ ἐπὶ βωμὸν ἄγων πολύμητις Ὀδυσσεὺς – „wtedy prowadząc ją w stronę ołtarza, przemyślny Odyseusz”; ponieważ hekatomba jest składana w okręgu świętym Apollona Sminteusa, narrator konsekwentnie wspomina ołtarz (por. w. 448). W drugiej obszernej scenie typowej w Iliadzie (2.402-432), gdy ofiara jest składana przez Agamemnona w obozie Achajów, narrator o ołtarzu milczy. </p>
                    <p>442:	πρό μ᾽ ἔπεμψεν ἄναξ ἀνδρῶν Ἀγαμέμνων; poeta konsekwentnie podkreśla rolę Agamemnona jako ofiarującego, pana ofiary w terminologii nauki niemieckiej (Opferherr). W mowie Odyseusza jego autorytet został podkreślony formułą epicką ἄναξ ἀνδρῶν Ἀγαμέμνων (zob. Hitch 2009: 81; 141 i nast.).</p>
                    <p>442–443:	Φοίβῳ θ᾽ ἱερὴν ἑκατόμβην / ῥέξαι ὑπὲρ Δαναῶν ὄφρ᾽ ἱλασόμεσθα ἄνακτα – „a Fojbosowi świętą hekatombę / złożyć w sprawie Danajów, abyśmy zjednali pana”; w sprawie wyrażenia ἔρδω + ἑκατόμβην, zob. Casabona 1966: 52. </p>
                    <p>447–468:	scena typowa – ofiara krwawa. Najobszerniejszy w Iliadzie opis ofiary zwierzęcej jest rozbudowaną sceną typową, która zawiera niemal wszystkie elementy rytuału uwzględniane w rozbudowanych przedstawieniach scen ofiary w eposie w narracji głównej. Warianty, które pojawiają się w poszczególnych scenach typowych, mają uzasadnienie w kontekście narracyjnym. Hekatombe składana dla Apollona jest rytuałem odprawianym przy ołtarzu świątynnym, z kapłanem jako ofiarnikiem i Achajami jako ofiarującymi</p>
                    <p>447–448: θεῶι κλειτὴν ἑκατόμβην… ἔστησαν ἐΰδμητον περὶ βωμόν – „ustawili bogu wokół dobrze zbudowanego ołtarza sławną hekatombę”; ustawienie w krąg zwierząt ofiarnych pojawia się w scenach typowych, zob. Il. 2.410a: βοῦν δὲ περιστήσαντο – „ustawili woły wokół”; Od. 356a: τὰς δὲ περιστήσαντο. Por. wariant w opisie ofiary z wieprza złożonej przez Eumajosa, gdzie zamiast ołtarza mamy ἔσχαρη, „palenisko, ognisko”, a jedno zwierzę uniemożliwia ustawienie wkoło: τὸν μὲν ἔπειτ᾽ ἔστησαν ἐπ᾽ ἐσχάρῃ – „ustawili go przy ognisku” (Od. 14.420). Dwa przysłówki podkreślają, że po przyprowadzeniu na miejsce składania ofiar zwierzęta ofiarne ustawia się szybko (ὦκα) i „we właściwym porządku” (ἑξείης), najpewniej po to, aby nie dopuścić do zamieszania, tumultu przy ołtarzu. Przeciwstawienie gwałtownej śmierci na polu bitewnym, uporządkowanej i kontrolowanej przemocy podczas ofiary jest jedną z cech charakterystycznych epickiego obrazu świata, zob. Seaford 1993. 
                        ἐΰδμητον περὶ βωμόν – „wokół dobrze zbudowanego ołtarza”; wyrażenie por. Od. 7.100 (poza kontekstem ofiarnym). 
                  </p>
                    <p>449:	χερνίψαντο δ᾽ ἔπειτα καὶ οὐλοχύτας ἀνέλοντο – „kiedy obmyli swe ręce i jęczmień ofiarny pobrali”; wers formularny (= Il. 2.410); pojawiają się w nim archaiczne terminy techniczne słownictwa ofiarniczego: χερνίπτομαι oraz οὐλόχυται. 
                        χερνίψαντο – „obmyli swe ręce”; czasownik → χερνίπτομαι, termin techniczny utworzony od rzeczownika → χέρνιψ, „woda do mycia rąk”, który w kontekście ofiary i modlitwy pojawia się również w opisie ofiary Nestora (Od. 3.440 i 445). Obmycie rąk, jako forma rytualnego oczyszczenia, była warunkiem niezbędnym przed przystąpieniem do rytuałów ofiary krwawej i płynnej (Il. 6.266–8). W Odysei, gdy nowi przybysze dołączają do ucztujących, otrzymują wnętrzności do spróbowania, ulewają libację i modlą się, lecz brak wzmianki o obmyciu rąk (zob. Od. 3.5 i nast.). Poza kontekstem ofiarnym χέρνιψ oznacza wodę do mycia rąk (przed posiłkiem: Od. 1.136; 4.52). Malarstwo wazowe przedstawia χέρνιψ jako misę z imadłami, por. dyskusja u Atenajosa (Ath. 408b–9b, 9.75–6). Stałe kamienne misy oczyszczalne pojawiają się w sanktuariach pod koniec VII w. p.n.e. (Parker, 1983: 19–20). Na temat rytów otwierających, zob. Ginouvès 1968: 313–4; Moulinier 1950 71–74; van Straten 1995: 31–40. </p>
                    <p>449b: καὶ οὐλοχύτας ἀνέλοντο – „pobrali krupy/ziarno jęczmienne”; wers formularny (= Il. 2.410b). Chociaż w Iliadzie brak wzmianek o koszu, w którym przynoszono ziarno na miejsce odprawienia rytuału, czasownik ἀνέλοντο – „pobrali” sugeruje istnienie pojemnika, w którym ziarno było przechowywane; ziarno zostanie rzucone na zwierzę po odmówieniu modlitwy do Apollona (w. 458). Słowo → οὐλόχυται jest złożeniem, w którym drugim elementem jest przymiotnik –χυτός, „wylany, nasypany” utworzony od czasownika χέω, „wylewać” (o ciałach stałych), „sypać”, „usypać”, „rozrzucać”. J. Casabona widzi w nim przymiotnik określający → κριθαί – „jęczmień”. Znaczenie elementu οὐλο– jest trudniejsze do ustalenia; poprzez analogię np. z τεῖχος ἀμφίχυτον można przypuszczać, że określał sposób, cel lub adresata gestu rozsypywania ziaren (Casabona 1966: 283). W Od. 3.441 oraz źródłach pohomeryckich został zastąpiony rzeczownikiem οὐλαί. Od. 3.444–5 wprost łączy użycie wody do oczyszczeń i wzięcie ziaren jęczmienia z początkiem rytuału ofiarnego przy ołtarzu (γέρων δ᾽ ἱππηλάτα Νέστωρ / χέρνιβά τ᾽ οὐλοχύτας τε κατήρχετο – „starzec, jeździec Nestor / rozpoczął od wody i jęczmienia”). Towarzysze Odyseusza, gdy musieli złożyć ofiarę w miejscu, gdzie nie mieli dostępu do zboża, zamiast jęczmienia używają liści dębu (Od. 3.357–8: φύλλα δρεψάμενοι τέρενα δρυὸς ὑψικόμοιο· / οὐ γὰρ ἔχον κρῖ λευκὸν ἐϋσσέλμου ἐπὶ νηός, zob. comm. ad loc.). </p>
                    <p>450:	τοῖσιν δὲ Χρύσης μεγάλ᾽ εὔχετο χεῖρας ἀνασχών – „za nich zaś Chryses głośno pomodlił się wznosząc w górę ramiona”; użycie w tym miejscu konstrukcji εὔχομαι + dat. oznacza, że Chryses wznosi modlitwę za Achajów, odwołując tym samym prośbę skierowaną do Apollona o ukaranie ich z powodu córki (Pulleyn 2002). W wersie 458. czasownik εὔχομαι jest użyty w liczbie mnogiej, co sugeruje, że modlitwa, nawet wznoszona przez jednostkę, mogła być postrzegana jako akt zbiorowy, podobnie jak inne działania rytualne. </p>
                    <p>458–469:	Po modlitwie następują wersy formularne, które zostaną powtórzone w scenie Il.2.421–432, przedstawiającej ofiarę złożoną przez Agamemnona, z wyjątkiem wersów Il.1.462–463, które w Il.2.425–426 odchodzą od wspólnego schematu, lecz powracają w scenie ofiary Nestora w Odysei (3.459–460). </p>
                    <p>458:	αὐτὰρ ἐπεί ῥ᾽ εὔξαντο καὶ οὐλοχύτας προβάλοντο – „gdy już się pomodlili i rzucili jęczmień”; wers formularny podsumowujący ryty wstępne towarzyszące modlitwie (= Il. 2.421 = Od. 3.447; por. wariant w Od.12.359: αὐτὰρ ἐπεί ῥ᾽ εὔξαντο καὶ ἔσφαξαν καὶ ἔδειραν). Hemistych formularny αὐτὰρ ἐπεί ῥ᾽ εὔξαντο jest używany wyłącznie w kontekście sakralnym w scenach typowych – ofiara zwierzęca, co wyklucza świecką interpretację czasownika εὔχομαι, który nie oznacza tutaj po prostu „wypowiadać na głos uroczyste słowa”, lecz bardziej specyficznie „modlić się, wznieść modlitwę”. Na temat tego czasownika zob. Benveniste 1968; Muellner 1976 (omawiane miejsce jest analizowane na s. 31–37).	οὐλοχύτας προβάλοντο – „rzucili jęczmień”; w Od. 3.446 obmycie rąk, rozrzucenie jęczmienia i spalenie ściętej sierści są określone jako obrzędy pierwocinowe, działania poprzedzające ubój rytualny. W późniejszych źródłach uczestnicy obrzędu rzucają jęczmień do ognia rozpalonego na ołtarzu, na zwierzę ofiarne lub na uczestników obrzędu. W. Burkert (1972: 5) interpretował rzucenie ziaren na zwierzę jako gest agresji, wskazując na rytuały, w których zamiast zboża rzucano kamienie. F. Graf natomiast zwrócił uwagę na gatunek wykorzystywanego zboża – jęczmień był uważany za zboże uprawiane przez ludzi w czasach pierwotnych (Graf 2002: 121). </p>
                    <p>459a: αὐέρυσαν μὲν πρῶτα – „najpierw odchylili” (gardło zwierzęcia); (wers formularny = Il. 2.422a) po spełnieniu rytów wstępnych, uczestnicy obrzędu przystępują do uboju rytualnego. W epickich opisach uboju zwierzęcia ofiarnego występuje stała sekwencja czynności, lecz poszczególne sceny ogniskują uwagę na wybranych elementach. Sekwencja w najpełniejszej postaci miałaby postać: „(1) ogłuszenie zwierzęcia, (2) zarzynanie, (3) oskórowanie, (4) wytrybowanie, (5) sprawienie mięsa”. Chociaż jest ona stałym elementem scen uboju w eposie, nigdy nie pojawiają się wszystkie jej elementy w jednym miejscu. W Iliadzie nie pojawia się element (1) ogłuszenie zwierzęcia, który występuje w Odysei poprzez zadanie ciosu w kark zwierzęcia toporem (bydło) lub polanem (trzoda). Tutaj są obecne trzy elementy: (2), (3). Pełniejsza sekwencja, złożona z trzech elementów: (2) zarzynianie, (3) oskórowanie i (5) sprawianie mięsa, jest obecna w Il. 24.622 i niemal dosłownie jest powtórzona w Il. 7.314–316. W scenie uboju i przygotowania wieczerzy w Il. 18.559 (tarcza Achillesa)  pojawiają się elementy (1) and (3); natomiast w Il. 23.167 (2) i (3) at, Od. 8.61, 19.421  Nie należy tego przypisywać różnicom rytuału, lecz dążeniu Homera do zwięzłości opisu. Znaczenie czasownika αὐέρυσαν wyjaśnia Apollonios Sofista (Lex. Hom.): εἰς τοὐπίσω εἵλκυσαν, „odchylili do tyłu (kark)” w celu poderżnięcia gardła.
                        καὶ ἔσφαξαν – „i zarżnęli”; wers formularny (= Il. 2.422). Czasownik → σφάζω należy do języka technicznego ofiary. Podobnie jak w przypadku modlitwy, liczba mnoga nie musi wskazywać na poderżnięcie gardła zwierzęcia przez większą liczbę uczestników obrzędu. Możliwe jednak, że liczba mnoga podkreśla współudział kilku osób w uśmierceniu zwierzęcia. W Od. 3.454 gardło krowy podrzyna Pejsistratos, jednak przedstawienie ofiary prywatnej, skupione na współudziale członków rodziny obu płci, wymuszało większą szczegółowość opisu, zob. komentarz ad loc.  
                        καὶ ἔδειραν – „i oskórowali”; epos homerycki nie mówi wprost o dalszym losie skóry ściągniętej ze zwierzęcia, ale możemy przypuszczać, że była ona wykorzystywana jako materiał, który podlegał dalszej redystrybucji. Por. Il. 23.144–151 z komentarzem.
                    </p>
                    <p>460–461a:	μηρούς τ᾽ ἐξέταμον κατά τε κνίσῃ ἐκάλυψαν/ δίπτυχα ποιήσαντες – „wycięli udźce i ukryli w tłuszczu (błony otrzewnej) / z dwóch stron obwijając”; wersy formularne (= Il. 2, 427 = Od. 12, 364). Po oskórowaniu tuszy zwierzęcia ofiarnicy przygotowują część poświęconą dla bogów. Wyrażenie μηρούς τ᾽ ἐξέταμον –„wycięli udźce” (por.  ἐκ μηρία τάμνον, z tmezą, Od. 3.456), które występuje wyłącznie w rozbudowanych scenach typowych, można przetłumaczyć jako „wycięli udźce” (= kości udowe) z okrywającego je mięsa lub „odcięli udźce” (od korpusu). Otwiera w scenach typowych powtarzalny układ wersów opisujący procedurę przygotowania udźców (μηρούς) do spalenia (3x: Il. 1.464–5 = Il. 2.427–8 = Od. 12.364–5): μηρούς τ᾽ ἐξέταμον κατά τε κνίσῃ ἐκάλυψαν / δίπτυχα ποιήσαντες, ἐπ᾽ αὐτῶν δ᾽ ὠμοθέτησαν, por. wariant w opisie złożonej przez Nestora ofiary dla Ateny (Od. 3.456b–457, zob. komentarz ad. loc.): ἄφαρ δ᾽ ἐκ μηρία τάμνον / πάντα κατὰ μοῖραν, κατά τε κνίσῃ ἐκάλυψαν. Na temat κνίση zob. wyżej, 1.60 z komentarzem.</p>
                    <p>461b: ἐπ᾽ αὐτῶν δ᾽ ὠμοθέτησαν – „na nich położyli kawałki surowego mięsa”; (= Il. 2.424 = Od. 3.458 = Od. 12.424); czasownik → ὠμοθετέω, złożony z przymiotnika ὠμός, „surowy”, „nie pieczony” (o mięsie) i θετέω, „ułożyć” (SłG.-P.: „kłaść kawałki surowego mięsa ofiarnego na ołtarz”). Ryt szczegółowo opisany w Od.14.427–8: ὁ δ᾽ ὠμοθετεῖτο συβώτης, / πάντων ἀρχόμενος μελέων, ἐς πίονα δημόν – „świniopas ułożył surowe kawałki mięsa na tłustym sadle, składając ofiarę pierwocinową z wszystkich członków”. Znaczenie rytu nie jest jasne. Według Karla Meuliego (Meuli 1946: 306) i Waltera Burkerta (Burkert 1983: 6, 16) ryt kontynuuje tradycję paleolitycznych łowców, którzy ofiarowując cząstki zabitej ofiary zapewniali przetrwanie stad zwierząt jako odpowiedź na poczucie winy. </p>
                    <p>462–4:	Po przygotowaniu części dla bogów, ofiarnik spala ją na ołtarzu, w tym samym czasie młodzież piecze → σπλάγχνα – „wnętrzności”. Podział ról jest wyraźnie zaznaczony: stary kapłan Chryses (ὁ γέρων) nadzoruje spalanie kości udowych owiniętych w tłustą błonę otrzewnej i leje na ogień wino, natomiast młodzi pieką na tym samym ogniu ołtarzowym wnętrzności wyjęte z otrzewnej oraz serce, w miejsce których włożono kości. </p>
                    <p>462:	καῖε δ᾽ ἐπὶ σχίζῃς – „spalał na szczapie”; rzeczownik → σχίζα, „szczapa”, „polano”, „drzewo opałowe”; ponieważ wcześniej (448) był wspomniany ołtarz, możemy przypuszczać, że polana zostały tutaj użyte metonimicznie w zastępstwie ołtrza (βωμός); por. wyrażenie πολλὰ δὲ μηρί᾽ ἔκηε θεῶν ἱεροῖσ᾽ ἐπὶ βωμοὶς – „liczne kości udowe spalałem na świętych ołtarzach bogów”, Od. 3.273. ὁ γέρων, ἐπὶ δ᾽ αἴθοπα οἶνον / λεῖβε – „spalał starzec na szczapie, polewał lśniącym winem”. </p>
                    <p>463:	νέοι δὲ παρ᾽ αὐτὸν ἔχον πεμπώβολα χερσίν – „a młodzi przy nim trzymali w rękach rożny o pięciu ostrzach”; wers formularny (= Od. 3.460); gdy ofiarnik skrapia spalaną część przeznaczoną dla istoty nadprzyrodzonej ofiarą płynną z wina, młodzi uczestnicy obrzędu opiekają w tym samym ogniu organy wewnętrzne zwierzęcia nadziane na rożny o pięciu ostrzach, → πεμπώβολα. Niektórzy komentatorzy sugerują, że przedmiot opisywany przez Homera był podobny do znalezionego na terenie sanktuarium Apollona w Dendra zębatego widelca o wymiarach 11,2 cm długości na 7,5 cm szerokości. Por. Bruns, Archaeologia Homerica, t. Q: 39, zob. również Od. 3.460, West comm. ad loc.</p>
                    <p>464–6:	Wersy formularne opisujące czynności następujące po rytualnym spaleniu części przeznaczonej dla istoty nadprzyrodzonej, wylaniu libacji i skosztowaniu kawałeczków organów wewnętrznych przez uczestników obrzędu. W homeryckich opisach ofiary zwierzęcej połączonej z ucztą uwaga poety skupia się na przygotowywaniu części poświęconej bogom i wnętrzności, a następnie mięsa spożywanego przez ludzi. Opisy te składają się z wersów formularnych, lecz dopuszczają szereg wariantów dostosowanych do kontekstu i potrzeb narracji, natomiast sama uczta jest wspomniana w dość stereotypowych wersach formularnych. Na temat przygotowywania posiłku mięsnego z ofiar zwierzęcych, zob. van Straten 1995: 144–153. </p>
                    <p>466:	αὐτὰρ ἐπεὶ κατὰ μῆρ’ ἐκάη καὶ σπλάγχνα πάσαντο – „gdy udźce zostały spalone i skosztowali wnętrzności”; wers formularny (= Il. 2.427 = Od. 3.461 = Od. 12.364) podsumowujący pierwszą część obrzędu. Podmiotem czasownika κατὰ… ἐκάη w 3 os. ind. aor. pass. 3 sg. są → μῆρα, archaiczny rzeczownik kolektywny używany jako termin oznaczający kości udowe spalane dla bogów, co może wskazywać na wczesne pochodzenie formuły.
                        σπλάγχνα πάσαντο – „skosztowali wnętrzności”; rzeczownik kolektywny σπλάγχνα, podobnie jak μῆρα, jest terminem technicznym używanym w kontekście rytuału ofiary zwierzęcej (por. ἔγκατα, plurale tantum, por. pol. „wnętrzności”), co można wyjaśnić dążeniem do ujęcia wnętrzności jako nierozłącznego zbioru organów wewnętrznych wyjmowanych z ubitego zwierzęcia. Zdaje się, że ta symetria nie jest przypadkowa: w pierwszej części rytów następujących po uboju zwierzęcia bogowie otrzymują μῆρα, a ludzie σπλάγχνα. Widzieliśmy, że spalenie bogom należnej im części, przemiana jej w dym (κνίση) jest istotą ofiary rozumianej jako akt komunikacji między ludźmi i bogami, metonimicznie oznacza sam obrzęd ofiarny. Ryt odbywa się na ołtarzu. Korzystając z tego samego ognia, w którym dym spalanych polan miesza się z gęstym dymem spalanych kości i tłuszczu, ludzie przygotowują części zwierzęcia, które będą spożyte na miejscu, przy samym ołtarzu (późniejsze źródła podkreślają, że jeszcze gorące). W eposie brak opisu wyszczególniającego organy wchodzące w skład σπλάγχνα. Arystoteles w traktacie O częściach zwierząt wyróżnia: serce, płuca, wątrobę, śledzionę i nerki (De partibus animalium 664b–672b). Na temat σπλάγχνα, zob. Stengel 1910 [1970]: 73–78; Rudhardt 1958: 262, przyp. 8; Detienne 1977: 174–179; Durand 1979: 133–166 (zwł. 139–150); Berthiaume 1982: 60–61; van Straten 1995: 131–41 (zwł. 131–3); Ekroth 2008: 87–111 (zwł. 93–95).
                    </p>
                    <p>465–6:	μίστυλλόν τ᾽ ἄρα τἆλλα καὶ ἀμφ᾽ ὀβελοῖσιν ἔπειραν / ὤπτησάν τε περιφραδέως, ἐρύσαντό τε πάντα – „posiekali resztę i na rożny nadziali, / opiekli starannie, a potem wszystkie z rożnów je ściągnęli”: wers formularny (=  Il. 2.428 = Il. 7.317 = Il. 24.623 = Od. 3.462 = Od. 12.365 = Od. 14.430). W opisach homerowych posiłek przeznaczony dla ludzi składa się z drobno posiekanych kawałków mięsa, opiekanych na rożnach, przypomina zatem szaszłyki (souvlaki). W późniejszych źródłach mięso jest przygotowywane również w kotłach jak gulasz. Pojawia się wówczas opozycja między pieczonymi splanchna i gotowaną sarks, zob. Detienne 1977: 174.</p>
                    <p>467:	αὐτὰρ ἐπεὶ παύσαντο πόνου τετύκοντό τε δαῖτα – „gdy odpoczęli po trudach i przygotowali ucztę”: wers formularny (Il. 1.467 = Il. 2.430 = Il. 7.319, por. οἱ δ᾽ ἐπεὶ οὖν παύσαντο πόνου τετύκοντό τε δαῖτα,  Od. 16.478 = 24.384).</p>
                    <p>468:	δαίνυντ᾽, οὐδέ τι θυμὸς ἐδεύετο δαιτὸς ἐΐσης – „ucztowali, i niczego nie brakowało sercu z równej uczty”: wers formularny (Il. 1.468 = Il. 1.602 = Il. 2.431 = Il. 7.320 = Il. 23.56 = Od. 16.479 = Od. 19.425; por. Il. 4.48 = Il. 24.69).</p>
                    <p>469:	αὐτὰρ ἐπεὶ πόσιος καὶ ἐδητύος ἐξ ἔρον ἕντο – „gdy napojem pragnienie i jadłem głód nasycili”; wers formularny (Il. 1.469 = Il. 2.432 = Il. 7.323 = Il. 9.92 = Il. 9.222 = Il. 13.638 = Il. 23.57 = Il. 24.227 = Il. 24.628; Od. 1.150 = Od. 3.67 = Od. 3.473 = Od. 4.68 = Od. 8.72 = Od. 8.485 = Od. 12.308 = Od. 14.454 = Od. 15.143 = Od. 15.303 = Od. 15.501 = Od. 16.55 = Od. 17.99 = Od. 24.489). Ta bardzo częsta formuła zamknięcia (Abschlussformel) zaznacza koniec pierwszej części biesiady heroicznej, w czasie której uczestnicy uczty zaspokajają pragnienie i głód. Zdaje się, że organizacja uczty heroicznej zakładała jednoczesne jedzenie i picie. Zamknięcie przebiegu całej biesiady zaspokajającej potrzeby biologiczne krótką formułą pozwala skupić się na innych działaniach biesiadników, por. Arend 1933: 69–78 (zwł. 70); Węcowski 2011: 184–5.</p>
                    <p>470:	κοῦροι μὲν κρητῆρας ἐπεστέψαντο ποτοῖο – „młodzieńcy wypełnili napojem mieszalniki po brzegi”; wino do kraterów (mieszalników) nalewają młodzieńcy (κοῦροι), raczej członkowie elity społecznej, niż młodzi niewolnicy (por. Il. 9.175; Od. 1.148; Od. 3.339; Od. 21.271).</p>
                    <p>471:	νώμησαν δ᾽ ἄρα πᾶσιν ἐπαρξάμενοι δεπάεσσιν – „i po ulaniu libacji rozlewali do wszystkich naczyń”: znaczenie tej formuły wyjaśnił Paul Mazon (1937). Po przygotowaniu krateru, młodzieńcy, pełniący funkcję podczaszych, nalewają do czary każdego uczestnika biesiady po kilka kropel wina, które następnie, prawdopodobnie jednocześnie, są ulewane jako libacja rozpoczynające wspólne picie. Por. Węcowski 2011: 189.</p>
                    <p>472–5: ofiara oraz następująca po niej biesiada arystokratyczna nie wyczerpują działań podejmowanych w tym dniu. Ponieważ do złożenia ofiary przystąpiono natychmiast po przybyciu poselstwa, można zasadnie pytać o znaczenie pajanu, który śpiewają i zapewne tańczą młodzieńcy achajscy. Równie zaskakujące jest użycie czasownika ἱλάσκομαι, który wcześniej był wiązany ze złożeniem hekatomby. Teraz, chociaż hekatomba przebłagalna została już przyjęta, młodzież achajska wznosi przebłagalny pajan, zob. Faraone 2015.</p>
                    <p>472:	οἳ δὲ πανημέριοι μολπῇ θεὸν ἱλάσκοντο – i przez cały dzień pieśnią modlitewną starali się zjednać boga: zarówno użycie przymiotnika πανημέριοι, „działający przez cały dzień”, jak i czasownika ἱλάσκοντο w indicativus imperfecti wyrażającym trwanie czynności, podkreślają długotrwałość obrzędowej pieśni przebłagalnej.  </p>
                    
                </div>
            </div>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
