<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>τρίττοια βούαρχος</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher><ref target="https://site.unibo.it/lares/">LARES Project</ref></publisher>
                <date when="2021"/>
                <idno type="filename">lexicon_trittoia_bouarchos</idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>"Animal Sacrifice in Ancient Greece" database (<ref corresp="http://www.sacrificium.filg.uj.edu.pl">http://www.sacrificium.filg.uj.edu.pl</ref>).</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change when="2022-02-03" who="Irene Vagionakis">encoded document in XML</change>
                <change when="2016-05-03" who="Krzysztof Bielawski">created document contents</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="edition" xml:lang="it">
                <div type="textpart" >
                    <p><w>τρίττοια</w> <w>βούαρχος</w> tritto[i]a bo[u]archos. Un'offerta di tre animali, di cui il primo, cioè quello condotto davanti e il più importante, è il bue.</p>            
                    <p>Τρίττοια (trittoia, trittoa, tritys): un sacrificio di tre animali.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="textpart" n="Certificati">
                    <head>Certificati</head>
                    <p>Τρίττοια βούαρχος. La forma τρίττοια Ziehen (1906: 10 con nota 23) considera quella attica corretta (anche se appare solo in Herodian, ed. Lentz, I, p. 281, sotto); sulle iscrizioni si presenta come τρίττοα βόαρχος (catalogo completo delle occorrenze sotto), e nei lessicografi e negli scolastici come τριττύς (Eustath. commento all'Odissea, 11, 130-131 [1, 404, 16-19]; schol. Arista. Plut. 820, Callimaco fr. 578 nel Lessico di Fozio - sotto).</p>
                    <p>Il nome completo di due parole per questo tipo di sacrificio si verifica solo su iscrizioni nel V e IV secolo a.C. e molto più tardi da lessicografi, commentatori e studiosi. I riferimenti nella letteratura contengono solo riferimenti indiretti ad esso.</p>
                    <p>Formalmente la frase è formata dall'aggettivo deduttivo τρίττοια nel genere femminile (le forme possibili che si trovano nei testi sono τρίττοα, τριττύα, τρικτύα - vedi Bekees, e Chantraine s.v. τριτύς), presumibilmente come appendice del predefinito θυσία, e un aggettivo composto, costruito dal soggetto βου(Ϝ) (Bekees, e Chantraine s.v. βοῦς) e il soggetto ἀρχ-/ἀρχε- (vedi Chantraine s.v. <w>ἄρχω</w>), legato alle categorie di inizio, guida e partenza (<w>ἀρχή</w>, <w>ἄρχομαι</w>).</p>
                </div>
                <div type="textpart" n="Fonti_letterarie">
                    <head>Fonti letterarie</head>
                    <p>In Porfirio (De abstin. 2.60.5) la "trinità dalle corna d'oro" appare in alternativa all'ecatomba: ἢ πόθεν οἳ μὲν τριτύας χρυσόκερως, οἳ δ' ἑκατόμβας (...) ἔθυεν. Nelle vicinanze della catomba, come sacrificio equivalente per significato e gravità ad essa ricorre anche Suda (s.v. βουθυτεῖ) con un riferimento al Plutos di Aristofane (v. 820): Βουθυτεῖ- δοτικῇ. ᾿Αριστοφάνης Πλούτῳ. ὁ δεσπότης ἔνδον βουθυτεῖ. καταχρηστικῶς εἴρηται ἡ βουθυσία, δηλοῦσα τόν τε ὄγκον τοῦ μεγέθους καὶ τὸ ἐντελὲς τῆς θυσίας, ἣν ἑκατόμβην καλοῦσι καὶ τριτύν. ("Egli sacrifica un toro [βουθυτεῖ]: [che] si collega con dativ. Aristofane in Plutos. Il signore sacrifica un toro nel mezzo. Per catacresi lì parlano di 'sacrificare un toro', indicando l'importanza della grandezza e la natura straordinaria del sacrificio, che chiamano hecatomb e triplo [τριττύν]"). Lo stesso commento è incluso nello scholion a Plutos con una precisazione dell'informazione che il triplice sacrificio era considerato perfetto come la catomba (ad. loc.): Μεγάλην θυσίαν ποιεῖ, ἢ ἁπλῶς θύει. βουθυτεῖν κυρίως τὸ βοῦν θύειν. ἐκάλουν δὲ τὴν ἐντελῆ θυσίαν ἑκατόμβην διὰ τὸ ἐκ βοῶν ἑκατὸν γίνεσθαι. ἦν δὲ καὶ ἄλλη ἐντελὴς θυσία τριτὺς λεγομένη, ἡ ἐκ χοίρου καὶ κριοῦ καὶ τράγου, ἣν καὶ ἐνταῦθα λέγει ("Egli offre un grande sacrificio, o semplicemente fa un sacrificio. Fondamentalmente βουθυτεῖν significa "offrire un bue". Un sacrificio perfetto era chiamato hecatomb perché consisteva in cento buoi. Tuttavia, un altro sacrificio perfetto è stato chiamato 'triplo'. [τριττύς], composto da un maialino, un montone e una capra, ed è a questo che ci si riferisce qui"). Suda lo menziona anche paragonandolo al sacrificio di dodici animali (s.v. δωδεκίδες): Δωδεκίδες: θυσίαι δώδεκα ἱερείων, ὡς τριττύς, ἡ ἐκ τριῶν ("I dodici: sacrifici di dodici animali, come il triplo di tre"), e viceversa, quando parla del "triplo sacrificio" lo accosta al sacrificio di dodici animali (s. v. τριττύς): Τριττύς: ἡ ἐντελὴς θυσία, ἐκ συός, κριοῦ καὶ τράγου. ἐκ τριῶν, ὥσπερ δωδεκίδες, θυσίαι δώδεκα ἱερείων ("Triple. Un sacrificio perfetto, composto da un maiale, un montone e un caprone. Di tre animali, così come i dodici sono sacrifici di dodici animali").</p>
                    <p>Eustathios nel suo commento all'Odissea 11, 130-131 [1, 404, 16-19]:</p>
                    <p>᾿Ιστέον δὲ ὅτι ἡ τοιαύτη θυσία τριτττύα λέγεται παρὰ τοῖς παλαιοῖς, οἳ τριττύαν ἔλεγον τὴν ἐκ τριῶν ζώων θυσίαν, οἷον, δύο μήλων καὶ βοὸς, ὡς ᾿Επίχαρμος, ἢ βοὸς καὶ αἰγὸς καὶ προβάτου, ἢ κάπρου καὶ κριοῦ καὶ ταύρου. ἡ δὲ τοιαύτη καὶ βούπρωρος φασὶν ἐλέγετο διὰ τὸ προηγεῖσθαι αὐτῆς οἷα νηὸς πρώραν τὸν βοῦν.</p>
                    <p>"Bisogna sapere che un tale sacrificio è chiamato dagli antichi triplice sacrificio (τριττύα), e lo chiamavano triplice perché consiste di tre animali: due capretti e un bue, come in Epicharmus, o un bue, una capra e una pecora, o un maiale e un montone e un toro. Dicono che si chiama o sacrificio con un bue davanti (βούπρωρος1), perché un bue è condotto in testa, come sulla prua di una nave."</p>
                    <p>Esichio (s.v.) invece del nome tρίττοια βούαρχος usa ellitticamente la parola τρικτύα stessa, che, per inciso, appare in questo senso solo un'altra volta, in Atenaeus 11.59.19):</p>
                    <p>τρικτύα- τριάδα. ἔνιοι θυσία κάπρου, κριοῦ, ταύρου.</p>
                    <p>"Triktya: triade. In alcuni [è] un'offerta di un maiale, un montone e un toro".</p>
                    <p>Il riferimento a un sacrificio composto da tre animali di specie diverse si trova ancora in Erodiano in un trattato sulla prosodia (Lentz 1867: 281):</p>
                    <p>Τρίττοια ἡ θυσία, ἥτις ἐκ τριῶν ζώων ἐθύετο, ἢ ὅτι τριγενῆ ἦν τὰ θυόμενα ("un triplo sacrificio è quello fatto di tre animali, o è così chiamato perché gli animali sacrificali appartenevano a tre specie"). Per la trittoia erodiana era prima di tutto un sacrificio di tre animali; la questione della loro differenziazione, per non parlare della funzione particolare del toro in questa sequenza, era di secondaria, se non nulla, importanza.</p>
                    <p>I testi letterari chiave a cui si riferiscono i commenti dei lessicografi e degli studiosi sono Odissea 11, 130-131 e il verso 820 di Plutos di Aristofane. Nell'Odissea è la descrizione di un sacrificio (ἱερὰ καλὰ) a Poseidone (Ποσειδάωνι ἄνακτι) composto da una pecora, un toro e un verro da riproduzione scelti dal gregge (ἀρνειὸν ταῦρόν τε συῶν τ' ἐπιβήτορα κάπρον): ἕρξας ἱερὰ καλὰ Ποσειδάωνι ἄνακτι, / ἀρνειὸν ταῦρόν τε συῶν τ' ἐπιβήτορα κάπρον (significato di ἐπιβήτωρ secondo LSJ Supplement, pp. v.). Nel Plutos di Aristofane, Carione parla di Chremylos che sacrifica (qui commentato dagli studiosi, usando comicamente il verbo βουθυτέω2) un maiale, una capra e un montone: (...) ὁ δεσπότης μὲν ἔνδον βουθυτεῖ / ὗν καὶ τράγον καὶ κριὸν (...). I commentari moderni su entrambi i passaggi non danno loro particolare attenzione (cfr. ad esempio Heubeck, Hoeckstra 1989: 85).</p>
                    <p>L'attenzione dei commentatori non è stata ancora attirata da altre attestazioni di un sacrificio fatto di tre animali, che è opportuno notare qui.</p>
                    <p>Xenofonte (An. 2.2.9) parla anche di un sacrificio (del tipo sphagia) composto da un toro, un maiale e un montone (ταῦρον καὶ κάπρον καὶ κριὸν). Così anche, e nello stesso ordine, Plutarco (Pyrrh. 6.9: ταύρου καὶ κάπρου καὶ κριοῦ προσαχθέντος). Diodoro il Siciliano (4.39) parla di un'offerta a Eracle, fatta per onorarlo "come un eroe" (τιμᾶν ὡς ἥρωα τὸν ῾Ηρακλέα), che consisteva in un maiale, un toro e un montone (κάπρον καὶ ταῦρον καὶ κριὸν θύσας).  Pausania (2.11. 7), invece, parla del culto di Alessandro e di Euamernion, il primo dei quali è adorato come un eros (τῷ μὲν ὡς ἥρωι) con offerte bruciate (ἐναγίζουσιν), e al secondo gli abitanti di Epidauros offrono un sacrificio "come a un dio" (Εὐαμερίωνι δὲ ὡς θεῷ θύουσιν); questo sacrificio consiste in un toro, una pecora e un maiale (θυομένων δὲ τῷ θεῷ ταύρου καὶ ἀρνὸς καὶ ὑὸς). Un passus di Callimaco (fr. 578 nell'edizione: Pfeiffer 1949: 403) conservato nel Lexicon di Phocius (s.v. τριττύαν - II.227 ) cita successivamente un ariete, un toro e un maiale (τριττύαν θυσίαν Καλλίμαχος μὲν τὴν ἐκ κριοῦ, ταύρου καὶ κάπρου), e un passus dell'opera di Istro sulle epifanie di Apollo, conservati allo stesso punto nel Lessico di Fozio - buoi, capre e porcellini, tutti di tre anni (ἐκ βοῶν, αἰγῶν, ὑῶν ἀρρένων, πάντων τριετῶν); L'osservazione sull'età degli animali sacrificali è in questo passus l'unica di tutti i testi fonte su questo tipo di sacrificio (cfr. Hermary, Legiuilloux 2004: 110 - dove sono citate alcune delle fonti discusse sopra).</p>
                    <p>Nessuno di questi testi letterari - ad eccezione dell'estratto focese di Callimaco, di cui non possiamo verificare la formulazione originale - utilizza nessuna delle possibili forme del nome tecnico del triplice sacrificio, né in versioni parziali (τρίττοια o derivati) né complete (τρίττοια βόαρχος o derivati), e la composizione degli animali varia. È anche intrigante che non in tutti i casi discussi sopra, da Ziehen (1939: 329) considerati come esempi dell'adempimento del sacrificio trittoa boarchos, il toro (o il bue) è menzionato per primo (solo in Senofonte e Pausania). Quindi possiamo concludere che poiché in un sacrificio del tipo trittoa boarchos il numero delle vittime è altrettanto importante quanto il fatto che un bue sia il più importante - il che sembra seguire direttamente dal nome - allora un sacrificio fatto di tre animali deve essere diverso da uno in cui un bue è a capo di tre animali. Quindi una trittoia sarebbe diversa da una trittoia boarchos. Mentre il primo - senza nome - è confermato nei testi letterari, il secondo - con il suo nome completo in due parti - appare solo sulle iscrizioni e in connessione diretta o indiretta con Eleusi (vedi analisi delle iscrizioni qui sotto). È significativo che lo stesso Ziehen, in un commento alla sua edizione delle iscrizioni (1906: 11), più di trent'anni prima di scrivere l'articolo per RE, considerasse questo tipo di sacrificio esclusivamente associato a Eleusi - e probabilmente a ragione, dato che il commento non fa alcun riferimento ad attestazioni extra-epigrafiche.</p>
                    <p>Fonti epigrafiche (vedi Hermary, Legiuilloux 2004: 110):</p>
                        <p>Il nome tecnico completo del sacrificio: τρίττοια βούαρχος (con possibili modifiche) ricorre solo nel materiale epigrafico e sempre in connessione diretta o indiretta con Eleusi (Lupu 2005: 144; Sokolowski 1969 individua tre occorrenze: 4.5 [= 13 nell'edizione di Clinton], 5.37 [28a nell'edizione di Clinton], 16.6-12, quest'ultimo tre volte [manca da Clinton], LSJ s.v. nota una sola occorrenza, quella nell'iscrizione 4 [LSG]).</p>
                    <p>Nel materiale epigrafico il termine denota sempre un sacrificio di tre animali, di cui il primo, cioè quello condotto davanti e il più importante, è il bue, il che sembra significativo (vedi Ziehen 1906: 10-11, Dittenberger 1915: 106, Straten van 1995: 16-17, 71, illustrazione 6, e Sokolowski 1969: 8). Riguardo agli altri due animali non si può essere certi, e in ogni caso una chiave di carattere normativo non si trova nelle fonti epigrafiche. Nell'illustrazione della collezione di van Straten citata sopra, una pecora e un maiale sono visibili accanto a un bue, il che, presumibilmente in giustapposizione con i dati letterari discussi sopra, ha portato questo studioso a considerare questa rappresentazione normativa; egli non considera altre possibilità (Straten van 1995: 16); inoltre non nota (a differenza di Lupu 2005: 144) che tutte le attestazioni epigrafiche di questo tipo di sacrificio sono legate direttamente o indirettamente a Eleusi, così che la sua ricerca di un sacrificio prototipo per l'iconografia attica in analisi al di fuori del contesto eleusino deve essere considerata piuttosto rischiosa3. L'accettazione categorica della sua convinzione che la trittoia consistesse in un bue, una pecora e un maiale portò van Straten a rintracciare proprio una tale sequenza di animali su un'iscrizione attica (Straten van 1995: 17), contenente il calendario sacrificale di Maratona e Trikorinth (Sokolowski 1969: 46-50, iscrizione 20, colonna B verso 21) e subito a prendere questo - un'enumerazione essenzialmente casuale di un certo numero di animali sacrificali, oltre una dozzina di sequenze simili - come prova di forme non ateniesi (nella sua interpretazione nemmeno extra-allegre) di questo tipo di sacrificio, il che mi sembra errato (questi risultati sono comunque accettati da Hermary, Legiuilloux 2004: 110). </p>
                    <p>Trittoia boarchos appare su un'altra iscrizione, notata da Sokolowski (1969: 32-33, iscrizione numero 16). Clinton non lo include, anche se vi compare un link a Eleusis. Van Straten (1995: 17), d'altra parte, lo considera anche una forte prova della pratica di questo tipo di sacrificio in altri demos fuori <placeName key="Athens">Atene</placeName>. Perché contiene il regolamento del calendario sacrificale di Oinoe, situato a circa 50 chilometri a nord-ovest di Atene, sulla strada per Eleutherai. È datato al IV secolo a.C. (nessuna delle edizioni dettaglia la datazione). Oltre alla triplice invocazione di un sacrificio di tipo trittoia, il boarchos contiene un riferimento a due kerici (v. 3) e a Eleusi, forse, a seconda della versione del supplemento adottata, Eleusini (v. 4). Questi due dati importanti, leggibili e indiscutibili, sono completamente ignorati nei commenti critici. L'iscrizione prescrive il compimento di tre sacrifici trittoia boarchos: per Atremida l'Oenos (v. 5), per Apollon Morios (vv. 8-10) e per Atena l'Oenos (vv. 11-13). Queste tre offerte a queste tre divinità particolari potrebbero effettivamente essere considerate un rituale di carattere locale se l'iscrizione non contenesse un chiaro riferimento a Eleusi. È difficile dire quale tipo di connessione queste offerte possano indicare con il santuario (che si trova a metà strada tra Ojnoe, a cui si riferisce, e Atene, dove è stato trovato), ma non può essere trascurato.</p>
                    <p>La convinzione di Van Straten sugli animali che compongono un sacrificio di tipo trittoia, sviluppata sulla base di un'analisi della rappresentazione iconografica unitaria e frammentaria, deve essere rivista nella prospettiva di altri dati epigrafici. Nelle iscrizioni eleusine commentate di seguito (28 e 37 secondo la numerazione di Clinton), si fa riferimento ad animali con corna dorate - così, oltre al bue, sono inclusi anche un ariete e una capra (cfr. osservazioni di Dittenberger 1915: 83).</p>
                    <p>Il sacrificio in questione appare anche su un'iscrizione contenente la legge degli Anfitrioni delfici del 380/379 a.C. (IG II2 1126 v. 34 = Ziehen 1906: 226-234 n. 75), dove il suo nome appare nell'unica forma lì attestata: τρίκτευα (θύεν τρικτεύαν κηΰαν) come appendice del sostantivo κηΰα - un hapax legomenon considerato equivalente a καθάρματα (così LSJ).</p>
                    <p>Un'altra - dubbia, poiché integrata - occorrenza di un sacrificio di tipo trittoia su un'iscrizione contenente norme rituali per il demu Erchia, pubblicata da Lupu (2005: 115-149, documento n. 1, verso 41), deve essere notata: ἐς Πυθίο Ἀπόλλωνος τρίτ[τοαν ...] - dopo aggiunte di Daux (1980) e Labarbe (1977). Ciò significherebbe che - secondo Lupu (2005: 144) - gli abitanti di Thorikos erano obbligati a inviare un'offerta di questo tipo a uno dei santuari di Apollo il Pitico in Attica (Parker 1987: 146 suggerisce che un tale santuario potrebbe anche essere esistito a Thorikos stesso). Lupu, invece, sostiene che la preposizione ἐς, qui insolita, può indicare l'"invio" della vittima oltre il demos. Egli prende in considerazione il santuario di Apollo a Dafne, che ha una forte connessione con il demos di Thorikos, che a sua volta fornisce una traccia, certamente tenue, della connessione del sacrificio trittoia con il contesto eleusino, poiché il santuario di Dafne si trovava sulla strada sacra da Atene a Eleusi ed era il luogo di celebrazione durante la processione eleusina dei misteri (Mylonas 1961: 255).</p>
                    <p>Offerte del tipo trittoia - anche se senza invocare il loro nome tecnico - si verificano su altre due iscrizioni del III secolo a.C. fuori dall'Attica (trascurate da van Straten): su una da Kamiros (Sokolowski 1962: 164-165 = LSS 94) e su una da Kos (Ziehen 1906, 326-329 no. 131, v. 55-74). Nel primo caso il sacrificio si riferisce al culto di Poseidone e consiste in un toro (non più giovane di un anno): ταῦρον [μ]ὴ νεώτερον [ἐ]νιαυτίου), un montone (κριὸν πρατήνιον) e un maialino (χοῖρον); e nel secondo, offerte a Zeus (due volte ciascuno di due tori, due pecore e due maiali), Atena (lo stesso) e ancora a Zeus e Atena una volta ciascuno di tre animali - un toro, una pecora e un maiale. </p>
                    <p>Hermary, Legiuilloux 2004: 110 citano reperti archeologici di Taso che attestano i resti di un bue, un maiale e un ariete su due pire funerarie.</p>
                    <p>Più su questo nel commento alle Iscrizioni Eleusine.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            
            <div type="edition" xml:lang="en">
                <div type="textpart" >
                    <p>τρίττοια βούαρχος tritto[i]a bo[u]archos. An offering of three animals, of which the first, i.e., the one led in front and the most important, is the ox.</p>            
                    <p>Τρίττοια (trittoia, trittoa, tritys): a sacrifice of three animals.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="textpart" n="Certificates">
                    <head>Certificates</head>
                    <p>Τρίττοια βούαρχος. The form τρίττοια Ziehen (1906: 10 with note 23) considers to be the correct Attic one (although it appears only in Herodian, ed. Lentz, I, p. 281, below); on inscriptions it occurs as τρίττοα βόαρχος (full catalogue of occurrences below), and in lexicographers and scholiasts as τριττύς (Eustath. commentary on the Odyssey, 11, 130-131 [1, 404, 16-19]; schol. Arist. Plut. 820, Callimachus fr. 578 in the Lexicon of Phocius - below).</p>
                    <p>The full, two-word name for this type of sacrifice occurs only on inscriptions in the 5th and 4th centuries BC and much later by lexicographers, commentators and scholiasts. References in the literature contain only indirect references to it.</p>
                    <p>Formally the phrase is formed by the deductive adjective τρίττοια in the feminine gender (possible forms found in the texts are τρίττοα, τριττύα, τρικτύα - see Bekees, and Chantraine s.v. τριτύς), presumably as an appendage to the default θυσία, and a compound adjective, built from the subject βου(Ϝ) (Bekees, and Chantraine s.v. βοῦς) and the subject ἀρχ-/ἀρχε- (see Chantraine s.v. ἄρχω), related to the categories of beginning, leading and starting (ἀρχή, ἄρχομαι).</p>
                </div>
                <div type="textpart" n="Literary_sources">
                    <head>Literary sources</head>
                    <p>In Porphyry (De abstin. 2.60.5) the "trinity with golden horns" appears as an alternative to the hecatomb: ἢ πόθεν οἳ μὲν τριτύας χρυσόκερως, οἳ δ' ἑκατόμβας (...) ἔθυεν. In the neighbourhood of the hecatomb, as a sacrifice equivalent in meaning and seriousness to it, it also occurs in Suda (s.v. βουθυτεῖ) with a reference to Aristophanes' Plutos (v. 820): Βουθυτεῖ- δοτικῇ. ᾿Αριστοφάνης Πλούτῳ. ὁ δεσπότης ἔνδον βουθυτεῖ. καταχρηστικῶς εἴρηται ἡ βουθυσία, δηλοῦσα τόν τε ὄγκον τοῦ μεγέθους καὶ τὸ ἐντελὲς τῆς θυσίας, ἣν ἑκατόμβην καλοῦσι καὶ τριτύν. ("He sacrifices a bull [βουθυτεῖ]: [which] connects with dativ. Aristophanes in Plutos. The lord sacrifices a bull in the middle. By catachresis there they speak of 'sacrificing a bull', indicating the importance of the magnitude and extraordinary nature of the sacrifice, which they call hecatomb and triple [τριττύν]"). The same commentary is included in the scholion to Plutos with a detailing of the information that the triple sacrifice was considered as perfect as the hecatomb (ad. loc.): Μεγάλην θυσίαν ποιεῖ, ἢ ἁπλῶς θύει. βουθυτεῖν κυρίως τὸ βοῦν θύειν. ἐκάλουν δὲ τὴν ἐντελῆ θυσίαν ἑκατόμβην διὰ τὸ ἐκ βοῶν ἑκατὸν γίνεσθαι. ἦν δὲ καὶ ἄλλη ἐντελὴς θυσία τριτὺς λεγομένη, ἡ ἐκ χοίρου καὶ κριοῦ καὶ τράγου, ἣν καὶ ἐνταῦθα λέγει ("He makes a great sacrifice, or simply offers a sacrifice. Basically βουθυτεῖν means 'to offer an ox'. A perfect sacrifice was called a hecatomb because it consisted of a hundred oxen. However, another perfect sacrifice was called 'triple' [τριττύς], consisting of a piglet, a ram and a goat, and it is this that is referred to here"). Suda also mentions it by comparing it with the sacrifice of twelve animals (s.v. δωδεκίδες): Δωδεκίδες: θυσίαι δώδεκα ἱερείων, ὡς τριττύς, ἡ ἐκ τριῶν ("The twelve: sacrifices of twelve animals, as the triple of three"), and conversely, when he speaks of the "triple sacrifice" he juxtaposes it with the sacrifice of twelve animals (s. v. τριττύς): Τριττύς: ἡ ἐντελὴς θυσία, ἐκ συός, κριοῦ καὶ τράγου. ἐκ τριῶν, ὥσπερ δωδεκίδες, θυσίαι δώδεκα ἱερείων ("Triple. A perfect sacrifice, composed of a pig, a ram, and a goat. Of three animals, just as the twelve are sacrifices of twelve animals").</p>
                    <p>Eustathios in his commentary on Odyssey 11, 130-131 [1, 404, 16-19]:</p>
                    <p>᾿Ιστέον δὲ ὅτι ἡ τοιαύτη θυσία τριττύα λέγεται παρὰ τοῖς παλαιοῖς, οἳ τριττύαν ἔλεγον τὴν ἐκ τριῶν ζώων θυσίαν, οἷον, δύο μήλων καὶ βοὸς, ὡς ᾿Επίχαρμος, ἢ βοὸς καὶ αἰγὸς καὶ προβάτου, ἢ κάπρου καὶ κριοῦ καὶ ταύρου. ἡ δὲ τοιαύτη καὶ βούπρωρος φασὶν ἐλέγετο διὰ τὸ προηγεῖσθαι αὐτῆς οἷα νηὸς πρώραν τὸν βοῦν.</p>
                    <p>"It must be known that such a sacrifice is called in the ancients a triple sacrifice (τριττύα), and they called it triple because it consists of three animals: two kids and an ox, as in Epicharmus, or an ox, a goat and a sheep, or a pig and a ram and a bull. They say that it is called o sacrifice with an ox in front (βούπρωρος1), because an ox is led at its head, as if on the prow of a ship."</p>
                    <p>Hesychius (s.v.) instead of the name tρίττοια βούαρχος uses elliptically the word τρικτύα itself, which, incidentally, appears in this sense only once more, in Athenaeus 11.59.19):</p>
                    <p>τρικτύα- τριάδα. ἔνιοι θυσία κάπρου, κριοῦ, ταύρου.</p>
                    <p>"Triktya: triad. In some [it is] an offering of a hog, a ram and a bull".</p>
                    <p>The reference to a sacrifice consisting of three animals of different kinds is still found in Herodian in a treatise on prosody (Lentz 1867: 281):</p>
                    <p>Τρίττοια ἡ θυσία, ἥτις ἐκ τριῶν ζώων ἐθύετο, ἢ ὅτι τριγενῆ ἦν τὰ θυόμενα ("a triple sacrifice is one made of three animals, or it is so called because the sacrificial animals belonged to three species"). For the Herodian trittoia was first and foremost a sacrifice of three animals; the question of their differentiation, let alone the particular function of the bull in this sequence, was of secondary, if any, importance.</p>
                    <p>The key literary texts to which the commentaries of lexicographers and scholiasts refer are Odyssey 11, 130-131 and verse 820 of Plutos by Aristophanes. In the Odyssey it is a description of a sacrifice (ἱερὰ καλὰ) to Poseidon (Ποσειδάωνι ἄνακτι) consisting of a sheep, a bull and a breeding boar chosen from the flock (ἀρνειὸν ταῦρόν τε συῶν τ' ἐπιβήτορα κάπρον): ἕρξας ἱερὰ καλὰ Ποσειδάωνι ἄνακτι, / ἀρνειὸν ταῦρόν τε συῶν τ' ἐπιβήτορα κάπρον (meaning of ἐπιβήτωρ according to LSJ Supplement, pp. v.). In Aristophanes' Plutos, Carion speaks of Chremylos sacrificing (here commented on by scholiasts, indeed comically using the verb βουθυτέω2) a pig, a goat and a ram: (...) ὁ δεσπότης μὲν ἔνδον βουθυτεῖ / ὗν καὶ τράγον καὶ κριὸν (...). Modern commentaries on both passages do not give them special attention (cf. e.g. Heubeck, Hoeckstra 1989: 85).</p>
                    
                    <p>The attention of commentators has not yet been attracted by other attestations of a sacrifice made of three animals, which should be noted here.</p>
                    <p>Xenophont (An. 2.2.9) also speaks of a sacrifice (of the sphagia type) consisting of a bull, a hog and a ram (ταῦρον καὶ κάπρον καὶ κριὸν). So also, and in the same order, Plutarch (Pyrrh. 6.9: ταύρου καὶ κάπρου καὶ κριοῦ προσαχθέντος). Diodorus the Sicilian (4.39) speaks of and offering to Heracles, made to honour him "like a hero" (τιμᾶν ὡς ἥρωα τὸν ῾Ηρακλέα), which consisted of a hog, a bull and a ram (κάπρον καὶ ταῦρον καὶ κριὸν θύσας).  Pausanias (2.11. 7), on the other hand, speaks of the worship of Alexander and Euamernion, the former of whom is worshipped like a heros (τῷ μὲν ὡς ἥρωι) with burnt offerings (ἐναγίζουσιν), and to the latter the inhabitants of Epidauros offer a sacrifice "as to a god" (Εὐαμερίωνι δὲ ὡς θεῷ θύουσιν); this sacrifice consists of a bull, a sheep and a pig (θυομένων δὲ τῷ θεῷ ταύρου καὶ ἀρνὸς καὶ ὑὸς). A passus from Callimachus (fr. 578 in the edition: Pfeiffer 1949: 403) preserved in the Lexicon of Phocius (s.v. τριττύαν - II.227 ) mentions successively a ram, a bull and a hog (τριττύαν θυσίαν Καλλίμαχος μὲν τὴν ἐκ κριοῦ, ταύρου καὶ κάπρου), and a passus from Istros' work on the epiphanies of Apollo, preserved at the same point in Phocius' Lexicon - oxen, goats, and piglets, all three years old (ἐκ βοῶν, αἰγῶν, ὑῶν ἀρρένων, πάντων τριετῶν); the remark on the age of the sacrificial animals is in this passus the only one of all the source texts on this type of sacrifice (cf. Hermary, Legiuilloux 2004: 110 - where some of the sources discussed above are cited).</p>
                    <p>None of these literary texts - with the exception of the Phocian extract from Callimachus, the original wording of which we cannot verify - uses any of the possible forms of the technical name of the triple sacrifice, neither in partial (τρίττοια or derivatives) nor full (τρίττοια βόαρχος or derivatives) versions, and the composition of the animals varies. It is also intriguing that not in all the instances discussed above, by Ziehen (1939: 329) considered as examples of the fulfilment of the trittoa boarchos sacrifice, the bull (or ox) is mentioned first (only in Xenophon and Pausanias). Therefore we can conclude that since in a sacrifice of the trittoa boarchos type the number of victims is equally important as the fact that an ox is the most important one - which seems to follow directly from the name - then a sacrifice made of three animals must be different from one in which an ox is at the head of three animals. So would a trittoia be different from a trittoia boarchos. While the former - unnamed - is confirmed in literary texts, the latter - with its full two-part name - appears only on inscriptions and in direct or indirect connection with Eleusis (see analysis of inscriptions below). It is significant that the same Ziehen, in a commentary on his edition of the inscriptions (1906: 11), more than thirty years before he wrote the article for RE, considered this type of sacrifice to be exclusively associated with Eleusis - and probably rightly so, since the commentary makes no reference to extra-epigraphic attestations.</p>
                    <p>Epigraphic sources (see Hermary, Legiuilloux 2004: 110):</p>
                    <p>The full technical name of the sacrifice: τρίττοια βούαρχος (with possible modifications) occurs only in epigraphic material and always in direct or indirect connection with Eleusis (Lupu 2005: 144; Sokolowski 1969 locates three occurrences: 4.5 [= 13 in Clinton's edition], 5.37 [28a in Clinton's edition], 16.6-12, the latter three times [missing from Clinton], LSJ s.v. notes only one occurrence, that in inscription 4 [LSG]).</p>
                    <p>In the inscriptional material the term always denotes a sacrifice of three animals, of which the first, i.e. the one led in front and the most important, is the ox, which seems significant (see Ziehen 1906: 10-11, Dittenberger 1915: 106, Straten van 1995: 16-17, 71, illustration 6, and Sokolowski 1969: 8). With regard to the other two animals one cannot be certain, and in any case no key of a normative nature can be found in the epigraphic sources. In the illustration in van Straten's collection cited above, a sheep and a pig are visible next to an ox, which - presumably in juxtaposition with the literary data discussed above - led this scholar to consider this representation normative; he does not consider other possibilities (Straten van 1995: 16); he also fails to note (unlike Lupu 2005: 144) that all epigraphic attestations of this type of sacrifice are related directly or indirectly to Eleusis, so that his search for a prototype sacrifice for the Attic iconography under analysis outside the Eleusinian context must be considered rather risky3. The categorical acceptance of his belief that the trittoia consisted of an ox, a sheep and a pig led van Straten to track down just such a sequence of animals on one Attic inscription (Straten van 1995: 17), containing the sacrificial calendar of Marathon and Trikorinth (Sokolowski 1969: 46-50, inscription 20, column B verse 21) and immediately to take this - an essentially random enumeration of a number of sacrificial animals, over a dozen similar sequences - as evidence for non-Athenian (in his interpretation not even extra-Aleuzian) forms of this type of sacrifice, which I believe to be incorrect (these findings are, however, accepted by Hermary, Legiuilloux 2004: 110). </p>
                    <p>Trittoia boarchos appears on yet another inscription, noted by Sokolowski (1969: 32-33, inscription number 16). Clinton does not include it, although a link to Eleusis appears on it. Van Straten (1995: 17), on the other hand, also regards it as strong evidence for the practice of this type of sacrifice in other demos outside Athens. For it contains the regulations of the sacrificial calendar for Oinoe, located about 50 kilometres north-west of Athens, on the road to Eleutherai. It is dated to the 4th century BC. (none of the editions detail the dating). In addition to the threefold invocation of a trittoia type sacrifice, the boarchos contains a reference to two kerics (v. 3) and to Eleusis, possibly, depending on the version of the supplement adopted, Eleusini (v. 4). These two important data, legible and indisputable, are completely ignored in critical commentaries. The inscription prescribes the fulfilment of three trittoia boarchos sacrifices: for Atremida the Oenos (v. 5), for Apollon Morios (vv. 8-10) and for Athena the Oenos (vv. 11-13). These three offerings to these particular three deities could indeed be considered a ritual of local character if the inscription did not contain a clear reference to Eleusis. It is difficult to say what kind of connection these offerings might indicate with the sanctuary (lying halfway between Ojnoe, to which it refers, and Athens, where it was found), but it cannot be overlooked.</p>
                    <p>Van Straten's conviction about the animals comprising a trittoia-type sacrifice, developed on the basis of an analysis of unitary and fragmentary iconographic representation, needs to be revised in the perspective of still other epigraphic data. In the Eleusinian inscriptions commented on below (28 and 37 according to Clinton's numbering), reference is made to animals with gilded horns - thus, in addition to the ox, a ram and a goat are also included (cf. remarks by Dittenberger 1915: 83).</p>
                    <p>The sacrifice in question also appears on an inscription containing the law of the Delphic Amphictyons from 380/379 BC. (IG II2 1126 v. 34 = Ziehen 1906: 226-234 no. 75), where its name appears in the only form attested there: τρίκτευα (θύεν τρικτεύαν κηΰαν) as an appendage to the noun κηΰα - a hapax legomenon considered equivalent to καθάρματα (so LSJ).</p>
                    <p>Another - doubtful, since supplemented - occurrence of a trittoia-type sacrifice on an inscription containing ritual regulations for the demu Erchia, published by Lupu (2005: 115-149, document no. 1, verse 41), needs to be noted: ἐς Πυθίο Ἀπόλλωνος τρίτ[τοαν ...] - after additions by Daux (1980) and Labarbe (1977). This would mean that - in Lupu's (2005: 144) view - the inhabitants of Thorikos were obliged to send an offering of this type to one of the shrines of Apollo the Pythian in Attica (Parker 1987: 146 suggests that such a shrine may also have existed in Thorikos itself). Lupu, on the other hand, argues that the preposition ἐς, unusual here, may indicate the 'sending' of the victim beyond the demos. He takes into account the shrine of Apollo at Daphne, which has a strong connection with the demos of Thorikos, which in turn provides an, admittedly tenuous, trace of the connection of the trittoia sacrifice with the Eleusinian context, since the shrine at Daphne lay on the sacred road from Athens to Eleusis and was the place of celebration during the Eleusinian procession of mysteries (Mylonas 1961: 255).</p>
                    <p>Offerings of the trittoia type - albeit without invoking their technical name - occur on two more inscriptions from the 3rd century BC outside Attica (overlooked by van Straten): on one from Kamiros (Sokolowski 1962: 164-165 = LSS 94) and on one from Kos (Ziehen 1906, 326-329 no. 131, v. 55-74). In the first case the sacrifice relates to the worship of Poseidon and consists of a bull (no younger than one year old: ταῦρον [μ]ὴ νεώτερον [ἐ]νιαυτίου), a ram (κριὸν πρατήνιον) and a piglet (χοῖρον); and in the second, offerings to Zeus (twice each of two bulls, two sheep and two pigs), Athena (the same) and again to Zeus and Athena once each of three animals - a bull, a sheep and a pig. </p>
                    <p>Hermary, Legiuilloux 2004: 110 cite archaeological findings from Thasos attesting to the remains of an ox, a pig and a ram on two funeral pyres.</p>
                    <p>More on this in the commentary on the Eleusinian Inscriptions.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            
            <div type="edition" xml:lang="pl">
                <div type="textpart" >
                    <p>τρίττοια βούαρχος tritto[i]a bo[u]archos. ofiara z trzech zwierząt, z których pierwszym, tj. prowadzonym na przedzie i najważniejszym, jest wół.</p>            
                    <p>Τρίττοια (trittoia, trittoa, tritys): ofiara z trzech zwierząt.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="textpart" n="Poświadczenia">
                    <head>Poświadczenia</head>
                    <p>Τρίττοια βούαρχος. Formę τρίττοια Ziehen (1906: 10 z przypisem 23) uznaje za poprawną attycką (chociaż pojawia się ona jedynie u Herodiana, ed. Lentz, I, p. 281, poniżej); na inskrypcjach występuje w postaci τρίττοα βόαρχος (pełen katalog wystąpień poniżej), a u leksykografów i scholiastów – τριττύς (Eustath. komentarz do Odysei, 11, 130-131 [1, 404, 16-19]; schol. Arist. Plut. 820, Kallimach fr. 578 w Leksykonie Focjusza – poniżej).</p>
                    <p>Pełna, dwuwyrazowa nazwa tego typu ofiary występuję wyłącznie na inskrypcjach w V i IV wieku p.n.e. oraz dużo później u leksykografów, komentatorów i scholiastów. Odniesienia w literaturze zawierają do niej jedynie pośrednie nawiązania.</p>
                    <p>Formalnie rzecz biorą zwrot tworzy przymiotnik odliczebnikowy τρίττοια w rodzaju żeńskim (możliwe formy występujące w tekstach to τρίττοα, τριττύα, τρικτύα – zob. Bekees, oraz Chantraine s.v. τριτύς), zapewne jako przydawka do domyślnego θυσία oraz przymiotnik złożony, zbudowany z tematu βου(Ϝ) (Bekees oraz Chantraine s.v. βοῦς) i tematu ἀρχ-/ἀρχε- (zob. Chantraine s.v. ἄρχω), związanego z kategoriami początku, przewodzenia i rozpoczynania (ἀρχή, ἄρχομαι).</p>                    
                </div>
                <div type="textpart" n="Źródła_literackie">
                    <head>Źródła literackie</head>
                    <p>U Porfiriusza (De abstin. 2.60.5) „trójca o złotych rogach” pojawia się jako alternatywa hekatomby: ἢ πόθεν οἳ μὲν τριττύας χρυσόκερως, οἳ δ' ἑκατόμβας (…) ἔθυεν. W sąsiedztwie hekatomby, jako ofiara równoważna jej znaczeniem i powagą występuje też w Suda (s.v. βουθυτεῖ) z odniesieniem do Plutosa Arystofanesa (w. 820): Βουθυτεῖ· δοτικῇ. ᾿Αριστοφάνης Πλούτῳ. ὁ δεσπότης ἔνδον βουθυτεῖ. καταχρηστικῶς εἴρηται ἡ βουθυσία, δηλοῦσα τόν τε ὄγκον τοῦ μεγέθους καὶ τὸ ἐντελὲς τῆς θυσίας, ἣν ἑκατόμβην καλοῦσι καὶ τριττύν. („Składa w ofierze byka [βουθυτεῖ]: [co] łączy się z datiwem. Arystofanes w Plutosie. Pan składa w środku w ofierze byka. Przez katachrezę mówi się tam o ‘składaniu w ofierze byka’, wskazując na ważność wielkości i niezwykłość ofiary, którą nazywają hekatombą i potrójną [τριττύν]”). Ten sam komentarz został umieszczony w scholion do Plutosa z uszczegółowieniem informacji na temat tego, że ofiara potrójna była uważana za ofiarę tak samo doskonałą jak hekatomba (ad. loc.): Μεγάλην θυσίαν ποιεῖ, ἢ ἁπλῶς θύει. βουθυτεῖν κυρίως τὸ βοῦν θύειν. ἐκάλουν δὲ τὴν ἐντελῆ θυσίαν ἑκατόμβην διὰ τὸ ἐκ βοῶν ἑκατὸν γίνεσθαι. ἦν δὲ καὶ ἄλλη ἐντελὴς θυσία τριττὺς λεγομένη, ἡ ἐκ χοίρου καὶ κριοῦ καὶ τράγου, ἣν καὶ ἐνταῦθα λέγει („Składa wielką ofiarę, albo po prostu skłąda ofiarę. Zasadniczo βουθυτεῖν oznacza ‘ofiarowywać wołu’. Doskonałą ofiarę nazywano hekatombą, ponieważ składała się ze stu wołów. Jednak inną doskonałą ofiarę nazywano ‘potrójną’ [τριττύς], złożoną z prosięcia, barana i kozła, i to niej jest tu mowa”). Suda wspomina też o niej zestawiając ją dla porównania z ofiarą z dwunastu zwierząt (s.v. δωδεκίδες): Δωδεκίδες: θυσίαι δώδεκα ἱερείων, ὡς τριττύς, ἡ ἐκ τριῶν („Dwunastki: ofiary z dwunastu zwierząt, tak jak potrójna z trzech”) oraz na odwrót – kiedy mówi o „ofierze potrójnej” zestawia ją z ofiarą z dwunastu zwierząt (s.v. τριττύς): Τριττύς: ἡ ἐντελὴς θυσία, ἐκ συός, κριοῦ καὶ τράγου. ἐκ τριῶν, ὥσπερ δωδεκίδες, θυσίαι δώδεκα ἱερείων („Potrójna. Ofiara doskonała, złożona ze świni, barana i kozła. Z trzech zwierząt, tak jak dwunastki są ofiarami z dwunastu zwierząt”).</p>
                    <p>Eustathios w komentarzu do Odysei 11, 130-131 [1, 404, 16-19]:</p>
                    <p>᾿Ιστέον δὲ ὅτι ἡ τοιαύτη θυσία τριττύα λέγεται παρὰ τοῖς παλαιοῖς, οἳ τριττύαν ἔλεγον τὴν ἐκ τριῶν ζώων θυσίαν, οἷον, δύο μήλων καὶ βοὸς, ὡς ᾿Επίχαρμος, ἢ βοὸς καὶ αἰγὸς καὶ προβάτου, ἢ κάπρου καὶ κριοῦ καὶ ταύρου. ἡ δὲ τοιαύτη καὶ βούπρωρος φασὶν ἐλέγετο διὰ τὸ προηγεῖσθαι αὐτῆς οἷα νηὸς πρώραν τὸν βοῦν.</p>
                    <p>„Trzeba wiedzieć, że taka ofiara nazywa się u starożytnych potrójną (τριττύα), a nazywali ją potrójną, ponieważ składa się z trzech zwierząt: dwóch koźląt i wołu, jak u Epicharma, albo wołu, kozy i owcy, albo świni i barana, i byka. Powiadają, że nazywa się ją o ofiarą z wołem na przodzie (βούπρωρος1), ponieważ na jej czele prowadzi się wołu, tak jakby na dziobie okrętu”.</p>
                    <p>Hezychiusz (s.v.) zamiast nazwy tρίττοια βούαρχος używa eliptycznie samego słowa τρικτύα, które zresztą w takim znaczeniu pojawia się jeszcze tylko raz, u Atenajosa 11.59.19):</p>
                    <p>τρικτύα· τριάδα. ἔνιοι θυσία κάπρου, κριοῦ, ταύρου.</p>
                    <p>„Triktya: triada. U niektórych [jest to] ofiara z wieprza, barana i byka”.</p>
                    <p>Nawiązanie do ofiary złożonej z trzech zwierząt różnego rodzaju występuje jeszcze u Herodiana w traktacie o prozodii (Lentz 1867: 281):</p>
                    <p>Τρίττοια ἡ θυσία, ἥτις ἐκ τριῶν ζώων ἐθύετο, ἢ ὅτι τριγενῆ ἦν τὰ θυόμενα („potrójna ofiara, to taka, którą składano z trzech zwierząt, albo też nazywa się tak dlatego, że zwierzęta ofiarne należały do trzech gatunków”). Dla Herodiana trittoia była przede wszystkim ofiarą z trzech zwierząt, kwestia ich zróżnicowania, a tym bardziej szczególna funkcja byka w tej sekwencji miała znaczenie wtórne, o ile o w ogóle jakieś.</p>
                    <p>Kluczowymi tekstami literackimi, do których odwołują się komentarze leksykografów i scholiastów są Odyseja 11, 130-131 oraz wers 820 Plutosa Arystofanesa. W Odysei jest to opis ofiary (ἱερὰ καλὰ) dla Posejdona (Ποσειδάωνι ἄνακτι), na którą składa się owca, byk i rozpłodowy knur wybrany spośród trzody (ἀρνειὸν ταῦρόν τε συῶν τ' ἐπιβήτορα κάπρον): ἕρξας ἱερὰ καλὰ Ποσειδάωνι ἄνακτι, / ἀρνειὸν ταῦρόν τε συῶν τ' ἐπιβήτορα κάπρον (znaczenie ἐπιβήτωρ wg LSJ Supplement, s.v.). W Plutosie Arystofanesa Karion mówi o tym, że Chremylos składa w ofierze (tu komentowany przez scholiastów, rzeczywiście komicznie użyty czasownik βουθυτέω2) świnię, kozła i barana: (…) ὁ δεσπότης μὲν ἔνδον βουθυτεῖ / ὗν καὶ τράγον καὶ κριὸν (…). Nowożytne komentarze do obydwu passusów nie poświęcają im specjalnej uwagi (por. np. Heubeck, Hoeckstra 1989: 85).</p>
                    <p>Uwagi komentatorów nie przyciągnęły jeszcze inne poświadczenia ofiary złożonej z trzech zwierząt, które należy tutaj odnotować.</p>
                    <p>Ksenofont (An. 2.2.9) również mówi o ofierze (typu sfagia), na którą złożyły się byk, wieprz i baran (ταῦρον καὶ κάπρον καὶ κριὸν). Tak samo i w takiej samej kolejności – Plutarch (Pyrrh. 6.9: ταύρου καὶ κάπρου καὶ κριοῦ προσαχθέντος). Diodor Sycylijski (4.39) mówi i ofierze dla Heraklesa, złożonej aby uczcić go „jak herosa” (τιμᾶν ὡς ἥρωα τὸν ῾Ηρακλέα), na którą składały się wieprz, byk i baran (κάπρον καὶ ταῦρον καὶ κριὸν θύσας).  Pauzaniasz (2.11.7) natomiast mówi o kulcie Aleksanora i Euamerniona, z których pierwszy jest czczony jak heros (τῷ μὲν ὡς ἥρωι) ofiarami całopalnymi (ἐναγίζουσιν), a drugiemu mieszkańcy Epidauros składają ofiarę „jak bogu” (Εὐαμερίωνι δὲ ὡς θεῷ θύουσιν); ofiara ta składa się z byka, owcy i świni (θυομένων δὲ τῷ θεῷ ταύρου καὶ ἀρνὸς καὶ ὑὸς). Passus z Kallimacha (fr. 578 w wydaniu: Pfeiffer 1949: 403) zachowany w Leksykonie Focjusza (s.v. τριττύαν – II.227) wymienia kolejno barana, byka i wieprza (τριττύαν θυσίαν Καλλίμαχος μὲν τὴν ἐκ κριοῦ, ταύρου καὶ κάπρου), a passus z dzieła Istrosa o epifaniach Apollona, zachowany w tym samym punkcie Leksykonu Focjusza – woły, kozy i prosięta, wszystkie trzyletnie (ἐκ βοῶν, αἰγῶν, ὑῶν ἀρρένων, πάντων τριετῶν); uwaga o wieku zwierząt ofiarnych jest w tym passusie jedyną spośród wszystkich tekstów źródłowych na temat tego typu ofiary (por. Hermary, Legiuilloux 2004: 110 – gdzie przywołana jest część źródeł omówionych powyżej źródeł).</p>
                    <p>Żaden z tych tekstów literackich – z wyjątkiem Focjuszowego wyimku z Kallimacha, którego pierwotnego brzmienia nie możemy zweryfikować – nie posługuje się jakąkolwiek z możliwych form technicznej nazwy potrójnej ofiary, ani w wersji częściowej (τρίττοια lub pochodne), ani pełnej (τρίττοια βόαρχος lub pochodne), a skład zwierząt jest różny. Intrygujące również, że nie we wszystkich wypadkach omówionych powyżej, przez Ziehena (1939: 329) uznanych za przykłady spełniania ofiary trittoa boarchos, byk (lub wół) wymieniane są na pierwszym miejscu (tylko u Ksenofonta i Pauzaniasza). Można więc wywieść wniosek, że skoro w ofierze typu trittoa boarchos równie istotna jest liczba ofiar, jak i fakt, że wół jest spośród nich najważniejszy – co zdaje się wynikać bezpośrednio z nazwy, to czym innym musi być ofiara z trzech zwierząt, a czym innym taka, w której na czele trzech zwierząt jest wół. Czy innym więc byłaby trittoia, a czym innym trittoia boarchos. O ile pierwsza z nich – nienazwana – znajduje potwierdzenie w tekstach literackich, o tyle druga – z pełną dwuczłonową nazwą – pojawia się wyłącznie na inskrypcjach i w bezpośrednim lub pośrednim związku z Eleusis (zob. analiza inskrypcji poniżej). Znamienne, że ten sam Ziehen w komentarzu do swojej edycji inskrypcji (1906: 11), ponad trzydzieści lat przed napisaniem artykułu do RE, uważał ten typ ofiary za wyłącznie związany z Eleusis – i zapewne słusznie, ponieważ komentarz ten nie zawiera odniesień do pozaepigraficznych poświadczeń.</p>
                    <p>Źródła epigraficzne (zob. Hermary, Legiuilloux 2004: 110):</p>
                    <p>Pełna nazwa techniczna ofiary: τρίττοια βούαρχος (z możliwymi modyfikacjami) występuje wyłącznie w materiale epigraficznym i zawsze w bezpośrednim lub pośrednim związku z Eleusis (Lupu 2005: 144; Sokolowski 1969 lokalizuje trzy wystąpienia: 4.5 [= 13 w edycji Clintona], 5.37 [28a w edycji Clintona], 16.6-12, w tej ostatnie trzykrotnie [brak u Clintona], LSJ s.v. notuje tylko jedno wystąpienie, to w inskrypcji 4 [LSG]).</p>
                    <p>W materiale inskrypcyjnym termin ten oznacza zawsze ofiarę z trzech zwierząt, z których pierwszym, tj. prowadzonym na przedzie i najważniejszym, jest wół, co zdaje się znaczące (zob. Ziehen 1906: 10-11, Dittenberger 1915: 106, Straten van 1995: 16-17, 71, ilustracja 6 oraz Sokolowski 1969: 8). Co do pozostałych dwóch zwierząt nie można mieć pewności, a w każdym razie w źródłach epigraficznych nie można znaleźć klucza o charakterze normatywnym. Na przywołanej powyżej ilustracji w zbiorze van Stratena obok wołu widoczne są owca i świnia, co – zapewne w zestawieniu z danymi literackimi, omówionymi powyżej – doprowadziło tego uczonego do uznania tego przedstawienia za normatywne; nie bierze on pod uwagę innych możliwości (Straten van 1995: 16); nie zauważył on również (inaczej niż Lupu 2005: 144), że wszystkie poświadczenia epigraficzne tego typu ofiary związane są bezpośrednio lub pośrednio z Eleusis, wobec czego jego poszukiwania prototypu ofiary dla analizowanej ikonografii attyckiej poza kontekstem eleuzyjskim należy uznać za dość ryzykowne3. Kategoryczne uznanie  swego przekonania o tym, że na trittoia składają się wół, owca i świnia za słuszne, doprowadziło van Stratena do wytropienia takiej właśnie sekwencji zwierząt na jednej inskrypcji attyckiej (Straten van 1995: 17), zawierającej kalendarz ofiarny Maratonu i Trikoryntu (Sokolowski 1969: 46-50, inskrypcja 20, kolumna B wers 21) oraz natychmiastowo do uznania tego – przypadkowego w gruncie rzeczy wyliczenia szeregu zwierząt ofiarnych, w ciągu kilkunastu podobnych sekwencji – za dowód na pozaateńskie (w jego interpretacji nawet nie pozaeleuzyjskie) formy tego typu ofiary, co uważam za błędne (ustalenia te przyjmują jednak Hermary, Legiuilloux 2004: 110).</p>
                    <p>Trittoia boarchos pojawia się na jeszcze jednej inskrypcji, odnotowanej przez Sokolowskiego (1969: 32-33, numer inskrypcji 16). Clinton jej nie uwzględnia, mimo że pojawia się na niej związek z Eleusis. Van Straten natomiast (1995: 17) ją także uznaje za mocny dowód na praktykowanie tego typu ofiary w innych demach poza Atenami. Zawiera ona bowiem regulacje kalendarza ofiarnego dla Oinoe, położonego ok. 50 kilometrów na północny-zachód od Aten, przy drodze do Eleutherai. Datowana jest na IV wiek p.n.e. (żadna z edycji nie uszczegóławia datacji). Oprócz trzykrotnego przywołania ofiary typu trittoia boarchos zawiera odniesienie do dwóch keryków (w. 3) oraz do Eleusis, ewentualnie, w zależności od przyjętej wersji suplementacji – eleuziniów (w. 4). Te dwie istotne dane, czytelne i bezsporne, w komentarzach krytycznych są całkowicie pomijane. Inskrypcja nakazuje spełnienie trzech ofiar typu trittoia boarchos: dla Atremidy Ojnoejskiej (w. 5), dla Apollona Moriosa (w. 8-10) i dla Ateny Ojnoejskiej (w. 11-13). Te trzy ofiary dla tych konkretnych trzech bóstw mogłyby rzeczywiście zostać uznane za rytuał o charakterze lokalnym, gdyby inskrypcja nie zawierała czytelnego odniesienia do Eleusis. Trudno orzec, na jakiego rodzaju związek tych ofiar z sanktuarium (leżącym w połowie drogi między Ojnoe, której dotyczy, a Atenami, gdzie została znaleziona) może to wskazywać, nie można jednak go nie dostrzegać.</p>
                    <p>Przekonanie van Stratena na temat zwierząt składających się na ofiarę typu trittoia, wypracowane w oparciu o analizę jednostkowego i fragmentarycznego przedstawienia ikonograficznego wymaga rewizji w perspektywie jeszcze innych danych epigraficznych. W komentowanych poniżej inskrypcjach eleuzyjskich (28 i 37 wg numeracji Clintona) mowa jest o zwierzętach, które mają złocone rogi – w rachubę wchodzą więc obok wołu jeszcze baran i kozioł (por. uwagi Dittenbergera 1915: 83).</p>
                    <p>Omawiana ofiara występuje też na inskrypcji zawierającej prawo amfiktionów delfickich z lat 380/379 p.n.e. (<ref type="ins">IG II2 1126</ref> w. 34 = Ziehen 1906: 226-234 nr 75), gdzie jej nazwa pojawia się w tylko tam poświadczonej formie: τρίκτευα (θύεν τρικτεύαν κηΰαν) jako przydawka do rzeczownika κηΰα – hapax legomenon uznawany za równoznaczny z καθάρματα (tak LSJ).</p>
                    <p>Odnotowania wymaga jeszcze jedno – wątpliwe, ponieważ suplementowane – wystąpienie ofiary typu trittoia na inskrypcji zawierającej regulacje rytualne dla demu Erchia, opublikowanej przez Lupu (2005: 115-149, dokument nr 1, wers 41): ἐς Πυθίο Ἀπόλλωνος τρίτ[τοαν ...] – za uzupełnieniami Dauxa (1980) i Labarbe (1977). Oznaczałoby to, że – w opinii Lupu (2005: 144) – mieszkańcy Thorikos zobowiązani byli do wysłania ofiary tego typu do jednego z sanktuariów <persName type="divine" key="Apollo">Apollona</persName> Pytyjskiego na terenie Attyki (Parker 1987: 146 sugeruje, że w samym Thorikos także mogło takie sanktuarium istnieć). Lupu z kolei argumentuje, że nietypowy tutaj przyimek ἐς może wskazywać na „wysyłanie” ofiary poza granice demu. Bierze on pod uwagę sanktuarium Apollona w Dafne, pozostające w silnym związku z demem Thorikos, co z kolei stanowi, nikły wprawdzie, ślad związku ofiary trittoia z kontekstem eleuzyjskim, ponieważ sanktuarium w Dafne leżało przy drodze świętej z Aten do Eleusis i było miejscem obchodów podczas procesji eleuzyjskiej misteriów (Mylonas 1961: 255).</p>
                    <p>Ofiary typu trittoia – jakkolwiek bez przywołania ich technicznej nazwy – występują jeszcze na dwóch inskrypcjach z III wieku p.n.e. spoza Attyki (przeoczył je van Straten): na jednej z Kamiros (Sokolowski 1962: 164-165 = LSS 94) oraz na jednej z Kos (Ziehen 1906, 326-329 nr 131, w. 55-74). W pierwszym przypadku ofiara dotyczy kultu <persName type="divine" key="Poseidon">Posejdona</persName> i składa się z byka (nie młodszego niż jednoroczny: ταῦρον [μ]ὴ νεώτερον [ἐ]νιαυτίου), barana (κριὸν πρατήνιον) i prosięcia (χοῖρον); a w drugim – ofiar dla Zeusa (dwa razy po dwa byki, dwie owce i dwie świnie), Ateny (tak samo) i jeszcze raz dla Zeusa i dla Ateny po jeden raz po trójce zwierząt – byk, owca i świnia.</p>
                    <p>Hermary, Legiuilloux 2004: 110 przytaczają wyniki badań archeologicznych z Thasos, poświadczających resztki wołu, świni i barana na dwóch stosach pogrzebowych.</p>
                    <p>Więcej na ten temat w komentarzu do Inskrypcji eleuzyjskich.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            
            <div type="bibliography">
                <p>Beekes R., 2010, Etymological Dictionary of Greek, dwa tomy, numeracja ciągła, Leiden.</p>
                <p>Chantraine, P., 1968, Dictionnaire étymologique de la langue grecque. Histoire des mots, Paris [avec un Supplément: 1999]</p>
                <p>Daux, G., 1980, “Calendrier sacrificial de Thorikos”, CRAI, 463-470.</p>
                <p>Dittenberger, G., 1915, Sylloge Inscriptionum Graecarum, vol. 1, Lipsiae.</p>
                <p>Hermary, A., Legiuilloux, M., 2004, Les sacrifices dans le monde grec, ThesCRA, vol. I, Los Angeles, 59-134.</p>
                <p>Heubeck, A., Hoeckstra, A., 1989, A Commentary on Homer’s Odyssey, vol. 2: Books IX-XVI, Oxford.</p>
                <p>Labarbe, J., 1977, Thorikos: Les Testimonia (FdTh I), Ghent.</p>
                <p>Lentz, A., (ed.), 1867, Herodiani Technici Reliquiae, Lipsiae.</p>
                <p>Lupu, E., 2005, Greek Sacred Law. A Collection of New Documents (NGSL), Leiden.</p>
                <p>Mylonas G., 1961, Eleusis and Eleusinian Mysteries, Princeton.</p>
                <p>Parker, R., 1987, “Festivals of the Attic Demes”, [w:] Gifts to the Gods: Proceedings of the Uppsala Symposium 1985 (Boreas 15), ed. T. Linders, G. Nordquist, 137-147.</p>
                <p>Pfeiffer, R., (ed.), 1949, Callimachus, vol 1: Fragmenta, Oxford.</p>
                <p>Sokolowski, F., 1962, Lois sacrées des cités grecques. Supplément, Paris (=LSS).</p>
                <p>Sokolowski F., 1969, Lois Sacrées des cites grecques, Paris (=LSCG).</p>
                <p>Straten van F.T., 1995, Hiera kala. Images of Animal Sacrifice in Archaic Classical Greece, Leiden.</p>
                <p>Ziehen, L., 1906, Leges Graecorum Sacrae e Titulis Collectae, pars altera, Lipsiae.</p>
                <p>Ziehen, L., 1939, Τρίττοια, RΕ, II/13, Stuttgart, 328-330.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
