<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Δωρίς</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher><ref target="https://site.unibo.it/lares/">LARES Project</ref></publisher>
                <date when="2021"/>
                <idno type="filename">lexicon_doris</idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>"Animal Sacrifice in Ancient Greece" database (<ref corresp="http://www.sacrificium.filg.uj.edu.pl">http://www.sacrificium.filg.uj.edu.pl</ref>).</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change when="2022-02-03" who="Irene Vagionakis">encoded document in XML</change>
                <change when="2018-05-08" who="Przemysław Biernat">updated document contents</change>
                <change when="2015-03-31" who="Przemysław Biernat">created document contents</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="edition" xml:lang="it">
                <div type="textpart">
                    <p><w>Δωρίς</w> Doris, ίδος, subst. f. nome di un tipo di coltello, letteralmente, doris</p>                    
                </div>
                <div type="textpart" n="Etimologia">
                    <head>Etimologia</head>
                    <p>Originariamente un aggettivo femminile con il significato di "Dorian" (cfr. Theoc. 2.156: τὰν Δωρίδα ... ὄλπαν, "Dorian olpe"). Usato per indicare un coltello, è diventato sostantivo, come indicato dal suo uso in Euripide (ὁ δ᾽ εὐκρότητον Δωρίδ᾽ ἁρπάσας χεροῖν, 'ed egli avendo afferrato nelle sue mani il ben forgiato Dorian ... ", Eu. El. 819). Morfologicamente la parola era formata con il suffisso -id-, usato per la derivazione degli aggettivi (Chantraine 1933: 339).</p>                    
                </div>
                <div type="textpart" n="Testimonianze">
                    <head>Testimonianze</head>
                    <p>Nella letteratura del periodo classico, la parola appare solo nell'Elettra di Euripide (E. El. 819), e il contesto della sua occorrenza suggerisce che fosse il nome di una varietà dorica (o almeno considerata tale) di coltello massiccio, chiamato kopida (Δωρικὴ [scil. κοπίς], E. El. 836; → <ref corresp="lexicon_kopis.html"><w>κοπίς</w></ref>).</p>
                    <p>Nella letteratura più tarda incontriamo anche il sostantivo δορίς, ίδος, che denota un coltello: nel comico Anaxippos (6.3) compare nel contesto di altri utensili da cucina, tra cui il kopid, mentre nell'Aites di Callimaco ricorre in un contesto esplicitamente sacrificale (οἱ βόες ὀξεῖαν δερκόμενοι δορίδα, Call. fr. 75.11). Data la bassa frequenza di occorrenze di questa parola, sembra che Callimaco la sostituisca al posto di una banale machaira (→ <ref corresp="lexicon_machaira.html">μάχαιρα</ref>), o come parte di uno sfoggio erudito (due righe prima lo stesso coltello era riferito dall'altrettanto rara, probabilmente eolica parola μαῦλις: Call. Fr. 75.9; cfr. Harder 2012: 591), o allo scopo di raggiungere la strumentazione del voicing (δερκόμενοι δορίδα), e molto probabilmente per entrambi gli scopi contemporaneamente. Che abbiamo a che fare con una parola rara è sostenuto dal fatto che sebbene l'Onomasticon di Polluce (II secolo d.C.) elenchi δορίδες come parte dell'attrezzatura del cuoco in una fila con la copida e le machaires (Poll. 6.89, cf. 10. 104: κοπίδες καὶ δορίδες καὶ μαχαιρίδες), poi già negli Attika onomata del contemporaneo di Polluce, il grammatico e lessicografo Elias Dionysius δορίδες sono spiegati come μαγειρικαὶ τράπεζαι, cime di cuoco (Ael.Dion, s.v.).</p>                    
                </div>
            </div>
            
            <div type="edition" xml:lang="en">
                <div type="textpart">
                    <p>Δωρίς Doris, ίδος, subst. f. name of a type of knife, literally, doris</p>                    
                </div>
                <div type="textpart" n="Etymology">
                    <head>Etymology</head>
                    <p>Originally a feminine adjective with the meaning "Dorian" (cf. Theoc. 2.156: τὰν Δωρίδα ... ὄλπαν, "Dorian olpe"). Used to denote a knife, it has become substantivised, as indicated by its use in Euripides (ὁ δ᾽ εὐκρότητον Δωρίδ᾽ ἁρπάσας χεροῖν, 'and he having grasped in his hands the well-forged Dorian ... ", Eu. El. 819). Morphologically the word was formed with the suffix -id-, used for the derivation of adjectives (Chantraine 1933: 339).</p>                    
                </div>
                <div type="textpart" n="Testimonies">
                    <head>Testimonies</head>
                    <p>In the literature of the classical period, the word appears only in Euripides' Electra (E. El. 819), and the context of its occurrence suggests that it was the name of a Doric (or at least considered to be such) variety of massive knife, called a kopida (Δωρικὴ [scil. κοπίς], E. El. 836; → <ref corresp="lexicon_kopis.html">κοπίς</ref>).</p>
                    <p>In later literature we also encounter the noun δορίς, ίδος, denoting a knife: in the comedian Anaxippos (6.3) it appears in the context of other cooking utensils, including the kopid, while in Callimachus' Aites it occurs in an explicitly sacrificial context (οἱ βόες ὀξεῖαν δερκόμενοι δορίδα, Call. fr. 75.11). Given the low frequency of occurrences of this word, it seems that Callimachus substitutes it in place of a trivial machaira (→ <ref corresp="lexicon_machaira.html">μάχαιρα</ref>), or as part of an erudite display (two lines earlier the same knife was referred to by the equally rare, probably aeolian word <w>μαῦλις</w>: Call. Fr. 75.9; cf. Harder 2012: 591), or for the purpose of gaining voicing instrumentation (δερκόμενοι δορίδα), and most likely for both purposes simultaneously. That we are dealing with a rare word is supported by the fact that although the Onomasticon of Pollux (2nd century AD) lists δορίδες as part of the cook's equipment in one row with the copida and the machaires (Poll. 6.89, cf. 10. 104: κοπίδες καὶ δορίδες καὶ μαχαιρίδες), then already in the Attika onomata of Pollux's contemporary the grammarian and lexicographer Elias Dionysius δορίδες are explained as μαγειρικαὶ τράπεζαι, cook tops (Ael.Dion, s.v.).</p>                    
                </div>
            </div>
            
            <div type="edition" xml:lang="pl">
                <div type="textpart">
                    <p>Δωρίς Doris, ίδος, subst. f. nazwa jakiegoś typu noża, dosł. doryjka</p>                    
                </div>
                <div type="textpart" n="Etymologia">
                    <head>Etymologia</head>
                    <p>Pierwotnie przymiotnik żeński o znaczeniu „doryjska” (cf. <ref type="lit">Theoc. 2.156</ref>: τὰν Δωρίδα … ὄλπαν, „doryjską olpe”). Użyty na określenie noża, uległ substantywizacji, na co wskazuje użycie u Eurypidesa (ὁ δ᾽ εὐκρότητον Δωρίδ᾽ ἁρπάσας χεροῖν, „on zaś chwyciwszy w dłonie dobrze wykutą doryjkę... “, Eu. El. 819). Morfologicznie wyraz utworzony został za pomocą sufiksu -id-, służącego do derywacji przymiotników (Chantraine 1933: 339).</p>                    
                </div>
                <div type="textpart" n="Poświadczenia">
                    <head>Poświadczenia</head>
                    <p>W literaturze epoki klasycznej słowo pojawia się jedynie w Elektrze Eurypidesa (<ref type="lit">E. El. 819</ref>), a z kontekstu jego wystąpienia wynika, że była to nazwa doryckiej (a przynajmniej uważanej za taką) odmiany masywnego noża, zwanego kopidą (Δωρικὴ [scil. κοπίς], E. El. 836; → <ref corresp="lexicon_kopis.html">κοπίς</ref>).</p>
                    <p>W późniejszej literaturze spotykamy się też z oznaczającym nóż rzeczownikiem δορίς, ίδος: u komediopisarza Anaksipposa (6.3) pojawia się ona w kontekście innych przyrządów kuchennych, m.in. kopid, w Aitiach Kallimacha występuje natomiast w kontekście jednoznacznie ofiarniczym (οἱ βόες ὀξεῖαν δερκόμενοι δορίδα, <ref type="lit">Call. fr. 75.11</ref>). Zważywszy na niską frekwencję wystąpień tego słowa wydaje się, że <persName key="Callimachus">Kallimach</persName> podstawia je w miejsce trywialnej machairy (→ <ref corresp="lexicon_machaira.html"><w>μάχαιρα</w></ref>), czy to w ramach erudycyjnego popisu (dwie linijki wcześniej ten sam nóż został określony równie rzadkim, prawdopodobnie eolskim słowem μαῦλις: Call. fr. 75.9; cf. Harder 2012: 591), czy dla uzyskania instrumentacji zgłoskowej (δερκόμενοι δορίδα), a najprawdopodobniej w obu tych celach jednocześnie. Za tym, że mamy do czynienia z rzadkim słowem, przemawia fakt, że chociaż Onomastikon Polluksa (II wiek n.e.) wymienia δορίδες jako element wyposażenia kucharza w jednym rzędzie z kopidą i machairami (<ref type="lit">Poll. 6.89</ref>, cf. 10.104: κοπίδες καὶ δορίδες καὶ μαχαιρίδες), to już w Attika onomata współczesnego Polluksowi gramatyka i leksykografa Eliusza Dionizjusza δορίδες objaśnione są jako μαγειρικαὶ τράπεζαι, blaty kucharskie (Ael.Dion., s.v.).</p>                    
                </div>
            </div>
            
            <div type="bibliography">
                <p> Chantraine, Pierre, 1933, La formation des noms en grec ancien, Paris.</p>
                <p>Harder, Anette, 2012, Callimachus, Aetia. Introduction, Text, Translation, and Commentary by Anette Harder, vol. 2, Oxford.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
