<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>μηρός</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher><ref target="https://site.unibo.it/lares/">LARES Project</ref></publisher>
                <date when="2021"/>
                <idno type="filename">lexicon_meros</idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digital document.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change when="2022-02-03" who="Irene Vagionakis">encoded document in XML</change>
                <change when="2015-03-31" who="Lech Trzcionkowski">created document contents</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="edition" xml:lang="it">
                <div type="textpart">
                    <p><w>μηρός</w> mēros, subst. m., coscia, nel contesto di un sacrificio di sangue più spesso al plurale. μηρούς, coscia.</p>                    
                </div>
                <div type="textpart" n="Etimologia">
                    <head>Etimologia</head>
                    <p>Il sostantivo μηρός, "coscia" deriva da i.e. *mēms-ro, cfr. latino membrum, membra, "membri del corpo, membra" (&amp;lt; pit. *memsro), st.irl. mír "porzione di carne, pezzo, scarto". Secondo Brent Vein, *mēms-ro è una derivazione a ritroso dal sostantivo collettivo *mēms-reh2 (Vein 2002). Secondo un'interpretazione più probabile, *mēms-ro è un aggettivo ("carnoso") che è diventato una parola non ufficiale in una fase iniziale, continuata da forme greche, latine e irlandesi. Queste parole, a differenza delle parole di continuazione cioè *mē(m)s-(o)-, hanno subito un processo di specializzazione e significano "parte di carne, boccone, porzione" o "membro muscolare, coscia".  Si può quindi supporre che l'evoluzione semantica della parola *mēms-ro sia andata come segue: "carnoso" &gt; "arto muscolare, membro del corpo" "coscia"; (nel contesto della macellazione) "gamba" (cfr. pol. "udo" / "udziec" - "coscia di un grosso animale destinato al consumo").</p>                    
                </div>
                <div type="textpart" n="Dichiarazioni">
                    <head>Dichiarazioni</head>
                    <p>Nell'epica omerica, <w>μηρούς</w> come termine sacrificale appare solo nel contesto della prima fase del processo rituale, cioè la preparazione della parte dell'animale sacrificale destinata agli dei: dopo che la μηρούς è stata tagliata, viene avvolta con il grasso su entrambi i lati e sopra vengono posti pezzi di carne cruda di altre parti dell'animale. Più tardi sembra essere sinonimo della parola → <w>μηρία</w>, che sostituisce nel tempo.</p>
                    <p>Nell'epica l'espressione μηρούς τ᾽ ἐξέταμον, "hanno tagliato le gambe" (Il. 1.464 = Il. 2.427 = Od. 12.364 (3x), cfr. ἐκ μηρία τάμνον, con la tesi, Od. 3.456) si verifica solo in descrizioni estese che descrivono il corso del rituale sacrificale (scena tipica). Il verbo <w>ἐκτάμνειν</w> può suggerire di tagliare le ossa nude e pulire la carne, ma può anche significare semplicemente 'tagliare, tagliare le gambe (dal corpo)'. 
                        Nelle scene tipiche troviamo una disposizione ripetitiva di versi che descrivono la procedura di preparazione delle gambe (μηρούς) per il rogo (Il. 1.464-5 = Il. 2.427-8 = Od. 12. 364-5): μηρούς τ᾽ ἐξέταμον κατά τε κνίσῃ ἐκάλυψαν / δίπτυχα ποιήσαντες, ἐπ᾽ αὐτῶν δ᾽ ὠμοθέτησαν, "tagliarono le gambe e le coprirono di grasso (membrane peritoneali) / su due lati avvolgenti, su di esse posero pezzi di carne cruda", cfr. variante nella descrizione di Nestore del sacrificio ad Atena (Od. 3.456b-457, vedi commento ad. loc. ): ἄφαρ δ᾽ ἐκ μηρία τάμνον / πάντα κατὰ μοῖραν, κατά τε κνίσῃ ἐκάλυψαν, "tagliarono i femori / tutti secondo i doli, e li ricoprirono di grasso (della membrana peritoneale)". Anche nel periodo post-classico, l'usanza tipicamente greca di tagliare le gambe / femori di un animale sacrificato e di bruciarle sull'altare sono espresse dalle frasi τοὺς μηροὺς ἐκτέμνειν, "tagliare le gambe" (Paus. 1.24.2; 2.11.7), τοὺς μηροὺς καύειν, "bruciare le gambe" (Paus. 2.10.1) e τοὺς μηροὺς θύειν, "sacrificare le gambe" (Paus. 2.10.5), cfr. Pirenne-Delforge 2008, 187-197.</p>
                    <p>Al di fuori dell'epica, le descrizioni tecniche della preparazione delle parti del sacrificio destinate agli dei appaiono principalmente nella commedia, dove, a causa della loro ambiguità, i termini μερώ o μερός "coscia / gamba" possono assumere sfumature sessuali. Allo stesso tempo, questi testi portano informazioni su altre parti dell'animale destinate agli dei avvolte in una membrana peritoneale grassa. Dalla confluenza di Ferekrates, risulta che gli dei ricevono il μερώ nascosto sotto i "numerosi θυλήματα" sbucciati dalla carne, insieme a ὀσφῦς e σπόνδυλος (fr. 28 Kassel-Austin = fr. 23 Kock: εὖ τὼ μηρὼ περιλέψαντες [κομιδῇ] μέχρι βουβώνων &lt;κρέα πάντα&gt; / καὶ τὴν ὀσφὺν κομιδῇ ψιλήν, λοιπὸν τὸν σπόνδυλον αὐτὸν / εἶτ᾽ ἀλλήλους αἰσχυνόμενοι θυλήμασι κρύπτετε πολλοῖς {testo rotto! : "[carne] dalle zampe mangiata fino all'osso [intero] / E quest'osso del tutto nudo con il resto del collo / ci date in modo ingannevole come cani rognosi / per vergogna che qualcuno veda, intero sotto copertura (trad. K. Bartol)" o "si afferrano entrambe le gambe, fino all'inguine / Tagliando accuratamente la carne; dall'anca l'osso completamente nudo, / Inoltre, avendo ripulito la spina dorsale come con una sega, / si getta a noi come ai cani, e per vergogna di fronte all'altro / si copre di nuovo con un dono sacrificale. (tradotto da Janina Niemirska-Pliszczyńska)". In Eubulos (fr. 127 Kassel-Austin fr. 130 Kock) gli dei si lamentano che gli umani sacrificano loro "solo coda e coscia (τὴν κέρκον μόνην / καὶ μηρὸν)", con un esplicito riferimento a rapporti anali pederastici.</p>
                    <p>Le fonti epigrafiche ci forniscono la prova dell'uso del sostantivo μηρούς per indicare la parte di un animale sacrificale destinata agli dei. Il più antico proviene da Mileto (c. 500 a.C.), dove una stele iscritta su due lati è stata trovata sul sito del Dauphinion con un'iscrizione contenente un oracolo di Apollo che regola il culto di Eracle (LSAM 42). Lo stato di conservazione del documento non ci permette di trarre conclusioni di vasta portata; tuttavia, a pagina B leggiamo la raccomandazione di bruciare le gambe posteriori (B, l. 2: μηροὶ καίωνται) e la localizzazione di qualcosa vicino al femore (B, ll. 3-4: π̣[α|ρ]ὰ τοῖς μηρίοισ[ι -| πα]ρατιθέναι). La mancanza di contesto impedisce la presentazione di un'ipotesi per spiegare l'esitazione tra μηροί e μηρία. L'iscrizione di Demu Phrearrhioi (300-250 a.C. circa). ) sul culto locale degli dei eleusini prescrive il compimento di qualche atto sugli altari (ἐπὶ δὲ τοὺς βωμοὺς), presumibilmente il rogo, 'μηροὺς μασχαλίσματα ἡμίκαιραν, "gambe, pezzi tagliati dalla spalla, mezza testa (SEG XXXV = NGSL 3, ll. 16-8)", vedi Lupu 2005, 166-168.</p>
                    <p>In epoca classica, appaiono le prime testimonianze di pratiche mantiche che accompagnano la combustione, e di conseguenza descrizioni dettagliate delle anomalie del processo di combustione della parte dedicata agli dei. I cattivi presagi sono descritti in dettaglio da Tiresia nell'Antigone di Sofocle (S.Ant. xx-xx ): ἀλλ᾽ ἐπὶ σποδῷ μυδῶσα κηκὶς μηρίων ἐτήκετο κἄτυφε κἀνέπτυε, καὶ μετάρσιοι χολαὶ διεσπείροντο, καὶ καταρρυεῖς μηροὶ καλυπτῆς ἐξέκειντο πιμελῆς, "ma dalle gambe trasudava / gorgogliando sulla cenere e scorreva, / e fumava, e sfrigolava, e la bile schizzava in alto, / le viscide gambe sacrificali emergevano da sotto il grasso che le ricopriva. "</p>
                    <p>Catalogo delle attestazioni (solo le occorrenze della parola μηροί nel contesto di un sacrificio di sangue):</p>
                    <p>1. femori:</p>
                    <p>a. tagliare, tagliare via</p>
                    <p>μηρούς + ἐκτάμνειν "tagliare le cosce, tagliare i femori (?)":Il. 1.464 = Il. 2.427 = Od. 12.364; Paus. 1.24.2; 2.11.7</p>
                    <p>b. pulito (di carne)</p>
                    <p>μηρώ + περιλέπειν "sbucciare, pulire (dalla carne)": Pherecr. fr. 28 Kassel-Austin = fr. 23 Kock</p>
                    <p>c. bruciare (su un altare):</p>
                    <p>μηροὺς + καύειν: Paus. 2.10.1</p>
                    <p>μηροί + καίεσθαι: LSAM 42, B, l. 2.</p>
                    <p>2. femori, gambe:</p>
                    <p>a. sacrificato</p>
                    <p>μηρόν o μηρούς + θύειν, "sacrificare le gambe": Euboulos, fr. 127 Kassel-Austin = fr. 130 Kock; Paus. 2.10.</p>                    
                </div>
            </div>
            
            <div type="edition" xml:lang="en">
                <div type="textpart">
                    <p>μηρός mēros, subst. m., thigh, in the context of a blood sacrifice more often in the plural. μηρούς, thigh.</p>                    
                </div>
                <div type="textpart" n="Etymology">
                    <head>Etymology</head>
                    <p>The noun μηρός, 'thigh' is derived from i.e. *mēms-ro, cf. Latin membrum, membra, "members of the body, limbs" (&amp;lt; pit. *memsro), st.irl. mír "portion of meat, piece, scrap". According to Brent Vein, *mēms-ro is a backward derivation from the collective noun *mēms-reh2 (Vein 2002). According to a more likely interpretation, *mēms-ro is an adjective ('meaty') which became a unofficial word at an early stage, continued by Greek, Latin and Irish forms. These words, unlike the continuation words i.e. *mē(m)s-(o)-, have undergone a process of specialisation and mean 'part of meat, bite, portion' or 'muscular member, thigh'.  It can therefore be assumed that the semantic evolution of the word *mēms-ro went as follows: "meaty" &gt; "muscular limb, member of the body" &gt; "thigh" &gt; (in the context of slaughter) "leg" (cf. pol. "udo" / "udziec" - "thigh of a large animal intended for consumption").</p>                    
                </div>
                <div type="textpart" n="Statements">
                    <head>Statements</head>
                    <p>In the Homeric epic, μηρούς as a sacrificial term appears only in the context of the first phase of the ritual process, i.e. the preparation of the part of the sacrificial animal destined for the gods: after the μηρούς is cut off, it is wrapped with fat on both sides and raw pieces of meat from other parts of the animal are laid on top. Later it seems to be synonymous with the word → μηρία, which it replaces over time.</p>
                    <p>In the epic the expression μηρούς τ᾽ ἐξέταμον, "they cut the legs" (Il. 1.464 = Il. 2.427 = Od. 12.364 (3x), cf. ἐκ μηρία τάμνον, with the thesis, Od. 3.456) occurs only in extended descriptions depicting the course of the sacrificial ritual (typical scene). The verb ἐκτάμνειν may suggest cutting out the bare bones and cleansing the meat, but it can also mean simply 'to cut off, to chop off the legs (from the body)'. In the typical scenes we find a repetitive arrangement of verses describing the procedure for preparing the legs (μηρούς) for burning (Il. 1.464-5 = Il. 2.427-8 = Od. 12. 364-5): μηρούς τ᾽ ἐξέταμον κατά τε κνίσῃ ἐκάλυψαν / δίπτυχα ποιήσαντες, ἐπ᾽ αὐτῶν δ᾽ ὠμοθέτησαν, "they cut out the legs and covered them with fat (peritoneal membranes) / on two sides wrapping, on these they laid pieces of raw meat", cf. variant in Nestor's description of the sacrifice to Athena (Od. 3.456b-457, see comment ad. loc. ): ἄφαρ δ᾽ ἐκ μηρία τάμνον / πάντα κατὰ μοῖραν, κατά τε κνίσῃ ἐκάλυψαν, "they cut out the femurs / all according to the doli, and covered them with fat (of the peritoneal membrane)". Also in the post-classical period, the typically Greek custom of cutting out the legs / femurs of an animal sacrificed and burning them on the altar are expressed by the phrases τοὺς μηροὺς ἐκτέμνειν, "cut out the legs" (Paus. 1.24.2; 2.11.7), τοὺς μηροὺς καύειν, "burn the legs" (Paus. 2.10.1) and τοὺς μηροὺς θύειν, "to sacrifice the legs" (Paus. 2.10.5), cf. Pirenne-Delforge 2008, 187-197.</p>
                    <p>Outside of the epic, technical descriptions of the preparation of parts of the sacrifice intended for the gods appear primarily in comedy, where, due to their ambiguity, the terms μερώ or μερός 'thigh / leg' can take on sexual overtones. At the same time, these texts bring information about other parts of the animal intended for the gods wrapped in a fatty peritoneal membrane. From the Ferekrates Confluence, it appears that the gods receive the μερώ hidden under the "numerous θυλήματα" peeled from the meat, together with ὀσφῦς and σπόνδυλος (fr. 28 Kassel-Austin = fr. 23 Kock: εὖ τὼ μηρὼ περιλέψαντες [κομιδῇ] μέχρι βουβώνων &lt;κρέα πάντα&gt; / καὶ τὴν ὀσφὺν κομιδῇ ψιλήν, λοιπὸν τὸν σπόνδυλον αὐτὸν / εἶτ᾽ ἀλλήλους αἰσχυνόμενοι θυλήμασι κρύπτετε πολλοῖς {text broken! : "[meat] from the legs eaten down to the bone [whole] / And this bone quite bare with the rest of the neck / you give deceitfully to us like mangy dogs / for shame that someone will see, whole under cover (transl. K. Bartol)" or "you grab both legs, up to the groin / Carefully cutting out the meat; from the hip the bone completely naked, / Also, having cleaned the spine as if with a saw, / you throw to us as if to dogs, and out of shame in front of each other / you cover it again with a sacrificial gift. (translated by Janina Niemirska-Pliszczyńska)'. In Eubulos (fr. 127 Kassel-Austin fr. 130 Kock) the gods complain that humans sacrifice to them "only tail and thigh (τὴν κέρκον μόνην / καὶ μηρὸν)", with an explicit reference to pederastic anal relations.</p>
                    <p>Epigraphic sources provide us with evidence of the use of the noun μηρούς to denote the part of a sacrificial animal intended for the gods. The earliest comes from Miletus (c. 500 BC), where a double-sided inscribed stele was found on the site of the Dauphinion with an inscription containing an oracle from Apollo regulating the cult of Heracles (LSAM 42). The state of preservation of the document does not allow us to draw far-reaching conclusions; nevertheless, on page B we read the recommendation to burn the hind legs (B, l. 2: μηροὶ καίωνται) and the location of something near the femur (B, ll. 3-4: π̣[α|ρ]ὰ τοῖς μηρίοισ[ι -| πα]ρατιθέναι). The lack of context prevents the presentation of a hypothesis to explain the hesitation between μηροί and μηρία. The inscription of Demu Phrearrhioi (c. 300-250 BC. ) on the local worship of the Eleusinian gods prescribes the performance of some act on the altars (ἐπὶ δὲ τοὺς βωμοὺς), presumably the burning, 'μηροὺς μασχαλίσματα ἡμίκαιραν, "legs, pieces cut off from the shoulder, half-head (SEG XXXV = NGSL 3, ll. 16-8)', see Lupu 2005, 166-168.</p>
                    <p>In the classical era, the first testimonies of mantic practices accompanying burning appear, and consequently detailed descriptions of the anomalies of the burning process of the part dedicated to the gods. The evil omens are described in detail by Tiresias in Sophocles' Antigone (S.Ant. xx-xx ): ἀλλ᾽ ἐπὶ σποδῷ μυδῶσα κηκὶς μηρίων ἐτήκετο κἄτυφε κἀνέπτυε, καὶ μετάρσιοι χολαὶ διεσπείροντο, καὶ καταρρυεῖς μηροὶ καλυπτῆς ἐξέκειντο πιμελῆς, "but from the legs oozed / bubbling on the ashes and flowed, / And smoked, and sizzled, and bile splashed high, / the slimy sacrificial legs emerged from under the fat covering them. "</p>
                    <p>Catalogue of attestations (only occurrences of the word μηροί in the context of a blood sacrifice):</p>
                    <p>1. femurs:</p>
                    <p>a. to cut out, to cut off</p>
                    <p>μηρούς + ἐκτάμνειν "cut off the thighs, cut out the femurs (?)":Il. 1.464 = Il. 2.427 = Od. 12.364; Paus. 1.24.2; 2.11.7</p>
                    <p>b. cleaned (of flesh)</p>
                    <p>μηρώ + περιλέπειν "to peel, cleanse (from meat)": Pherecr. fr. 28 Kassel-Austin = fr. 23 Kock</p>
                    <p>c. to burn (on an altar):</p>
                    <p>μηροὺς + καύειν: Paus. 2.10.1</p>
                    <p>μηροί + καίεσθαι: LSAM 42, B, l. 2.</p>
                    <p>2. femurs, legs:</p>
                    <p>a. sacrificed</p>
                    <p>μηρόν or μηρούς + θύειν, "to sacrifice the leg(s)": Euboulos, fr. 127 Kassel-Austin = fr. 130 Kock; Paus. 2.10.</p>                    
                </div>
            </div>
            
            <div type="edition" xml:lang="pl">
                <div type="textpart">
                    <p>μηρός mēros, subst. m., udo, w kontekście ofiary krwawej częściej w l.mn. μηρούς, udźce.</p>                    
                </div>
                <div type="textpart" n="Etymologia">
                    <head>Etymologia</head>
                    <p>Rzeczownik μηρός, „udo” wywodzi się od i.e. *mēms-ro, por. łac. membrum, membra, „członki ciała, kończyny” (&amp;lt; pit. *memsro), st.irl. mír „porcja mięsa, kawałek, skrawek”. Według Brenta Veina *mēms-ro jest derywacją wsteczną od rzeczownika zbiorczego *mēms-reh2 (Vein 2002). Według bardziej prawdopodobnej interpretacji *mēms-ro jest przymiotnikiem („mięsny”), który na wczesnym etapie został urzeczownikowiony, czego kontynuacją są formy greckie, łacińskie i irlandzkie. Słowa te, w przeciwieństwie do słów kontynuujących i.e. *mē(m)s-(o)-, uległy procesowi specjalizacji i oznaczają „część mięsa, kęs, porcję” lub „umięśniony członek, udo”.  Można przypuszczać zatem, że ewolucja semantyczna słowa *mēms-ro przebiegała następująco: „mięsny” &gt; „umięśniona kończyna, członek ciała” &gt; „udo” &gt; (w kontekście uboju) „udziec” (por. pol. „udo” / „udziec” – „udo dużego zwierzęcia przeznaczone do spożycia”).</p>                    
                </div>
                <div type="textpart" n="Poświadczenia">
                    <head>Poświadczenia</head>
                    <p>W eposie homerowym μηρούς jako termin ofiarniczy pojawia się wyłącznie w kontekście pierwszej fazy procesu rytualnego, czyli przygotowania części zwierzęcia ofiarnego przeznaczonej dla bogów: po odcięciu μηρούς, owija się je dwustronnie tłuszczem i układa na nich surowe kawałki mięsa z innych części zwierzęcia. W późniejszym okresie zdaje się być synonimem słowa → μηρία, które z czasem zastępuje.</p>
                    <p>W eposie wyrażenia μηρούς τ᾽ ἐξέταμον, „wycięli udźce” (Il. 1.464 = Il. 2.427 = Od. 12.364 (3x), por.  ἐκ μηρία τάμνον, z tmezą, Od. 3.456) występuje wyłącznie w rozbudowanych opisach przedstawiających przebieg rytuału ofiary (scena typowa). Czasownik ἐκτάμνειν może sugerować wycięcie nagich kości i oczyszczenie z mięsa, lecz może też oznaczać po prostu „odciąć, odrąbać udźce (od korpusu)”. W scenach typowych znajdujemy powtarzalny układ wersów opisujący procedurę przygotowania udźców (μηρούς) do spalenia (Il. 1.464-5 = Il. 2.427-8 = Od. 12.364-5): μηρούς τ᾽ ἐξέταμον κατά τε κνίσῃ ἐκάλυψαν / δίπτυχα ποιήσαντες, ἐπ᾽ αὐτῶν δ᾽ ὠμοθέτησαν, „wycięli udźce i zakryli tłuszczem (błony otrzewnej) / z dwóch stron obwijając, na nich położyli kawałki surowego mięsa”, por. wariant w opisie złożonej przez Nestora ofiary dla Ateny (Od. 3.456b-457, zob. komentarz ad. loc.): ἄφαρ δ᾽ ἐκ μηρία τάμνον / πάντα κατὰ μοῖραν, κατά τε κνίσῃ ἐκάλυψαν, „wycieli kości udowe / wszystkie wedle doli, i zakryli tłuszczem (błony otrzewnej)”. Również w okresie poklasycznym typowo grecki obyczaj wycinania  udźców / kości udowych zwierzęcia złożonego w ofierze i spalania ich na ołtarzu są wyrażane zwrotami τοὺς μηροὺς ἐκτέμνειν, „wyciąć udźce” (Paus. 1.24.2; 2.11.7), τοὺς μηροὺς καύειν, „spalić udźce” (Paus. 2.10.1) oraz τοὺς μηροὺς θύειν, „składać udźce w ofierze” (Paus. 2.10.5), por. Pirenne-Delforge 2008, 187-197.</p>
                    <p>Poza eposem techniczne opisy przyrządzania części ofiary przeznaczonej dla bogów pojawiają się przede wszystkim w komedii, gdzie ze względu na swą dwuznaczność terminy μερώ lub μερός „udo / udziec” mogą przybrać podtekst seksualny. Jednocześnie teksty te przynoszą informacje o innych częściach zwierzęcia przeznaczonych dla bogów zawiniętych w otłuszczoną błonę otrzewnej. Ze Zbiegów Ferekratesa wynika, że bogowie otrzymują ukryte pod „licznymi θυλήματα” μερώ obrane z mięsa, razem z ὀσφῦς i σπόνδυλος (fr. 28 Kassel-Austin = fr. 23 Kock: εὖ τὼ μηρὼ περιλέψαντες [κομιδῇ] μέχρι βουβώνων &lt;κρέα πάντα&gt; / καὶ τὴν ὀσφὺν κομιδῇ ψιλήν, λοιπὸν τὸν σπόνδυλον αὐτὸν / εἶτ᾽ ἀλλήλους αἰσχυνόμενοι θυλήμασι κρύπτετε πολλοῖς {tekst zepsuty!: „[mięso] z udźców obżarte aż do kości [całe] / I tę kość całkiem gołą wraz z resztą karkówki / dajecie oszukańczo nam jak psom parszywym / ze wstydu, że ktoś ujrzy, całe pod osłoną (tłum. K. Bartol)” lub „chwytacie obydwa udźce, aż po pachwinę / Starannie wyciąwszy mięso; z biodra kość nagą zupełnie, / Kręgosłup też oczyściwszy jakby piłą cały, / Rzucacie nam jakby psom, a ze wstydu przed sobą nawzajem / Przykrywacie znowu rozlicznym darem ofiarnym. (tłum. Janina Niemirska-Pliszczyńska)”. U Eubulosa (fr. 127 Kassel-Austin fr. 130 Kock) bogowie skarżą się, że ludzie składają im w ofierze „wyłącznie ogon i udo (τὴν κέρκον μόνην / καὶ μηρὸν)”, z wyraźnym odniesieniem do pederastycznych stosunków analnych.</p>
                    <p>Źródła epigraficzne dostarczają nam świadectwa używania rzeczownika μηρούς na oznaczenie części zwierzęcia ofiarnego przeznaczonej dla bogów. Najstarsze pochodzi z Miletu (ok. 500 p.n.e.), gdzie na terenie Delfinionu znaleziono zapisaną dwustronnie stelę z inskrypcją zawierającą wyrocznię Apollona regulującą kult Heraklesa (LSAM 42). Stan zachowania dokumentu nie pozwala na wyciąganie daleko idących wniosków, niemniej na stronie B czytamy zalecenie spalania udźców (B, l. 2: μηροὶ καίωνται) oraz położenie czegoś przy kościach udowych (B, ll. 3-4: π̣[α|ρ]ὰ τοῖς μηρίοισ[ι -| πα]ρατιθέναι). Brak kontekstu uniemożliwia przedstawienie hipotezy wyjaśniającej wahanie między μηροί a μηρία. Inskrypcja demu Phrearrhioi (ok. 300-250 p.n.e.) w sprawie lokalnego kultu bogów eleuzyńskich nakazuje dokonywanie jakiś czynności na ołtarzach (ἐπὶ δὲ τοὺς βωμοὺς), najpewniej spalenie, „μηροὺς μασχαλίσματα ἡμίκαιραν, „udźców, kawałków odciętych z łopatki, półgłowia (SEG XXXV = NGSL 3, ll. 16-8)”, zob. Lupu 2005, 166-168.</p>
                    <p>W epoce klasycznej pojawiają się pierwsze świadectwa praktyk mantycznych towarzyszących spalaniu, a w konsekwencji szczegółowe opisy anomalii procesu spalania części poświęconej bogom. Złe znaki wróżebne opisuje szczegółowo Tejrezjasz w Antygonie Sofoklesa (S.Ant. xx-xx ): ἀλλ᾽ ἐπὶ σποδῷ μυδῶσα κηκὶς μηρίων ἐτήκετο κἄτυφε κἀνέπτυε, καὶ μετάρσιοι χολαὶ διεσπείροντο, καὶ καταρρυεῖς μηροὶ καλυπτῆς ἐξέκειντο πιμελῆς, „ale z udźców sączyła się / bulgocząca na popiele ciecz i spływała, / I dymiła, i skwierczała, i żółć rozpryskiwała wysoko, / oślizgłe udźce ofiarne wyłaniały się spod okrywającego je tłuszczu.”</p>
                    <p>Katalog poświadczeń (wyłącznie wystąpienia słowa μηροί w kontekście ofiary krwawej):</p>
                    <p>1. kości udowe:</p>
                    <p>a. wyciąć, odciąć</p>
                    <p>μηρούς + ἐκτάμνειν „odciąć udźce, wyciąć kości udowe (?)”:Il. 1.464 = Il. 2.427 = Od. 12.364; Paus. 1.24.2; 2.11.7</p>
                    <p>b. oczyścić (z mięsa)</p>
                    <p>μηρώ + περιλέπειν „obierać, oczyszczać (z mięsa)”: Pherecr. fr. 28 Kassel-Austin = fr. 23 Kock</p>
                    <p>c. spalić (na ołtarzu):</p>
                    <p>μηροὺς + καύειν: Paus. 2.10.1</p>
                    <p>μηροί + καίεσθαι: LSAM 42, B, l. 2.</p>
                    <p>2. kości udowe, udźce:</p>
                    <p>a. złożyć w ofierze</p>
                    <p>μηρόν lub μηρούς + θύειν, „składać w ofierze udziec / udźce”: Euboulos, fr. 127 Kassel-Austin = fr. 130 Kock; Paus. 2.10.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            
            <!--<div type="bibliography">
                <p>...</p>
            </div>-->
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
