<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> 
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
  <title xml:lang="grc">Ὀρφικíδαι</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher><ref target="https://site.unibo.it/lares/">LARES
                    Project</ref></publisher>
                <date when="2023"/>
                <idno type="filename">lexicon_ὀρφικίδαι</idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative
                        Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digital document.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change when="2024-02-20" who="Caterina_Borgatti">encoded in XML</change>
                <change when="2024-02-19" who="Alessio_Ciarini">written contents</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="edition" xml:lang="en">
                <div type="textpart" n="Morphology">
                    <head>Morphology</head>
                    <p/>
                    <p><rs type="Human_agents" subtype="Groups"><foreign xml:lang="grc"><w lemma="Ὀρφικiδαι">Ὀρφικiδαι</w></foreign></rs>, noun m. pl (sing., <foreign xml:lang="grc">Ὀρφικiδας</foreign>, genitive, <foreign
                            xml:lang="grc">Ὀρφικιδάων</foreign> > -ᾶν), enigmatic group which
                        dedicated a votive plaque to <persName type="divine"><rs type="Super-human_agents" subtype="Divinities">Poseidon</rs> <rs type="Super-human_agents" subtype="Epithets"><hi rend="italic">Geraistos</hi></rs></persName>. The plaque was found in
                        the ancient city of <placeName key="Kos">Kos</placeName> (once the capital of the homonymus island), inside
                        the temple of the god <rs type="Super-human_agents" subtype="Divinities"><persName type="divine">Asclepius</persName></rs>. The
                        inscription is the only evidence of this group and it is dated to the III
                        century BCE, reading as follows: <quote><foreign xml:lang="grc"
                                >[Π]οσειδ[ᾶνος] | Γεραστίί̣[ου] | Ὀρφικιδᾶν</foreign></quote> [ <ref
                            type="ins">IG XII 4,2.</ref> 1224 (SHERWINWHITE 1978, p. 167, n. 8 and
                        JEREZ SÁNCHEZ 2019, p. 54, p. 166, p. 413.)].</p>

                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="edition" xml:lang="en">
                <div type="textpart" n="Etymology">
                    <head>Etymology</head>
                    <p/>
                    <p>From an etymological point of view, the lemma <foreign xml:lang="grc"><w
                                lemma="Ὀρφικiδαι">Ὀρφικiδαι</w></foreign> is composed by the root
                        ՚ορφικ- and patronymic suffix -iδαι (sing., -iδας/-ιδης) showing descent
                        from a common ancestor: so, the <foreign xml:lang="grc"
                            >Ἀλκμαιωνίδαi</foreign> are “the progeny of <persName key="Alcmaeon"
                            >Alcmaeon</persName>”, the <foreign xml:lang="grc">Νέστoριδαι</foreign>
                        are “the progeny of <persName key="Nestor">Nestor</persName>”, and so on.
                        Given that, the aforementioned root would seems to be connected with the
                        name of the mythical musician <rs type="Human_agents" subtype="Individuals"><persName key="Orpheus">Orpheus</persName></rs>
                        but, as underlined by Susan Sherwin-White (1978, p. 167, n. 8), this
                        reconstruction is not quite tenable:</p>
                    <p><quote>It is difficult to connect the name <rs type="Human_agents" subtype="Gropus"><hi rend="italic">Orphikidai</hi></rs> with the
                            personal name <rs type="Human_agents" subtype="Individuals"><persName key="Orpheus">Orpheus</persName></rs> in view of its
                            composite nature; the collective name combines both the adjectival
                            termination -ikos and the patronymic ending -idai. If it does denote a
                            group of followers of <rs type="Human_agents" subtype="Individuals"><persName key="Orpheus">Orpheus</persName></rs>, i.e.
                            initiates, the name is unlikely to be of great antiquity. We can compare
                            the Thasian <hi rend="italic">patra Neophantidai</hi>, attested in the fifth centwy and derived
                            by Rolley, BCH 89, 1965, p. 461, from neophantes (the newly initiated)
                            of the <rs type="Institutions" subtype="Religious_Knowledge_Depository">Orphic hymns</rs>. But the oddity of the combination of an adjectival
                            epithet with a patronymic termination argues against the derivation of
                        <rs type="Human_agents" subtype="Gropus"><hi rend="italic">Orphikidai</hi></rs> from <hi rend="italic">Orphikos</hi>. The name may have been based
                            on some unknown word, or compounded from orphos, as for example the name
                                <persName key="Orphondas">Orphondas</persName> was, cf. Bechtel,
                            loc. cit., p. 508.</quote></p>
                    <p>the word <hi rend="italic">orphos</hi>, quoted by the author, is obviously
                        not the noun <foreign xml:lang="grc">ορφος/ὀρφως</foreign> “redfish”, but
                        the reconstructed original form of <foreign xml:lang="grc"
                            >ὀρφανος</foreign> (“orphan”): <foreign xml:lang="grc"
                            >*ὀρφος</foreign>, derived from words like <foreign xml:lang="grc"
                            >ὀρφοβοται</foreign> and <foreign xml:lang="grc">ωρφωσεν·
                            ὠρφανιζεν</foreign>, and corresponding to the Armenian orb, -oy and the
                        Latin <foreign xml:lang="lat">orbus</foreign> (CHANTRAINE 1999 (1968), pp.
                        829-830 and BEEKES 2010, pp. 1113-1115).</p>
                    <p/>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="edition" xml:lang="en">
                <div type="textpart" n="Testimonies">
                    <head>Testimonies</head>
                    <p/>
                    <p>The group of votive plaques found in the <rs type="Spaces"
                            subtype="Buildings">Asclepeion</rs> of <placeName key="Kos"
                            >Kos</placeName> comprises findings, ranging from the IV century BCE to
                        the late Hellenistic age, that show the city's social subdivisions. Many of
                        these associations, all having the gentilitial suffix -ιδαι, or -αδαι, seem
                        to be of great antiquity, displaying patronymic references to both local and
                        Panhellenic mythology. In fact, although none of the plaques is older than
                        366 BCE, date of the city's foundation, the groups quoted on the
                        inscriptions may have existed before the synoecism that lead to the
                        capital's creation (SHERWIN-WHITE 1978, pp. 153-169). The same presence of
                        gentilitial suffixes suggests the archaism of these organizations, linking
                        them with that social groups that were based on kinship ties, such as the
                            <rs type="Institutions" subtype="Administration"><foreign xml:lang="grc"
                                    ><w lemma="φυλή">φυλή</w></foreign> (“tribe”)</rs>, the <rs
                            type="Institutions" subtype="Administration"><foreign xml:lang="grc"><w lemma="γένος">γένος</w></foreign> (“clan”, o “patrilineal
                                        family”)</rs> or the <rs type="Institutions" subtype="Administration"><foreign xml:lang="grc">φρατρία</foreign></rs> (“brotherhood”). Their origin is quite uncertain but they appear to have
                        had, at least originally, a military function (BRYANT 1996, p. 16 e LACEY
                        1968, pp. 25-26), as is shown in the <ref type="lit">Iliad Hom., Il. II,
                            360-364</ref> :
                    </p>
                    <p><quote><foreign xml:lang="grc">ἀλλὰ ἄναξ αὐτός τ᾽ εὖ μήδεο πείθεό τ᾽ ἄλλῳ: οὔ τοι ἀπόβλητον ἔπος ἔσσεται ὅττί κεν εἴπω: κρῖν᾽ ἄνδρας κατὰ φῦλα κατὰ φρήτρας Ἀγάμεμνον, ὡς φρήτρη φρήτρηφιν ἀρήγῃ, φῦλα δὲ φύλοις. εἰ δέ κεν ὣς ἕρξῃς καί τοι πείθωνται Ἀχαιοί</foreign> </quote></p>
                    <p><quote>But do thou, O king, thyself take good counsel, and hearken to
                            another; the word whatsoever I speak, shalt thou not lightly cast aside.
                            Separate thy men by tribes (κατὰ φυλα), by clans (κατὰ φρητρας),
                            Agamemnon, that clan. may bear aid to clan and tribe to
                            tribe. (MURRAY 1946, p. 77) </quote></p>
                    <p/>
                    <p>This passage, combined with the importance held by nobility of blood during the Archaic age, shows the antiquity of these institutions. From this angle, the <rs type="Human_agents" subtype="Groups"><foreign xml:lang="grc"><w lemma="Ὀρφικiδαι">Ὀρφικiδαι</w></foreign></rs> must have been, originally, a <rs
                        type="Institutions" subtype="Administration"><foreign xml:lang="grc"><w lemma="γένος">γένος</w></foreign></rs> or <rs type="Institutions" subtype="Administration"><foreign xml:lang="grc">φρατρία</foreign></rs>, since these were large groups of <foreign xml:lang="grc">οἶκοι</foreign>, “families”, that claimed descent from a common ancestor. What is surprising about these institutions is that, despite the etymology of their name, as well as the name of their own festival, the <rs type="Activities" subtype="Feasting"><hi rend="italic">Apaturia</hi></rs> (from <foreign xml:lang="grc">Ομοπατόρια</foreign>, “the festival of the ones with the same father”), their members were not actually blood-related; for example, the members of the  <rs type="Human_agents" subtype="Groups"><foreign xml:lang="grc">Ὁμηρίδαι</foreign></rs> clan, were not the real progeny of <persName key="Homer">Homer</persName>, but the followers of his art (LAMBERT 1993, p. 9). That was known even in ancient times, considering that the Greeks used the term <foreign xml:lang="grc">αδελφός</foreign> to describe a biological brother  and not the word <foreign xml:lang="grc">φράτηρ</foreign>, from which φρατρία is derived (LACEY 1968,  26, BRYANT 1996,  16 e LAMBERT 1993, 8).  Anyway, whatever position these groups covered in the Archaic age, in later times, they played mostly religious functions, but they also had a key role in the assignment of citizenship (LACEY 1968,  25-26). That is true also in <placeName key="Kos">Kos</placeName>' case, where, following the social and political reorganization caused by the synoecism, the old gentilitial groups became subdivisions of the civic body, organized on a numerical basis, and not following kinship ties (SHERWIN-WHITE 1978, 153-174). </p>
                    <p>As it can be seen from the inscription, the <rs type="Human_agents" subtype="Groups"><foreign xml:lang="grc"><w lemma="Ὀρφικiδαι">Ὀρφικiδαι</w></foreign></rs> dedicated their plaque to <persName type="divine"><rs type="Super-human_agents" subtype="Divinities">Poseidon</rs> <rs type="Super-human_agents" subtype="Epithets"><hi rend="italic">Geraistos</hi></rs></persName>. This particular epiclesis came from the Euboian city of the same name, located in the vicinity of <placeName key="Carystus">Carystus</placeName>, in the southernmost point of the island [<ref type="lit">Strab. X. 1. 7</ref>] </p>
                    <p>The local sanctuary of the god seems to be linked with two other <rs type="Super-human_agents" subtype="Divinities"><persName key="Poseidon">Poseidon</persName></rs>'s cult places, as noted by many scholars such as  Rob W. M. Schumacher: the one on <placeName key="Cape Tainaron">Cape Tainaron</placeName> and the one on the island of <placeName key="Kalauria">Kalauria</placeName> (SCHUMACHER 1993, 52). This hypothesis is strengthened by several evidences: the presence of a month named <hi rend="italic">Geraistos</hi> and of <rs type="Activities" subtype="Feasting"><hi rend="italic">Geraistia</hi></rs> festivals in all the three cities, and the fact that all were asylum sanctuaries, considered places of refuge (SCHUMACHER 1993, 52 and  63-64). In this regard, it must be noted that the month of <hi rend="italic">Geraistos</hi> was also present in <placeName key="Kos">Kos</placeName>. Also, this particular cult of <rs type="Super-human_agents" subtype="Divinities"><persName key="Poseidon">Poseidon</persName></rs> was linked, in the <placeName key="Peloponnese">Peloponnese</placeName>, with patrician clans, similar to the <rs type="Human_agents" subtype="Groups"><foreign xml:lang="grc"><w lemma="Ὀρφικiδαι">Ὀρφικiδαι</w></foreign></rs>: the <hi rend="italic">Geraistiastai</hi> in <placeName key="Troezen">Troezen</placeName> (the city which controlled <placeName key="Kalauria">Kalauria</placeName>) and the <rs type="Human_agents" subtype="Groups"><hi rend="italic">Tainarioi/Tainaristai</hi></rs> in <placeName key="Cape Tainaron">Cape Tainaron</placeName> (SCHUMACHER 1993,  54 and 67, n. 17).  Lastly, there is a very interesting passage from the <ref type="lit">Ethnika</ref> of <persName key="Stephanus">Stephanus of Byzantium</persName>, that speaks about these interconnected sanctuaries [St. Byz., s.v. Tainaros e <hi rend="italic">Geraistos</hi> (SCHUMACHER 1993, p. 52)]: </p>
                    <p/>
                    <p><quote><placeName key="Tainaros"><hi rend="italic">Tainaros</hi></placeName>: ‘polis, [named] after <persName key="Tainaros">Tainaros</persName>, the brother of <persName key="Geraistos">Geraistos</persName> and child of <rs type="Super-human_agents" subtype="Divinities"><persName key="Zeus">Zeus</persName></rs>; who sailed with his brother <persName key="Kalauros">Kalauros</persName> and, having seized a place on the <placeName key="Peloponnese">Peloponnese</placeName>, set up a sanctuary of <rs type="Super-human_agents" subtype="Divinities"><persName key="Poseidon">Poseidon</persName></rs>, which is called <rs type="Super-human_agents" subtype="Epithets">Tainaron</rs>...’. In the same work is written under <placeName key="Geraistos"><hi rend="italic">Geraistos</hi></placeName>: Village on <placeName key="Euboea">Euboea</placeName>, in which is a sanctuary of <rs type="Super-human_agents" subtype="Divinities"><persName key="Poseidon">Poseidon</persName></rs>, [named] after <persName key="Geraistos">Geraistos</persName>, the son of <rs type="Super-human_agents" subtype="Divinities"><persName key="Zeus">Zeus</persName></rs></quote></p>
                    <p/>
                    <p>This seems to be a common foundation myth, in which the three brothers appear as the founders of three eponymous sanctuaries of <rs type="Super-human_agents" subtype="Divinities"><persName key="Poseidon">Poseidon</persName></rs>: <rs type="Institutions">Geraistos</rs> for the Euboian town, <rs type="Institutions">Tainaros</rs> for <placeName>Cape Tainaron</placeName> and <rs type="Institutions">Kalauros</rs> (even though is not explicitly stated) for the Peloponnesian city of <placeName key="Kalauria">Kalauria</placeName>, seat of an ancient and powerful <rs type="Institutions" subtype="Politics">amphictiony</rs> [Strab. VIII. 6. 14]: </p>
                    <p/>
                    <p><quote>Here there was an asylum sacred to Poseidon... There was also a kind of Amphiktyony at this sanctuary for the seven cities that share in the sacrifices. These were Hermion, Epidauros, Aigina, Athens, the Prasians, the Nauplians, and Minyan Orchomenos.</quote></p>
                    <p/>
                    <p>Since the aforementioned tale speak of  a sailing voyage made by <rs type="Super-human_agents" subtype="Divinities"><persName>Tainaros</persName></rs> and <rs type="Super-human_agents" subtype="Divinities"><persName>Kalauros</persName></rs>,  would seem that the cult of <rs type="Super-human_agents" subtype="Divinities"><persName key="Poseidon">Poseidon</persName></rs> was exported from the <rs type="Institutions">Geraistos</rs>' sanctuary, in <placeName key="Euboea">Euboea</placeName> (SCHUMACHER 1993, 52).  In the light of that, many scholars have hypothesized that the diffusion of the cult of <rs type="Super-human_agents" subtype="Divinities"><persName key="Geraistos">Geraistos</persName></rs> was linked to a “wondering tribe” of <rs type="Human_agents" subtype="Groups">Minyans</rs> or <rs type="Human_agents" subtype="Groups">Dryopians</rs>.  In fact, <persName>Euphemos</persName>, hero and Argonaut of Minyan descent, was said to have been son of <rs type="Super-human_agents" subtype="Divinities"><persName key="Poseidon">Poseidon</persName></rs> and to have lived around <placeName key="Tainaron">Tainaron</placeName> [Pind., Pyth. IV. 43–5] and, interestingly, <persName key="Herodotus">Herodotus</persName> speaks of <rs type="Human_agents" subtype="Groups">Minyans</rs> on <placeName key="Lemnos">Lemnos</placeName>, “descendants of <persName key="Euphemos">Euphemos</persName> and the other Argonauts, who were expelled from their island by the <rs type="Human_agents" subtype="Groups">Pelasgians</rs>, sailed to southern <placeName key="Lakonia">Lakonia</placeName>, sat down on the <placeName key="Taygetos">Taygetos</placeName> mountain range and were eventually admitted to Lakonian society” [Hdt., IV. 145]These <rs type="Human_agents" subtype="Groups">Minyans</rs> of <placeName key="Lemnos">Lemnos</placeName> could be linked with other groups of <rs type="Human_agents" subtype="Groups">Lemnians</rs>, <rs type="Human_agents" subtype="Groups">Imbrians</rs> and <rs type="Human_agents" subtype="Groups">Pelasgians</rs> that, according to the testimony of <persName key="Conon">Conon</persName> and <persName key="Nicholaus of Damascus">Nicholaus of Damascus</persName>, were admitted in <placeName key="Laconia">Laconia</placeName> after the Dorian invasion [<ref type="lit">Conon, Fr. XXXVI/Phot. Bibl. 186 and Nic. Dam. Exc. De Virt. I/ Fr. XXXVI</ref>]. The <rs type="Human_agents" subtype="Groups">Dryopians</rs> were, on the other hand, a tribe native of <placeName key="Thessaly">Thessaly</placeName>, which was scattered by the <rs type="Human_agents" subtype="Groups">Dorians</rs> in the southern tip of <placeName key="Euboea">Euboea</placeName>, some other <placeName key="Aegean islands">Aegean islands</placeName>, and in the <placeName key="Argolid">Argolid</placeName>; the people in the area around <placeName key="Hermione">Hermione</placeName> (just to the south-west of <placeName key="Troizen">Troizen</placeName> and <placeName key="Kalaureia">Kalaureia</placeName>) were said to be <rs type="Human_agents" subtype="Groups">Dryopians</rs> from <placeName key="Euboea">Euboea</placeName> (SCHUMACHER 1993, p. 53).</p>
                    <p/>
                    <p/>
                    <p/>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="edition" xml:lang="en">
                <div type="textpart" n="Catalogue of occurences">
                    <head>Catalogue of occurences</head>
                    <p/>
                    <p><hi rend="italic">Literary sources</hi></p>
                    <p><list rend="bulleted">
                        <item><ref type="lit"><ref corresp="http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=Hom.+Il.+2.360&amp;fromdoc=Perseus%3Atext%3A1999.01.0133">Hom., Il. II, 360-364</ref> 
                        </ref></item>
                        <item><ref type="lit">St. Byz., s.v. Tainaros
                        </ref></item>
                        <item><ref type="lit">St. Byz., s.v. Geraistos
                        </ref></item>
                        
                        <item><ref type="lit"><ref corresp="http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=Strab.+10.1.7&amp;fromdoc=Perseus%3Atext%3A1999.01.0198">Strab. X. 1. 7 </ref>
                        </ref></item>
                        <item><ref type="lit"><ref corresp="http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=Strab.+8.6.14&amp;fromdoc=Perseus%3Atext%3A1999.01.0198">Strab. VIII. 6. 14</ref>
                        </ref></item>
                        <item><ref type="lit">
                            <ref corresp="http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=Pind.+P.+4&amp;fromdoc=Perseus%3Atext%3A1999.01.0162">Pind., Pyth. IV. 43–5</ref>                        
                        </ref></item>
                        <item><ref type="lit"><ref corresp="http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=Perseus%3Atext%3A1999.01.0126%3Abook%3D4%3Achapter%3D145">Hdt., IV. 145  </ref>
                        </ref></item>
                        <item><ref type="lit"><ref corresp="https://stephanus.tlg.uci.edu/Iris/inst/browser.jsp#doc=tlg&amp;aid=4040&amp;wid=001&amp;st=702526&amp;et=702537&amp;hl=%7B%22hl%22%3A%5B%7B%22start%22%3A702526%2C%22end%22%3A702537%2C%22color%22%3A%22HI1%22%2C%22backToStartSnippet%22%3Afalse%2C%22forwardToEndSnippet%22%3Afalse%2C%22outOfSnippet%22%3Afalse%7D%5D%7D&amp;type=browser">Conon, Fr. XXXVI/Phot. Bibl. 186</ref>
                        </ref></item>
                        <item><ref type="lit"><ref corresp="https://stephanus.tlg.uci.edu/Iris/inst/browser.jsp#doc=tlg&amp;aid=0577&amp;wid=003&amp;ct=~y36z9&amp;rt=y&amp;l=20&amp;td=greek&amp;links=tlg">Nic. Dam. Exc. De Virt. I/ Fr. XXXVI</ref>
                        </ref></item></list></p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Inscriptions</hi></p>
                        <p><list rend="bulleted">
                            <item><ref type="ins"><ref corresp="https://epigraphy.packhum.org/text/350801?hs=42-48">IG XII 4,2. 1224</ref>
                        </ref></item>
                    </list></p>
                    
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="edition" xml:lang="en">
                <div type="textpart" n="Discussion/interpretation">
                    <head>Discussion/interpretation</head>
                    <p/>
                    <p>In summary, the <rs type="Human_agents" subtype="Groups"><foreign xml:lang="grc"><w lemma="Ὀρφικiδαι">Ὀρφικiδαι</w></foreign></rs> were probably a religious association, which spread an ancient cult of  <rs type="Super-human_agents" subtype="Divinities"><persName key="Poseidon">Poseidon</persName></rs>  from the town of <placeName key="Geraistos">Geraistos</placeName>, in <placeName key="Euboea">Euboea</placeName>, to the island of <placeName key="Kos">Kos</placeName>, similarly to what was done by other groups, like the <rs type="Human_agents" subtype="Groups">Geraistiastai</rs> in the island of <placeName key="Kalauria">Kalauria</placeName> and the <rs type="Human_agents" subtype="Groups">Tainarioi</rs> at <placeName key="Cape Tainaron">Cape Tainaron</placeName>. The alleged antiquity of this group, combined with its apparent Euboian connections, would seems to suggest a very archaic origin, probably during the Iron Age. In fact, during that period the <rs type="Human_agents" subtype="Groups">Euboians</rs> formed a <hi rend="italic">koine</hi> within the <rs type="Human_agents" subtype="Groups">Aegean</rs>, from the 11th to the middle of the 9th century BCE, which encompassed both <placeName key="Boeotia">Boeotia</placeName> and <placeName key="Thessaly">Thessaly</placeName> (LEMOS 1998); that would explained the link between the cult of <persName type="divine"><rs type="Super-human_agents" subtype="Divinities">Poseidon</rs> <rs type="Super-human_agents" subtype="Epithets"><hi rend="italic">Geraistos</hi></rs></persName> and Aeolic (or, at least, not Ionians) populations such as the <rs type="Human_agents" subtype="Groups">Minyans</rs> and the <rs type="Human_agents" subtype="Groups">Dryopians</rs>. This hypothesis is strengthened by the particular position of <placeName key="Kos">Kos</placeName>, that was the connection point in the commercial route that, moving from <placeName key="Anatolia">Anatolia</placeName>, reached <placeName key="Attica">Attica</placeName>, the island of <placeName key="Kalauria">Kalauria</placeName>, <placeName key="Cape Tainaron">Cape Tainaron</placeName> and <placeName key="Crete">Crete</placeName> (MELE 1982, p. 21 e p. 29). This connection is also enlightened by some cultural traits shared with the <placeName key="Euboea">Euboea</placeName>, like the character of <persName key="Chalcodon">Chalcodon</persName> and the common links with Aeolic world (MELE 1982, p. 21 e p. 29).</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="edition" xml:lang="en">
                <div type="textpart" n="Bibliography">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p/>
                    <p>BEEKES 2010 = R. Beekes, <hi rend="italic">Etymological Dictionary of Greek</hi>, Leiden and New York, 2010.</p>
                    <p>BRYANT 1996 = J. M. Bryant, <hi rend="italic">Moral codes and social structure in Ancient Greece</hi>, New York, 1996.</p>
                    <p>CHANTRAINE 1999 (1968) = P. Chantraine, <hi rend="italic">Dictionnaire Etymologique de la Langue Grecque: Histoire des mots</hi>, Paris, 1999.</p>
                    <p>JACOBY 1986 = F. Jacoby, <hi rend="italic">Die Fragmente der Griechischen Historiker. Zweiter Teil, Zeitgeschichte A</hi>, Brill, Leide, 1986 (1926).</p>
                    <p>JACOBY 1995 = F. Jacoby, <hi rend="italic">Die Fragmente der Griechischen Historiker. Erster Teil, Genealogie und Mytholographie</hi>, Brill, Leide, 1995 (1957).</p>
                    <p>JEREZ SÁNCHEZ 2019 = G. Jerez Sánchez, <hi rend="italic">Gramática de las inscripciones de Cos: fonética y morfología</hi>, Madrid, 2019.</p>
                    <p>LACEY 1968 = W. K. Lacey, <hi rend="italic">The family in classical Greece</hi>, London, 1968.</p>
                    <p>LEMOS 1998 = I. S. Lemos, <hi rend="italic">Euboea and its Aegean koine</hi>, in B. D'Agostino and M. Bats (editors) <hi rend="italic">EUBOICA. L'Eubea e la presenza euboica in Calcidica e in Occidente</hi>, Napoi, 1998.</p>
                    <p>MELE 1982 = A. Mele, <hi rend="italic">I Ciclopi, Calcodonte e la metallurgia caldicese</hi>, in <hi rend="italic">Nouvelle contribution à l’étude
                        de la société et de la colonisation eubéennes</hi>, Napoli, 1982.
                    </p>
                    <p>MURRAY 1946 = M. T. Murray (editor), Homer, <hi rend="italic">The Iliad</hi>,  Harvard, 1946.</p>
                    <p>ROLLER 2014= D.W. Roller (editors), Strabone, <hi rend="italic">Geografia</hi>, Cambridge, 2014.</p>
                    <p>SCHUMACHER 1993, R. W. M. Schumacher, <hi rend="italic">Three related sanctuaries of Poseidon: Geraistos, Kalaureia and
                        Tainaron</hi>, in R. Hagg e N. Marinatos, <hi rend="italic">Greek Sanctuaries: New Approaches</hi>, New York, 2005 (1993).
                    </p>
                    <p>SHERWIN-WHITE 1978 = S.M. Sherwin-White, Ancient Cos. <hi rend="italic">An historical study from the Dorian
                        settlement to the Imperial period</hi>, Göttingen, 1978.
                    </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
