<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>κοπίς</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher><ref target="https://site.unibo.it/lares/">LARES Project</ref></publisher>
                <date when="2021"/>
                <idno type="filename">lexicon_kopis</idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digital document.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change when="2022-02-03" who="Irene Vagionakis">encoded document in XML</change>
                <change when="2015-04-21" who="Przemysław Biernat">updated document contents</change>
                <change when="2015-03-31" who="Przemysław Biernat">created document contents</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="edition" xml:lang="it">
                <div type="textpart">
                    <p><w>κοπίς</w> kopis; κοπίς, ίδος, subst. f.: un massiccio coltello per affettare, mannaia, poet. agg. mannaia; forse per metonimia: il nome di una festa alle feste dei Giacinti e dei Tithenidi a Sparta.</p>                    
                </div>
                <div type="textpart" n="Etimologia">
                    <head>Etimologia</head>
                    <p>Derivato dal verbo <w>κόπτω</w>, "colpire" (Chantraine 1968 s.v. κόπτω, Beekes 2010 s.v. κόπτω). Il verbo è probabilmente indoeuropeo (cfr. lit. kàpti, pl. kick), anche se Beekes non esclude che possa provenire da un substrato (cfr. Mallory, Adams 1997, che non lo includono nella loro enciclopedia). Se questa ipotesi fosse accettata, la parola κοπίς potrebbe essere collegata al sostantivo σκέπαρνος (una specie di ascia), che, come molti nomi di utensili, non ha un'etimologia indoeuropea convincente (Beekes 2010 s.v. <w>σκέπαρνος</w>; sul mobile -s- nelle parole pre-greche: Beekes 2010: vol. 1, xxiii). Gordon ha attirato l'attenzione sulla possibile associazione della parola κοπίς con il nome di un'arma del Vicino Oriente conosciuta dalle fonti egiziane come un kh.p.sh di costruzione simile (Gordon 1958: 24). Questo naturalmente non implica un'etimologia vicino-orientale della parola (kh.p.sh può essere un lemma miceneo).</p>    
                    <p>Κοπίς come nome della festa che cade il primo giorno della festa spartana di Hyacinthia può essere di natura metonimica e forse parte dell'usanza di nominare particolari elementi delle feste dopo attività o, più importante in questo contesto, oggetti che giocano un ruolo importante in esse, come era il caso del terzo giorno di Anthesteria, che porta il nome Χύτραι, 'Pentole'.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="textpart" n="Aspetto_e_funzione">
                    <head>Aspetto e funzione</head>
                    <p>La copida era il secondo strumento da macellaio usato nel rito sacrificale oltre alla machaira (→ <ref corresp="lexicon_machaira.html">μάχαιρα</ref>). Veniva usato per scuoiare l'animale (βύρσαν ἐξέδειρεν: E. El. 824) e per rompere le ossa del petto (ἀναρρῆξαι χέλυν: E. El. 837).* Dall'Elettra di Euripide possiamo dedurre che esistevano sottotipi di copidi probabilmente legati al luogo originario della loro produzione: Oreste prima scuoia l'animale con un "dorico" (E. El. 819, → <ref corresp="lexicon_doris.html">Δωρίς</ref>), o Δωρικὴ κοπίς (E. El. 836-7), e poi chiede che gli venga data una mannaia da Phthya (Φθιάδ ̓ ἀντὶ Δωρικῆς, 836), con cui si spacca il petto e uccide anche Ajgistos (E. El. 836-838; vedi anche riproduzioni di vasi in: Berthiaume 1982: planches 19, 20). La pratica di usare diversi coltelli (e quindi probabilmente anche diversi tipi di coltelli) durante un sacrificio è catturata nelle raffigurazioni dei vasi (van Straten 1995: 18, fig. 7).</p>
                    <p>I confini degli usi di machaira e copida sembrano fluidi: Euripide nei Ciclopi usa la parola κοπίς come aggettivo a μάχαιρα, parlando di "coltelli a mannaia" (E. Cyc. 241-2). Nella descrizione del sacrificio di Elettra citato sopra, la kopida può essere identica a → <ref corresp="lexicon_sphagis.html">σφαγίς</ref> del verso 811, che è probabilmente un altro termine per machaira. 
                        Senofonte, scrivendo di armi, sembra anche trattare le parole μάχαιρα e κοπίς come sinonimi: "[Per i combattimenti a cavallo] raccomando la machaira piuttosto che lo xiphos: per il cavaliere di sopra, un colpo con la copida è migliore di un colpo con lo xiphos" (μάχαιραν μὲν μᾶλλον ἢ ξίφος ἐπαινοῦμεν: ἐφ ̓ ὑψηλοῦ γὰρ ὄντι τῷ ἱππεῖ κοπίδος μᾶλλον ἡ πληγὴ ἢ ξίφους ἀρκέσει, Eq. 12.11). Sulla sinonimia di copida e machaira sembra essersi basato il presunto gioco di parole di Acheo - τίς ὑποκεκρυμμένος μένει, σαραβάκων κοπίδων συνομώνυμε;, "chi si nasconde lì, omonimo delle mannaie della vulva?" (Atene. 173d = TrGF 20 F 13; le parole erano rivolte a un delfico, e la chiave per svelare il gioco di parole è il detto "machaira delfica"). È possibile che la differenza tra i due sia stata determinata solo dalla massa della lama.</p>
                    <p>Come nel caso della machaira, il termine copida è usato per descrivere il tipo di arma usata dagli orientali (X. Cyr. 1.2.9, 1.2.13, 2.1.9, 2.2.9, 4.2.22, 5.2.1, 6.2.10, 7.3.8, 8.8.23). Per i Greci del V e IV secolo a.C. è probabilmente esclusivamente uno strumento di macellazione, di sacrificio e di cucina (μαγειρικῶν κοπίς: Ar., Fr. 138; storia del venditore di carne che taglia la mano di Killikont con una kopida: Theopomp.Hist. 111; Anaxipp. 6; vedi anche Berthiaume 1982: 46).</p>
                    <p>Probabilmente per metonimia, la kopida divenne anche il nome di una festa serale che cadeva il primo giorno della festa laconica dei Giacinti (dedicata ad Apollo) e si svolgeva nel villaggio di Amyklai, a sud di Sparta. Gli animali sacrificati a quel tempo erano esclusivamente capre (Ath. 138f). I primi riferimenti letterari alla festa κοπίς provengono dai comici Kratinos, Eupolis ed Epilykos (Crat. 166, Eup. 138, Epil. 3), citati da Ateneo nella sua descrizione dell'evento (137e-f, 140a). I loro resoconti mostrano che la kopida laconica era conosciuta ad Atene come una festa in cui non era vietato mangiare nemmeno agli stranieri (τοῖς ξένοισιν, Crat. 166.1); il fatto che la carne dei sacrifici, insieme ad altre delizie, fosse data a tutti i presenti è sottolineato anche dal narratore di Atene (τῶν κρεῶν διδόασι μοίρας πᾶσι, Ath. 139a). 
                        È nel libero accesso di tutti i partecipanti alla festa alla carne degli animali sacrificali che possiamo vedere la fonte del potenziale trasferimento metonimico del nome del coltello a tutta la festa. Il resoconto di Ateneo mostra anche che il termine copida era usato a Sparta per riferirsi non solo alla festa dei Giacinti, ma anche alla "κοπίδες in città" che aveva luogo durante la festa kurotrofica dei Tithenidi (Ath. 139a, RE 1511-1512; secondo Goldstein, tuttavia, questa frase dovrebbe essere intesa diversamente: "celebrano la kopides in città e durante la Tithenidia"; Goldstein 1978: 30), celebrata in onore di Artemide soprannominata Corythallia (cfr. RE 1346, soprattutto 1390). Gli animali sacrificati in quel momento erano giovani maialini di 4-8 settimane (γαλαθηνοὶ ὀρθαγορίσκοι, chiamati "lattonzoli" nella nomenclatura zootecnica polacca).</p>
                    <p>Κοπίς è anche il termine proposto da Jortin (Griffith 1999: 226; cf. anche Brown 1993: 173) emendazione della parola κόνις (polvere) nel verso 602 dell'Antigone di Sofocle: νῦν γὰρ ἐσχάτας ὕπερ ῥίζας ὃ τέτατο φάος ἐν Οἰδίπου δόμοις, κατ ̓ αὖ νιν φοινία θεῶν τῶν νερτέρων ἀμᾷ κόνις λόγου τ ̓ ἄνοια καὶ φρενῶν ἐρινύς ("Quando ora la luce cadde sulle radici più profonde della casa di Edipo, li coprì di nuovo con la polvere sanguinolenta degli dei sotterranei, la follia della parola e l'Erynia della mente", S. Formica. 599-602). L'immagine delle "radici" della casa di Edipo, che sarebbe così "decapitata" (καταμάω) dalla "mannaia degli dei degli inferi". Un recente editore di Antigone, tuttavia, rifiuta questa emendazione, sostenendo che "κοπίς è propriamente una 'scimitarra' o 'mannaia', non uno strumento di potatura o di raccolta, (...) e perché gli dei di sotto dovrebbero brandire una 'scimitarra insanguinata'? (Griffith 1999: 226; vedi anche Smith 1961). Griffith è indubbiamente corretto nel respingere l'emendazione di Jortin, la linea lessicologica della sua argomentazione, tuttavia, è imperfetta. 
                        Lo studioso, probabilmente privo di uno studio sistematico della parola κοπίς, sopravvaluta il fatto che significa spada - questo significato è secondario e appare principalmente nelle descrizioni dei popoli orientali. Invece, la tradizione manoscritta e la coerenza dell'immaginario poetico sono a favore del rifiuto dell'emendazione. Se consideriamo che καταμάω non significa "tagliare" ma, come suggerisce lo studioso, "coprire" (cfr. Griffith 1999: 226), otteniamo un'immagine organizzata intorno a una metafora storica dell'accecamento: la luce che cadeva sulle radici nella casa di Edipo non cade più su di esse, perché sono state coperte dalla polvere di sangue degli dei degli inferi, l'insensatezza della ragione e l'Erynia della mente. Queste ultime due frasi evocano un'altra metafora - la follia e l'ignoranza come cecità - ed evocano un piano psicologico che si traduce perfettamente nel contesto della metafora della copertura/accecamento, con meno successo nel contesto della tosatura. Inoltre, Griffith omette di notare che non solo la ἄνοια del verso 602. si riferisce al comportamento di Antigone (cfr. S. Ant. 383, 562; Griffith 1999: 226), ma anche κόνις, poiché fu con la polvere che Antigone cosparse il corpo morto del fratello (S. Ant. 247; Brown 1993: 173).</p>
                    <p>Catalogo delle occorrenze nel contesto del sacrificio o del pasto:</p>
                    <p>1. mannaia: E. Cyc. 241 (adj.), E. El. 819 (→ <ref corresp="lexicon_doris.html">Δωρίς</ref>), 836 (Phthias ~), 837 (Dorike ~), TrGF 20 F12, Ar. Fr. 138, Theopomp.Hist. 111;</p>
                    <p>2. festa delle feste: Crat. 166, Eup. 138, Epil. 3.</p>                    
                </div>
            </div>
            
            <div type="edition" xml:lang="en">
                <div type="textpart">
                    <p>κοπίς kopis; κοπίς, ίδος, subst. f.: a massive slicing knife, cleaver, poet. adj. cleaver; perhaps by metonymy: the name of a feast at the feasts of the Hyacinthians and Tithenidians in Sparta.</p>                    
                </div>
                <div type="textpart" n="Etymology">
                    <head>Etymology</head>
                    <p>Derivative from the verb κόπτω, "to strike" (Chantraine 1968 s.v. κόπτω, Beekes 2010 s.v. κόπτω). The verb is possibly Indo-European (cf. lit. kàpti, pl. kick), although Beekes does not rule out that it may come from a substrate (cf. Mallory, Adams 1997, who do not include it in their Encyclopedia). If this hypothesis were accepted, the word κοπίς could be related to the noun σκέπαρνος (a kind of axe), which, like many tool names, has no convincing Indo-European etymology (Beekes 2010 s.v. σκέπαρνος; on the movable -s- in pre-Greek words: Beekes 2010: vol. 1, xxiii). Gordon has drawn attention to the possible association of the word κοπίς with the name of a Near Eastern weapon known from Egyptian sources as a kh.p.sh of similar construction (Gordon 1958: 24). This of course does not imply a Near Eastern etymology of the word (kh.p.sh may be a Mycenaean loanword).</p>
                    <p>Κοπίς as the name of the feast falling on the first day of the Spartan feast of Hyacinthia may be metonymic in character, and is perhaps part of the custom of naming particular elements of feasts after activities or, more importantly in this context, objects that play an important role in them, as was the case with the third day of Anthesteria, bearing the name Χύτραι, 'Pots'.</p>                    
                </div>
                <div type="textpart" n="Appearance_and_function">
                    <head>Appearance and function</head>
                    <p>The copida was the second butcher's tool used in the sacrificial ritual besides the machaira (→ <ref corresp="lexicon_machaira.html">μάχαιρα</ref>). It was used for skinning the animal (βύρσαν ἐξέδειρεν: E. El. 824) and breaking the bones of the chest (ἀναρρῆξαι χέλυν: E. El. 837).* From Euripides' Electra we can infer that there were subtypes of copids probably related to the original place of their production: Orestes first skins the animal with a "doric" (E. El. 819, → <ref corresp="lexicon_doris.html">Δωρίς</ref>), or Δωρικὴ κοπίς (E. El. 836-7), and then asks to be given a cleaver from Phthya (Φθιάδ ̓ ἀντὶ Δωρικῆς, 836), with which he splits his chest and also kills Ajgistos (E. El. 836-838; see also reproductions of vases in: Berthiaume 1982: planches 19, 20). The practice of using several knives (and thus probably also several types of knives) during a sacrifice is captured in vase depictions (van Straten 1995: 18, fig. 7).</p>
                    <p>The boundaries of the uses of machaira and copida seem fluid: Euripides in Cyclops uses the word κοπίς as an adjective to μάχαιρα, speaking of "cleaver knives" (E. Cyc. 241-2). In the description of the Electra sacrifice cited above, the kopida may be identical with → <ref corresp="lexicon_sphagis.html">σφαγίς</ref> of verse 811, which is probably another term for machaira. Xenophon, writing about weapons, also seems to treat the words μάχαιρα and κοπίς synonymously: "[For fighting from horseback] I recommend the machaira rather than the xiphos: for the rider above, a blow with the copida is better than a blow with the xiphos" (μάχαιραν μὲν μᾶλλον ἢ ξίφος ἐπαινοῦμεν: ἐφ ̓ ὑψηλοῦ γὰρ ὄντι τῷ ἱππεῖ κοπίδος μᾶλλον ἡ πληγὴ ἢ ξίφους ἀρκέσει, Eq. 12.11). 
                        The synonymy of copida and machaira seems to have been relied upon by the presumed pun of Achaeus - τίς ὑποκεκρυμμένος μένει, σαραβάκων κοπίδων συνομώνυμε;, "who hides there, namesake of vulva cleavers?" (Athen. 173d = TrGF 20 F 13; the words were addressed to a Delphic, and the key to unraveling the pun is the saying "Delphic machaira"). It is possible that the difference between the two was determined solely by the massiveness of the blade.</p>
                    <p>As in the case of the machaira, the term copida is used to describe the type of weapon used by the Easterners (X. Cyr. 1.2.9, 1.2.13, 2.1.9, 2.2.9, 4.2.22, 5.2.1, 6.2.10, 7.3.8, 8.8.23). For the Greeks in the 5th and 4th centuries BC it is probably exclusively a butchery, sacrificial and kitchen tool (μαγειρικῶν κοπίς: Ar., Fr. 138; story of the meat seller who cuts off Killikont's hand with a kopida: Theopomp.Hist. 111; Anaxipp. 6; see also Berthiaume 1982: 46).</p>
                    <p>Probably by metonymy, the kopida also became the name of an evening feast that fell on the first day of the Laconian festival of Hyacinths (dedicated to Apollon) and took place in the village of Amyklai, south of Sparta. The animals sacrificed at that time were exclusively goats (Ath. 138f). The earliest literary references to the κοπίς feast come from the comedians Kratinos, Eupolis and Epilykos (Crat. 166, Eup. 138, Epil. 3), quoted by Athenaeus in his description of the event (137e-f, 140a). Their accounts show that the Laconian kopida was known in Athens as a festive feast at which even foreigners were not forbidden to eat (τοῖς ξένοισιν, Crat. 166.1); the fact that meat from the sacrifices, alongside other delicacies, was given to everyone present is also emphasised by Athenaeus' narrator (τῶν κρεῶν διδόασι μοίρας πᾶσι, Ath. 139a). 
                        It is in the free access of all festival participants to the meat of sacrificial animals that we can see the source of the potential metonymic transfer of the name of the knife to the whole festival. Athenaeus' account also shows that the term copida was used in Sparta to refer not only to the feast of the Hyacinthian feast, but also to the 'κοπίδες in the city' that took place during the kurotrophic feast of the Tithenidians (Ath. 139a, RE 1511-1512; according to Goldstein, however, this sentence should be understood differently: "they celebrate kopides in the city and during Tithenidia"; Goldstein 1978: 30), celebrated in honour of Artemis nicknamed Corythallia (cf. RE 1346, especially 1390). The animals sacrificed at that time were young piglets aged 4-8 weeks (γαλαθηνοὶ ὀρθαγορίσκοι, called 'suckling piglets' in Polish zootechnical nomenclature).</p>
                    <p>Κοπίς is also the term proposed by Jortin (Griffith 1999: 226; cf. also Brown 1993: 173) emendation of the word κόνις (dust) in verse 602 of Sophocles' Antigone: νῦν γὰρ ἐσχάτας ὕπερ ῥίζας ὃ τέτατο φάος ἐν Οἰδίπου δόμοις, κατ ̓ αὖ νιν φοινία θεῶν τῶν νερτέρων ἀμᾷ κόνις λόγου τ ̓ ἄνοια καὶ φρενῶν ἐρινύς ("When now light fell on the deepest roots of the house of Oedipus, covered them again with the bloody dust of the subterranean gods, the madness of speech and the Erynia of the mind", S. Ant. 599-602). The image of the "roots" of the house of Oedipus, which would thus be "beheaded" (καταμάω) by the 'cleaver of the underworld gods'. 
                        A recent editor of Antigone, however, rejects this emendation, arguing that "κοπίς is properly a 'scimitar' or 'cleaver', not a pruning or harvesting implement, (...) and why should the gods below be wielding a 'bloody scimitar'?" (Griffith 1999: 226; see also Smith 1961). Griffith is undoubtedly correct in rejecting Jortin's emendation, the lexicological line of his argument, however, is flawed. The scholar, probably lacking a systematic study of the word κοπίς, overestimates the fact that it means sword - this meaning is secondary and appears primarily in descriptions of Eastern peoples. Instead, manuscript tradition and the coherence of poetic imagery argue in favour of rejecting emendation. 
                        If we consider that καταμάω does not mean "to cut down" but, as scholiast suggests, "to cover" (cf. Griffith 1999: 226), we get an image organised around a storied metaphor of blinding: the light that fell on the roots in Oedipus' house no longer falls on them, for they have been covered by the blood-dust of the underworld gods, the mindlessness of reason and the Erynia of the mind. These last two phrases evoke another metaphor - madness and ignorance as blindness - and evoke a psychological plane that translates perfectly in the context of the covering/blinding metaphor, less successfully in the context of shearing. Moreover, Griffith fails to note that not only the ἄνοια of verse 602. refers to Antigone's behaviour (cf. S. Ant. 383, 562; Griffith 1999: 226), but also κόνις, as it was with dust that Antigone sprinkled her brother's dead body (S. Ant. 247; Brown 1993: 173).</p>
                    <p>Catalogue of occurrences in the context of sacrifice or meal:</p>
                    <p>1. cleaver: E. Cyc. 241 (adj.), E. El. 819 (→ <ref corresp="lexicon_doris.html">Δωρίς</ref>), 836 (Phthias ~), 837 (Dorike ~), TrGF 20 F12, Ar. Fr. 138, Theopomp.Hist. 111;</p>
                    <p>2. feast of feasts: Crat. 166, Eup. 138, Epil. 3.</p>                    
                </div>
            </div>
            
            <div type="edition" xml:lang="pl">
                <div type="textpart">
                    <p>κοπίς kopis; κοπίς, ίδος, subst. f.: masywny nóż do krojenia, tasak, poet. adj. tasakowy; być może przez metonimię: nazwa uczty podczas świąt Hiacyntiów i Tithenidiów w Sparcie.</p>                    
                </div>
                <div type="textpart" n="Etymologia">
                    <head>Etymologia</head>
                    <p>Derywat od czasownika κόπτω, „uderzać” (Chantraine 1968 s.v. κόπτω, Beekes 2010 s.v. κόπτω). Czasownik jest być może indoeuropejski (cf. lit. kàpti, pl. kopać), chociaż Beekes nie wyklucza, że może pochodzić z substratu (cf. Mallory, Adams 1997, którzy nie uwzględniają go w swojej Encyklopedii). Gdyby przyjąć tę hipotezę, wyraz κοπίς można wiązać z rzeczownikiem σκέπαρνος (rodzaj topora), który, jak wiele nazw narzędzi, nie ma przekonującej indoeuropejskiej etymologii (Beekes 2010 s.v. σκέπαρνος; o ruchomym -s- w wyrazach przedgreckich: Beekes 2010: vol. 1, xxiii). Gordon zwrócił uwagę na możliwy związek słowa κοπίς z nazwą bliskowschodniej broni znanej ze źródeł egipskich jako kh.p.sh o podobnej budowie (Gordon 1958: 24). Nie implikuje to oczywiście bliskowschodniej etymologii słowa (kh.p.sh może być mykeńską pożyczką).</p>
                    <p>Κοπίς jako nazwa przypadającej na pierwszy dzień spartańskiego święta Hiacyntiów uczty może mieć charakter metonimiczny i być może wpisuje się w zwyczaj nadawania nazw poszczególnym elementom świąt od czynności lub, co w tym kontekście ważniejsze, przedmiotów odgrywających w nich istotną rolę, jak to było w przypadku trzeciego dnia Anthesteriów, noszącego nazwę Χύτραι, „Garnki”.</p>                    
                </div>
                <div type="textpart" n="Wygląd_i_funkcja">
                    <head>Wygląd i funkcja</head>
                    <p>Kopida była drugim obok machairy (→ <ref corresp="lexicon_machaira.html">μάχαιρα</ref>) narzędziem rzeźniczym wykorzystywanym w rytuale ofiarniczym. Służyła do skórowania zwierzęcia (βύρσαν ἐξέδειρεν: E. El. 824) i łamania kości klatki piersiowej (ἀναρρῆξαι χέλυν: E. El. 837).* Z Elektry Eurypidesa możemy wnioskować, że istniały podtypy kopid związane prawdopodobnie z pierwotnym miejscem ich produkcji: Orestes najpierw skóruje zwierzę „doryjką” (E. El. 819, → <ref corresp="lexicon_doris.html">Δωρίς</ref>), czyli Δωρικὴ κοπίς (E. El. 836-7), a następnie prosi, aby podano mu tasak z Fthyi (Φθιάδ ̓ ἀντὶ Δωρικῆς, 836), którym rozłupuje jego klatkę piersiową, a także zabija Ajgistosa (E. El. 836-838; zob. też reprodukcje waz w: Berthiaume 1982: planches 19, 20). Praktyka wykorzystywania kilku noży (a więc pewnie także kilku ich typów) podczas ofiary została uchwycona na przedstawieniach wazowych (van Straten 1995: 18, ryc. 7).</p>
                    <p>Granice zastosowań machairy i kopidy wydają się płynne: Eurypides w Cyklopie posługuje się wyrazem κοπίς jako przymiotnikiem do μάχαιρα, mówiąc o „tasakowych nożach” (E. Cyc. 241-2). W przywołanym wyżej opisie ofiary z Elektry kopida może być tożsama ze → <ref corresp="lexicon_sphagis.html">σφαγίς</ref> z wersu 811, która jest prawdopodobnie innym określeniem machairy. Również piszący o broni Ksenofont wydaje się traktować wyrazy μάχαιρα i κοπίς synonimicznie: „[Do walki z końskiego grzbietu] zalecam raczej machairę niż ksifos: dla znajdującego się wyżej jeźdźca cios kopidą jest lepszy, niż cios ksifosem” (μάχαιραν μὲν μᾶλλον ἢ ξίφος ἐπαινοῦμεν: ἐφ ̓ ὑψηλοῦ γὰρ ὄντι τῷ ἱππεῖ κοπίδος μᾶλλον ἡ πληγὴ ἢ ξίφους ἀρκέσει, Eq. 12.11). 
                        Wydaje się, że na synonimii kopidy i machairy opiera się domniemany kalambur Achajosa - τίς ὑποκεκρυμμένος μένει, σαραβάκων κοπίδων συνομώνυμε;, „kto się tam kryje, imienniku sromowych tasaków?” (Athen. 173d = TrGF 20 F 13; słowa skierowane były do delfijczyka, a kluczem do rozwikłania kalamburu jest powiedzenie „delficka machaira”). Niewykluczone, że o różnicy między nimi decydowała wyłącznie masywność ostrza.</p>
                    <p>Podobnie jak w przypadku machairy, mianem kopidy określa się typ broni używanej przez mieszkańców wschodu (X. Cyr. 1.2.9, 1.2.13, 2.1.9, 2.2.9, 4.2.22, 5.2.1, 6.2.10, 7.3.8, 8.8.23). Dla Greków w V i IV wieku p.n.e. jest to chyba wyłącznie narzędzie rzeźnicze, ofiarnicze i kuchenne (μαγειρικῶν κοπίς: Ar., Fr. 138; historia sprzedawcy mięsa, który kopidą odcina rękę Killikontowi: Theopomp.Hist. 111; Anaxipp. 6; zob. też Berthiaume 1982: 46).</p>
                    <p>Prawdopodobnie przez metonimię, kopida stała się również nazwą wieczornej uczty, która przypadała na pierwszy dzień lakońskiego święta Hiacyntiów (dedykowanego Apollonowi) i miała miejsce w położonej na południe od Sparty miejscowości Amyklai. Zwierzętami, które składano wówczas w ofierze, były wyłącznie kozy (Ath. 138f). Najwcześniejsze literackie wzmianki o uczcie κοπίς pochodzą z komediopisarzy Kratinosa, Eupolisa i Epilykosa (Crat. 166, Eup. 138, Epil. 3), zacytowanych przez Atenajosa w jego opisie tego wydarzenia (137e-f, 140a). Z ich przekazów wynika, że lakońską kopidę znano w Atenach jako świąteczną ucztę, na której jedzenia nie wzbrania się nawet cudzioziemcom (τοῖς ξένοισιν, Crat. 166.1); fakt, że mięso z ofiar, obok innych smakołyków, otrzymywał każdy z obecnych, podkreśla również narrator Atenajosa (τῶν κρεῶν διδόασι μοίρας πᾶσι, Ath. 139a). 
                        Właśnie w wolnym dostępie wszystkich uczestników święta do mięsa ofiarnych zwierząt możemy upatrywać źródeł potencjalnego metonimicznego przeniesienia nazwy noża na całe święto. Z przekazu Atenajosa wynika również, że mianem kopidy określano w Sparcie nie tylko ucztę podczas święta Hiacyntiów, ale też „κοπίδες w mieście”, które miały miejsce podczas kurotroficznego święta Tithenidiów (Ath. 139a, RE 1511-1512; zdaniem Goldsteina zdanie to należy jednak rozumieć inaczej: „obchodzą kopides w mieście i podczas Tithenidiów”; Goldstein 1978: 30), obchodzonego ku czci Artemidy o przydomku Korythallia (cf. RE 1346, a zwłaszcza 1390). Składanymi wówczas w ofierze zwierzętami były młode prosięta w wieku 4-8 tygodni (γαλαθηνοὶ ὀρθαγορίσκοι, zwane w polskiej nomenklaturze zootechnicznej „prosiętami ssącymi”).</p>
                    <p>Κοπίς jest również zaproponowaną przez Jortina (Griffith 1999: 226; zob. też Brown 1993: 173) emendacją wyrazu κόνις (pył) w wersie 602 Antygony Sofoklesa: νῦν γὰρ ἐσχάτας ὕπερ ῥίζας ὃ τέτατο φάος ἐν Οἰδίπου δόμοις, κατ ̓ αὖ νιν φοινία θεῶν τῶν νερτέρων ἀμᾷ κόνις λόγου τ ̓ ἄνοια καὶ φρενῶν ἐρινύς („Gdy teraz na najgłębsze korzenie domu Edypa padło światło, zakrył je znów krwawy pył bogów podziemnych, szaleństwo mowy i Erynia umysłu”, S. Ant. 599-602). Do emendacji takiej skłania obraz „korzeni” domu Edypa, które zostałyby tym samym „ścięte” (καταμάω) przez „tasak bogów podziemnych”. 
                        Ostatni wydawca Antygony odrzuca jednak tę emendację, argumentując, że „κοπίς is properly a 'scimitar' or 'cleaver', not a pruning or harvesting implement, (...) and why should the gods below be wielding a 'bloody scimitar'?” (Griffith 1999: 226; zob. też Smith 1961). Griffith ma niewątpliwie rację, odrzucając emendację Jortina, leksykologiczna linia jego argumentacji jest jednak błędna. Uczony, nie dysponując zapewne systematycznym opracowaniem słowa κοπίς, przecenia fakt, że oznacza ono miecz - znaczenie to jest wtórne i pojawia się przede wszystkim w opisach ludów wschodu. Za odrzuceniem emendacji przemawiają natomiast tradycja manuskryptowa i koherencja poetyckiego obrazowania. Jeżeli uznamy, że καταμάω nie znaczy „ścinać”, tylko, jak sugeruje scholiasta, „zakrywać” (cf. Griffith 1999: 226), otrzymamy obraz zorganizowany wokół piętrowej metafory zaślepiania: światło, które padło na korzenie w domu Edypa, już na nie nie pada, ponieważ zakryły je krwawy pył bogów podziemnych, bezmyślność rozumu i Erynia umysłu. 
                        Te dwa ostatnie wyrażenia ewokują inną metaforę – szaleństwa i niewiedzy jako zaślepienia – oraz przywołują plan psychologiczny, który doskonale tłumaczy się w kontekście metafory zakrywania/zaślepiania, mniej udatnie – w kontekście ścinania. Co więcej, Griffith nie zauważa, że nie tylko ἄνοια z wersu 602. odnosi się do zachowania Antygony (cf. S. Ant. 383, 562; Griffith 1999: 226), ale również κόνις, jako że pyłem właśnie Antygona posypała martwe ciało brata (S. Ant. 247; Brown 1993: 173).</p>
                    <p>Katalog wystąpień w kontekście ofiary lub posiłku:</p>
                    <p>1. tasak: E. Cyc. 241 (adj.), E. El. 819 (→ <ref corresp="lexicon_doris.html">Δωρίς</ref>), 836 (Phthias ~), 837 (Dorike ~), TrGF 20 F12, Ar. Fr. 138, Theopomp.Hist. 111;</p>
                    <p>2. uczta świąteczna: Crat. 166, Eup. 138, Epil. 3.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            
            <div type="bibliography">
                <p>Beekes, R. (2010), Etymological Dictionary of Greek, Leiden-Boston.</p>
                <p>Berthiaume, G. (1982), Les rôles du mágeiros. Étude sur la boucherie, la cuisine et sacrifice dans la Grèce ancienne, Leiden.</p>
                <p>Brown, A. (1998), Sophocles: Antigone, Warminster.</p>
                <p>Goldstein, M.S. (1978), The Setting of the Ritual Meal in Greek Sanctuaries: 600-300 B.C., nieopublikowana praca doktorska.</p>
                <p>Gordon, D.H. (1958), 14. Scimitars, Sabres and Falchions, Man, Vol. 58, s. 22-27.</p>
                <p>Griffith, M. (1999), Sophocles, Antigone, Cambridge.</p>
                <p>Mallory, J.P.; Adams, D. Q. (1997), Encyclopedia of Indo-European Culture, London.</p>
                <p>Smith, P. J. (1961), Sophocles, „Ant”. 599-603, The Classical World, Vol. 54, No. 6, s. 175-176.</p>
                <p>van Straten, F. T. (1995), Hiera kala. Images of Animal Sacrifice in Archaic and Classical Greece, Leiden – New York – Köln.</p>
                <p>Wernicke (1894), Artemis, [w:] Paulys Real-Encyklopaedie der Classischen Altertumswissenschaft, Stuttgart, 1335-1440.</p>
                <p>Ziehen, Ludwig (1894), Τιθηνίδια, [w:] Paulys Real-Encyklopaedie der Classischen Altertumswissenschaft, Stuttgart, 1511-1512.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
