<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>μῆρα</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher><ref target="https://site.unibo.it/lares/">LARES Project</ref></publisher>
                <date when="2021"/>
                <idno type="filename">lexicon_mera</idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>"Animal Sacrifice in Ancient Greece" database (<ref>http://www.sacrificium.filg.uj.edu.pl</ref>).</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change when="2022-02-03" who="Irene Vagionakis">encoded in XML</change>
                <change when="2015-03-31" who="Lech Trzcionkowski">written contents</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="edition" xml:lang="it">
                <div type="textpart" >
                    <p><w>μῆρα</w> mēra, subst. n., plurale tantum, i femori di bovini, ovini o caprini bruciati su un altare.</p>                    
                </div>
                <div type="textpart" n="Etimologia">
                    <head>Etimologia</head>
                    <p>Il sostantivo μῆρα è probabilmente una continuazione della forma arcaica del sostantivo collettivo (collettivo) *mēms-reh2 (Vine 2002, 333), cfr. toch B mīsa 'carne' (&lt; ptoch. *myämsa, con la regolare perdita della consonante nasale per -s-, Hackstein 2011/2, 154). Come sostantivo collettivo la parola *mēms-reh2 significava un insieme di oggetti, il significato originale di i.-e. *mēms-reh2 dovrebbe quindi essere definito come "(insieme, collezione) di parti, pezzi di animali > carne". 
                        Tuttavia, questa ipotesi non spiega la forma attestata della parola, poiché secondo le regole del cambiamento fonetico ci si aspetterebbe la forma *μεμβρ- (Beekes 2010, 947). È quindi possibile che il greco μῆρα derivi da una forma priva della consonante nasale -m-: cioè *mēs-reh2. In greco, attraverso un processo di specializzazione, la parola μῆρα venne a significare "un insieme, un insieme di femori", opportunamente preparati e offerti agli esseri soprannaturali [?"(un insieme, una collezione) di parti di animali > femori bruciati per gli dei"].</p>
                    <p>La specializzazione in greco è particolare, forse legata all'evoluzione del rito del sacrificio di sangue animale (cfr. un altro termine tecnico espresso dal sostantivo collettivo <w>σπλάγχνα</w>). In altre lingue dalla stessa base di vocabolario, cioè *mēs/*mēms 'carne', sostantivi evoluti che significano 'carne' o 'carne'. La forma atematica è stata mantenuta dal sostantivo scr. mās- 'carne'. In molte lingue si è formato il sostantivo soggetto r.n. *mēms-(o)-m, da cui derivano sostantivi che significano "carne", cfr. pol. mięso, "parti commestibili di animali macellati", "parti molli del corpo umano", ogsł. *maso: scs. męso, cz. maso, ros. mjáso; lit. mėsà, lat. mìesa ("carne", "corpo"); goc. mimz (acc. sg.); stind. māṁsám (n.), "carne", orm. mis (cfr. Polomé 1967). In greco cioè *mēs/*mēms nel senso di "carne" ha ripreso un altro sostantivo di origine indoeuropea, <w>κρέας</w>, "carne cruda" (vedi s.v.).</p>
                </div>
                <div type="textpart" n="Testimonianze">
                    <head>Testimonianze</head>
                    <p>Il sostantivo collettivo μῆρα è un termine tecnico arcaico per i femori avvolti in una membrana peritoneale grassa che venivano sacrificati su un altare e bruciati. Nell'epica omerica ricorre in contesti strettamente specializzati in modo intercambiabile con il termine → <ref corresp="lexicon_meria.html">μηρία</ref>. In primo luogo, nel composto fraseologico <w>μῆρα</w> + <w>ἐπιτίθημι</w>, 'deporre (sull'altare) i femori (nascosti nella membrana peritoneale)' come metonimia per 'offrire un sacrificio animale' (nella memoria di Nestore dei sacrifici fatti in passato: Od. 3.178-9: Ποσειδάωνι δὲ ταύρων / πόλλ᾽ ἐπὶ μῆρ᾽ ἔθεμεν, a Poseidone abbiamo offerto una coscia di toro plurale). Tuttavia, appare più frequentemente nelle descrizioni finali in esametri standard di un sacrificio di sangue combinato con un pasto (una scena tipica): αὐτὰρ ἐπεὶ κατὰ μῆρ᾽ ἐκάη καὶ σπλάγχνα πάσαντο "quando le gambe erano bruciate e avevano assaggiato le interiora (4x: Il. 1.464=Il. 2.427=Od. 3.461= Od. 12.364). In una variante di questo esametro in Od. 3.9 μῆρα è stato sostituito dal sostantivo più frequente μηρία: εὖθ᾽ οἱ σπλάγχνα πάσαντο, θεῷ δ᾽ ἐπὶ μηρί᾽ ἔκηαν. Oltre a questo lo troviamo nella descrizione della festa di Feak (Od. 13.25-6: μῆρα δὲ κήαντες δαίνυντ᾽ ἐρικυδέα δαῖτα τερπόμενοι). Nell'epica più tarda la scena tipica fu trasformata mantenendo il sostantivo arcaico (A.Rh. 1.433-434: "tagliarono anche le gambe, tutte le parti accuratamente ricoperte di grasso abbondante", τε καὶ ἱερὰ μῆρ᾽ ἐτάμοντο, / κὰδ δ᾽ ἄμυδις τάγε πάντα καλύψαντες πύκα δημῷ).</p>                    
                </div>
                <div type="textpart" n="Catalogo_delle_apparizioni">
                    <head>Catalogo delle apparizioni</head>
                    <p>1. femori</p>
                    <p>a. ἐπιτίθημι + μῆρα deposto sull'altare: Da. 3.179</p>
                    <p>b. κατακαίειν + μῆρα per bruciare: Il. 1.464=Il. 2.427 = Od. 3,461= Od. 12.364 (verso formulare), Od. 13.25;</p>
                    <p>2. gambe</p>
                    <p>a. τάμνειν + μῆρα per tagliare: A.Rh. 1,433</p>                    
                </div>
            </div>
            
            <div type="edition" xml:lang="en">
                <div type="textpart" >
                    <p>μῆρα mēra, subst. n., plurale tantum, the femurs of cattle, sheep, or goats burned on an altar.</p>                    
                </div>
                <div type="textpart" n="Etymology">
                    <head>Etymology</head>
                    <p>The noun μῆρα is probably a continuation of the archaic form of the collective (collective) noun *mēms-reh2 (Vine 2002, 333), cf. toch B mīsa 'meat' (&lt; ptoch. *myämsa, with the regular loss of the nasal consonant by -s-, Hackstein 2011/2, 154). As a collective noun the word *mēms-reh2 meant a set of objects, the original meaning of i.-e. *mēms-reh2 would therefore have to be defined as '(set, collection) of parts, pieces of animal > meat'. However, this hypothesis does not explain the attested form of the word, since according to the rules of phonetic change one would expect the form *μεμβρ- (Beekes 2010, 947). It is therefore possible that the Greek μῆρα derives from a form lacking the nasal consonant -m-: i.e. *mēs-reh2. In Greek, through a process of specialisation, the word μῆρα came to mean "a set, a set of femurs", properly prepared and offered to supernatural beings [?"(a set, a collection) of animal parts > femurs burned for the gods"].</p>
                    <p>The specialisation in Greek is peculiar, perhaps related to the evolution of the ritual of animal blood sacrifice (cf. another technical term expressed by the collective noun σπλάγχνα). In other languages from the same vocabulary base, i.e. *mēs/*mēms 'meat', evolved nouns meaning 'meat' or 'flesh'. The athematic form was retained by the scr. noun mās- 'meat'. In many languages the subject noun r.n. was formed. *mēms-(o)-m, from which are derived nouns meaning "meat", cf. pol. mięso, "edible parts of slaughtered animals", "soft parts of the human body", ogsł. *maso: scs. męso, cz. maso, ros. mjáso; lit. mėsà, lat. mìesa ("meat", "body"); goc. mimz (acc. sg.); stind. māṁsám (n.), "meat", orm. mis (cf. Polomé 1967). In Greek i.e. *mēs/*mēms in the sense of "meat" took over another noun of Indo-European origin, κρέας, "raw meat" (see s.v.).</p>                    
                </div>
                <div type="textpart" n="Testimonies">
                    <head>Testimonies</head>
                    <p>The collective noun μῆρα is an archaic technical term for femurs wrapped in fatty peritoneal membrane that were sacrificed on an altar and burned. In Homeric epic it occurs in strictly specialized contexts interchangeably with the term → <ref corresp="lexicon_meria.html">μηρία</ref>. First, in the phraseological compound μῆρα + ἐπιτίθημι, 'to lay (on the altar) femurs (hidden in the peritoneal membrane)' as a metonymy for 'to offer an animal sacrifice' (in Nestor's memoir of sacrifices performed in the past: Od. 3.178-9: Ποσειδάωνι δὲ ταύρων / πόλλ᾽ ἐπὶ μῆρ᾽ ἔθεμεν, to Poseidon we offered a plural leg of bulls). However, it appears most frequently in the standard hexameter ending descriptions of a blood sacrifice combined with a meal (a typical scene): αὐτὰρ ἐπεὶ κατὰ μῆρ᾽ ἐκάη καὶ σπλάγχνα πάσαντο 'when the legs had burned and they had tasted the entrails' (4x: Il. 1.464=Il. 2.427=Od. 3.461= Od. 12.364). In a variant of this hexameter in Od. 3.9 μῆρα has been replaced by the more frequent noun μηρία: εὖθ᾽ οἱ σπλάγχνα πάσαντο, θεῷ δ᾽ ἐπὶ μηρί᾽ ἔκηαν. In addition to this we find it in the description of the feast at Feak (Od. 13.25-6: μῆρα δὲ κήαντες δαίνυντ᾽ ἐρικυδέα δαῖτα τερπόμενοι). In the later epic the typical scene was transformed retaining the archaic noun (A.Rh. 1.433-434: 'they also chopped off the legs, all the parts thoroughly covered with abundant fat', τε καὶ ἱερὰ μῆρ᾽ ἐτάμοντο, / κὰδ δ᾽ ἄμυδις τάγε πάντα καλύψαντες πύκα δημῷ).</p>                    
                </div>
                <div type="textpart" n="Catalogue_of_appearances">
                    <head>Catalogue of appearances</head>
                    <p>1. femurs</p>
                    <p>a. ἐπιτίθημι + μῆρα laid on the altar: From. 3.179</p>
                    <p>b. κατακαίειν + μῆρα to burn: Il. 1.464=Il. 2.427 = Od. 3.461= Od. 12.364 (formular verse), Od. 13.25;</p>
                    <p>2. legs</p>
                    <p>a. τάμνειν + μῆρα to chop off: A.Rh. 1,433</p>                    
                </div>
            </div>
            
            <div type="edition" xml:lang="pl">
                <div type="textpart" >
                    <p>μῆρα mēra, subst. n., plurale tantum, kości udowe bydlęce, owcze lub kozie spalane na ołtarzu.</p>                    
                </div>
                <div type="textpart" n="Etymologia">
                    <head>Etymologia</head>
                    <p>Rzeczownik μῆρα jest prawdopodobnie kontynuacją archaicznej formy rzeczownika zbiorczego (kolektywnego) *mēms-reh2 (Vine 2002, 333), por. toch B mīsa „mięso” (&lt; ptoch. *myämsa, z regularną utratą zgłoski nosowej przez –s-, Hackstein 2011/2, 154). Jako rzeczownik kolektywny słowo *mēms-reh2 oznaczało zestaw przedmiotów, pierwotne znaczenie i.-e. *mēms-reh2 należałoby zdefiniować zatem jako „(zestaw, zbiór) części, kawałki zwierzęcia > mięso”. Hipoteza ta nie wyjaśnia jednak poświadczonej formy słowa, gdyż zgodnie z regułami zmian fonetycznych należałoby się spodziewać formy *μεμβρ- (Beekes 2010, 947). Możliwe zatem, że greckie μῆρα wywodzi się z formy pozbawionej zgłoski nosowej –m–: i.e. *mēs-reh2. W języku greckim w wyniku procesu specjalizacji słowo μῆρα zaczęło oznaczać „zestaw, komplet kości udowych”, odpowiednio przygotowanych i ofiarowanych istotom nadprzyrodzonym [?„(zestaw, zbiór) części zwierzęcia > kości udowe spalane dla bogów”].</p>
                    <p>Specjalizacja w języku greckim jest szczególna, być może związana z ewolucją rytuału krwawej ofiary zwierzęcej (por. inny termin techniczny wyrażony rzeczownikiem kolektywnym σπλάγχνα). W innych językach z tej samej podstawy słowotwórczej, i.e. *mēs/*mēms „mięso”, wyewoluowały rzeczowniki oznaczające „mięso” lub „ciało”. Formę atematyczną zachował skr. rzeczownik mās- „mięso”. W wielu językach został utworzony rzeczownik tematyczny r.n. *mēms-(o)-m, od którego wywodzą się rzeczowniki oznaczające „mięso”, por. pol. mięso, „jadalne części zabitych zwierząt”, „miękkie części organizmu ludzkiego”, ogsł. *męso: scs. męso, cz. maso, ros. mjáso; lit. mėsà, łot. mìesa („mięso”, „ciało”); goc. mimz (acc. sg.); stind. māṁsám (n.), „mięso”, orm. mis (por. Polomé 1967). W języku greckim i.e. *mēs/*mēms w znaczeniu „mięso” przejął inny rzeczownik pochodzenia indoeuropejskiego, κρέας, „surowe mięso” (zob. s.v.).</p>
                </div>
                <div type="textpart" n="Poświadczenia">
                    <head></head>
                    <p>Rzeczownik zbiorowy μῆρα jest archaicznym terminem technicznym oznaczającym kości udowe zawinięte w otłuszczoną błonę otrzewnej, które były składane na ołtarzu i spalane. W eposie homeryckim występuje w ściśle wyspecjalizowanych kontekstach wymiennie z terminem → <ref corresp="lexicon_meria.html">μηρία</ref>. Po pierwsze w związku frazeologicznym μῆρα + ἐπιτίθημι, „kłaść (na ołtarzu) kości udowe (ukryte w błonie otrzewnej)” jako  metonimia „składać ofiarę zwierzęcą” (we wspomnieniu Nestora o ofiarach spełnionych w przeszłości: Od. 3.178-9: Ποσειδάωνι δὲ ταύρων / πόλλ᾽ ἐπὶ μῆρ᾽ ἔθεμεν, Posejdonowi złożyliśmy mnogie udźce byków). Najczęściej pojawia się jednak w standardowym heksametrze kończącym opisy ofiary krwawej połączonej z posiłkiem (scena typowa): αὐτὰρ ἐπεὶ κατὰ μῆρ᾽ ἐκάη καὶ σπλάγχνα πάσαντο „gdy już udźce spłonęły i skosztowali wnętrzności” (4x: Il. 1.464=Il. 2.427=Od. 3.461= <ref type="lit">Od. 12.364</ref>). W wariancie tego heksametru w Od. 3.9 μῆρα zostały zastąpione przez częstszy rzeczownik μηρία: εὖθ᾽ οἱ σπλάγχνα πάσαντο, θεῷ δ᾽ ἐπὶ μηρί᾽ ἔκηαν. Oprócz tego znajdujemy go w opisie uczty u Feaków (Od. 13.25-6: μῆρα δὲ κήαντες δαίνυντ᾽ ἐρικυδέα δαῖτα τερπόμενοι). W późniejszym eposie scena typowa uległa transformacji zachowując archaiczny rzeczownik (A.Rh. 1.433-434: „odrąbali też udźce, wszystkie części dokładnie tłuszczem obfitym pokrywszy”,  τε καὶ ἱερὰ μῆρ᾽ ἐτάμοντο, / κὰδ δ᾽ ἄμυδις τάγε πάντα καλύψαντες πύκα δημῷ).</p>                    
                </div>
                <div type="textpart" n="Katalog_wystąpień">
                    <head>Katalog wystąpień</head>
                    <p>1. kości udowe</p>
                    <p>a. ἐπιτίθημι + μῆρα kłaść na ołtarzu: Od. 3.179</p>
                    <p>b. κατακαίειν + μῆρα spalać: Il. 1.464=Il. 2.427 = Od. 3.461= Od. 12.364 (wers formularny), Od. 13.25;</p>
                    <p>2. udźce</p>
                    <p>a. τάμνειν + μῆρα odrąbać: A.Rh. 1,433</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            
            <div type="bibliography">
                <p>Beekes, Robert (2010), Etymological Dictionary of Greek, Leiden.</p>
                <p>Hackstein, Olav (2011-2), Collective and Feminine in Tocharian, w: Multilingualism and History of Knowledge, t.2: Linguistic Developments along the Silk Road. Archaism and Innovation in Tocharian, ed. by Olav Hackstein, Ronald I. Kim, Wien, s. 143-177 (Osterreichische Akademie der Wissenschaften, phil.-hist. Klasse Sitzungsberichte, 834. Band.).</p>
                <p>Vine, Brent (2002), On full-grade *-ro formations in Greek and Indo-European, w: Indo-European Perspectives, ed. M.V.S. Southern, Washington, s. 329-350.</p>
                <p>Polomé, E.R. (1967), Notes on the Reflexes of ie /ms/ in Germanic, „Revue Belge de Philologie et d’Histoire”, 45, s. 800-826.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
