<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>σφαγίς</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher><ref target="https://site.unibo.it/lares/">LARES Project</ref></publisher>
                <date when="2021"/>
                <idno type="filename">lexicon_sphagis</idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digital document.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change when="2022-02-03" who="Irene Vagionakis">encoded document in XML</change>
                <change when="2018-05-08" who="Przemysław Biernat">created document contents</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="edition" xml:lang="it">
                <div type="textpart" >
                    <p><w>σφαγίς</w> sfagis, ίδος, subst. f. un coltello per macellare.</p>                    
                </div>
                <div type="textpart" n="Etimologia">
                    <head>Etimologia</head>
                    <p>Derivato dal verbo → <w>σφάζω</w> 'macellare' (Chantraine 1968: 1073, Beekes 2010: 1426). Anche se il soggetto sphag- è isolato in altre lingue indoeuropee, la sua produttività chiama in causa l'origine non indoeuropea del verbo.</p>                    
                </div>
                <div type="textpart" n="Testimonianze">
                    <head>Testimonianze</head>
                    <p>Nella letteratura classica, sfagida appare solo nell'Elettra di Euripide (E. El. 811, 1142), in un significato e una funzione identica a machaira (→ <ref corresp="lexicon_machaira.html"><w>μάχαιρα</w></ref>). Nella descrizione della scena del sacrificio alle Ninfe, Aigistos tira fuori una sfagida da un cesto (→ κανοῦν) e con essa taglia i capelli dalla testa del vitello (E. El. 811-812, cfr. Hom. Il. 3.271, 19.252, dove una machaira è usata a questo scopo). Sfagida appare anche nascosta in una cesta (come la machaira in Ar. Pax 948) in una scena parallela di preparazione al sacrificio di un toro, durante il quale Clitennestra deve essere uccisa (E. El. 1142-1146). In una conversazione sul crimine commesso, i fratelli tragici nominano lo strumento del crimine successivamente con le parole → <ref corresp="lexicon_phasganon.html"><w>φάσγανον</w></ref> (E. El. 1222) e <w>ξίφος</w> (E. El. 1225), che significa spada. Si tratta certamente di una licenza poetica (cfr. Eu. Alc. 74: ξίφος in funzione di machairy). Sulla base dell'uso della parola da parte di Euripide, possiamo quindi concludere che sfagida è un iponimo di machaira che indica non tanto una differenza essenziale nella costruzione degli oggetti quanto lo scopo per cui il coltello deve essere usato. In assenza di altre fonti del periodo, tuttavia, l'ipotesi non può essere verificata.</p>
                    <p>Nei testi successivi la parola appare più frequentemente, mantenendo la sua connotazione morfologicamente consolidata con l'attività di macellazione degli animali (mentre machaira era anche un termine per le armi). Nelle Antiquitates Romanae 2.52 di Dionigi di Alicarnasso (circa 60 - 7 a.C.) si legge di Tatius ucciso con μαγειρικαῖς σφαγίσι, macellato con sfagidi, durante il sacrificio. Lo sfagide menzionato da Polyainos (Polyaenus Rhetor, II secolo d.C., Strategemata 3.9.40) era destinato alla macellazione delle pecore. Infine, un epigramma votivo fittizio dell'Antologia greca menziona τὰν λαιμοτόμον <w>σφαγίδα</w>, uno sfagide taglia gola, tra gli strumenti di macellazione dati in dono a Hermes da un certo libertino (Aristo, Anth. Graeca 6.306).</p>                    
                </div>
            </div>
            
            <div type="edition" xml:lang="en">
                <div type="textpart" >
                    <p>σφαγίς sfagis, ίδος, subst. f. a knife for butchering.</p>                    
                </div>
                <div type="textpart" n="Etymology">
                    <head>Etymology</head>
                    <p>Derivative from the verb → σφάζω 'to butcher' (Chantraine 1968: 1073, Beekes 2010: 1426). Although the subject sphag- is isolated to other Indo-European languages, its productivity calls into question the non-Indo-European origin of the verb.</p>                    
                </div>
                <div type="textpart" n="Testimonies">
                    <head>Testimonies</head>
                    <p>In classical literature, sphagida appears only in Euripides' Electra (E. El. 811, 1142), in a meaning and function identical to machaira (→ <ref corresp="lexicon_machaira.html">μάχαιρα</ref>). In the description of the scene of the sacrifice to the Nymphs, Aigistos brings out a sphagid from a basket (→ κανοῦν) and cuts the hair from the calf's head with it (E. El. 811-812, cf. Hom. Il. 3.271, 19.252, where a machaira is used for this purpose). Sfagida also appears hidden in a basket (like the machaira in Ar. Pax 948) in a parallel scene of preparation for the sacrifice of a bull, during which Clytemnestra is to be killed (E. El. 1142-1146). In a conversation about the crime committed, the tragedian siblings name the instrument of the crime successively with the words → <ref corresp="lexicon_phasganon.html">φάσγανον</ref> (E. El. 1222) and ξίφος (E. El. 1225), meaning sword. We are certainly dealing here with poetic licence (cf. Eu. Alc. 74: ξίφος in the function of machairy). On the basis of Euripides' use of the word, we can therefore conclude that sphagida is a hyponym of machaira indicating not so much an essential difference in the construction of the objects as the purpose for which the knife is to be used. In the absence of other sources from the period, however, the hypothesis cannot be verified.</p>
                    <p>In later texts the word appears more frequently, retaining its morphologically well-established connotation with the activity of slaughtering animals (while machaira was also a term for weapons). In Antiquitates Romanae 2.52 by Dionysius of Halicarnassus (circa 60 - 7 BC) we read about Tatius murdered with μαγειρικαῖς σφαγίσι, butchered with sphagids, while making a sacrifice. The sphagid mentioned by Polyainos (Polyaenus Rhetor, 2nd century AD, Strategemata 3.9.40) was intended for butchering sheep. Finally, a fictional votive epigram from the Greek Anthology mentions τὰν λαιμοτόμον σφαγίδα, a throat-cutting sphagid, among the butchery implements given as a gift to Hermes by a certain libertine (Aristo, Anth. Graeca 6.306).</p>                    
                </div>
            </div>
            
            <div type="edition" xml:lang="pl">
                <div type="textpart" >
                    <p>σφαγίς sfagis, ίδος, subst. f. nóż do zarzynania.</p>                    
                </div>
                <div type="textpart" n="Etymologia">
                    <head>Etymologia</head>
                    <p>Derywat od czasownika → σφάζω „zarzynać” (Chantraine 1968: 1073, Beekes 2010: 1426). Chociaż temat sphag- jest izolowany na tle innych języków indoeuropejskich, jego produktywność stawia pod znakiem zapytania nieindoeuropejskie pochodzenie czasownika.</p>                    
                </div>
                <div type="textpart" n="Poświadczenia">
                    <head>Poświadczenia</head>
                    <p>W literaturze klasycznej sfagida pojawia się wyłącznie w Elektrze Eurypidesa (E. El. 811, 1142),  w znaczeniu i funkcji tożsamej z machairą (→ <ref corresp="lexicon_machaira.html">μάχαιρα</ref>). W opisie sceny ofiary dla Nimf, Aigistos wydobywa sfagidę z kosza (→ κανοῦν) i obcina nią włosy z głowy cielęcia (E. El. 811-812, cf. Hom. Il. 3.271, 19.252, gdzie służy do tego machaira). Sfagida pojawia się również ukryta w koszu (jak machaira w Ar. Pax 948) w paralelnej scenie przygotowań do ofiary z byka, podczas której zginąć ma Klitajmestra (E. El. 1142-1146). W rozmowie o dokonanej zbrodni, tragediowe rodzeństwo nazywa jej narzędzie kolejno słowami → <ref corresp="lexicon_phasganon.html">φάσγανον</ref> (E. El. 1222) i ξίφος (E. El. 1225), oznaczającymi miecz. Mamy tu z pewnością do czynienia z licencją poetycką (cf. Eu. Alc. 74: ξίφος w funkcji machairy). Na podstawie użycia wyrazu przez Eurypidesa możemy więc stwierdzić, że sfagida jest hiponimem machairy wskazującym nie tyle na istotną różnicę w budowie przedmiotów, co na cel, w jakim nóż ma zostać użyty. W świetle braku innych źródeł z epoki, hipoteza nie daje się jednak zweryfikować.</p>
                    <p>W późniejszych tekstach wyraz pojawia się częściej, zachowując swoją morfologicznie ugruntowaną konotację z czynnością zarzynania zwierząt (podczas gdy machaira bywała też określeniem broni). W Antiquitates Romanae 2.52 Dionizjusza z Halikarnasu (circa 60 – 7 r. p.n.e.) czytamy o Tatiusie zamordowanym μαγειρικαῖς σφαγίσι, rzeźniczymi sfagidami, podczas składania ofiary. Do zarzynania owiec przeznaczona była sfagida wymieniona przez Polyainosa (Polyaenus Rhetor, 2 wiek n.e., Strategemata 3.9.40). Wreszcie, fikcyjny epigram wotywny z Antologii Greckiej wymienia τὰν λαιμοτόμον σφαγίδα, podrzynającą gardło sfagidę, wśród narzędzi rzeźniczych złożonych w darze Hermesowi przez pewnego wyzwoleńca (Aristo, Anth. Graeca 6.306).</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            
            <div type="bibliography">
                <p>Beekes Robert, 2010, Etymological Dictionary of Greek, Leiden-Boston.</p>
                <p>Chantraine Pierre, 1968, Dictionnaire étymologique de la langue grecque, Paris.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
