<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>θυηπολέω</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher><ref target="https://site.unibo.it/lares/">LARES Project</ref></publisher>
                <date when="2021"/>
                <idno type="filename">lexicon_thyepoleo</idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digital document.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change when="2021-10-12" who="Irene Vagionakis">encoded document in XML</change>
                <change when="2016-03-07" who="Przemysław Biernat">created document contents</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="edition" xml:lang="it">
                <div type="textpart">
                    <p>θυηπολέω thyepoleo, v.: poet. compiere un sacrificio.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="textpart" n="Etimologia_e_morfologia">
                    <head>Etimologia e morfologia</head>
                    <p>Verbo composto dal soggetto sostantivo thue-, 'sacrificio', e dal soggetto verbale pole-, 'camminare'. Il sostantivo soggetto thue- è un derivato del verbo θύω e forma la base del sostantivo θύος, εος, n. "sacrificio" (Hom. Il. 6.270, Od. 15.261; Hes. Op. 338; A. Ag. 1409, Eu. 835). Il verbo πολέω "muoversi, essere da qualche parte" è deverbativum da ie. il soggetto *kwel-, "girare" (Beekes 2010: 1168-1169 s.v. πέλομαι, 1462-1463 s.v. τέλομαι). Nella semantica composta pole- gravita verso 'lottare per qualcosa, prendersi cura di qualcosa, occuparsi di qualcosa', cfr. πυρπολέω, 'prendersi cura del fuoco', αἰπόλος 'capraio'.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="textpart" n="Attestazioni">
                    <head>Attestazioni</head>
                    <p>Il verbo θ. ricorre principalmente nella poesia scritta in metro giambico (A. Ag. 262; E. Tr. 330, El. 665, 1134, Heracl. 401, S. fr. 47.9 Nauck = Strabone 10.3.14), per cui la sua struttura ilo-temporale lo predestina (questo è notato anche da Casabona, 1966: 121), ed è sinonimo di θύω. Nella prosa classica, θ. appare solo nello Stato di Platone (R. 364e), dove si riferisce a specialisti rituali itineranti che fanno sacrifici (θυηπολοῦσιν) secondo gli scritti di Musaeus e Orpheus. Si può supporre che Platone abbia preso l'espressione dal gergo degli stessi Orfei, mentre loro l'hanno trovata nei testi poetici a cui si riferivano.</p>
                    <p>Troviamo anche il verbo θ. nel testo dell'oracolo delfico, consegnato per giambo e trasmesso da Pausania (4.9.4), e su due iscrizioni. Il primo è IG XI.4 1299 del III secolo a.C., che contiene la storia dell'arrivo del culto di Sarapis a Delo (vedi Moyer 2008). La storia è trasmessa in parte in prosa e in parte in esametri, e troviamo il verbo di interesse nella parte metrica. La seconda iscrizione è IosPE I² 175 del II secolo d.C. da Olbia, indirizzata ad Apollo e commissionata dagli strateghi che finanziarono la rifinitura del tempio del dio. L'iscrizione termina con un distico elegiaco, in cui troviamo il verbo θ. Possiamo quindi supporre che il verbo θ., come il relativo → θυηπόλος, appartenesse al registro poetico e non fosse di natura tecnica.</p>
                    <p>Nella prosa post-classica il verbo θ. è usato da Dionigi di Alicarnasso (2.67) in riferimento ai doveri cultuali delle Vestali romane. Questo è certamente uno sforzo consapevole dell'autore, che si riferisce costantemente alle Vestali come θυηπόλοι (2.64, 2.65, 3.67).</p>
                </div>
                <div type="textpart" n="Occorrenze">
                    <head>Occorrenze</head>
                    <p>A. Ag. 262; E. Tr. 330; El. 665, 1134; Heracl. 401; S. fr. 47.9 Nauck = Strabo 10.3.14; S. fr. 126; Pl. R. 364e; D.H. 2.67; Paus. 4.9.4.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            
            <div type="edition" xml:lang="en">
                <div type="textpart">
                    <p>θυηπολέω thyepoleo, v.: poet. to perform a sacrifice.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="textpart" n="Etymology_and_morphology">
                    <head>Etymology and morphology</head>
                    <p>Verb composed of the noun subject thue-, 'sacrifice', and the verb subject pole-, 'to walk'. The noun subject thue- is a derivative from the verb θύω and forms the basis of the noun θύος, εος, n. "sacrifice" (Hom. Il. 6.270, Od. 15.261; Hes. Op. 338; A. Ag. 1409, Eu. 835). The verb πολέω "to move, to be somewhere" is deverbativum from ie. the subject *kwel-, "to turn" (Beekes 2010: 1168-1169 s.v. πέλομαι, 1462-1463 s.v. τέλομαι). In the compound semantics pole- gravitates towards 'to strive for something, take care of something, deal with something', cf. πυρπολέω, 'to take care of the fire', αἰπόλος 'goat herder'.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="textpart" n="Testimonies">
                    <head>Testimonies</head>
                    <p>The verb θ. occurs mainly in poetry written in iambic metre (A. Ag. 262; E. Tr. 330, El. 665, 1134, Heracl. 401, S. fr. 47.9 Nauck = Strabo 10.3.14), for which its ilo-temporal structure predestines it (this is also noted by Casabona, 1966: 121), and is synonymous with θύω. In classical prose, θ. appears only in Plato's State (R. 364e), where it refers to itinerant ritual specialists who make sacrifices (θυηπολοῦσιν) according to the writings of Musaeus and Orpheus. It can be assumed that Plato took the expression from the jargon of the Orpheotists themselves, while they found it in the poetic texts they referred to.</p>
                    <p>We also find the verb θ. in the text of the Delphic oracle, delivered by iamb and transmitted by Pausanias (4.9.4), and on two inscriptions. The first is IG XI.4 1299 from the 3rd century BC, containing the story of the bringing of the Sarapis cult to Delos (see Moyer 2008). The story is transmitted partly in prose and partly in hexameter, and we find the verb of interest in the metrical part. The second inscription is IosPE I² 175 from 2nd century AD from Olbia, addressed to Apollo and commissioned by the strategists who financed the finishing of the god's temple. The inscription ends with an elegiac distich, in which we find the verb θ. We may therefore assume that the verb θ., like the related → θυηπόλος, belonged to the poetic register and was not technical in nature.</p>
                    <p>In post-classical prose the verb θ. is used by Dionysius of Halicarnassus (2.67) in reference to the cultic duties of the Roman Vestals. This is certainly a conscious effort by the author, who consistently refers to the Vestalki as θυηπόλοι (2.64, 2.65, 3.67).</p>
                </div>
                <div type="textpart" n="Occurrences">
                    <head>Occurrences</head>
                    <p>A. Ag. 262; E. Tr. 330; El. 665, 1134; Heracl. 401; S. fr. 47.9 Nauck = Strabo 10.3.14; S. fr. 126; Pl. R. 364e; D.H. 2.67; Paus. 4.9.4.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            
            <div type="edition" xml:lang="pl">
                <div type="textpart">
                    <p>θυηπολέω thyepoleo, v.: poet. spełniać ofiarę.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="textpart" n="Etymologia_i_morfologia">
                    <head>Etymologia i morfologia</head>
                    <p>Czasownik złożony z rzeczownikowego tematu thue-, „ofiara”, i czasownikowego tematu pole-, „chodzić”. Rzeczownikowy temat thue- jest derywatem od czasownika θύω i stanowi podstawę rzeczownika θύος, εος, n. „ofiara” (Hom. Il. 6.270, Od. 15.261; Hes. Op. 338; A. Ag. 1409, Eu. 835). Czasownik πολέω „poruszać się, przebywać gdzieś” to deverbativum z ie. tematu *kwel-, „obracać” (Beekes 2010: 1168-1169 s.v. πέλομαι, 1462-1463 s.v. τέλομαι). W złożeniach semantyka pole- ciąży ku „starać się o coś, dbać o coś, zajmować się czymś”, por. πυρπολέω, „dbać o ogień”, αἰπόλος „pasterz kóz”.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="textpart" n="Poświadczenia">
                    <head>Poświadczenia</head>
                    <p>Czasownik θ. występuje głównie w poezji pisanej metrum jambicznym (A. Ag. 262; E. Tr. 330, El. 665, 1134, Heracl. 401, S. fr. 47.9 Nauck = Strabo 10.3.14), do której predestynuje go jego budowa iloczasowa (zauważa to również Casabona, 1966: 121), i jest synonimem θύω. W prozie klasycznej θ. pojawia się wyłącznie w Państwie Platona (R. 364e), gdzie mowa jest o wędrownych specjalistach rytualnych, którzy składają ofiary (θυηπολοῦσιν) podług pism Muzajosa i Orfeusza. Można przypuszczać, że Platon zaczerpnął to wyrażenie z żargonu samych orfeotelestów, oni natomiast znaleźli je w tekstach poetyckich, na które się powoływali.</p>
                    <p>Czasownik θ. odnajdujemy również w tekście wyroczni delfickiej, wygłoszonej jambem i przekazanej przez Pauzaniasza (4.9.4), oraz na dwóch inskrypcjach. Pierwszą jest IG XI,4 1299 z III wieku p.n.e., zawierająca opowieść o sprowadzeniu kultu Sarapisa na Delos (zob. Moyer 2008). Opowieść przekazana jest częściowo prozą a częściowo heksametrem, a interesujący nas czasownik odnajdujemy w części metrycznej. Druga inskrypcja to IosPE I² 175 z II w. n.e. z Olbii, skierowana do Apollona i zlecona przez strategów, którzy sfinansowali wykończenie świątyni boga. Inskrypcja kończy się dystychem elegijnym, w którym odnajdujemy czasownik θ. Można więc przypuszczać, że czasownik θ., podobnie jak pokrewne → θυηπόλος, należał do rejestru poetyckiego i nie miał charakteru technicznego.</p>
                    <p>W prozie poklasycznej czasownikiem θ. posługuje się Dionizjusz z Halikarnasu (2.67) w odniesieniu do obowiązków kultowych rzymskich Westalek. Jest to z pewnością świadomy zabieg autora, który konsekwentnie określa Westalki mianem θυηπόλοι (2.64, 2.65, 3.67).</p>
                </div>
                <div type="textpart" n="Wystąpienia">
                    <head>Wystąpienia</head>
                    <p>A. Ag. 262; E. Tr. 330, El. 665, 1134, Heracl. 401; S. fr. 47.9 Nauck = Strabo 10.3.14; S. fr. 126; Pl. R. 364e; D.H. 2.67; Paus. 4.9.4.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            
            <div type="bibliography">
                <p>Beekes, Robert (2010). Etymological Dictionary of Greek. Leiden-Boston.</p>
                <p>Casabona, J. (1966). Recherches sur le vocabulaire des sacrifices en grec, des origines à la fin de l'époque classique. Aix-en-Provence.</p>
                <p>Moyer, Ian S. (2008). Notes on Re-Reading the Delian Aretalogy of Sarapis (“IG” XI.4 1299). Zeitschrift für Papyrologie und Epigraphik 166: 101-107.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>