<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>μηρία</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher><ref target="https://site.unibo.it/lares/">LARES Project</ref></publisher>
                <date when="2021"/>
                <idno type="filename">lexicon_meria</idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>"Animal Sacrifice in Ancient Greece" database (<ref>http://www.sacrificium.filg.uj.edu.pl</ref>).</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change when="2022-02-03" who="Irene Vagionakis">encoded in XML</change>
                <change when="2015-03-31" who="Lech Trzcionkowski">written contents</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="edition" xml:lang="it">
                <div type="textpart">
                    <p><w>μηρία</w> mēría, subst. n., plurale tantum, femur, femora (l.poj. femur).</p>
                </div>
                <div type="textpart" n="Etimologia">
                    <head>Etimologia</head>
                    <p>Aggettivo utilitaristico μηρία "femore, femore"  (&lt; „udowe”, domyśl. ὄστεα „kości”) pochodzi od rzeczownika μηρός, „udo” (Risch 1974, 115); używany w l. mn. w technicznym znaczeniu „kości udowe bydlęce, owcze lub kozie” zawinięte w tłustą błonę otrzewnej (<w>κνῖσα</w>, rzadziej: <w>δημός</w>, <w>ἐπιπόλαιον</w>, <w>πιμελή</w>), a następnie spalane na ołtarzu. W eposie homeryckim synonim rzeczownika zbiorczego μῆρα (→ <ref corresp="lexicon_mera.html"><w>μῆρα</w></ref>), w późniejszych tekstach niemal całkowicie go zastąpił (Chantraine 1999 [1968], 697). Zob. również → <ref corresp="lexicon_meros.html"><w>μηροί</w></ref></p>
                </div>
                <div type="textpart" n="Testimonianze">
                    <head>Testimonianze</head>
                    <p>Il verbo μηρία appare nel contesto di attività che comprendono tre fasi successive del processo rituale: (1) la preparazione della parte dell'animale sacrificale destinata agli dei, cioè (1a) il taglio delle zampe e la spuntatura della μηρία ἐκτάμνω/ἐκτέμνω, 'taglio, taglio, taglio', cfr. Meuli, 1946, 216-7), (1b) "nascondere" la μηρία avvolgendola bilateralmente con una membrana grassa peritoneale ([κνίσῃ] κατακαλύπτω, "copro (di grasso)", e (1c) mettere su di loro pezzi di carne cruda di altre parti dell'animale (ἐπ᾽ αὐτῶν ὠμοθετέω, "su di loro (cioè gambe) depongo i pezzi di carne"); (2) la deposizione della porzione destinata agli dei sull'altare: ἐπιτίθημι, "dispongo, depongo su (l'altare predefinito.)"; (3) bruciare: καίω, "brucio, brucio", δαύω, "brucio". A questo bisogna aggiungere i riferimenti a (4) l'uso delle ceneri risultanti dalle ossa bruciate.</p>
                    <p>1. La preparazione della parte destinata agli dei.
                        Nell'epica omerica, l'espressione ἐκ μηρία τάμνον ("tagliarono i femori", con la tesi Od. 3.456) appare in una descrizione dettagliata del sacrificio fatto da Nestore ad Atena (Od. 3. 456b-457): ἄφαρ δ᾽ ἐκ μηρία τάμνον / πάντα κατὰ μοῖραν, κατά τε κνίσῃ ἐκάλυψαν ("quando tagliarono i femori, tutti come dovevano essere, e li nascosero nel grasso del peritoneo"), che è una variante di una versione più comune della descrizione della procedura di preparazione delle cosce (μηρούς) per il rogo (Il. 1.464-5 = Il. 2.427-8 = Od. 12. 364-5): μηρούς τ᾽ ἐξέταμον κατά τε κνίσῃ ἐκάλυψαν / δίπτυχα ποιήσαντες, ἐπ᾽ αὐτῶν δ᾽ ὠμοθέτησαν, "tagliarono le zampe posteriori e le nascosero nel grasso del peritoneo, / doppiamente avvolte, e vi misero sopra delle guarnizioni crude". Nelle menzioni di sacrifici inserite negli enunciati dei personaggi, l'avvolgimento di μηρία con il grasso è metonimicamente segnalato dagli aggettivi πίων 'grasso' (7x nell'epica omerica), ἀγλαά "lucido" (Hes. Op.337), il sostantivo δημός "grasso" (2x) o l'espressione καλύψας πίονι δημῷ (1x).</p>
                    <p>Nella Stanza di Aristofane (Pax 1025) si raccomanda di tagliare i femori dopo il sacrificio, cioè dopo la macellazione rituale dell'animale nella skene, e di portarli all'orchestra: θύσας τὰ μηρὶ᾽ ἐξελὼν δευρ᾽ ἔκφερε. La parola μηρία appare probabilmente in un frammento della commedia Semele Eubulos (fr. 94 Kassel-Austin = fr. 95 Kock, testo corrotto, crux philologorum), dove Dioniso si lamenta della composizione delle parti dell'animale sacrificale destinate agli dei: πρῶτον μὲν ὅταν ἐμοί τι θύωσίν τινες, / αἷμα, κύστιν, ἧπαρ, καρδίαν, / ὑμέν᾽ ἐπιπόλαιον- οὐδ᾽ ἐγὼ γὰρ ἐσθίω / γλυκεῖαν οὐδὲ μηρία. "Prima, quando mi danno qualche offerta, / È solo sangue e vescica, cuore, fegato anche, / E la sottile membrana esterna, ma io non mangio, / Né fiele né osso dell'anca presi dopo tutto. / (...) e la parte superiore dell'anca (traduzione di Janina Niemirska-Pliszczyńska).</p>
                        <p>2. La disposizione della parte destinata agli dei sull'altare.</p>
                        <p>Il composto fraseologico μηρία + <w>ἐπιτίθημι</w>, 'deporre (sull'altare) una gamba' = 'offrire un sacrificio animale' nell'epica appare nei comandi per preparare il sacrificio (Od. 21.267: ὄφρ᾽ ἐπὶ μηρία θέντες Ἀπόλλωνι, dice Alkinoos, cfr. A.Rh.  2.691: δὴ τότε οἱ κεραῶν ἐπὶ μηρία θήσομεν αἰγῶν "sacrificiamo per lui i capri cornuti". Cfr. la menzione di sacrifici compiuti (Nestore, Od. 3.178-9: Ποσειδάωνι δὲ ταύρων / πόλλ᾽ ἐπὶ μῆρ᾽ ἔθεμεν). Nelle iscrizioni μηρία è talvolta sostituita da altre espressioni, vedi LSAM 24 (380/360 a.C. circa), Erythraj, l.33-34: ὅταν τὴν ἱρὴν μοῖραν ἐπιθῆι. La gamba distesa sull'altare come sfondo alla morte violenta che minaccia il sacrificatore appare nel passo di Euripide (E.Fr. 143 = Ar. Th. 694) citato da Aristofane: ἐπὶ τῶν μηρίων.</p>
                        <p>3. l'incendio della parte dedicata agli dei.</p>
                        <p>Nell'epica, il sostantivo μηρία ricorre più spesso in congiunzione con il verbo "bruciare" καίω e i suoi derivati. Nei sacrifici rappresentati dal narratore principale, il rogo delle gambe è un elemento centrale della scena di un tipico banchetto sacrificale (vedi Corpus, Homer, Introduzione). Nella formula omerica καῖε δ᾽ ἐπὶ σχίζῃς ὁ γέρων, ἐπὶ δ᾽ αἴθοπα οἶνον / λεῖβε "allora il vecchio bruciò sui ceppi, versò il vino frizzante sul vino (Il. 1.462-463 = Od. 3.459-460) il complemento predefinito è una gamba avvolta nel grasso con pezzi di carne cruda sopra. In una variante di questo esametro καὶ τὰ μὲν ἂρ σχίζῃσιν ἀφύλλοισιν κατέκαιον "e li bruciò su ceppi senza foglie (Il. 2.425) il pronome τὰ indica direttamente le gambe, cfr. A.Rh. 1.434-5: τά γε πάντα (...) καῖον ἐπὶ σχίζῃσιν.</p>
                        <p>Il ruolo chiave del bruciare i femori e dell'assaggiare le interiora è indicato dall'esametro formale, che riassume la descrizione del processo rituale con le parole: εὖθ᾽ οἱ σπλάγχνα πάσαντο, θεῷ δ᾽ ἐπὶ μηρί᾽ ἔκηαν "quando ebbero assaggiato le interiora, e bruciato i femori al dio" (Od. 3.9), cfr. la sua forma standard: αὐτὰρ ἐπεὶ κατὰ μῆρ᾽ ἐκάη καὶ σπλάγχνα πάσαντο "dopo aver bruciato le ossa della coscia e assaggiato le interiora" (4x: Il. 1, 464=Il. 2, 427=Od. 3, 461=Od. 12,364).</p>
                        
                    <p>Al di là delle scene tipiche, l'espressione καίω + μηρία nell'epica omerica è usata come metonimia per i sacrifici menzionati dal narratore principale (aojda) o nelle dichiarazioni dei personaggi. Il narratore principale lo usa in due luoghi: quando menziona i sacrifici fatti da Autolykos per Hermes (Od. 19.397-398: τῷ γὰρ κεχαρισμένα μηρία καῖεν / ἀρνῶν ἠδ᾽ ἐρίφων) e quando presenta i pensieri di Tespi su come salvare la sua vita durante il massacro dei pretendenti (Od. 22.334-336: ἢ ἐκδὺς μεγάροιο Διὸς μεγάλου ποτὶ βωμὸν (...) / ἔνθ᾽ ἄρα πολλὰ / Λαέρτης Ὀδυσεύς τε βοῶν ἐπὶ μηρί᾽ ἔκηαν). Nel primo caso, si tratta di offerte "gentili (κεχαρισμένα)", che sono legate al favore speciale di Hermes per un adoratore dotato dal dio di qualità speciali; nel secondo, fa parte della descrizione dell'altare di Zeus, il protettore della casa, e sottolinea il legame di Odisseo come sacrificatore zelante con un luogo dove il supplicante può cercare protezione dalla sua ira.</p>
                    <p>Nei discorsi dei personaggi, il bruciare le gambe per il dio è un elemento tipico della preghiera, e il suo ricordo legato a una richiesta a un essere soprannaturale crea un rapporto di reciprocità. Le preghiere possono ricordare i sacrifici che essi stessi hanno fatto una volta:</p>
                    <p>Il. 1.40-41 (Crisi): ἢ εἰ δή ποτέ τοι κατὰ πίονα μηρί᾽ ἔκηα / ταύρων ἠδ᾽ αἰγῶν, "se ti ho bruciato quando ho bruciato le gambe grasse / di tori e capre"; Il. 8. 240 (Agamennone): ἀλλ᾽ ἐπὶ πᾶσι βοῶν δημὸν καὶ μηρί᾽ ἔκηα, "ma su tutti (gli altari) ho bruciato il grasso e le gambe posteriori"; Il. 15. 373-374 (Agamennone): ἢ βοὸς ἢ οἰὸς κατὰ πίονα μηρία καίων / εὔχετο νοστῆσαι, "(se io) pregassi per il ritorno bruciando le gambe grasse di un bue o di una pecora". Se invece chi prega è una figura che occupa una posizione sociale inferiore (Eumaios, Penelope), invoca i sacrifici fatti in passato dall'ospite legittimo, Odisseo:</p>
                    <p>Da. 17.240-242 (Eumajos): Νύμφαι κρηναῖαι, κοῦραι Διός, εἴ ποτ᾽ Ὀδυσσεὺς / ὔμμ᾽ ἐπὶ μηρί᾽ ἔκηε, καλύψας πίονι δημῷ, / ἀρνῶν ἠδ᾽ ἐρίφων, τόδε μοι κρηήνατ᾽ ἐέλδωρ; Od. 4.763-765 (Penelope): εἴ ποτέ τοι πολύμητις ἐνὶ μεγάροισιν Ὀδυσσεὺς / ἢ βοὸς ἢ ὄϊος κατὰ πίονα μηρία κῆε, / τῶν νῦν μοι μνῆσαι καί μοι φίλον υἷα σάωσον. Caratteristicamente, in tutti i casi le zampe posteriori bruciate sono indicate come grasso (πίονα μηρία, Il. 1.40; 11.773; 15.373; Od. 4.764) o, nel caso della preghiera di Eumaios, si sottolinea il fatto che sono nascoste nel grasso (καλύψας πίονι δημῷ, Od. 17.241).</p>
                    <p>In diversi punti i personaggi menzionano nelle loro storie le zampe posteriori bruciate da uno qualsiasi degli eroi in passato. Due volte è detto da Nestore, che, come il più vecchio degli eroi venuti a Troia, è il portatore della memoria storica della generazione che ha combattuto nella guerra di Troia. In Il. 11.772-773 cita il sacrificio fatto da Peleo quando Nestore arrivò in Ftia prima della guerra di Troia (γέρων δ᾽ ἱππηλάτα Πηλεὺς / πίονα μηρία καῖε βοὸς Διὶ τερπικεραύνῳ). Questo si riferisce a una versione della tipica scena "festa sacrificale + arrivo degli ospiti" adattata al formato del discorso degli eroi. Al contrario, in Od. 3.273 Nestore parla di Ajgistos, sottolineando la futilità dei suoi sacrifici (πολλὰ δὲ μηρί᾽ ἔκηε θεῶν ἱεροῖσ᾽ ἐπὶ βωμοῖς). Nel 24° canto dell'Iliade, gli dei menzionano due volte la gamba bruciata da Ettore (Il. 24.33-34; Apollon: οὔ νύ ποθ᾽ ὑμῖν / Ἕκτωρ μηρί᾽ ἔκηε βοῶν αἰγῶν τε τελείων; Il. 24.170-3; Zeus: (Ἕκτωρ) ὅς μοι πολλὰ βοῶν ἐπὶ μηρί᾽ ἔκηεν / Ἴδης ἐν κορυφῇσι πολυπτύχου, ἄλλοτε δ᾽ αὖτε / ἐν πόλει ἀκροτάτῃ). Infine, quando Odisseo racconta delle zampe posteriori da lui bruciate in sacrificio durante le sue peregrinazioni, usa la frase, ῥέξας μηρί᾽ ἔκαιον (Od. 9.550 ἀρνειὸν (...) /- τὸν δ᾽ ἐπὶ θινὶ / Ζηνὶ κελαινεφέϊ Κρονίδῃ, ὃς πᾶσιν ἀνάσσει, / ῥέξας μηρί᾽ ἔκαιον- ὁ δ᾽ οὐκ ἐμπάζετο ἱρῶν).</p>
                    <p>La bruciatura delle gambe come metonimia del sacrificio ricorre anche in altri generi poetici: nell'elegia (Thgn. 1145: che preghi gli dei e offra sacrifici (...) bruciando zampe posteriori splendenti, εὐχέσθω δὲ θεοῖσι, καὶ ἀγλαὰ μηρία καίων (...) θυέτω), nel paean Bakchylides (B. 1. 66: ἐπὶ βω[μῶν] [θεοῖσιν αἴθε]σθαι βο[ῶν ξανθᾷ φλογί] [[μηρί᾽ εὐ]μάλ]λων τε [μήλων] "sugli altari / nel fuoco luminoso agli dei posati / bruciano le gambe dei buoi e delle pecore lanose (traduzione di J. Danielewicz)". Nel testo: Call. frg.2a: μνῆσαι δ᾽, εἴ κοτέ τοι μηρία καλὰ βοῶν.</p>
                    <p>Aristofane negli Uccelli adotta un'ottica invertita, il sacrificio visto dall'alto; sposta l'accento dal processo di combustione al suo risultato, il fumo 'oleoso' che sale al cielo (Ar. Av. 193): διὰ τῆς πόλεως ... τὴν κνῖσαν οὐ διαφρήσετε "dalle cerve bruciate non farai scorrere il fumo nella tua città (traduzione di J. Ławińska-Tyszkowska)", cfr. 1517-8 ("né il fumo delle cerve bruciate / scorrerà fino a noi", οὐδὲ κνῖσα μηρίων ἄπο / ανῆλθεν). La frase τῶν μηρίων τὴν κνῖσαν, per inversione, trova la sua controparte in κεκίς μηρίων nell'Antigone di Sofocle.</p>
                    <p>In epoca classica, appaiono le prime testimonianze di pratiche mantiche che accompagnano la combustione, e di conseguenza descrizioni dettagliate delle anomalie del processo di combustione della parte dedicata agli dei. I cattivi presagi sono descritti in dettaglio da Tiresia nell'Antigone di Sofocle (S.Ant. 1005-1020): ἀλλ᾽ ἐπὶ σποδῷ μυδῶσα κηκὶς μηρίων ἐτήκετο κἄτυφε κἀνέπτυε, καὶ μετάρσιοι χολαὶ διεσπείροντο, καὶ καταρρυεῖς μηροὶ καλυπτῆς ἐξέκειντο πιμελῆς, "ma sulla cenere il liquido filtrante e ribollente delle ossa sacrificali si scioglieva e fumava e sfrigolava, e gocce di bile schizzavano in alto, e le gambe viscide cadevano dal grasso che le ricopriva".</p>
                    <p>Nelle iscrizioni dei periodi arcaico e classico la parola appare raramente. Lo stato di conservazione di un'iscrizione che regola le norme rituali del culto di Eracle a Mileto (LSAM 42, Mileto, 500 a.C. circa) non permette di determinare il contesto della parola, ma il verbo παρατίθημι può suggerire che si è incaricati di mettere qualcosa accanto o davanti alle gambe posteriori (]ὰ τοῖσι μηρίοισ[ι | πα]ρατιθέναι- ἔρ̣δεν ο-).</p>
                    <p>Nella prosa successiva, la combustione delle zampe posteriori è menzionata dagli autori quando si tratta di un sacrificio insolito, come il sacrificio di un cervo sacrificato a Megalopoli: καὶ τά τε μηρία ἐκτεμόντες καίουσι καὶ δὴ καὶ ἀναλίσκουσιν αὐτόθι τοῦ ἱερείου τὰ κρέα, "dopo aver tagliato i femori, li bruciano e mangiano la carne dell'animale sacrificale nel recinto sacro stesso (Paus. 8.38.8)".</p>
                    <p>4. L'uso della cenere della μηρία bruciata.</p>
                    <p>Le ceneri della μηρία bruciata venivano talvolta raccolte in luoghi speciali: sull'heroon (Hdt 4. 35: καὶ τῶν μηρίων καταγιζομένων ἐπὶ τῷ βωμῷ τὴν σποδὸν ταύτην ἐπὶ τὴν θήκην τὴν Ὤπιός τε καὶ Ἄργης ἀναισιμοῦσθαι ἐπιβαλλομένην, "le ceneri delle gambe bruciate sull'altare servono a cospargere la tomba di Opis e Argi"). </p>
                </div>
                <div type="textpart" n="Catalogo_delle_occorrenze">
                    <head>Catalogo delle occorrenze</head>
                        <p>1) Verbo. + μηρία:</p>
                        <p>ἐκτάμνω + μηρία, "tagliare": Od. 3.456; Paus. 8.38.8</p>
                        <p>ἐξαιρέω + μηρία, "portare fuori": A. Pax 1021</p>
                        <p>ἐπιτίθημι + μηρία, "deporre (sull'altare)": Od. 21.267; Ap. Rhod. 2.691; cfr. ἐπὶ τῶν μηρίων E. fr. 143 = A.Th. 694</p>
                        <p>καίω + μηρία, "bruciare": Il. 1.40; 8.240; 11.773; 22.34; Od. 3.273; 9.553; 19.366; 19.397; 22.336; Hes. Op. 337; Thgn. 1.1145; default. [μηρία], Il. 1.462 = Od. 3.459; Il. 2.425; A.Rh. 1.435; Paus. 8.38.8</p>
                        <p>ἐπικαίω + μηρία, "bruciare": Od. 3.9; Od. 17.241;</p>
                        <p>κατακαίω + μηρία, "bruciare":  Il. 1.40; Il. 15.373; Il. 22.170; Od. 4,764; [Call. Eleg. 2a]; default. Il. 2.425</p>
                        <p>δαύω + μηρία, "bruciare": Sem. 30 (μηρίων δεδαυμένων)</p>
                        <p>2) Aggettivo + μηρία</p>
                        <p>Nell'epica, il sostantivo μηρία ricorre con le appendici:</p>
                        <p>πίονα 'grasso': Hom. Il. 1.40; Il. 15.373; Il. 11.773; Od. 4.764</p>
                        <p>ἀγλαὰ 'splendente': Hes. Op. 337; Thgn. 1.1145</p>
                        <p>πολλὰ 'numerosi, plurali': Hom. Od. 3.273; 24.170</p>
                        <p>κεχαρισμένα "piacevole": Hom. Od. 19.397)</p>
                        <p>ἱερὰ 'santo': A.Rh. 1.433.</p>
                        <p>Sembra che πίονα sia usato principalmente nelle preghiere come metonimia che indica il processo rituale di preparazione della porzione destinata agli dei.</p>
                        <p>3) μηρία + SubstGEN</p>
                        <p>I nomi degli animali sacrificali appaiono come complementi: ἢ βοὸς ἢ ὄϊος (Il. 15.373: per Zeus; Od. 4. 763: per Zeus), ταύρων ἠδ᾽ αἰγῶν (Il. 1.41; per Apollon), ταύρων (Od. 3.178, per Poseidone); βοῶν (Il. 8.240; per Zeus; Il.24 .170; per Zeus, Od. 22.336; per Zeus Herkeios), βοῶν αἰγῶν τε (Il. 24.34; le offerte di Ettore agli dei, dice Apollon), ἀρνῶν ἠδ᾽ ἐρίφων (Od. 17.242; per Ninfe, Od. 19.397, per Hermes).</p>
                        <p>animale sacrificale - destinatario del sacrificio</p>
                        <p>ταύρων - Poseidon</p>
                        <p>ταύρων ἠδ᾽ αἰγῶν - Apollon</p>
                        <p>βοῶν - Zeus (3x)</p>
                        <p>βοῶν αἰγῶν τε - dei (dice Apollon)</p>
                        <p>ἢ βοὸς ἢ ὄϊος - Zeus (2x)</p>
                        <p>ἀρνῶν ἠδ᾽ ἐρίφων - Ninfe (1x), Hermes (1x)</p>
                        <p>Sembra che la scelta degli animali sacrificali non sia casuale. Poseidone e Apollo ricevono tori non castrati (ταύροι), Zeus - buoi (βοῦς) e pecore (οἶς), Ninfe ed Hermes, divinità strettamente correlate - "agnelli e capretti" (ἀρνῶν ἠδ᾽ ἐρίφων); vale la pena notare che quando Apollon appare nel contesto, appaiono anche le capre, αἰγῶν. Cfr. A.Rh. 2.697: κεραῶν ἐπὶ μηρία θήσομεν αἰγῶν. Nessun maiale appare nella frase μηρία + SubstGEN.</p>
                        <p>4) μηρία καίειν + ἐπί Substdat. loc. o ἐν Substdat. loc.</p>
                        <p>Nell'epica la frase può verificarsi con la circostanza di luogo "sull'altare": Od. 3.273: ἱεροῖσ᾽ ἐπὶ βωμοῖς; Il. 8.240: ἐπὶ πᾶσι (scil. βωμοῖς); oppure "sulla riva (del mare)". Od. 9.550: ἐπὶ θινὶ.</p>
                        <p>Il. 24.170-3: Ἴδης ἐν κορυφῇσι πολυπτύχου, (...) ἐν πόλει ἀκροτάτῃ; Od. 4.763-765: ἐνὶ μεγάροισιν.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="textpart" n="Discussione/Interpretazione">
                    <head>Discussione/Interpretazione</head>
                    <p>Si è discusso a lungo se la parola μηρία significhi "gamba", cioè "femore con i muscoli circostanti", o "osso della coscia, femore". In un articolo di riferimento di Karl Meuli, ha dimostrato che il secondo significato è corretto (Meuli 1946, bibliografia precedente, ibid., p. 215, nota 6; cfr. Detienne, Vernant 1979, Detienne 1998, pp. 70-2, van Straten 1995; Ekroth 2007, 2009, 2013). Più recentemente, Guy Berthiaume ha suggerito che sacrificare ossa pulite o ossa con carne non era la norma assoluta, ma dipendeva dalle circostanze e dalla decisione del sacrificatore (Berthiaume 2005), ma le fonti citate a sostegno di questa tesi non sono convincenti (Ekroth 2009, 127-8). Esiodo, nella Teogonia, giustifica l'usanza di bruciare μηρία, mēría sugli altari con il mito dell'inganno a cui Prometeo ricorse durante la separazione finale di dei e uomini (ἐκ τοῦ δ᾽ ἀθανάτοισιν ἐπὶ χθονὶ φῦλ᾽ ἀναθρώπων / καίουσ᾽ ὀστέα λευκὰ θυηέντων ἐπὶ βωμῶν, → cf. commento a Esiodo, Teogonia, 535-558). L'espressione ὀστέα λευκὰ qui è l'equivalente funzionale di μηρία, il che potrebbe suggerire che i femori puliti dalla carne venivano bruciati sull'altare o che erano l'ingrediente più importante della porzione dedicata agli dei, da cui l'uso metonimico. Anche se l'epica primitiva non usa la parola 'sacrificio', l'epiteto che descrive gli altari in combinazione con ὀστέα λευκὰ καίειν, 'bruciare le ossa bianche' cattura l'essenza del rituale sacrificale: esso comporta la produzione di fumo durante la combustione dei femori, un segnale visibile inviato dal popolo come segno di riverenza all'interno di una relazione reciproca (Parker 1998; 2011).</p>
                    <p>L'interpretazione del sostantivo μηρία come termine tecnico che denota femori puliti dalla carne è confermato dalla tradizione lessicografica. Esichio lo definisce τὰ ἐκ τῶν μηρῶν ἐξαιρούμενα ὀστᾶ "ossa tagliate dalle cosce (s.v. μηρία), cfr. l'uso del verbo in Ar. Pax 1021). Allo stesso modo in Apollon. Lex. s.v. μηρία- οὐχ ὡς ἡμεῖς, ἀλλὰ τὰ ἐκ τῶν μηριῶν ἐξαιρούμενα καὶ ἱεροθυτούμενα ὀστᾶ "diverso dal nostro uso, significa ossa tagliate dalle gambe e offerte agli dei". Considerando che Etym. M. (p. 585, 22) spiega: μηρία- τὰ μηριαῖα ὀστᾶ "ossa del femore" (Meuli 1946, 216).</p>
                    <p>Nell'epica omerica, l'atto di bruciare la μηρία sull'altare è una metonimia del sacrificio di sangue, soprattutto negli enunciati dei personaggi che ricordano i sacrifici passati o prefigurano quelli futuri. Si tratta di azioni compiute che, se gradite al dio, conquistano la sua benevolenza, charis. Una connessione diretta tra il concetto di charis e le gambe bruciate sugli altari si trova in Od. 19.397 (κεχαρισμένα μηρία). Non è un semplice scambio basato sul principio del do ut des, ma un rapporto fisso di reciprocità, una reciprocità generalizzata (sulla charis: Parker 2011; Loew, 1908; Latacz 1967, pp. 78-98; Moussy 1966, 411-415).</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            
            <div type="edition" xml:lang="en">
                <div type="textpart">
                    <p>μηρία mēría, subst. n., plurale tantum, femur, femora (l.sing. femur).</p>
                </div>
                <div type="textpart" n="Etymology">
                    <head>Etymology</head>
                    <p>The participial adjective μηρία "femur, thighbone" (&lt; "thigh", default. ὄστεα "bones") comes from the noun μηρός, "thigh" (Risch 1974, 115); used in the plural in the technical sense of "thigh bones of cattle, sheep or goats" wrapped in a fatty peritoneal membrane (κνῖσα, less commonly: δημός, ἐπιπόλαιον, πιμελή) and then burned on an altar. In the Homeric epic a synonym for the collective noun μῆρα (→ <ref corresp="lexicon_mera.html">μῆρα</ref>), in later texts it has almost completely replaced it (Chantraine 1999 [1968], 697). See also → <ref corresp="lexicon_meros.html">μηροί</ref>.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="textpart" n="Testimonies">
                    <head>Testimonies</head>
                        <p>The verb μηρία appears in the context of activities comprising three successive phases of the ritual process: (1) the preparation of the part of the sacrificial animal destined for the gods, i.e. (1a) the cutting off of the legs and the trimming of the μηρία ἐκτάμνω/ἐκτέμνω, 'I cut off, I cut out, I trim', cf. Meuli, 1946, 216-7), (1b) 'hiding' the μηρία by wrapping them bilaterally with a fatty peritoneal membrane ([κνίσῃ] κατακαλύπτω, 'I cover (with fat)', and (1c) placing raw pieces of meat from other parts of the animal on them (ἐπ᾽ αὐτῶν ὠμοθετέω, 'on them (i.e. legs) I lay the pieces of meat"); (2) the laying of the portion destined for the gods on the altar: ἐπιτίθημι, 'I arrange, lay on (the default. altar)'; (3) burning: καίω, 'I burn, I burn', δαύω, 'I burn'. To this should be added references to (4) the use of the ashes resulting from the burnt bones.</p>
                        <p>1. The preparation of the part destined for the gods.</p>
                            <p>In the Homeric epic, the expression ἐκ μηρία τάμνον ("they cut out the femurs", with the thesis Od. 3.456) appears in a detailed description of the sacrifice made by Nestor to Athena (Od. 3. 456b-457): ἄφαρ δ᾽ ἐκ μηρία τάμνον / πάντα κατὰ μοῖραν, κατά τε κνίσῃ ἐκάλυψαν ('when they cut out the femurs, all as they should be, and hid them in the fat of the peritoneum'), which is a variant of a more common version of the description of the procedure for preparing the thighs (μηρούς) for burning (Il. 1.464-5 = Il. 2.427-8 = Od. 12. 364-5): μηρούς τ᾽ ἐξέταμον κατά τε κνίσῃ ἐκάλυψαν / δίπτυχα ποιήσαντες, ἐπ᾽ αὐτῶν δ᾽ ὠμοθέτησαν, 'they cut out the hind legs and hid them in the fat of the peritoneum, / doubly wrapped, and laid raw trimmings on them'. In the mentions of sacrifices embedded in the characters' utterances, the wrapping of μηρία with fat is metonymically signalled by the adjectives πίων 'fat' (7x in the Homeric epic), ἀγλαά "shiny" (Hes. Op.337), the noun δημός "fat" (2x) or the expression καλύψας πίονι δημῷ (1x).</p>
                        <p>In the Room of Aristophanes (Pax 1025) it is recommended that the femurs be cut out after the sacrifice, i.e. after the ritual slaughter of the animal in the skene, and brought to the orchestra: θύσας τὰ μηρὶ᾽ ἐξελὼν δευρ᾽ ἔκφερε. The word μηρία probably appears in a fragment of Eubulos' comedy Semele Eubulos (fr. 94 Kassel-Austin = fr. 95 Kock, corrupted text, crux philologorum), where Dionysus complains about the composition of the parts of the sacrificial animal intended for the gods: πρῶτον μὲν ὅταν ἐμοί τι θύωσίν τινες, / αἷμα, κύστιν, ἧπαρ, καρδίαν, / ὑμέν᾽ ἐπιπόλαιον- οὐδ᾽ ἐγὼ γὰρ ἐσθίω / γλυκεῖαν οὐδὲ μηρία. "First, when any offerings they give me, / It is only blood and bladder, heart, liver also, / And the thin outer membrane, but I eat not, / Neither gall nor bone from the hip taken after all. / (...) and the upper part of the hip (translated by Janina Niemirska-Pliszczyńska).</p>
                            <p>2. Arranging the part destined for the gods on the altar.</p>
                    <p>The phraseological compound μηρία + ἐπιτίθημι, 'to lay (on the altar) a leg' = 'to offer an animal sacrifice' in the epic appears in the commands to prepare the sacrifice (Od. 21.267: ὄφρ᾽ ἐπὶ μηρία θέντες Ἀπόλλωνι, says Alkinoos, cf. A.Rh.  2.691: δὴ τότε οἱ κεραῶν ἐπὶ μηρία θήσομεν αἰγῶν 'let us sacrifice the horned goats' for him. Cf. the mention of fulfilled sacrifices (Nestor, Od. 3.178-9: Ποσειδάωνι δὲ ταύρων / πόλλ᾽ ἐπὶ μῆρ᾽ ἔθεμεν). In the inscriptions μηρία is sometimes replaced by other expressions, see LSAM 24 (c.380/360 BC), Erythraj, l.33-34: ὅταν τὴν ἱρὴν μοῖραν ἐπιθῆι. The leg lying on the altar as a backdrop to the violent death threatening the sacrificer appears in the passage by Euripides (E.Fr. 143 = Ar. Th. 694) cited by Aristophanes: ἐπὶ τῶν μηρίων.</p>
                    <p>3. the burning of the part dedicated to the gods.</p>
                    <p>In the epic, the noun μηρία occurs most often in conjunction with the verb 'to burn' καίω and its derivatives. In the sacrifices depicted by the main narrator, the burning of the legs is a central element of the scene of a typical sacrificial feast (see Corpus, Homer, Introduction). In the Homeric formula καῖε δ᾽ ἐπὶ σχίζῃς ὁ γέρων, ἐπὶ δ᾽ αἴθοπα οἶνον / λεῖβε 'then the old man burned on stumps, poured sparkling wine over the wine' (Il. 1.462-463 = Od. 3.459-460) the default complement is a fat-wrapped leg with pieces of raw meat on top. In a variant of this hexameter καὶ τὰ μὲν ἂρ σχίζῃσιν ἀφύλλοισιν κατέκαιον 'and burned them on leafless stumps' (Il. 2.425) the pronoun τὰ points directly to the legs, cf. A.Rh. 1.434-5: τά γε πάντα (...) καῖον ἐπὶ σχίζῃσιν.</p>
                    <p>The key role of burning the femurs and tasting the entrails is indicated by the formal hexameter, which sums up the description of the ritual process with the words: εὖθ᾽ οἱ σπλάγχνα πάσαντο, θεῷ δ᾽ ἐπὶ μηρί᾽ ἔκηαν "when they had tasted the entrails, and burned the femurs to the god" (Od. 3.9), cf. its standard form: αὐτὰρ ἐπεὶ κατὰ μῆρ᾽ ἐκάη καὶ σπλάγχνα πάσαντο "when they had burnt the thigh-bones and tasted the entrails" (4x: Il. 1, 464=Il. 2, 427=Od. 3, 461=Od. 12,364).</p>
                    <p>Beyond the typical scenes, the expression καίω + μηρία in the Homeric epic is used as a metonymy for the victims mentioned by the main narrator (aojda) or in the statements of the characters. The main narrator uses it in two places: when mentioning the sacrifices made by Autolykos for Hermes (Od. 19.397-398: τῷ γὰρ κεχαρισμένα μηρία καῖεν / ἀρνῶν ἠδ᾽ ἐρίφων) and when presenting the thoughts of Thespis considering how to save his life during the slaughter of the suitors (Od. 22.334-336: ἢ ἐκδὺς μεγάροιο Διὸς μεγάλου ποτὶ βωμὸν (...) / ἔνθ᾽ ἄρα πολλὰ / Λαέρτης Ὀδυσεύς τε βοῶν ἐπὶ μηρί᾽ ἔκηαν). In the former case, it is about "kind (κεχαρισμένα)" offerings, which are linked to Hermes' special favour for a worshipper endowed by the god with special qualities; in the latter, it is part of the description of the altar of Zeus, the protector of the homestead, and emphasises Odysseus' connection as a zealous sacrificer with a place where the supplicant can seek protection from his wrath.</p>
                    <p>In the characters' speeches, the burning of the legs for the god is a typical element of prayer, and its recollection linked to a request to a supernatural being creates a relationship of reciprocity. Prayers may recall offerings they themselves once made:</p>
                    <p>Il. 1.40-41 (Chryses): ἢ εἰ δή ποτέ τοι κατὰ πίονα μηρί᾽ ἔκηα / ταύρων ἠδ᾽ αἰγῶν, "if I burned you when I burned the fat legs / of bulls and goats"; Il. 8. 240 (Agamemnon): ἀλλ᾽ ἐπὶ πᾶσι βοῶν δημὸν καὶ μηρί᾽ ἔκηα, "but on all (the altars) the fat and the hind legs I burned"; Il. 15. 373-374 (Agamemnon): ἢ βοὸς ἢ οἰὸς κατὰ πίονα μηρία καίων / εὔχετο νοστῆσαι, '(if I) prayed for return by burning the fat legs of an ox or a sheep'. If, on the other hand, the person praying is a figure occupying a lower social position (Eumayos, Penelope), he invokes the sacrifices made in the past by the rightful host, Odysseus:</p>
                    <p>From. 17.240-242 (Eumajos): Νύμφαι κρηναῖαι, κοῦραι Διός, εἴ ποτ᾽ Ὀδυσσεὺς / ὔμμ᾽ ἐπὶ μηρί᾽ ἔκηε, καλύψας πίονι δημῷ, / ἀρνῶν ἠδ᾽ ἐρίφων, τόδε μοι κρηήνατ᾽ ἐέλδωρ; Od. 4.763-765 (Penelope): εἴ ποτέ τοι πολύμητις ἐνὶ μεγάροισιν Ὀδυσσεὺς / ἢ βοὸς ἢ ὄϊος κατὰ πίονα μηρία κῆε, / τῶν νῦν μοι μνῆσαι καί μοι φίλον υἷα σάωσον. Characteristically, in all cases the burnt hind legs are referred to as fat (πίονα μηρία, Il. 1.40; 11.773; 15.373; Od. 4.764) or, in the case of Eumaios' prayer, the fact that they are hidden in fat is emphasised (καλύψας πίονι δημῷ, Od. 17.241).</p>
                    <p>In several places the characters mention in their stories the hind legs burnt by any of the heroes in the past. Twice it is spoken by Nestor, who, as the oldest of the heros who came to Troy, is the bearer of the historical memory of the generation fighting in the Trojan War. In Il. 11.772-773 he mentions the sacrifice made by Peleus when Nestor arrived in Phthia before the Trojan War (γέρων δ᾽ ἱππηλάτα Πηλεὺς / πίονα μηρία καῖε βοὸς Διὶ τερπικεραύνῳ). This refers to a version of the typical scene "sacrificial feast + arrival of guests" adapted to the speech format of the heros. By contrast, in Od. 3.273 Nestor speaks of Ajgistos, emphasising the futility of his sacrifices (πολλὰ δὲ μηρί᾽ ἔκηε θεῶν ἱεροῖσ᾽ ἐπὶ βωμοῖς). In the 24th song of the Iliad, the gods twice mention the leg burned by Hector (Il. 24.33-34; Apollon: οὔ νύ ποθ᾽ ὑμῖν / Ἕκτωρ μηρί᾽ ἔκηε βοῶν αἰγῶν τε τελείων; Il. 24.170-3; Zeus: (Ἕκτωρ) ὅς μοι πολλὰ βοῶν ἐπὶ μηρί᾽ ἔκηεν / Ἴδης ἐν κορυφῇσι πολυπτύχου, ἄλλοτε δ᾽ αὖτε / ἐν πόλει ἀκροτάτῃ). Finally, when Odysseus tells of the hind legs burnt in sacrifice by him during his wanderings, he uses the phrase, ῥέξας μηρί᾽ ἔκαιον (Od. 9.550 ἀρνειὸν (...) /- τὸν δ᾽ ἐπὶ θινὶ / Ζηνὶ κελαινεφέϊ Κρονίδῃ, ὃς πᾶσιν ἀνάσσει, / ῥέξας μηρί᾽ ἔκαιον- ὁ δ᾽ οὐκ ἐμπάζετο ἱρῶν).</p>
                    <p>The burning of the legs as a metonymy of sacrifice also occurs in other poetic genres: in the elegy (Thgn. 1145: let him pray to the gods and offer sacrifice (...) burning shining hind legs, εὐχέσθω δὲ θεοῖσι, καὶ ἀγλαὰ μηρία καίων (...) θυέτω), in the paean Bakchylides (B. 1. 66: ἐπὶ βω[μῶν] [θεοῖσιν αἴθε]σθαι βο[ῶν ξανθᾷ φλογί] [[μηρί᾽ εὐ]μάλ]λων τε [μήλων] 'on the altars / in the bright fire to the gods laid / the legs of oxen and woolly sheep burn (translated by J. Danielewicz)'. In the lyric: Call. frg.2a: μνῆσαι δ᾽, εἴ κοτέ τοι μηρία καλὰ βοῶν.</p>
                    <p>Aristophanes in the Birds adopts an inverted optic, the sacrifice seen from above; he shifts the emphasis from the burning process to its result, the 'oily' smoke rising to the sky (Ar. Av. 193): διὰ τῆς πόλεως ... τὴν κνῖσαν οὐ διαφρήσετε "from the burnt hinds you shall not let the smoke flow through your city (translated by J. Ławińska-Tyszkowska)," cf. 1517-8 ("neither shall the smoke from the burnt hinds / flow to us," οὐδὲ κνῖσα μηρίων ἄπο / ανῆλθεν). The phrase τῶν μηρίων τὴν κνῖσαν, by way of reversal, finds its counterpart in κεκίς μηρίων in Sophocles' Antigone.</p>
                    <p>In the classical era, the first testimonies of mantic practices accompanying burning appear, and consequently detailed descriptions of the anomalies of the burning process of the part dedicated to the gods. The evil omens are described in detail by Tiresias in Sophocles' Antigone (S.Ant. 1005-1020): ἀλλ᾽ ἐπὶ σποδῷ μυδῶσα κηκὶς μηρίων ἐτήκετο κἄτυφε κἀνέπτυε, καὶ μετάρσιοι χολαὶ διεσπείροντο, καὶ καταρρυεῖς μηροὶ καλυπτῆς ἐξέκειντο πιμελῆς, "but on the ashes the seeping, bubbling liquid of the sacrificial bones melted and smoked and sizzled, and drops of bile splashed high, and the slimy legs fell out of the fat covering them".</p>
                    <p>In inscriptions of the archaic and classical periods the word appears rarely. The state of preservation of an inscription regulating the ritual norms of the cult of Heracles at Milet (LSAM 42, Milet, c. 500 BC) does not allow the context of the word to be determined, but the verb παρατίθημι may suggest that one is instructed to place something beside or in front of the hind legs (]ὰ τοῖσι μηρίοισ[ι | πα]ρατιθέναι- ἔρ̣δεν ο-).</p>
                    <p>In later prose, the burning of hind legs is mentioned by authors when an unusual sacrifice is involved, such as the sacrifice of a deer sacrificed at Megalopolis: καὶ τά τε μηρία ἐκτεμόντες καίουσι καὶ δὴ καὶ ἀναλίσκουσιν αὐτόθι τοῦ ἱερείου τὰ κρέα, "after cutting out the femurs, they burn them and eat the meat of the sacrificial animal in the sacred precinct itself (Paus. 8.38.8)".</p>
                    <p>4. The use of the ashes of the burnt μηρία.</p>
                    <p>The ashes of burnt μηρία were sometimes collected in special places: on the heroon (Hdt 4. 35: καὶ τῶν μηρίων καταγιζομένων ἐπὶ τῷ βωμῷ τὴν σποδὸν ταύτην ἐπὶ τὴν θήκην τὴν Ὤπιός τε καὶ Ἄργης ἀναισιμοῦσθαι ἐπιβαλλομένην, "the ashes of the legs burnt on the altar are used to sprinkle the tomb of Opis and Argi"). </p>
                </div>
                <div type="textpart" n="Catalogue_of_occurrences">
                    <head>Catalogue of occurrences</head>
                        <p>1) Verb. + μηρία:</p>
                        <p>ἐκτάμνω + μηρία, "to cut out": Od. 3.456; Paus. 8.38.8</p>
                        <p>ἐξαιρέω + μηρία, "to take out": A. Pax 1021</p>
                        <p>ἐπιτίθημι + μηρία, "to lay (on the altar)": Od. 21.267; Ap. Rhod. 2.691; cf. ἐπὶ τῶν μηρίων E. fr. 143 = A.Th. 694</p>
                        <p>καίω + μηρία, "to burn": Il. 1.40; 8.240; 11.773; 22.34; Od. 3.273; 9.553; 19.366; 19.397; 22.336; Hes. Op. 337; Thgn. 1.1145; default. [μηρία], Il. 1.462 = Od. 3.459; Il. 2.425; A.Rh. 1.435; Paus. 8.38.8</p>
                        <p>ἐπικαίω + μηρία, "to burn": Od. 3.9; Od. 17.241;</p>
                        <p>κατακαίω + μηρία, "to burn":  Il. 1.40; Il. 15.373; Il. 22.170; Od. 4.764; [Call. Eleg. 2a]; default. Il. 2.425</p>
                        <p>δαύω + μηρία, "to burn": Sem. 30 (μηρίων δεδαυμένων)</p>
                        <p>2) Adj. + μηρία</p>
                        <p>In the epic, the noun μηρία occurs with the appendages:</p>
                        <p>πίονα 'fat': Hom. Il. 1.40; Il. 15.373; Il. 11.773; Od. 4.764</p>
                        <p>ἀγλαὰ 'shining': Hes. Op. 337; Thgn. 1.1145</p>
                        <p>πολλὰ 'numerous, plural': Hom. Od. 3.273; 24.170</p>
                        <p>κεχαρισμένα "pleasant": Hom. Od. 19.397)</p>
                        <p>ἱερὰ 'holy': A.Rh. 1.433.</p>
                        <p>It seems that πίονα is used primarily in prayers as a metonymy signalling the ritual process of preparing the portion intended for the gods.</p>
                        <p>3) μηρία + SubstGEN</p>
                        <p>The names of sacrificial animals appear as complements: ἢ βοὸς ἢ ὄϊος (Il. 15.373: for Zeus; Od. 4. 763: for Zeus), ταύρων ἠδ᾽ αἰγῶν (Il. 1.41; for Apollon), ταύρων (Od. 3.178, for Poseidon); βοῶν (Il. 8.240; for Zeus; Il.24 .170; for Zeus, Od. 22.336; for Zeus Herkeios), βοῶν αἰγῶν τε (Il. 24.34; Hector's offerings to the gods, says Apollon), ἀρνῶν ἠδ᾽ ἐρίφων (Od. 17.242; for Nymphs, Od. 19.397, for Hermes).</p>
                        <p>sacrificial animal - recipient of sacrifice</p>
                        <p>ταύρων - Poseidon</p>
                        <p>ταύρων ἠδ᾽ αἰγῶν - Apollon</p>
                        <p>βοῶν - Zeus (3x)</p>
                        <p>βοῶν αἰγῶν τε - gods (says Apollon)</p>
                        <p>ἢ βοὸς ἢ ὄϊος - Zeus (2x)</p>
                        <p>ἀρνῶν ἠδ᾽ ἐρίφων - Nymphs (1x), Hermes (1x)</p>
                        <p>It seems that the choice of sacrificial animals is not random. Poseidon and Apollon receive uncastrated bulls (ταύροι), Zeus - oxen (βοῦς) and sheep (οἶς), Nymphs and Hermes, closely related deities - "lambs and kids" (ἀρνῶν ἠδ᾽ ἐρίφων); it is worth noting that when Apollon appears in the context, goats, αἰγῶν, also appear. Cf. A.Rh. 2,697: κεραῶν ἐπὶ μηρία θήσομεν αἰγῶν. No pigs appear in the phrase μηρία + SubstGEN.</p>
                        <p>4) μηρία καίειν + ἐπί Substdat. loc. or ἐν Substdat. loc.</p>
                        <p>In the epic the phrase may occur with the place circumstance "on the altar": Od. 3.273: ἱεροῖσ᾽ ἐπὶ βωμοῖς; Il. 8.240: ἐπὶ πᾶσι (scil. βωμοῖς); or "on the shore (of the sea)". Od. 9.550: ἐπὶ θινὶ.</p>
                        <p>Il. 24.170-3: Ἴδης ἐν κορυφῇσι πολυπτύχου, (...) ἐν πόλει ἀκροτάτῃ; Od. 4.763-765: ἐνὶ μεγάροισιν.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="textpart" n="Discussion/Interpretation">
                    <head>Discussion/Interpretation</head>
                    <p>There has long been debate as to whether the word μηρία means "leg", i.e. "femur with surrounding muscles", or "thigh bone, femur". In a landmark article by Karl Meuli, he showed that the second meaning is correct (Meuli 1946, earlier bibliography, ibid., p. 215, note 6; cf. Detienne, Vernant 1979, Detienne 1998, pp. 70-2, van Straten 1995; Ekroth 2007, 2009, 2013). More recently, Guy Berthiaume has suggested that sacrificing cleaned bones or bones with meat was not the absolute norm, but depended on the circumstances and the decision of the sacrificer (Berthiaume 2005), but the sources cited in support of this thesis are not convincing (Ekroth 2009, 127-8). Hesiod, in the Theogony, justified the custom of burning μηρία, mēría on the altars with the myth of deception to which Prometheus resorted during the final separation of gods and men (ἐκ τοῦ δ᾽ ἀθανάτοισιν ἐπὶ χθονὶ φῦλ᾽ ἀναθρώπων / καίουσ᾽ ὀστέα λευκὰ θυηέντων ἐπὶ βωμῶν, → cf. commentary on Hesiod, Theogony, 535-558). The expression ὀστέα λευκὰ here is the functional equivalent of μηρία, which could suggest that the flesh-cleansed femurs were burned on the altar or that they were the most important ingredient of the portion dedicated to the gods, hence the metonymic usage. Although the early epic does not use the word 'sacrifice', the epithet describing altars in conjunction with ὀστέα λευκὰ καίειν, 'to burn the white bones' captures the essence of the sacrificial ritual: it involves the production of smoke during the burning of the femurs, a visible signal sent by the people as a sign of reverence within a reciprocal relationship (Parker 1998; 2011).</p>
                    <p>The interpretation of the noun μηρία as a technical term denoting flesh-cleaned femurs is confirmed by lexicographical tradition. Hesychios defines it as τὰ ἐκ τῶν μηρῶν ἐξαιρούμενα ὀστᾶ 'bones cut from the thighs' (s.v. μηρία), cf. the use of the verb in Ar. Pax 1021). Similarly in Apollon. Lex. s.v. μηρία- οὐχ ὡς ἡμεῖς, ἀλλὰ τὰ ἐκ τῶν μηριῶν ἐξαιρούμενα καὶ ἱεροθυτούμενα ὀστᾶ "different from our usage, means bones cut from the legs and offered to the gods". Whereas Etym. M. (p. 585, 22) explains: μηρία- τὰ μηριαῖα ὀστᾶ "femurs" (Meuli 1946, 216).</p>
                    <p>In the Homeric epic, the act of burning μηρία on the altar is a metonymy of blood sacrifice, especially in the utterances of characters recalling past or foreshadowing future sacrifices. It is about deeds performed, which, if pleasing to the god, win his goodwill, charis. A direct connection between the concept of charis and the legs burnt on the altars is found in Od. 19.397 (κεχαρισμένα μηρία). It is not a simple exchange based on the principle of do ut des, but a fixed relationship of reciprocity, a generalized reciprocity (on charis: Parker 2011; Loew, 1908; Latacz 1967, pp. 78-98; Moussy 1966, 411-415).</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            
            <div type="edition" xml:lang="pl">
                <div type="textpart">
                    <p>μηρία mēría, subst. n., plurale tantum, kości udowe, femora (l.poj. femur).</p>
                </div>
                        <div type="textpart" n="Etymologia">
                            <head>Etymologia</head>
                            <p>Urzeczownikowiony przymiotnik μηρία „kości udowe, udźce” (&lt; „udowe”, domyśl. ὄστεα „kości”) pochodzi od rzeczownika μηρός, „udo” (Risch 1974, 115); używany w l. mn. w technicznym znaczeniu „kości udowe bydlęce, owcze lub kozie” zawinięte w tłustą błonę otrzewnej (<w>κνῖσα</w>, rzadziej: <w>δημός</w>, <w>ἐπιπόλαιον</w>, <w>πιμελή</w>), a następnie spalane na ołtarzu. W eposie homeryckim synonim rzeczownika zbiorczego μῆρα (→ <ref corresp="lexicon_mera.html">μῆρα</ref>), w późniejszych tekstach niemal całkowicie go zastąpił (Chantraine 1999 [1968], 697). Zob. również → <ref corresp="lexicon_meros.html">μηροί</ref>.</p>
                        </div>
                <div type="textpart" n="Poświadczenia">
                    <head>Poświadczenia</head>
                    <p>Rzeczownik μηρία pojawia się w kontekście działań składających się trzy kolejne fazy procesu rytualnego: (1) przygotowanie części zwierzęcia ofiarnego przeznaczonej dla bogów, czyli (1a) odcięcie udźców i wykrojenie μηρία ἐκτάμνω/ἐκτέμνω, „odcinam, wycinam, wykrajam”, por. Meuli, 1946, 216-7), (1b) „ukrycie” μηρία poprzez owinięcie ich dwustronnie tłustą błoną otrzewnej ([κνίσῃ] κατακαλύπτω, „zakrywam (tłuszczem)” oraz (1c) ułożenie na nich surowych kawałków mięsa z innych części zwierzęcia (ἐπ᾽ αὐτῶν ὠμοθετέω, „na nich (tzn. udźcach) kładę kawałki mięsa”); (2) złożenie części przeznaczonej dla bogów na ołtarzu: ἐπιτίθημι, „układam, kładę na (domyśl. ołtarzu)”; (3) spalenie: καίω, „spalam, palę”, δαύω, „spalam”. Do tego należy dodać wzmianki o (4) wykorzystaniu popiołów powstałych ze spalonych kości.</p>
                    <p>1. Przygotowanie części przeznaczonej dla bogów.
                        W eposie homeryckim wyrażenie ἐκ μηρία τάμνον („wycięli kości udowe”, z tmezą Od. 3.456) pojawia się w szczegółowym opisie złożonej przez Nestora ofiary dla Ateny (Od. 3.456b-457): ἄφαρ δ᾽ ἐκ μηρία τάμνον / πάντα κατὰ μοῖραν, κατά τε κνίσῃ ἐκάλυψαν („gdy wycięli kości udowe, wszystkie jak się należy, i ukryli w tłuszczu otrzewnej”), który jest wariantem powszechniejszej wersji opisu procedury przygotowania udźców (μηρούς) do spalenia (Il. 1.464-5 = Il. 2.427-8 = Od. 12.364-5): μηρούς τ᾽ ἐξέταμον κατά τε κνίσῃ ἐκάλυψαν / δίπτυχα ποιήσαντες, ἐπ᾽ αὐτῶν δ᾽ ὠμοθέτησαν, „udźce wycieli i ukryli w tłuszczu otrzewnej, / podwójnie zawinąwszy, na nie zaś położyli surowe skrawki”. We wspomnieniach o ofiarach wbudowanych w wypowiedzi postaci owinięcie μηρία tłuszczem jest metonimicznie sygnalizowane przymiotnikami πίων „tłuste” (7x w eposie homeryckim), ἀγλαά „błyszczące” (Hes. Op.337), rzeczownikiem δημός „tłuszcz” (2x) lub wyrażeniem καλύψας πίονι δημῷ (1x).</p>
                    <p>W Pokoju Arystofanesa (Pax 1025) poleca się wycięcie kości udowych po złożeniu ofiary, czyli po dokonaniu rytualnego uboju zwierzęcia w skene, i przyniesienie ich na orchestrę: θύσας τὰ μηρὶ᾽ ἐξελὼν δευρ᾽ ἔκφερε. Słowo μηρία pojawia się prawdopodobnie we fragmencie komedii Eubulosa Semele Eubulosa (fr. 94 Kassel-Austin = fr. 95 Kock, tekst zepsuty, crux philologorum), gdzie Dionizos skarży się na skład części zwierzęcia ofiarnego przeznaczonych dla bogów: πρῶτον μὲν ὅταν ἐμοί τι θύωσίν τινες, / αἷμα, κύστιν, ἧπαρ, καρδίαν, / ὑμέν᾽ ἐπιπόλαιον· οὐδ᾽ ἐγὼ γὰρ ἐσθίω / γλυκεῖαν οὐδὲ μηρία. „Po pierwsze, gdy ofiary jakieś dają mi, / To tylko krew i pęcherz, serce, wątrobę też, / I cienką błonę wierzchnią, lecz nie jadam ja, / Ni żółci, ani kości z biodra wziętych wszak. / (…) i biodra górną część (tłum. Janina Niemirska-Pliszczyńska)”.</p>
                    <p>2. Ułożenie części przeznaczonej dla bogów na ołtarzu.</p>
                    <p>Związek frazeologiczny μηρία + ἐπιτίθημι, „kłaść (na ołtarzu) udźce” = „składać ofiarę zwierzęcą” w eposie pojawia się w poleceniach przygotowanie ofiary (Od. 21.267: ὄφρ᾽ ἐπὶ μηρία θέντες Ἀπόλλωνι, mówi Alkinoos, por. A.Rh.  2.691: δὴ τότε οἱ κεραῶν ἐπὶ μηρία θήσομεν αἰγῶν „udźce rogatych kozłów złóżmy dla niego w ofierze”. Por. wspomnienie o ofiarach spełnionych (Nestor, Od. 3.178-9: Ποσειδάωνι δὲ ταύρων / πόλλ᾽ ἐπὶ μῆρ᾽ ἔθεμεν). W inskrypcjach μηρία jest zastępowane czasami innymi wyrażeniami, zob. LSAM 24 (ok. 380/360 p.n.e.), Erythraj, l.33-34: ὅταν τὴν ἱρὴν μοῖραν ἐπιθῆι. Udźce leżące na ołtarzu jako tło gwałtownej śmierci grożącej ofiarnikowi pojawiają się w przywołanym przez Arystofanesa fragmencie Eurypidesa (E.Fr. 143 = Ar. Th. 694): ἐπὶ τῶν μηρίων.</p>
                    <p>3. Spalenie części poświęconej bogom.</p>
                    <p>W eposie rzeczownik μηρία występuje najczęściej w połączeniu z czasownikiem „spalać” καίω i jego pochodnymi. W ofiarach przedstawionych przez głównego narratora spalanie udźców stanowi centralny element sceny typowej uczta ofiarna (zob. Korpus, Homer, Wprowadzenie). W homeryckiej formule καῖε δ᾽ ἐπὶ σχίζῃς ὁ γέρων, ἐπὶ δ᾽ αἴθοπα οἶνον / λεῖβε „następnie starzec spalił na szczapach, polał skrzącym winem winem” (Il. 1.462-463 = Od. 3.459-460) domyślnym dopełnieniem są udźce zawinięte w tłuszcz z kawałkami surowego mięsa na wierzchu. W wariancie tego heksametru καὶ τὰ μὲν ἂρ σχίζῃσιν ἀφύλλοισιν κατέκαιον „i spalił je na szczapach bezlistnych” (Il. 2.425) zaimek τὰ wskazuje bezpośrednio na udźce, por. A.Rh. 1.434-5: τά γε πάντα (…) καῖον ἐπὶ σχίζῃσιν.</p>
                    <p>Na kluczową rolę spalania kości udowych i kosztowania wnętrzności wskazuje formularny heksametr, który podsumowuje opis procesu rytualnego słowami: εὖθ᾽ οἱ σπλάγχνα πάσαντο, θεῷ δ᾽ ἐπὶ μηρί᾽ ἔκηαν „gdy skosztowali wnętrzności, i spalili bogu kości udowe” (Od. 3.9), por. jego standardowa postać: αὐτὰρ ἐπεὶ κατὰ μῆρ᾽ ἐκάη καὶ σπλάγχνα πάσαντο „gdy już udźce spalili i skosztowali wnętrzności” (4x: Il. 1, 464=Il. 2, 427=Od. 3, 461= Od. 12,364).</p>
                    <p>Poza scenami typowymi wyrażenie καίω +  μηρία w eposie homerowym jest używane jako metonimia ofiar wspominanych przez narratora głównego (aojdę) lub w wypowiedziach postaci. Narrator główny używa go w dwóch miejscach: wspominając ofiary składane przez Autolykosa dla Hermesa (Od. 19.397-398: τῷ γὰρ κεχαρισμένα μηρία καῖεν / ἀρνῶν ἠδ᾽ ἐρίφων) oraz przedstawiając myśli Thespisa rozważającego, jak uratować życie w czasie rzezi zalotników (Od. 22.334-336: ἢ ἐκδὺς μεγάροιο Διὸς μεγάλου ποτὶ βωμὸν (…) / ἔνθ᾽ ἄρα πολλὰ / Λαέρτης Ὀδυσεύς τε βοῶν ἐπὶ μηρί᾽ ἔκηαν). W pierwszym wypadku chodzi “miłe (κεχαρισμένα)” ofiary, które łączą się ze szczególną przychylnością Hermesa dla czciciela obdarzonego przez boga specjalnymi przymiotami, w drugim jest elementem opisu ołtarza Zeusa, opiekuna zagrody, i podkreśla związek Odyseusza jako gorliwego ofiarnika z miejscem, gdzie błagalnik może szukać ochrony przed gniewem tegoż.</p>
                    <p>W wypowiedziach postaci spalenie udźców dla boga jest typowym elementem modlitwy, a jego przypomnienie powiązane z prośbą skierowaną  do istoty nadprzyrodzonej tworzy relację wzajemności. Modlący się mogą przywołać ofiary, które sami niegdyś złożyli:</p>
                    <p>Il. 1.40-41 (Chryzes): ἢ εἰ δή ποτέ τοι κατὰ πίονα μηρί᾽ ἔκηα / ταύρων ἠδ᾽ αἰγῶν, „jeżelim Ci kiedy spalił tłuste udźce / byków i kozłów”; Il. 8.240 (<persName type="myth" key="Agamemnon">Agamemnon</persName>): ἀλλ᾽ ἐπὶ πᾶσι βοῶν δημὸν καὶ μηρί᾽ ἔκηα, „lecz na wszystkich (ołtarzach) tłuszcz i udźce spalałem”; Il. 15.373-374 (Agamemnon): ἢ βοὸς ἢ οἰὸς κατὰ πίονα μηρία καίων  / εὔχετο νοστῆσαι, „(jeżelim) modlił się o powrót spalając tłuste udźce wołu lub owcy”. Jeśli natomiast modlącym jest postać zajmująca niższą pozycję społeczną (Eumajos, Penelopa), przywołuje ofiary złożone w przeszłości przez prawowitego gospodarza, Odyseusza:</p>
                    <p>Od. 17.240-242 (Eumajos): Νύμφαι κρηναῖαι, κοῦραι  Διός, εἴ ποτ᾽  Ὀδυσσεὺς / ὔμμ᾽ ἐπὶ μηρί᾽ ἔκηε, καλύψας πίονι δημῷ, / ἀρνῶν ἠδ᾽ ἐρίφων, τόδε μοι κρηήνατ᾽ ἐέλδωρ; Od. 4.763-765 (Penelopa): εἴ ποτέ τοι πολύμητις ἐνὶ μεγάροισιν  Ὀδυσσεὺς / ἢ βοὸς ἢ ὄϊος κατὰ πίονα μηρία κῆε, / τῶν νῦν μοι μνῆσαι καί μοι φίλον υἷα σάωσον. Charakterystyczne, że we wszystkich przypadkach spalane udźce są określone jako tłuste (πίονα μηρία, Il. 1.40; 11.773; 15.373; Od. 4,764) lub – w przypadku modlitwy Eumajosa – podkreśla się fakt ukrycia ich w tłuszczu (καλύψας πίονι δημῷ, Od. 17.241).</p>
                    <p>W kilku miejscach postaci wspominają w swoich opowiadaniach udźce spalane przez któregoś z herosów w przeszłości. Dwukrotnie mówi Nestor, który, jako najstarszy z herosów przybyłych pod Troję, jest nosicielem pamięci historycznej pokolenia walczącego w wojnie trojańskiej. W Il. 11.772-773 wspomina ofiarę składaną przez Peleusa w chwili, gdy <persName type="myth" key="Nestor">Nestor</persName> przed wojną trojańską  przybył do Ftyi (γέρων δ᾽ ἱππηλάτα Πηλεὺς / πίονα μηρία καῖε βοὸς Διὶ τερπικεραύνῳ). 
                        Chodzi o wersję sceny typowej „uczta ofiarna + przybycie gości” dostosowaną do formatu mowy herosa. Natomiast w Od. 3.273  Nestor mówi o Ajgistosie, podkreślając bezskuteczność jego ofiar (πολλὰ δὲ μηρί᾽ ἔκηε θεῶν ἱεροῖσ᾽ ἐπὶ βωμοῖς). W 24. pieśni Iliady bogowie dwukrotnie wspominają udźce spalane przez Hektora (Il. 24.33-34; Apollon: οὔ νύ ποθ᾽ ὑμῖν / Ἕκτωρ μηρί᾽ ἔκηε βοῶν αἰγῶν τε τελείων; Il. 24.170-3; Zeus: (Ἕκτωρ) ὅς μοι πολλὰ βοῶν ἐπὶ μηρί᾽ ἔκηεν / Ἴδης ἐν κορυφῇσι πολυπτύχου, ἄλλοτε δ᾽ αὖτε / ἐν πόλει ἀκροτάτῃ). Wreszcie, gdy Odyseusz opowiada o udźcach spalonych w ofierze przez siebie w trakcie wędrówki, używa zwrotu, ῥέξας μηρί᾽ ἔκαιον (Od. 9.550 ἀρνειὸν (…) /· τὸν δ᾽ ἐπὶ θινὶ / Ζηνὶ κελαινεφέϊ  Κρονίδῃ, ὃς πᾶσιν ἀνάσσει, / ῥέξας μηρί᾽ ἔκαιον· ὁ δ᾽ οὐκ ἐμπάζετο ἱρῶν).</p>
                    <p>Spalanie udźców jako metonimia ofiary występuje również w innych gatunkach poetyckich: w elegii (Thgn. 1145: niech modli się do bogów i składa ofiarę (…) spalając lśniące udźce, εὐχέσθω δὲ θεοῖσι, καὶ ἀγλαὰ μηρία καίων (…) θυέτω), w peanie Bakchylides (B. 1.66: ἐπὶ βω[μῶν] [θεοῖσιν αἴθε]σθαι βο[ῶν ξανθᾷ φλογί] [[μηρί᾽ εὐ]μάλ]λων τε [μήλων] „na ołtarzach / w jasnym ogniu bogom złożone / udźce wołów i owiec płoną wełnistych (tłum. J. Danielewicz)”. W liryce: Call. frg.2a: μνῆσαι δ᾽, εἴ κοτέ τοι μηρία καλὰ βοῶν.</p>
                    <p>Arystofanes w Ptakach przyjmuje optykę odwróconą, ofiary widzianej z góry; przenosi akcent ze procesu spalania na jego rezultat, „tłusty” dym wznoszący się do nieba (Ar. Av. 193): διὰ τῆς πόλεως ... τὴν κνῖσαν οὐ διαφρήσετε „z udźców palonych dymu nie puścicie przez swoje miasto (tłum. J. Ławińska-Tyszkowska),” por. 1517-8 („ani dym z palonych udźców / nie płynie do nas”, οὐδὲ κνῖσα μηρίων ἄπο / ανῆλθεν). Zwrot τῶν μηρίων τὴν κνῖσαν, na zasadzie odwrócenie, znajduje swój odpowiednik w κεκίς μηρίων w Antygonie Sofoklesa.</p>
                    <p>W epoce klasycznej pojawiają się pierwsze świadectwa praktyk mantycznych towarzyszących spalaniu, a w konsekwencji szczegółowe opisy anomalii procesu spalania części poświęconej bogom. Złe znaki wróżebne opisuje szczegółowo Tejrezjasz w Antygonie Sofoklesa (S.Ant. 1005-1020): ἀλλ᾽ ἐπὶ σποδῷ μυδῶσα κηκὶς μηρίων ἐτήκετο κἄτυφε κἀνέπτυε, καὶ μετάρσιοι χολαὶ διεσπείροντο, καὶ καταρρυεῖς μηροὶ καλυπτῆς ἐξέκειντο πιμελῆς, „lecz na popiele wyciekająca, bulgocąca ciecz z kości ofiarnych topiła się i dymiła i skwierczała, i krople żółci pryskały wysoko, a oślizgłe udźce wypadły z zakrywającego je tłuszczu”.</p>
                    <p>W inskrypcjach okresu archaicznego i klasycznego słowo pojawia się rzadko. Stan zachowania napisu regulującego normy rytualne kultu Heraklesa w Milecie (LSAM 42, Milet, ok. 500 r. p.n.e.) nie pozwala ustalić kontekstu słowa, jednak czasownik παρατίθημι może sugerować, że poleca się ułożenie czegoś przy lub przed udźcami (]ὰ τοῖσι μηρίοισ[ι | πα]ρατιθέναι· ἔρ̣δεν ο-).</p>
                    <p>W późniejszej prozie o spalaniu udźców autorzy mówią wówczas, gdy chodzi o ofiarę nietypową, na przykład ofiarę z odyńca składaną w Megalopolis: καὶ τά τε μηρία ἐκτεμόντες καίουσι καὶ δὴ καὶ ἀναλίσκουσιν αὐτόθι τοῦ ἱερείου τὰ κρέα, „po wycięciu kości udowych, spalają je i zjadają mięso zwierzęcia ofiarnego w samym okręgu świętym (Paus. 8.38.8)”.</p>
                    <p>4. Wykorzystanie popiołu spalonych μηρία.</p>
                    <p>Popiół spalonych μηρία bywał gromadzony w specjalnych miejscach: na heroonie (<ref type="lit">Hdt 4.35</ref>: καὶ τῶν μηρίων καταγιζομένων ἐπὶ τῷ βωμῷ τὴν σποδὸν ταύτην ἐπὶ τὴν θήκην τὴν  Ὤπιός τε καὶ  Ἄργης ἀναισιμοῦσθαι ἐπιβαλλομένην, „popiół ze spalonych na ołtarzu udźców zużywa się na posypanie grobu Opis i Argi”).</p>
                </div>
                <div type="textpart" n="Katalog_wystąpień">
                    <head>Katalog wystąpień</head>
                    <p>1) Verb. + μηρία:</p>
                    <p>ἐκτάμνω + μηρία, „wyciąć”: Od. 3.456; Paus. 8.38.8</p>
                    <p>ἐξαιρέω + μηρία, „wyjąć”: A. Pax 1021</p>
                    <p>ἐπιτίθημι + μηρία, „położyć (na ołtarzu)”: Od. 21.267; <ref type="lit">Ap. Rhod. 2.691</ref>; por. ἐπὶ τῶν μηρίων E. fr. 143 = A.Th. 694</p>
                    <p>καίω + μηρία, „spalić”: Il. 1.40; 8.240; 11.773; 22,34; Od. 3.273; 9.553; 19.366; 19.397; 22.336; Hes. Op. 337; Thgn. 1.1145; domyśl. [μηρία], Il. 1.462 = Od. 3.459; Il. 2.425; A.Rh. 1,435; Paus. 8.38.8</p>
                    <p>ἐπικαίω + μηρία, „spalić”: Od. 3.9; Od. 17.241;</p>
                    <p>κατακαίω + μηρία, „spalić”:  Il. 1.40; Il. 15.373; Il. 22.170; Od. 4.764; [Call. Eleg. 2a]; domyśl. Il. 2.425</p>
                    <p>δαύω + μηρία, „spalić”: Sem. 30 (μηρίων δεδαυμένων)</p>
                    <p>2) Adj. + μηρία</p>
                    <p>W eposie rzeczownik μηρία występować z przydawkami:</p>
                    <p>πίονα „tłuste”: Hom. Il. 1.40; Il. 15.373; Il. 11.773; Od. 4.764</p>
                    <p>ἀγλαὰ „błyszczące”: Hes. Op. 337; Thgn. 1.1145</p>
                    <p>πολλὰ „liczne, mnogie”: Hom. Od. 3.273; 24.170</p>
                    <p>κεχαρισμένα „miłe”: Hom. Od. 19.397)</p>
                    <p>ἱερὰ „święte”: A.Rh. 1.433.</p>
                    <p>Wydaje się, że πίονα jest używane przede wszystkim w modlitwach jako metonimią sygnalizującą proces rytualny przygotowywania części przeznaczonej dla bogów.</p>
                    <p>3) μηρία + SubstGEN</p>
                    <p>Jako dopełnienie pojawiają się nazwy zwierząt ofiarnych: ἢ βοὸς ἢ ὄϊος (Il. 15.373: dla Zeusa; Od. 4.763: dla Zeusa), ταύρων ἠδ᾽ αἰγῶν (Il. 1.41; dla Apollona), ταύρων (Od. 3.178, dla Posejdona); βοῶν (Il. 8.240; dla Zeusa; Il.24.170; dla Zeusa, Od. 22.336; dla Zeusa Herkeiosa), βοῶν αἰγῶν τε (Il. 24.34; ofiary Hektora dla bogów, mówi Apollon), ἀρνῶν ἠδ᾽ ἐρίφων (Od. 17.242; dla Nimf, Od. 19.397, dla Hermesa).</p>
                    <p>zwierzę ofiarne - adresat ofiary</p>
                    <p>ταύρων - Posejdon</p>
                    <p>ταύρων ἠδ᾽ αἰγῶν - Apollon</p>
                    <p>βοῶν - Zeus (3x)</p>
                    <p>βοῶν αἰγῶν τε - bogowie (mówi Apollon)</p>
                    <p>ἢ βοὸς ἢ ὄϊος - Zeus (2x)</p>
                    <p>ἀρνῶν ἠδ᾽ ἐρίφων - Nimfy (1x), Hermes (1x)</p>
                    <p>Zdaje się, że wybór zwierząt ofiarnych nie jest przypadkowy. Posejdon i Apollon otrzymują niekastrowane byki (ταύροι), Zeus – woły (βοῦς) oraz owce (οἶς), Nimfy i Hermes, bóstwa ściśle ze sobą związane – „jagnięta i koźlęta” (ἀρνῶν ἠδ᾽ ἐρίφων); warto zauważyć, że gdy w kontekście pojawia się Apollon, pojawiają się również kozy, αἰγῶν. Por. A.Rh. 2,697: κεραῶν ἐπὶ μηρία θήσομεν αἰγῶν. W zwrocie μηρία + SubstGEN nie pojawiają się świnie.</p>
                    <p>4) μηρία καίειν + ἐπί Substdat. loc. lub ἐν Substdat. loc.</p>
                    <p>W eposie zwrot może występować z okolicznikiem miejsca „na ołtarzu”: Od. 3.273:  ἱεροῖσ᾽ ἐπὶ βωμοῖς; Il. 8.240: ἐπὶ πᾶσι (scil. βωμοῖς); lub „na brzegu (morza)” Od. 9.550: ἐπὶ θινὶ.</p>
                    <p>Il. 24.170-3: Ἴδης ἐν κορυφῇσι πολυπτύχου, (…) ἐν πόλει ἀκροτάτῃ; Od. 4.763-765: ἐνὶ μεγάροισιν.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="textpart" n="Dyskusja/Interpretacja">
                            <head>Dyskusja/Interpretacja</head>
                    <p>Długo toczyła się dyskusja, czy słowo μηρία oznacza „udziec”, czyli „kość udową z otaczającymi ją mięśniami”, czy „kość udową, femur”. W przełomowym artykule Karl Meuli,  wykazał, że drugie znaczenie jest właściwe (Meuli 1946, wcześniejsza bibliografia, tamże, s. 215, przyp. 6; por. Detienne, Vernant 1979, Detienne 1998, s. 70-2, van Straten 1995; Ekroth 2007, 2009, 2013). Ostatnio Guy Berthiaume zasugerował, że składanie w ofierze oczyszczonych kości lub kości z mięsem nie było bezwzględną normą, lecz zależało od okoliczności i decyzji ofiarnika (Berthiaume 2005), jednak przytoczone na poparcie tej tezy źródła nie są przekonujące (Ekroth 2009, 127-8). Hezjod w Teogonii uzasadniał zwyczaj palenia na ołtarzach μηρία, mēría mitem o podstępie, do którego uciekł się Prometeusz podczas ostatecznego rozdziału bogów i ludzi (ἐκ τοῦ δ᾽ ἀθανάτοισιν ἐπὶ χθονὶ φῦλ᾽ ἀναθρώπων / καίουσ᾽ ὀστέα λευκὰ θυηέντων ἐπὶ βωμῶν, →zob. komentarz do Hezjod, Teogonia, 535-558). Wyrażenie ὀστέα λευκὰ jest tutaj funkcjonalnym odpowiednikiem μηρία, co mogłoby sugerować, że na ołtarzu spalano oczyszczone z mięsa kości udowe lub że były one najważniejszym składnikiem części przeznaczonej bogom, stąd użycie metonimiczne. Chociaż wczesny epos nie używa słowa „ofiara”, epitet określający ołtarze w połączeniu z ὀστέα λευκὰ καίειν, „palić białe kości” ujmuje istotę rytuału ofiarnego: chodzi o wytworzenie dymu podczas spalania kości udowych, widocznego sygnału przesyłanego przez ludzi jako znaku czci w ramach relacji wzajemności (Parker 1998; 2011).</p>
                    <p>Interpretację rzeczownika μηρία jako terminu technicznego oznaczającego oczyszczone z mięsa kości udowe potwierdza tradycja leksykograficzna. Hesychios definiuje je jako τὰ ἐκ τῶν μηρῶν ἐξαιρούμενα ὀστᾶ „kości wykrojone z udźców” (s.v. μηρία), por. użycie czasownika w Ar. Pax 1021). Podobnie u Apollon. Lex. s.v. μηρία· οὐχ ὡς ἡμεῖς, ἀλλὰ τὰ ἐκ τῶν μηριῶν ἐξαιρούμενα καὶ ἱεροθυτούμενα ὀστᾶ „odmiennie niż w naszym użyciu, oznacza kości wykrojone z udźców i ofiarowane bogom”. Natomiast Etym. M. (p. 585, 22) wyjaśnia: μηρία· τὰ μηριαῖα ὀστᾶ „kości udowe” (Meuli 1946, 216).</p>
                    <p>W eposie homerowym akt spalania μηρία na ołtarzu jest metonimią ofiary krwawej, zwłaszcza w wypowiedziach bohaterów wspominających przeszłe lub zapowiadających przyszłe ofiary. Chodzi o czyny dokonane, które – jeśli miłe bogu – zjednują, zaskarbiają jego życzliwość, charis. Bezpośredni związek między pojęciem charis a udźcami spalanymi na ołtarzach znajdujemy w Od. 19.397 (κεχαρισμένα μηρία). Nie chodzi o prostą wymianę opartą na zasadzie do ut des, lecz o stałą relację wzajemności, generalized reciprocity (na temat charis: Parker 2011; Loew, 1908; Latacz 1967, s. 78-98; Moussy 1966, 411-415).</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            
            <div type="bibliography">
                <p>Berthiaume, Guy (1982), Les rôles du mágeiros. Études sur la boucherie, la cuisine et le sacrifice dans la Grèce ancienne, Leiden.</p>
                <p>Detienne, Marcel, Vernant, Jean-Pierre (1979), La cuisine du sacrifice en pays grec, avec les contributions de Jean-Louis Durand, Stella Georgoudi, François Hartog et Jasper Svenbro, Gallimard, Paris.</p>
                <p>Ekroth, Gunnel (2007), Meat in ancient Greece: sacrificial, sacred or secular? “Food &amp; History” 5, s. 249-272.</p>
                <p>Ekroth, Gunnel (2009), Thighs or tails? The osteological evidence as a source for Greek ritual norms, w: Le norme en matière religieuse dans la Grèce ancienne. Actes du XIe colloque du CIERGA (Rennes, septembre 2007), ed. P. Brulé, Liège, s. 125-151.</p>
                <p>Ekroth, Gunnel (2013), Forlegs in Greek cult, w: Perspectives on ancient Greece. Papers in celebration of the 60th anniversary of the Swedish Institute at Athens, ed. Ann-Louise Schallin, Stockholm, s. 113-134.</p>
                <p>Latacz, Joachim (1967) Zum Wortfeld „Freude” in der Sprache Homers, Heidelberg.</p>
                <p>Loew, O. (1908) ΧΑΡΙΣ, diss. Marburg.</p>
                <p>Meuli, Karl (1946) Griechische Opferbaüche, w: Phyllobolia. Für Peter von der Mühll zum 60. Geburtstag am 1. August 1945, Basel, s. 185 – 288.</p>
                <p>Moussy, Claude (1966), Grātia et sa famille, Paris.</p>
                <p>Parker, Robert (1998), Pleasing Thighs: Reciprocity in Greek Religion [w:] Reciprocity in Ancient Greece, edited by Christopher Gill, Norman Postlethwaite and Richard Seaford, Oxford 1998, s. 105-125.</p>
                <p>Pirenne-Delforge, Vincienne (2008), Retour à la source. Pausanias et la religion grecque, Liège.</p>
                <p>Risch, Ernst (1974), Wortbildung der homerischen Sprache, Berlin.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
