<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>κηΰα</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher><ref target="https://site.unibo.it/lares/">LARES Project</ref></publisher>
                <date when="2021"/>
                <idno type="filename">lexicon_keya</idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digital document.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change when="2022-02-03" who="Irene Vagionakis">encoded document in XML</change>
                <change when="2018-06-26" who="Krzysztof Bielawski">updated document contents</change>
                <change when="2016-05-03" who="Krzysztof Bielawski">created document contents</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="edition" xml:lang="it">
                <div type="textpart">
                    <p>κηΰα keÿa, n.: offerta bruciata, forse (seguendo Esichio) anche purificatoria.</p>
                    <p>Hapax legomenon che si verifica solo una volta su un'iscrizione contenente la legge degli anfiteatri delfici del 380/379 a.C. (<ref corresp="https://epigraphy.packhum.org /text/3341">IG II2 1126</ref> in. 34 = Ziehen 1906: 226-234 n. 75, v. 34 con commento a p. 233). Deriva dal verbo καίω (vedi Chantraine 1968: 481 e 528, rispettivamente s.v.: καίω e κήυα).</p>
                    <p>Sull'iscrizione summenzionata si presenta evidentemente come il nome di un sacrificio di tre animali (τρίττοια, qui nella forma τρίκτευα).</p>
                    <p>Secondo LSJ (s.v.) e i commenti all'edizione delle iscrizioni secondo il lessico di Esichio (s.v. κήϊα, κέϊα) significa un sacrificio purificatorio, equivalente a καθάρματα, che non è affatto indicato dal contesto in cui appare.</p>                    
                </div>
            </div>
            
            <div type="edition" xml:lang="en">
                <div type="textpart">
                    <p>κηΰα keÿa, n.: burnt offering, perhaps (following Hesychius) also purificatory.</p>
                    <p>Hapax legomenon occurring only once on an inscription containing the law of Delphic amphictyons from 380/379 BC. (<ref corresp="https://epigraphy.packhum.org /text/3341">IG II2 1126</ref> in. 34 = Ziehen 1906: 226-234 no. 75, v. 34 with commentary on p. 233). Derived from the verb καίω (see Chantraine 1968: 481 and 528, respectively s.v.: καίω and κήυα).</p>
                    <p>On the aforementioned inscription it evidently occurs as the name of a sacrifice of three animals (τρίττοια, here in the form τρίκτευα).</p>
                    <p>According to LSJ (s.v.) and the commentaries on the edition of the inscriptions following the lexicon of Hesychius (s.v. κήϊα, κέϊα) it means a purificatory sacrifice, equivalent to καθάρματα, which is by no means indicated by the context in which it appears.</p>                    
                </div>
            </div>
            
            <div type="edition" xml:lang="pl">
                <div type="textpart">
                    <p>κηΰα keÿa, n.: ofiara spalana, może (za Hezychiuszem) także oczyszczająca.</p>
                    <p>Hapax legomenon występujące tylko jeden raz na inskrypcji zawierającej prawo amfiktionów delfickich z lat 380/379 p.n.e. (<ref corresp="https://epigraphy.packhum.org /text/3341">IG II2 1126</ref> w. 34 = Ziehen 1906: 226-234 nr 75, w. 34 z komentarzem na s. 233). Pochodzi od czasownika καίω (zob. Chantraine 1968: 481 i 528, odpowiednio s.v.: καίω i κήυα).</p>
                    <p>Na wspomnianej inskrypcji występuje ewidentnie jako nazwa ofiary z trzech zwierząt (τρίττοια, tutaj w formie τρίκτευα).</p>
                    <p>Według LSJ (s.v.) oraz komentarzy do edycji inskrypcji idących za leksykonem Hezychiusza (s.v. κήϊα, κέϊα) oznacza ofiarę oczyszczającą, równoznaczną z καθάρματα, na co nie wskazuje bynajmniej kontekst, w jakim się pojawia.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            
            <div type="bibliography">
                <p>Chantraine, P., 1968, Dictionnaire étymologique de la langue grecque. Histoire des mots, Paris [avec un Suppléement: 1999].</p>
                <p>Ziehen, L., 1906, Leges Graecorum Sacrae e Titulis Collectae, pars altera, Lipsiae.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
