<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>θυσίαν ἄγειν</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher><ref target="https://site.unibo.it/lares/">LARES Project</ref></publisher>
                <date when="2021"/>
                <idno type="filename">lexicon_thysian_agein</idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>"Animal Sacrifice in Ancient Greece" database (<ref corresp="http://www.sacrificium.filg.uj.edu.pl">http://www.sacrificium.filg.uj.edu.pl</ref>).</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change when="2022-02-03" who="Irene Vagionakis">encoded document in XML</change>
                <change when="2018-06-26" who="Przemysław Biernat">created document contents</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="edition" xml:lang="it">
                <div type="textpart">
                    <p><w>θυσίαν</w> <w>ἄγειν</w> thysian agein, 1. portare a termine, compiere un sacrificio (Anassimene vel ps.-Arist., Rh. Al., 2.7; Pl., Alc. 2, 148e; D. S., 4.23; D. H., Antiq. Rom., 2.18.2, 2.19.4; Plut. Sep. sap. 162e, Quest. Gr., 301e, De exilio 601b; App., Mith., 279; Paus. 1.42.7, 2.19.5; X.Eph. 5.11; Hld. 5.13.2; Anonym., De obsidione toleranda, 58); 2. partecipare a un sacrificio (Isoc. 19.10); 3. condurre gli animali al sacrificio (la parola thysia è poi usata metonimicamente) (D. H., Lys. 29; Paus. 4.30.3, 6.2.6).</p>
                    <p>L'espressione non compare da nessuna parte nel tempo aoristo, perfectum o futuro.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="textpart" n="Commento">        
                        <head>Commento</head>
                        <p>In epoca classica, l'espressione thysian agein appare solo nei testi degli autori in declino, Isocrate e Anassimene di Lampsakos (se è l'autore della Retorica ad Alexandrum), e probabilmente per questo motivo è stata tralasciata da Casabona nelle sue Recherches sur le vocabulaire des sacrifices en Grec (lo studioso include invece occorrenze delle espressioni thysian anagein e thysian prosagein, Casabona 1966: 135). Si noti che Isocrate è l'unico a usare l'espressione thysian agein nel senso di "prendere parte al sacrificio" piuttosto che "compiere il sacrificio" (ἕως μὲν γὰρ παῖδες ἦμεν, περὶ πλείονος ἡμᾶς αὐτοὺς ἡγούμεθα ἢ τοὺς ἀδελφούς, καὶ οὔτε θυσίαν οὔτε θεωρίαν οὔτ᾽ ἄλλην ἑορτὴν οὐδεμίαν χωρὶς ἀλλήλων ἤγομεν: ἐπειδὴ δ᾽ ἄνδρες ἐγενόμεθα..., "Finché eravamo bambini, restavamo in maggiore intimità tra di noi che con i nostri fratelli, e non c'era sacrificio, pellegrinaggio (theoria), o qualche altra festa a cui non prendessimo parte insieme. E da quando siamo diventati uomini...", Isoc. 19.10).</p>
                    <p>L'espressione è spesso usata quando l'informazione sulla ripetizione dei sacrifici è importante dal punto di vista del mittente (Pl., Alc. 2, 148e; D. H., Antiq. Rom. 2.19.4, Plut. Quest. Gr., 301e, De exilio 601b, Paus. 1.42.7, Hld. 5.13.2). Quando ci si riferisce al sacrificio come evento unico, il verbo agein può essere sostituito da un altro, ad esempio poiein o epitelein (cfr. i due passi in D. H., Antiq. Rom.: θυσίας ἄγουσιν ἀνὰ πᾶν ἔτος, 2.19.4 e τάς τε θυσίας ἐπετέλεσε, 2.30.4).</p>
                    <p>In molti casi il sostantivo thysia è usato in contrasto con un altro, ad esempio heorte, panegyris o pompe, per il principio di contrapporre un evento puntuale a un evento esteso nel tempo (cfr. Casabona 1966: 132). Allora thysia è il complemento di epitelein, poiein o verbi simili, mentre agein regola il secondo sostantivo (X., Cyr. 6.2.8, 8.2.4; D. S., 1.72.2; Eratosth., Cat., 1.13; Lucianus, Syr. D. 1, Zonar. 1.272).</p>
                    <p>L'espressione è usata tre volte nel senso di "far correre gli animali al luogo del loro sacrificio". La parola thysia è usata qui metonimicamente, come totum pro parte: 'sacrificio' invece di 'animali sacrificali' (cfr. Le parole di Apollon rivolte ai primi abitanti di Delfi: σφάζειν αἰεὶ μῆλα ... ὅσσα τ᾽ ἐμοί κ᾽ ἀγάγωσι περικλυτὰ φῦλ᾽ ἀνθρώπων, "[che ognuno] macelli ancora le pecore che porteranno (agein) a me le famose tribù di uomini", h. Hom. 3. 536-7).</p>                    
                </div>
            </div>
            
            <div type="edition" xml:lang="en">
                <div type="textpart">
                    <p>θυσίαν ἄγειν thysian agein, 1. to carry out, to fulfill a sacrifice (Anaximenes vel ps.-Arist., Rh. Al., 2.7; Pl., Alc. 2, 148e; D. S., 4.23; D. H., Antiq. Rom., 2.18.2, 2.19.4; Plut. Sep. sap. 162e, Quest. Gr., 301e, De exilio 601b; App., Mith., 279; Paus. 1.42.7, 2.19.5; X.Eph. 5.11; Hld. 5.13.2; Anonym., De obsidione toleranda, 58); 2. to take part in a sacrifice (Isoc. 19.10); 3. to drive animals to sacrifice (the word thysia is then used metonymically) (D. H., Lys. 29; Paus. 4.30.3, 6.2.6).</p>
                    <p>The expression nowhere occurs in the aorist, perfectum or future tense.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="textpart" n="Comment">
                    <head>Comment</head>
                    <p>In the classical era, the expression thysian agein appears only in the texts of the declining authors, Isocrates and Anaximenes of Lampsakos (if he is the author of the Rhetorica ad Alexandrum), and probably for this reason it was missed by Casabona in his Recherches sur le vocabulaire des sacrifices en Grec (the scholar instead includes occurrences of the expressions thysian anagein and thysian prosagein, Casabona 1966: 135). It should be noted that Isocrates is the only one to use the expression thysian agein in the sense of 'to take part in the sacrifice' rather than 'to carry out the sacrifice' (ἕως μὲν γὰρ παῖδες ἦμεν, περὶ πλείονος ἡμᾶς αὐτοὺς ἡγούμεθα ἢ τοὺς ἀδελφούς, καὶ οὔτε θυσίαν οὔτε θεωρίαν οὔτ᾽ ἄλλην ἑορτὴν οὐδεμίαν χωρὶς ἀλλήλων ἤγομεν: ἐπειδὴ δ᾽ ἄνδρες ἐγενόμεθα..., "As long as we were children, we remained in greater intimacy with one another than with our brothers, and there was no sacrifice, pilgrimage (theoria), or some other festival in which we did not take part together. And since we became men...", Isoc. 19.10).</p>
                    <p>The expression is often used where information about the repetition of sacrifices is important from the point of view of the sender (Pl., Alc. 2, 148e; D. H., Antiq. Rom. 2.19.4, Plut. Quest. Gr., 301e, De exilio 601b, Paus. 1.42.7, Hld. 5.13.2). When referring to the sacrifice as a one-time event, the verb agein may be replaced by another, e.g. poiein or epitelein (cf. the two passages in D. H., Antiq. Rom.: θυσίας ἄγουσιν ἀνὰ πᾶν ἔτος, 2.19.4 and τάς τε θυσίας ἐπετέλεσε, 2.30.4).</p>
                    <p>In many cases the noun thysia is used in contrast to another, e.g. heorte, panegyris or pompe, on the principle of contrasting a point event with an event stretched over time (cf. Casabona 1966: 132). Then thysia is the complement of epitelein, poiein or similar verbs, while agein rules the second noun (X., Cyr. 6.2.8, 8.2.4; D. S., 1.72.2; Eratosth., Cat., 1.13; Lucianus, Syr. D. 1, Zonar. 1.272).</p>
                    <p>The expression is used three times in the sense of "to rush the animals to the place of their sacrifice". The word thysia is used here metonymically, as totum pro parte: 'sacrifice' instead of 'sacrificial animals' (cf. Apollon's words addressed to the first inhabitants of Delphi: σφάζειν αἰεὶ μῆλα ... ὅσσα τ᾽ ἐμοί κ᾽ ἀγάγωσι περικλυτὰ φῦλ᾽ ἀνθρώπων, "[let everyone] slaughter still the sheep that will bring (agein) to me the famous tribes of men", h. Hom. 3. 536-7).</p>                    
                </div>
            </div>
            
            <div type="edition" xml:lang="pl">
                <div type="textpart">
                    <p>θυσίαν ἄγειν thysian agein, 1. przeprowadzać, spełniać ofiarę (Anaximenes vel ps.-Arist., Rh. Al., 2.7; Pl., Alc. 2, 148e; D. S., 4.23; D. H., Antiq. Rom., 2.18.2, 2.19.4; Plut. Sep. sap. 162e, Quest. Gr., 301e, De exilio 601b; App., Mith., 279; Paus. 1.42.7, 2.19.5; X.Eph. 5.11; Hld. 5.13.2; Anonym., De obsidione toleranda, 58); 2. brać udział w ofierze (Isoc. 19.10); 3. pędzić zwierzęta na ofiarę (słowo thysia jest wówczas użyte metonimicznie) (D. H., Lys. 29; Paus. 4.30.3, 6.2.6)</p>
                    <p>Wyrażenie nigdzie nie występuje w aoryście, w perfectum ani w czasie przyszłym.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="textpart" n="Komentarz">
                    <head>Komentarz</head>
                    <p>W epoce klasycznej wyrażenie thysian agein pojawia się dopiero w tekstach autorów schyłkowych, Izokratesa i Anaksymenesa z Lampsakos (jeżeli to on jest autorem Rhetorica ad Alexandrum), i zapewne z tego powodu zostało przegapione przez Casabonę w jego Recherches sur le vocabulaire des sacrifices en Grec (uczony uwzględnia natomiast wystąpienia wyrażeń thysian anagein i thysian prosagein, Casabona 1966: 135). Należy zauważyć, że Izokrates jako jedyny posługuje się wyrażeniem thysian agein w znaczeniu “brać udział w ofierze”, a nie “przeprowadzać ofiarę” (ἕως μὲν γὰρ παῖδες ἦμεν, περὶ πλείονος ἡμᾶς αὐτοὺς ἡγούμεθα ἢ τοὺς ἀδελφούς, καὶ οὔτε θυσίαν οὔτε θεωρίαν οὔτ᾽ ἄλλην ἑορτὴν οὐδεμίαν χωρὶς ἀλλήλων ἤγομεν: ἐπειδὴ δ᾽ ἄνδρες ἐγενόμεθα…, “Póki byliśmy dziećmi, pozostawaliśmy w większej zażyłości między sobą, niż z naszymi braćmi, i nie było ofiary, pielgrzymki (theoria), czy jakiegoś innego święta, w którym nie bralibyśmy udziału razem. Skoro zaś staliśmy się mężczyznami…”, Isoc. 19.10).</p>
                    <p>Wyrażenie często używane jest tam, gdzie istotna z punktu widzenia nadawcy jest informacja o powtarzalności ofiar (Pl., Alc. 2, 148e; D. H., Antiq. Rom. 2.19.4, Plut. Quest. Gr., 301e, De exilio 601b, Paus. 1.42.7, Hld. 5.13.2). Kiedy mowa o ofierze jako jednorazowym wydarzeniu, czasownik agein może zostać zastąpiony innym, np. poiein lub epitelein (por. dwa passusy u D. H., Antiq. Rom.: θυσίας ἄγουσιν ἀνὰ πᾶν ἔτος, 2.19.4 oraz τάς τε θυσίας ἐπετέλεσε, 2.30.4).</p>
                    <p>W wielu przypadkach rzeczownik thysia użyty jest w kontraście do innego, np. heorte, panegyris lub pompe, na zasadzie przeciwstawienia zdarzenia punktowego zdarzeniu rozciągniętemu w czasie (por. Casabona 1966: 132). Wówczas thysia jest dopełnieniem czasowników epitelein, poiein lub podobnych, natomiast agein rządzi drugim rzeczownikiem (X., Cyr. 6.2.8, 8.2.4; D. S., 1.72.2; <ref type="lit">Eratosth., Cat., 1.13</ref>; Lucianus, Syr. D. 1, Zonar. 1.272).</p>
                    <p>Wyrażenie trzykrotnie użyte jest w znaczeniu “pędzić zwierzęta do miejsca ich ofiarowania”. Słowo thysia jest w nim użyte metonimicznie, jako totum pro parte: “ofiara” zamiast “zwierzęta ofiarne” (por. skierowane do pierwszych mieszkańców Delf słowa Apollona: σφάζειν αἰεὶ μῆλα … ὅσσα τ᾽ ἐμοί κ᾽ ἀγάγωσι περικλυτὰ φῦλ᾽ ἀνθρώπων, “[niech każdy] zarzyna wciąż owce, które przywiodą (agein) do mnie sławne plemiona ludzi”, h.Hom. 3. 536-7).</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            
            <!--<div type="bibliography">
                <p>...</p>
            </div>-->
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
