<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">  
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title xml:lang="grc">χρυσόκερως</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher><ref target="https://site.unibo.it/lares/">LARES Project</ref></publisher>
                <date when="2021"/>
                <idno type="filename">lexicon_chrysokeros</idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>"Animal Sacrifice in Ancient Greece" database (<ref>http://www.sacrificium.filg.uj.edu.pl</ref>).</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change when="2022-02-03" who="Irene Vagionakis">encoded in XML</change>
                <change when="2016-09-06" who="Przemysław Biernat">written contents</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="edition" xml:lang="it">
                <div type="textpart">
                    <p><w>χρυσόκερως</w> chrysokeros, agg. aureo</p>
                </div>
                <div type="textpart" n="Morfologia">
                    <head>Morfologia</head>
                    <p>La parola è un composto dell'aggettivo chrysos, 'dorato', e del sostantivo keros 'corno'.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="textpart" n="Attestazioni">
                    <head>Attestazioni</head>
                    <p>L'aggettivo χρυσόκερως è usato dagli autori antichi principalmente in due contesti: come termine per la cerva di Artemide, che Herakles doveva catturare come parte delle sue dodici fatiche, e come termine per il bestiame sacrificale, le cui corna erano coperte da una placca d'oro per decorazione. Questi due contesti hanno probabilmente contribuito alla descrizione di un mitografo tardo antico del gregge rubato da Hermes ad Apollon, fratello di Artemide, come "dalle corna d'oro". (Filostrato, Imagines, 1.26.3). Inoltre, l'aggettivo appare ancora negli scritti dei grammatici come esempio di parole coniugate nella cosiddetta "declinazione attica".</p>
                    <p>Omero conosce l'usanza di decorare le corna del bestiame sacrificale con l'oro (cfr. Hom., Il. 10.294, Od. 3.430-438), sebbene non usi l'aggettivo χρυσόκερως. Come spiega lo stesso Omero nei passi citati dell'Odissea, la doratura delle corna serve a rendere il dono più gradito alla dea (ἵν᾽ ἄγαλμα θεὰ κεχάροιτο ἰδοῦσα, 438). Sembra inappropriato mettere in relazione il sostantivo <w>ἄγαλμα</w> del passus citato con la giovenca sacrificata (così, ad esempio, Autenrieth 1984, s.v. ἄγαλμα). Più probabilmente, è usato qui nel suo senso abituale di dono votivo (così ad es. Montanari 2015, s.v. ἄγαλμα): una volta compiuto il sacrificio, il cranio della giovenca con le corna dorate sarà depositato nel tempio ed è in questa forma che allieterà gli occhi di Atena (così Seaford 2004: 62 ss.).</p>
                    <p>Poiché i bovini erano il tipo di animale sacrificale più costoso, i bovini con le corna dorate rappresentavano la forma più costosa possibile di sacrificio animale, associata alle più importanti feste di stato (<ref corresp="https://epigraphy.packhum.org/text/79">IG I3 78a</ref>, 36-40, vedi → <ref corresp="https://epigraphy.packhum.org/book/876">Iscrizioni Eleusine</ref>). L'espressione "bestiame dalle corna d'oro" può anche essere usata come metonimia per i sacrifici costosi (Pl., Alc.2. 149c).
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="textpart" n="Apparizioni">
                    <head>Apparizioni</head>
                    <p>Aeschin 3.164; Thphr. De piet. Fr. 7, Fr. 8; [Pl.] Alc. 2. 149c; J. AJ 13.242; Plu. Aem. 33.2; [Plu.] Apoph. 184e; Polyaen. 8.43; Lib. Decl. 23.1.10.</p>                    
                </div>
            </div>
            
            <div type="edition" xml:lang="en">
                <div type="textpart">
                    <p>χρυσόκερως chrysokeros, adj. golden-horned</p>
                </div>
                <div type="textpart" n="Morphology">
                    <head>Morphology</head>
                    <p>The word is a compound of the adjective chrysos, 'golden', and the noun keros 'horn'.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="textpart" n="Statements">
                    <head>Statements</head>
                    <p>The adjective χρυσόκερως is used by ancient authors primarily in two contexts: as a term for the doe of Artemis, which Herakles was to catch as part of his twelve labours, and as a term for sacrificial cattle, whose horns were covered with a gold plate for decoration. These two contexts probably contributed to one late antique mythographer's description of Hermes' stolen flock of Apollon, Artemis' brother, as "golden-horned" (Philostratus, Imagines, 1.26.3). Besides, the adjective still appears in the writings of grammarians as an example of words that are conjugated within the so-called 'Attic declension'.</p>
                    <p>Homer knows the custom of decorating the horns of sacrificial cattle with gold (cf. Hom., Il. 10.294, Od. 3.430-438), although he does not use the adjective χρυσόκερως. As Homer himself explains in the referenced passages from the Odyssey, the gilding of the horns is to make the gift more pleasing to the goddess (ἵν᾽ ἄγαλμα θεὰ κεχάροιτο ἰδοῦσα, 438). It seems inappropriate to relate the noun ἄγαλμα of the quoted passus to the sacrificed heifer (so, e.g., Autenrieth 1984, s.v. ἄγαλμα). More likely, it is used here in its usual sense of a votive gift (so e.g. Montanari 2015, s.v. ἄγαλμα): once the sacrifice has been fulfilled, the skull of the heifer with its gilded horns will be deposited in the temple and it is in this form that it will gladden the eyes of Athena (so Seaford 2004: 62 ff.).</p>
                    <p>Since cattle were the most expensive type of sacrificial animal, cattle with gilded horns represented the most expensive possible form of animal sacrifice, associated with the most important state holidays (<ref corresp="https://epigraphy.packhum.org/text/79">IG I3 78a</ref>, 36-40, see → <ref corresp="https://epigraphy.packhum.org/book/876">Eleusinian Inscriptions</ref>). The expression 'golden-horned cattle' can also be used as a metonymy for costly sacrifices (Pl., Alc.2. 149c).
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="textpart" n="Appearances">
                    <head>Appearances</head>
                    <p>Aeschin 3.164; Thphr. De piet. Fr. 7, Fr. 8; [Pl.] Alc. 2. 149c; J. AJ 13.242; Plu. Aem. 33.2; [Plu.] Apoph. 184e; Polyaen. 8.43; Lib. Decl. 23.1.10.</p>                    
                </div>
            </div>
            
            <div type="edition" xml:lang="pl">
                <div type="textpart">
                    <p>χρυσόκερως chrysokeros, adj. złotorogi</p>
                </div>
                <div type="textpart" n="Morfologia">
                    <head>Morfologia</head>
                <p>Wyraz stanowi złożenie przymiotnika chrysos, „złoty”, i rzeczownika keros „róg”.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="textpart" n="Poświadczenia">
                    <head>Poświadczenia</head>
                    <p>Przymiotnik χρυσόκερως używany jest przez autorów antycznych przede wszystkim w dwóch kontekstach: jako określenie łani <persName type="divine" key="Artemis">Artemidy</persName>, którą w ramach dwunastu prac miał złapać Herakles, oraz jako określenie bydła ofiarnego, któremu dla ozdoby pokrywano rogi złotą blaszką. Te dwa konteksty przyczyniły się zapewne do tego, że jeden z późnoantycznych mitografów opisał skradzione przez <persName type="divine" key="Hermes">Hermesa</persName> trzody <persName type="divine" key="Apollo">Apollona</persName>, brata Artemidy, jako „złotorogie” (Philostratus, Imagines, 1.26.3). Poza tym, przymiotnik pojawia się jeszcze w pismach gramatyków jako przykład wyrazów, które odmieniają się w ramach tak zwanej „deklinacji attyckiej”.</p>
                    <p>Homer zna zwyczaj ozdabiania złotem rogów ofiarnego bydła (cf. <ref type="lit">Hom., Il. 10.294</ref>, Od. 3.430-438), chociaż przymiotnika χρυσόκερως nie używa. Jak sam Homer wyjaśnia w przywołanym passusie z Odysei, złocenie rogów ma sprawić, że dar będzie milszy bogini (ἵν᾽ ἄγαλμα θεὰ κεχάροιτο ἰδοῦσα, 438). Wydaje się, że nie należy odnosić rzeczownika ἄγαλμα z cytowanego passusu do ofiarowanej jałówki (tak np. Autenrieth 1984, s.v. ἄγαλμα). Bardziej prawdopodobne, że użyty jest tutaj w swoim zwyczajowym znaczeniu daru wotywnego (tak np. Montanari 2015, s.v. ἄγαλμα): po spełnieniu ofiary czaszka jałówki o pozłoconych rogach zostanie złożona w świątyni i właśnie w tej formie będzie radować oczy Ateny (tak Seaford 2004: 62 i nn.).</p>
                    <p>Ponieważ bydło było najdroższym typem zwierzęcia ofiarnego, bydło o złoconych rogach stanowiło najdroższą możliwą formę ofiary zwierzęcej, związaną z najważniejszymi świętami państwowymi (<ref corresp="https://epigraphy.packhum.org/text/79">IG I3 78a</ref>, 36-40, zob. → <ref corresp="https://epigraphy.packhum.org/book/876">Inskrypcje Eleuzyńskie</ref>). Wyrażenie „złotorogie bydło” może być też użyte jako metonimia kosztownych ofiar (Pl., Alc.2. 149c).</p>
                </div>
                <div type="textpart" n="Wystąpienia">
                    <head>Wystąpienia</head>
                    <p>Aeschin 3.164; Thphr. De piet. fr. 7, fr. 8; [Pl.] Alc. 2. 149c; J. AJ 13.242; Plu. Aem. 33.2; [Plu.] Apoph. 184e; Polyaen. 8.43; Lib. Decl. 23.1.10.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            
            <div type="bibliography">
                <p>Autenrieth, G. (2004). Homeric Dictionary. London.</p>
                <p>Montanari, F. (2015). The Brill Dictionary of Ancient Greek. Boston-Leiden.</p>
                <p>Seaford, R. (2004). Money and the Early Greek Mind: Homer, Philosophy, Tragedy. Cambridge.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
