<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">  
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title xml:lang="grc">μάχαιρα</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher><ref target="https://site.unibo.it/lares/">LARES Project</ref></publisher>
                <date when="2021"/>
                <idno type="filename">lexicon_machaira</idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>"Animal Sacrifice in Ancient Greece" database (<ref>http://www.sacrificium.filg.uj.edu.pl</ref>).</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change when="2022-02-03" who="Irene Vagionakis">encoded in XML</change>
                <change when="2015-04-21" who="Przemysław Biernat">updated document contents</change>
                <change when="2015-03-31" who="Przemysław Biernat">written contents</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="edition" xml:lang="it">
                <div type="textpart">
                    <p><w>μάχαιρα</w> machaira, ας, subst. f.: grande coltello</p>
                </div>
                <div type="textpart" n="Etimologia_e_morfologia">
                    <head>Etimologia e morfologia</head>
                    <p>La morfologia della parola indica che è un derivato di -ya- e come tale può essere ricostruita alla forma *makhar-ya (Chantraine 1968: 673, Beekes 2010: 915), il che suggerisce un'affinità con la parola <w>μῆχαρ</w> 'mezzo, modo'. Il loro elemento comune può essere ricostruito alla forma *meh2gh- e collegato al verbo <w>μάχεσθαι</w> 'combattere'. Beekes, tuttavia, respinge questa ipotesi (2010: 915, vedi anche 916 e 950), postulando un'origine pre-greca della parola e collegandola a μάγειρος 'macellaio, cuoco'. La parola ha il suo pendant nell'ebraico mekērā 'spada', ma sembra essere un prestito greco (Chantraine 1968: 673, Beekes 2010: 915). La forma micenea ma-ke-ra è interpretata come un nome personale, anche se è stato suggerito di vederla come machaira (Diccionario Micénico, vol. I: 419, bibliografia ivi).</p>                    
                </div>
                <div type="textpart" n="Costruzione_e_funzione">
                    <head>Costruzione e funzione</head>
                    <p>Con la parola μάχαιρα i Greci si riferivano a grandi coltelli da taglio (τέμνειν: cfr. Hom. Il. 11.844, Democr. 302) con una lama leggermente ricurva e a un solo taglio (vide Gordon 1958: 25, fig. 2). Possono essere stati fatti di bronzo (cfr. Hom. Il. 3.292, 19.266) o di ferro (Daimachus 8c, cfr. Booikidis, Strout 1997: 77 - lame di coltelli di ferro trovate tra le ossa di animali sacrificali, VI secolo a.C.), motivo per cui nella poesia nelle descrizioni del sacrificio si incontra spesso l'uso metonimico di parole che significano "bronzo" (cfr. Hom. Il. 3.292, 19.266) e "ferro" (cfr. Hom. Il. 23.30) nel senso di coltello. La loro fabbricazione era effettuata da artigiani speciali, μαχαιροποιοί (D. 27.9) o μαχαιρουργοί (Demad. Fr. 75). I manici dei coltelli potrebbero essere stati fatti di avorio (D. 27.9, cfr. anche Theopomp.Com. 7: ἐλεφαντοκώπους ξιφομαχαίρας).</p>
                    <p>Sembra certo che nel rituale sacrificale il μάχαιρα agisse come strumento multifunzionale. Veniva usato per infliggere un colpo a un animale che doveva trarne sangue (σφάζειν: h Hom. 3.535; μαγειρικῶς σφάζειν: Ar. Pax 1017-8; τέμνειν σφάγια: E. Supp. 1196; τράχηλον τρίβειν: Esopo. 92.12 aliter), mentre più tardi fu usato per tagliare la carne (χρῆσθαι, nel contesto di spiedo e pentola: Hdt. 2.41; διατέμνειν κρέας: Hdt. 2.41) e, probabilmente, anche per scuoiare l'animale (ἐκτείνειν δέρμα: Pi. P. 4. 241-3, vedi anche → <ref corresp="lexicon_kopis.html">κοπίς</ref>). Le parti più dure dell'animale, come le ossa, venivano tagliate con una mannaia → <ref corresp="lexicon_kopis.html">κοπίς</ref>. Nel caso di animali più grandi, come i buoi, un'ascia → <ref corresp="lexicon_pelekys.html">πέλεκυς</ref> veniva usata per dare il colpo di grazia. Nella poesia il coltello sacrificale è talvolta indicato come una 'spada', ξίφος. Questo è frequente soprattutto in Euripide. In Alkestis 74 Thanatos vuole consegnare la protagonista al sacrificio (κατάρχεσθαι) tagliandole ciocche di capelli con una spada (ξίφει, 73-76; cf. Hom. Il. 3.271-273, 19.252-254, dove μάχαιρα è usato per questo scopo). In un'altra tragedia del poeta, Elektra, abbiamo la sinonimia σφαγίς-φάσγανον-ξίφος (E. El. 1142, 1222, 1225, vedi → <ref corresp="lexicon_sphagis.html">σφαγίς</ref>), usato per varietas stilistiche (vide etiam Eu. IT 27, 621, 880, 1190, 1459).</p>
                    <p>Incontriamo anche la machaira come strumento per tagliare la carne al di fuori di un contesto esplicitamente sacrificale (τέμνειν κατὰ μέλη: Pi. O. 1.49; σφάζειν: E. Ciclo. 242-243;</p>
                    <p>†καθαρπάζειν†: E. Ciclo. 403; τέμνειν D. 25.46), e nella commedia è un attributo frequente di cuochi, macellai e salumieri (Ar. Eq. 489, Ar. Pax 1017-1018, Alex. 174, vide etiam D. 25.46). Nel racconto omerico del giuramento, μάχαιρα era anche usato per tagliare il pelo dell'animale destinato al sacrificio commestibile (τέμνειν τρίχας: Hom. Il. 3.271-273, 19.252-254). L'usanza di mettere la machaira nel cesto κανοῦν durante il rito sacrificale ateniese ha fornito l'impulso per il concetto di sacrificio come "commedia dell'innocenza" (Burkert 1983; cfr. Parker 2011: 127-131, Graf 2012; criticamente sul concetto di Burkert: Naiden 2013: 9 e segg.), ha anche un ruolo importante nella teoria di Vernant, che lo vedeva come uno dei mezzi per spogliare la vittima dei segni dell'omicidio (φόνος) (per una rivalutazione critica delle teorie di Burkert e Vernant in termini di rappresentazioni vascolari, si veda: Pierce 1993).</p>
                    <p>La multifunzionalità della machaira è allusa da Aristotele nella Politica (Arist. Pol. 1252b), anche se in questo caso parla della machaira delfica, forse una specifica varietà di coltello (Aristotele, Politica 1252b). Il Μάχαιρα può anche essere stato usato per tagliare i capelli umani (in un contesto rituale: Hdt. 2.61; fuori dal contesto rituale: Ar. Ach. 849, Ephipp. 14), e due machaira incrociate formano delle forbici - μάχαιραι κουρίδες (Cratin. 37). Lo Pseudo-Aristotele (Ps.-Arist. Mir. 847a) e lo Pseudo-Plutarco (Ps.- Plu. Fluv. 10.5) citano una pietra nata sul monte Berekynthos chiamata machaira che fa impazzire chi la trova durante i misteri di Hekate (τῶν μυστερίων τῆς Ἑκάτης ἐπιτελουμένων ἐμμανὴς γίνεται). L'origine del nome non è chiara, e la spiegazione data dallo Pseudo-Plutarco che la pietra contiene ferro potrebbe essere secondaria.</p>                    
                </div>
                <div type="textpart" n="Storia">
                    <head>Storia</head>
                    <p>Nella spiegazione della parola μάχαιρα nel suo lessico, Esichio la equipara principalmente alla spada ξίφος. Anche il libro dei Suda lo considera come una specie di spada (σπάθη), presentando una descrizione in cui non c'è traccia di un contesto sacrificale - μάχαιρα è descritto lì dal punto di vista della storia dell'esercito romano e dell'interpretazione dei sogni con le spade* (http://P1). Incontriamo un fraintendimento della parola nello scoliasta Pindaro, che commenta così la morte di Neoptolemo, ucciso da una machaira durante una discussione sulla carne di un animale sacrificale (κρεῶν νιν ὑπὲρ μάχας ἔλασεν ἀντιτυχόντ ̓ ἀνὴρ μαχαίρᾳ, Pi. N. 7.42): "Dicono che quando Neoptolemos offriva il sacrificio, i Delfi portarono via i thymata, come è loro abitudine. E Neoptolemos, non potendo sopportarlo, li fermò. Ed essi, armati di spade (ξίφη ἔχοντας), lo misero a morte" (Scholia vetera in Pindari carmina, A. B. Drachmann, vol. III, p. 125, scholion 42a). Questa spiegazione è chiaramente sbagliata e mostra come a volte poco della realtà linguistica e cultuale del V secolo a.C. sia stata compresa dai greci tardo antichi.</p>
                    <p>Sembra certo che per Omero μάχαιρα non era ancora un'arma, anche se i guerrieri omerici la portavano con sé. Nell'Iliade, Patroklos lo usa per estrarre una punta di freccia dalla ferita di Euripilo (Hom. Il. 11. 844), il μάχαιρα pende anche accanto alla spada ξίφος alla cintura di Agamennone, che lo usa per tagliare il pelo degli animali destinati al sacrificio accompagnato dal giuramento (Ἀτρεΐδης δὲ ἐρυσσάμενος χείρεσσι μάχαιραν, ἥ οἱ πὰρ ξίφεος μέγα κουλεόν αἰὲν ἄωρτο, "E Atreides estrasse il coltello che aveva sempre accanto al grande fodero della sua spada", Hom. Il. 3.271-272, 19.252-253). Quando le gole degli animali devono essere tagliate dopo che le parole del giuramento sono state pronunciate, si usa per questo 'pant', che qui è probabilmente una metonimia di machairy: ἦ, καὶ ἀπὸ στομάχους animal τάμε νηλέϊ χαλκῷ ('disse e tagliò le gole [degli animali] con pant, che non conosce pietà', Hom. Il. 3.292, 19.266). Le machaires dorate erano anche indossate dai ragazzi del corteo danzante scolpito sullo scudo di Achille (Hom. Il. 18.597).</p>
                    <p>L'immagine che emerge dal poema omerico è confermata dalle rappresentazioni dei vasi. Come sostiene Gordon, μάχαιρα come arma hoplite prima del 530 a.C. non appare affatto su di essi, anche se appare nel contesto del sacrificio (cfr. Pierce 1993: 256). È solo dopo il 510 a.C. che le raffigurazioni della machaira del soldato appaiono in numero crescente sui vasi a figure rosse (Gordon 1958: 24, senza bibliografia).</p>
                    <p>La machaira come equipaggiamento dell'oplita greco appare anche in Erodoto (7.225), e il contesto - i soldati circondati di Leonida combattono con machairas, pugni e denti - può indicare che era ancora un'arma a cui si ricorreva solo come ultima risorsa. Sappiamo da Senofonte che i cavalieri della guardia avanzata di Dario avevano delle "machaires greche", il che indicherebbe l'esistenza di una variante utilitaria e militare di questo coltello al suo tempo (sulle machaires militari, vedi Gordon 1958). Il termine μάχαιρα è anche regolarmente applicato alle armi usate dai popoli orientali (Hdt 7.79, 7.89, 7.91, X. An. 4.6.26, 7.2.30, 7.4.16, X. Cyr. 1.2.13, 2.1.16, 2.3.10, 4.1.3, 4.5.58, 7.1.2, 7.1.33, 7.1.34, 7.1.37), il che naturalmente non significa che i Colchi, gli Egiziani o i sudditi del Grande Re combattessero con coltelli greci. Le realtà dell'esercito antico possono quindi essere viste come la fonte di confusioni successive, anche se va notato che le lame militari del tipo μάχαιρα non hanno mai guadagnato popolarità nel mondo greco (Gordon 1958: 25).</p>
                    <p>Catalogo delle occorrenze nel contesto del sacrificio o del pasto</p>
                    <p>1. coltello da macello: h Hom. 3.535, Esopo. 92.13 alliter, E. Cyc. 242 (macellazione di esseri umani), E. Supp. 1206, E. Fr. 143 = Ar. Th. 694, Hdt. 2.41, Ar. Pax 1017, Thphr. Fr. 18;</p>
                    <p>2. ~ per tagliare la carne: Pi. O. 1.49 (carne umana), Hdt. 2.41, E. Cyc. 403 (carne umana), Pherecr. 82, Ar. Eq. 489 (coltello da salsiccia), D. 25.46 (coltello da macellaio), Archestr. 31.5;</p>
                    <p>3. ~ per scuoiare un animale: Pi. P. 4.242;</p>
                    <p>4. ~ nel contesto generale del sacrificio: Pi. N. 7.42, Ar. Fr. 684, Ar. Pax 948, Pl.Com. 91;</p>
                    <p>5. ~ Ad altre azioni durante i giuramenti: Hom. Il. 3.271, 19.252, Hdt. 4.70;</p>
                    <p>6. ~ Delfico: Arist. Pol. 1252b.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            
            <div type="edition" xml:lang="en">
                <div type="textpart">
                    <p>μάχαιρα machaira, ας, subst. f.: large knife</p>                    
                </div>
                <div type="textpart" n="Etymology_and_morphology">
                    <head>Etymology and morphology</head>
                    <p>The morphology of the word indicates that it is a derivative of -ya- and as such can be reconstructed to the form *makhar-ya (Chantraine 1968: 673, Beekes 2010: 915), which suggests an affinity with the word μῆχαρ 'means, manner'. Their common element can be reconstructed to the form *meh2gh- and linked to the verb μάχεσθαι 'to fight'. Beekes, however, rejects this hypothesis (2010: 915, see also 916 and 950), postulating a pre-Greek origin of the word and linking it to μάγειρος 'butcher, cook'. The word has its pendant in the Hebrew mekērā 'sword', but it seems to be a Greek loan (Chantraine 1968: 673, Beekes 2010: 915). The Mycenaean form ma-ke-ra is interpreted as a personal name, although there has been a suggestion to see it as machaira (Diccionario Micénico, vol. I: 419, bibliography there).</p>                    
                </div>
                <div type="textpart" n="Construction_and_function">
                    <head>Construction and function</head>
                    <p>With the word μάχαιρα the Greeks referred to large, cutting-adapted (τέμνειν: cf. Hom. Il. 11.844, Democr. 302) knives with a slightly curved, single-edged blade (vide Gordon 1958: 25, fig. 2). They may have been made of bronze (cf. Hom. Il. 3.292, 19.266) or of iron (Daimachus 8c, cf. Booikidis, Strout 1997: 77 - blades of iron knives found among the bones of sacrificial animals, 6th century BC), which is why in the poetry in the descriptions of the sacrifice we often encounter the metonymic use of words meaning "bronze" (cf. Hom. Il. 3.292, 19.266) and "iron" (cf. Hom. Il. 23.30) in the sense of a knife. Their manufacture was carried out by special craftsmen, μαχαιροποιοί (D. 27.9) or μαχαιρουργοί (Demad. Fr. 75). The handles of the knives may have been made of ivory (D. 27.9, cf. also Theopomp.Com. 7: ἐλεφαντοκώπους ξιφομαχαίρας).</p>
                    <p>It seems certain that in the sacrificial ritual the μάχαιρα acted as a multifunctional tool. It was used to inflict a blow on an animal that was supposed to draw blood from it (σφάζειν: h Hom. 3.535; μαγειρικῶς σφάζειν: Ar. Pax 1017-8; τέμνειν σφάγια: E. Supp. 1196; τράχηλον τρίβειν: Aesop. 92.12 aliter), while later it was used for cutting meat (χρῆσθαι, in the context of spit and pot: Hdt. 2.41; διατέμνειν κρέας: Hdt. 2.41) and, probably, also for skinning the animal (ἐκτείνειν δέρμα: Pi. P. 4. 241-3, see also → <ref corresp="lexicon_kopis.html">κοπίς</ref>). Harder parts of the animal, such as bones, were cut with a cleaver → <ref corresp="lexicon_kopis.html">κοπίς</ref>. In the case of larger animals, such as oxen, an axe → <ref corresp="lexicon_pelekys.html">πέλεκυς</ref> was used to deliver the killing blow. In poetry the sacrificial knife is sometimes referred to as a 'sword', ξίφος. This is frequent especially in Euripides. In Alkestis 74 Thanatos wants to consign the title character to sacrifice (κατάρχεσθαι) by cutting strands of her hair with a sword (ξίφει, 73-76; cf. Hom. Il. 3.271-273, 19.252-254, where μάχαιρα is used for this purpose). In another of the poet's tragedies, Elektra, we have the synonymy σφαγίς-φάσγανον-ξίφος (E. El. 1142, 1222, 1225, see → <ref corresp="lexicon_sphagis.html">σφαγίς</ref>), used for stylistic varietas (vide etiam Eu. IT 27, 621, 880, 1190, 1459).</p>
                    <p>We also encounter the machaira as a tool for cutting meat outside an explicitly sacrificial context (τέμνειν κατὰ μέλη: Pi. O. 1.49; σφάζειν: E. Cyc. 242-243;</p>
                    <p>†καθαρπάζειν†: E. Cyc. 403; τέμνειν D. 25.46), and in comedy it is a frequent attribute of cooks, butchers and sausage-makers (Ar. Eq. 489, Ar. Pax 1017-1018, Alex. 174, vide etiam D. 25.46). In the Homeric account of the oath, μάχαιρα was also used to cut the hair of the animal intended for the commodious sacrifice (τέμνειν τρίχας: Hom. Il. 3.271-273, 19.252-254). The custom of placing the machaira in the κανοῦν basket during the Athenian sacrificial ritual provided the impetus for the concept of sacrifice as a 'comedy of innocence' (Burkert 1983; cf. Parker 2011: 127-131, Graf 2012; critically on Burkert's concept: Naiden 2013: 9 ff.), it also plays an important role in the theory of Vernant, who saw it as one of the means of stripping the victim of the hallmarks of murder (φόνος) (for a critical reevaluation of Burkert's and Vernant's theories in terms of vase representations, see: Pierce 1993).</p>
                    <p>The multifunctionality of the machaira is alluded to by Aristotle in the Politics (Arist. Pol. 1252b), although in this case he speaks of the Delphic machaira, perhaps a specific variety of knife (Aristotle, Politics 1252b). The Μάχαιρα may also have been used to cut human hair (in a ritual context: Hdt. 2.61; outside the ritual context: Ar. Ach. 849, Ephipp. 14), and two crossed machaira formed scissors - μάχαιραι κουρίδες (Cratin. 37). Pseudo-Aristotle (Ps.-Arist. Mir. 847a) and Pseudo-Plutarch (Ps.- Plu. Fluv. 10.5) mention a stone born on Mount Berekynthos called machaira which drives mad whoever finds it during the mysteries of Hekate (τῶν μυστερίων τῆς Ἑκάτης ἐπιτελουμένων ἐμμανὴς γίνεται). The origin of the name is not clear, and the explanation given by Pseudo-Plutarch that the stone contains iron may be secondary.</p>                           
                </div>
                <div type="textpart" n="History">
                    <head>History</head>
                    <p>In explaining the word μάχαιρα in his lexicon, Hesychius equates it primarily with the sword ξίφος. The book of Suda also regards it as a kind of sword (σπάθη), presenting a description in which there is no trace of a sacrificial context - μάχαιρα is described there from the perspective of the history of the Roman army and the interpretation of dreams starring swords* (http://P1). We encounter a misunderstanding of the word in the scholiast Pindar, who comments on the death of Neoptolemos, killed by a machaira during an argument over meat from a sacrificial animal, as follows (κρεῶν νιν ὑπὲρ μάχας ἔλασεν ἀντιτυχόντ ̓ ἀνὴρ μαχαίρᾳ, Pi. N. 7.42): "They say that when Neoptolemos was offering the sacrifice, the Delphians carried off the thymata, as is their custom. And Neoptolemos, not being able to bear it, stopped them. And they, armed with swords (ξίφη ἔχοντας), put him to death" (Scholia vetera in Pindari carmina, A. B. Drachmann, vol. III, p. 125, scholion 42a). This explanation is clearly wrong and shows how at times little of the linguistic and cultic reality of the fifth century BC was understood by the late antique Greeks.</p>
                    <p>It seems certain that for Homer μάχαιρα was not yet a weapon, although Homeric warriors carried it with them. In the Iliad, Patroklos uses it to extract an arrowhead from the wound of Euripylos (Hom. Il. 11. 844), the μάχαιρα also hangs beside the sword ξίφος at the belt of Agamemnon, who uses it to cut off the hair of the animals destined for the oath-accompanied sacrifice (Ἀτρεΐδης δὲ ἐρυσσάμενος χείρεσσι μάχαιραν, ἥ οἱ πὰρ ξίφεος μέγα κουλεόν αἰὲν ἄωρτο, "And Atreides drew the knife which he always had by the great scabbard of his sword", Hom. Il. 3.271-272, 19.252-253). When the throats of the animals have to be cut after the words of the oath have been spoken, 'pant' is used for this, which here is probably a metonymy of machairy: ἦ, καὶ ἀπὸ στομάχους animal τάμε νηλέϊ χαλκῷ ('he said and cut the throats [of the animals] with pant, which knows no mercy', Hom. Il. 3.292, 19.266). Gilded machaires were also worn by the boys in the dancing procession carved on the shield of Achilles (Hom. Il. 18.597).</p>
                    <p>The picture emerging from the Homeric poem is confirmed by the vase depictions. As Gordon argues, μάχαιρα as a hoplite weapon before 530 BC does not appear on them at all, although it does appear in the context of sacrifice (cf. Pierce 1993: 256). It is only after 510 BC that depictions of the soldier's machaira appear in increasing numbers on red-figure vases (Gordon 1958: 24, no bibliography).</p>
                    <p>The machaira as the equipment of the Greek hoplite also appears in Herodotus (7.225), and the context - Leonidas' surrounded soldiers fight with machairas, fists and teeth - may indicate that it was still a weapon that was only resorted to as a last resort. We know from Xenophon that the horsemen of Darius' advance guard had 'Greek machaires', which would indicate the existence of a utilitarian and military variant of this knife in his time (on military machaires, vide Gordon 1958). The term μάχαιρα is also regularly applied to weapons used by Eastern peoples (Hdt 7.79, 7.89, 7.91, X. An. 4.6.26, 7.2.30, 7.4.16, X. Cyr. 1.2.13, 2.1.16, 2.3.10, 4.1.3, 4.5.58, 7.1.2, 7.1.33, 7.1.34, 7.1.37), which of course does not mean that the Colchians, Egyptians or subjects of the Great King fought with Greek knives. The realities of the ancient military can therefore be seen as the source of later confusions, although it should be noted that military knife-blades of the μάχαιρα type never gained popularity in the Greek world (Gordon 1958: 25).</p>
                    <p>Catalogue of occurrences in the context of sacrifice or meal</p>
                    <p>1. slaughter knife: h Hom. 3.535, Aesop. 92.13 alliter, E. Cyc. 242 (slaughter of humans), E. Supp. 1206, E. Fr. 143 = Ar. Th. 694, Hdt. 2.41, Ar. Pax 1017, Thphr. Fr. 18;</p>
                    <p>2. ~ for cutting meat: Pi. O. 1.49 (human meat), Hdt. 2.41, E. Cyc. 403 (human meat), Pherecr. 82, Ar. Eq. 489 (sausage-knife), D. 25.46 (butcher's knife), Archestr. 31.5;</p>
                    <p>3. ~ for skinning an animal: Pi. P. 4.242;</p>
                    <p>4. ~ in the general context of sacrifice: Pi. N. 7.42, Ar. Fr. 684, Ar. Pax 948, Pl.Com. 91;</p>
                    <p>5. ~ To other actions during the oaths: Hom. Il. 3.271, 19.252, Hdt. 4.70;</p>
                    <p>6. ~ Delphic: Arist. Pol. 1252b.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            
            <div type="edition" xml:lang="pl">
                <div type="textpart">
                    <p>μάχαιρα machaira, ας, subst. f.: duży nóż</p>                    
                </div>
                <div type="textpart" n="Etymologia_i_morfologia">
                    <head>Etymologia i morfologia</head>
                    <p>Morfologia wyrazu wskazuje, że jest to derywat na -ya- i jako taki daje się rekonstruować do postaci *makhar-ya (Chantraine 1968: 673, Beekes 2010: 915), która sugeruje pokrewieństwo z wyrazem μῆχαρ „środek, sposób”. Ich wspólny pierwiastek rekonstruować można do postaci *meh2gh- i powiązać z czasownikiem μάχεσθαι „walczyć”. Beekes odrzuca jednak tę hipotezę (2010: 915, zob. też 916 i 950), postulując przedgreckie pochodzenie wyrazu i wiążąc go z μάγειρος „rzeźnik, kucharz”. Słowo ma swoje pendant w hebrajskim mekērā „miecz”, wydaje się jednak, że jest to grecka pożyczka (Chantraine 1968: 673, Beekes 2010: 915). Mykeńska forma ma-ke-ra interpretowana jest jako imię własne, chociaż pojawiła się sugestia, by widzieć w niej machairę (Diccionario Micénico, vol. I: 419, tam bibliografia).</p>                    
                </div>
                
                <div type="textpart" n="Budowa_i_funkcja">
                    <head>Budowa i funkcja</head>
                    <p>Słowem μάχαιρα Grecy określali duże, przystosowane do cięcia (τέμνειν: cf. Hom. Il. 11.844, Democr. 302) noże o lekko zakrzywionej, jednosiecznej głowni (vide Gordon 1958: 25, fig. 2). Mogły być one wykonane z brązu (cf. Hom. Il. 3.292, 19.266) albo z żelaza (Daimachus 8c, cf. Booikidis, Strout 1997: 77 – ostrza żelaznych noży znalezione wśród kości zwierząt ofiarnych, VI wiek p.n.e), dlatego w poezji w opisach ofiary często spotykamy się z metonimicznym użyciem słów oznacząjących „brąz” (cf. Hom. Il. 3.292, 19.266) i „żelazo” (cf. Hom. Il. 23.30) w znaczeniu noża. Ich wytwarzaniem zajmowali się specjalni rzemieślnicy, μαχαιροποιοί (D. 27.9) lub μαχαιρουργοί (Demad. Fr. 75). Uchwyty noży mogły być wykonane z kości słoniowej (D. 27.9, cf. też Theopomp.Com. 7: ἐλεφαντοκώπους ξιφομαχαίρας).</p>
                    <p>Wydaje się pewne, że w rytuale ofiarniczym μάχαιρα pełniła rolę wielofunkcyjnego narzędzia. Służyła do zadawania zwierzęciu ciosu, który miał wytoczyć zeń krew (σφάζειν: h Hom. 3.535; μαγειρικῶς σφάζειν: Ar. Pax 1017-8; τέμνειν σφάγια: E. Supp. 1196; τράχηλον τρίβειν: Aesop. 92.12 aliter), następnie zaś wykorzystywano ją do krojenia mięsa (χρῆσθαι, w kotekście rożna i garnka: Hdt. 2.41; διατέμνειν κρέας: Hdt. 2.41) i, prawdopodobnie, również skórowania zwierzęcia (ἐκτείνειν δέρμα: Pi. P. 4. 241-3, zob. też → <ref corresp="lexicon_kopis.html">κοπίς</ref>). Twardsze części zwierzęcia, jak np. kości, krojono przy pomocy tasaka → <ref corresp="lexicon_kopis.html">κοπίς</ref>. W przypadku większych zwierząt, takich jak woły, do zadania zabójczego ciosu służył topór → <ref corresp="lexicon_pelekys.html">πέλεκυς</ref>. W poezji ofiarniczy nóż bywa określany mianem „miecza”, ξίφος. Jest to częste zwłaszcza u Eurypidesa. W Alkestis 74 Thanatos chce przeznaczyć tytułową bohaterkę na ofiarę (κατάρχεσθαι), ścinając kosmyki jej włosów mieczem (ξίφει, 73-76; por. Hom. Il. 3.271-273, 19.252-254, gdzie do tego celu służy μάχαιρα). W innej tragedii poety, Elektrze, mamy do czynienia z synonimią σφαγίς-φάσγανον-ξίφος (E. El. 1142, 1222, 1225, zob. → <ref corresp="lexicon_sphagis.html">σφαγίς</ref>), zastosowaną dla uzyskania stylistycznej varietas (vide etiam Eu. IT 27, 621, 880, 1190, 1459).</p>
                    <p>Z machairą jako narzędziem do krojenia mięsa spotykamy się również poza kontekstem jednoznacznie ofiarniczym (τέμνειν κατὰ μέλη: Pi. O. 1.49; σφάζειν: E. Cyc. 242-243;</p>
                    <p>†καθαρπάζειν†: E. Cyc. 403; τέμνειν D. 25.46), a w komedii jest częstym atrybutem kucharzy, rzeźników i kiełbaśników (Ar. Eq. 489, Ar. Pax 1017-1018, Alex. 174, vide etiam D. 25.46). W homeryckim opisie przysięgi, μάχαιρα służyła też do obcinania włosów zwierzęcia przeznaczonego na towarszyszącą jej ofiarę (τέμνειν τρίχας: Hom. Il. 3.271-273, 19.252-254). Zwyczaj umieszczania machairy w koszu κανοῦν podczas ateńskiego rytuału ofiarniczego stanowił impuls dla koncepcji ofiary jako „komedii niewinności” (Burkert 1983; cf. Parker 2011: 127-131, Graf 2012; krytycznie o koncepcji Burkerta: Naiden 2013: 9 i n.), gra również ważną rolę w teorii Vernanta, który widział w nim jeden ze środków odbierających ofierze znamiona morderstwa (φόνος) (krytyczna reewaluacja teorii Burkerta i Vernanta pod kątem przedstawień wazowych: Pierce 1993).</p>
                    <p>Do wielofunkcyjności machairy nawiązuje Arystoteles w Polityce (Arist. Pol. 1252b), choć w tym wypadku mówi on o machairze delfickiej, być może specyficznej odmianie noża (Arystoteles, Polityka 1252b). Μάχαιρα mogła służyć też do obcinania ludzkich włosów (w kontekście rytualnym: Hdt. 2.61; poza kontekstem rytualnym: Ar. Ach. 849, Ephipp. 14), a dwie skrzyżowane machairy tworzyły nożyce – μάχαιραι κουρίδες (Cratin. 37). Pseudo-Arystoteles (<ref type="lit">Ps.-Arist. Mir. 847a</ref>) i Pseudo-Plutarch (Ps.-Plu. Fluv. 10.5) wzmiankują rodzący się na górze Berekynthos kamień nazywany machairą który doprowadza do szaleństwa tego, kto odnajdzie go podczas misteriów Hekate (τῶν μυστερίων τῆς Ἑκάτης ἐπιτελουμένων ἐμμανὴς γίνεται). Geneza nazwy nie jest jasna, a podane przez Pseudo-Plutarcha wyjaśnienie, że kamień zawiera żelazo, może być wtórne.</p>                    
                </div>
                
                <div type="textpart" n="Historia">
                    <head>Historia</head>
                    <p>Wyjaśniając słowo μάχαιρα w swoim leksykonie, Hezychiusz zrównuje ją w pierwszej kolejności z mieczem ξίφος. Również księga Sudy uważa ją za rodzaj miecza (σπάθη), przedstawiając opis w którym nie ma śladu kontekstu ofiarniczego – μάχαιρα opisana jest w nim z perspektywy historii armii rzymskiej i interpretacji snów z mieczami w roli głównej* (http://P1). Z błędnym rozumieniem słowa spotykamy się u scholiasty Pindara, który tak komentuje śmierć Neoptolemosa, zabitego machairą podczas kłótni o mięso z ofiarnego zwierzęcia (κρεῶν νιν ὑπὲρ μάχας ἔλασεν ἀντιτυχόντ ̓ ἀνὴρ μαχαίρᾳ, Pi. N. 7.42): „Mówią, że kiedy <persName type="myth" key="Neoptolemus">Neoptolemos</persName> składał ofiarę, Delfijczycy porwali thymata, jak mają w zwyczaju. Neoptolemos zaś, nie mogąc tego zdzierżyć, powstrzymywał ich. Oni zaś, uzbrojeni w miecze (ξίφη ἔχοντας), zgładzili go” (Scholia vetera in Pindari carmina, A. B. Drachmann, vol. III, s. 125, scholion 42a). Wyjaśnienie to jest w oczywisty sposób błędne i pokazuje, jak momentami niewiele z rzeczywistości językowej i kultowej piątego wieku p.n.e. rozumieli późnoantyczni Grecy.</p>
                    <p>Wydaje się pewne, że dla Homera μάχαιρα jeszcze bronią nie była, chociaż homeryccy wojownicy nosili ją przy sobie. W Iliadzie Patroklos używa jej, aby wydobyć grot strzały z rany Eurypylosa (Hom. Il. 11.844), μάχαιρα wisi również obok miecza ξίφος u pasa Agamemnona, który używa jej, by odcinać włosy zwierząt przeznaczonych na towarzyszącą przysiędze ofiarę (Ἀτρεΐδης δὲ ἐρυσσάμενος χείρεσσι μάχαιραν, ἥ οἱ πὰρ ξίφεος μέγα κουλεόν αἰὲν ἄωρτο, „Atryda zaś wyciągnął nóż, który miał zawsze przy wielkiej pochwie miecza”, Hom. Il. 3.271-272, 19.252-253). Kiedy po wypowiedzeniu słów przysięgi należy podciąć gardła zwierzętom, służy do tego „spiż”, który w tym miejscu jest prawdopodobnie metonimią machairy: ἦ, καὶ ἀπὸ στομάχους zwierzę τάμε νηλέϊ χαλκῷ („rzekł i gardła [zwierząt] ciął spiżem, który nie zna litości”, Hom. Il. 3.292, 19.266). Pozłacane machairy nosili też chłopcy z tanecznego korowodu wykutego na tarczy Achillesa (Hom. Il. 18.597).</p>
                    <p>Wyłaniający się z homerowego poematu obraz potwierdzają przedstawienia wazowe. Jak twierdzi Gordon, μάχαιρα jako broń hoplity przed rokiem 530 p.n.e. w ogóle na nich nie występuje, choć pojawia się w kontekście ofiary (cf. Pierce 1993: 256). Dopiero po roku 510 p.n.e. na wazach czerwonofigurowych pojawiają się coraz liczniejsze przedstawienia żołnierskiej machairy (Gordon 1958: 24, bez bibliografii).</p>
                    <p>Machaira jako wyposażenie greckiego hoplity pojawia się również u <persName key="Herodotus">Herodota</persName> (7.225), a kontekst – otoczeni żołnierze Leonidasa walczą machairami, pięściami i zębami – może wskazywać, że wciąż była to broń, po którą sięgano jedynie w ostateczności. Z Ksenofonta wiemy, że jeźdźcy ze straży przybocznej Dariusza mieli „greckie machairy”, co wskazywałoby na istnienie w jego czasach użytkowego i wojskowego wariantu tego noża (o wojskowych machairach, vide Gordon 1958). Terminem μάχαιρα określa się również regularnie broń używaną przez ludy wschodu (Hdt 7.79, 7.89, 7.91, X. An. 4.6.26, 7.2.30, 7.4.16, X. Cyr. 1.2.13, 2.1.16, 2.3.10, 4.1.3, 4.5.58, 7.1.2, 7.1.33, 7.1.34, 7.1.37), co nie znaczy oczywiście, że Kolchowie, Egipcjanie czy poddani Wielkiego Króla walczyli greckimi nożami. W realiach starożytnej wojskowości upatrywać więc można źródeł późniejszych konfuzji, choć zaznaczyć należy, że wojskowe nożo-miecze typu μάχαιρα nigdy nie zdobyły popularności w świecie greckim (Gordon 1958: 25).</p>
                    <p>Katalog wystąpień w kontekście ofiary lub posiłku</p>
                    <p>1. nóż do uboju: h Hom. 3.535, Aesop. 92.13 aliter, E. Cyc. 242 (ubój ludzi), E. Supp. 1206, E. Fr. 143 = Ar. Th. 694, Hdt. 2.41, Ar. Pax 1017, Thphr. Fr. 18;</p>
                    <p>2. ~ do krojenia mięsa: Pi. O. 1.49 (ludzkie mięso), <ref type="lit">Hdt. 2.41</ref>, E. Cyc. 403 (ludzkie mięso), Pherecr. 82, Ar. Eq. 489 (nóż kiełbaśnika), D. 25.46 (nóż rzeźnika), Archestr. 31.5;</p>
                    <p>3. ~ do skórowania zwierzęcia: Pi. P. 4.242;</p>
                    <p>4. ~ w ogólnym kontekście ofiary: Pi. N. 7.42, Ar. Fr. 684, Ar. Pax 948, Pl.Com. 91;</p>
                    <p>5. ~ do innych czynności podczas składania przysiąg: Hom. Il. 3.271, 19.252, Hdt. 4.70;</p>
                    <p>6. ~ delficki: Arist. Pol. 1252b.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            
            <div type="bibliography">
                <p>Beekes Robert, 2010, Etymological Dictionary of Greek, Leiden-Boston.</p>
                <p>Bookidis Nancy and Stroud Ronald S., 1997, „The Sanctuary of Demeter and Kore: Topography and Architecture”, Corinth, Vol. 18, No. 3.</p>
                <p>Burkert Walter, 1983, Homo Necans, Berkeley.</p>
                <p>Chantraine Pierre, 1968, Dictionnaire étymologique de la langue grecque, Paris Diccionario Micénico, 1985, vol. I, red. Francisco Aura Jorro, Madrid.</p>
                <p>Gordon, D.H., 1958, „14. Scimitars, Sabres and Falchions”, Man, Vol. 58, s. 22-27.</p>
                <p>Graf Fritz, 2012, „One generation after Burkert and Girard. Where are the great theories?”, Greek and Roman Animal Sacrifice. Ancient Victims, Modern Observers, red. Christopher A. Faraone, F. S. Naiden, s. 32-51, Cambridge.</p>
                <p>Naiden Fred, 2013 Smoke Signals for the Gods, Oxford Parker Robert, 2011, On Greek Religion, Oxford.</p>
                <p>Pierce Sarah, 1993, „Death, Revelry and 'Thysia'”, Classical Antiquity, Vol. 12, No. 2, s. 219-266.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
