<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">    
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Ἰουδαῖος / Ioudaios</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher><ref target="https://site.unibo.it/lares/">LARES Project</ref></publisher>
                <date when="2023"/>
                <idno type="filename">lexicon_ioudaios</idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digital document.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change when="2023-05-22" who="Iida_Huitula">encoded in XML</change>
                <change when="2023-05-22" who="Iida_Huitula">written contents</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="edition" xml:lang="en">
                <div type ="textpart" n="morphology">
                   <p><w lemma="Ἰουδαῖος"> Ἰουδαῖος</w> -α -ον adj. Jewish, Judean; subst. a Jew, a Judean, Judea; personal name; lat. <w lemma="Iudaeus">Iudaeus -a -um</w></p>
                   <p> <w lemma="Ἰουδαῖος"> ἡ Ἰουδαία / Ιούδα </w> subst. <placeName key="Iudaea">Judea (the region)</placeName>, lat.  <w lemma="Iudaea">Iuda / Iudaea </w></p>
                          <p>  <w lemma="Ἰουδαῖος"> Ἰουδαῖος</w> a personal name</p>
                    <p>a rare form:  <w lemma="Ἰουδαϊκός"> Ἰουδαϊκός -ή -όν</w> adj., lat.  <w lemma="Iudaicus"> Iudaicus -a -um</w></p>
                       <p>a rare derivant:  <w lemma="Ἰουδαϊσμός">ὁ Ἰουδαϊσμός</w> subst. Judaism, lat.  <w lemma="Iudaismus"> Iudaismus</w></p>
                </div>
                    
                <div type="textpart" n="etymology">
                    
                    <head>Etymology</head>
                    <p>From the Hebrew noun <foreign xml:lang= "he">ּדָה (y'huda)</foreign> which is the kingdom of Judah and its region, and a personal name. Occurs in the Hebrew bible 819 times (Liljeqvist 2010, 204).  Also the Hebrew adjective <foreign xml:lang= "he">יְהוּדִי(y'hudi)</foreign> meaning “of Judah”, especially “of the tribe of Judah”. Occurs in the Hebrew bible 76 times (Liljeqvist 2010, 204).  Closely related to the origins of Judaism.</p>  
                    <p>The Aramaic noun is  <foreign xml:lang= "ar">הוּד (y’hud)</foreign> and adjective <foreign xml:lang= "ar"> יְהוּדָי (y’hudai)</foreign> (Liljeqvist 2010, 585).  Probably the Greek word is loaned from Aramaic rather than Hebrew for the former was the official language of the area during Persian rule, and more widely used before  <persName key="Alexander_the_Great">Alexander’s</persName> conquest, and the Aramaic word also has the /ai/ element visible in the Greek. However, the Hebrew and Aramaic words are almost identical. </p>
                    <p>The Greek word family is originated from the place name, <placeName key="Iudaea">Judah</placeName> (Bauer 1988, Ἰουδαία), with which the form Ιούδα seemingly coincides. If loaned from the Hebrew noun, for the adjective an ending with a iota has been added, resulting as Ἰουδα-ῖος. If loaned from the Aramaic adjective, the Greek ending was added, resulting as Ἰουδαῖ-ος. A variant of the place name, ἡ Ἰουδαία, is derived from the Greek adjective. The rare adjectival variant <w lemma="Ἰουδαϊκός"> Ἰουδαϊκός</w> bears the same meaning. This form may be modelled on adjectives like <w lemma="Ἑλληνικός"> Ἑλληνικός</w> and <w lemma="Ῥωμαϊκός">Ῥωμαϊκός</w> (derived respectively from <w lemma="Ἕλλην">Ἕλλην</w> and <w lemma="Ῥωμαῖος">Ῥωμαῖος</w>). However, <w lemma="Ἰουδαϊκός">Ἰουδαϊκός</w> is very rare and its meaning seems to be the same as <w lemma="Ἰουδαῖος">Ἰουδαῖος</w>, which some authors use of people, and <w lemma="Ἰουδαϊκός">Ἰουδαϊκός</w> of things. The substantive <w lemma="Ἰουδαϊσμός">ὁ Ἰουδαϊσμός</w> (Judaism) is very rare in Antiquity, appearing during the Hellenistic era, formed in the same way as <w lemma="Ἑλληνισμός">Ἑλληνισμός</w> (Hellenism). </p>
                    <p>The Latin word <w lemma="Iudaeus">Iudaeus</w> is loaned from Greek and attested since <persName key="Cicero">Cicero</persName> (A. Ernout, A. Meillet 1959, iudaeus).  The region is either <w lemma="Iudaea">Iuda or Iudaea</w> (Maltby 1991, Iudaea). Also the vartiant <w lemma="Iudaicus">Iudaicus</w> exists. In later Latin, the term <w lemma="Iudaismus">Iudaismus</w> is sometimes found in reference to Judaism.</p>
                    <p>As a personal name,<w lemma="Ἰουδαῖος"> Ἰουδαῖος</w> is a variant of  <w lemma="Ἰούδας"> Judas</w> (Williams 1997, 250). </p>
                    <p>The rare verb <w lemma="Ἰουδαΐζω"> Ἰουδαΐζω</w>, in Lat. <w lemma="Iudaizo">Iudaizo</w>, has been derived from the adjective, as well as the rare adverb <w lemma="Ἰουδαῖος">Ἰουδαϊκῶς</w>, in Lat. <w lemma="Iudaea">Ioudaice</w>.</p>                  
                </div>
            </div>
            
            <div type="edition" xml:lang="en">
                <div type="textpart" n="testimonies">
                    <head>Testimonies</head>
                    <p>The word has two main meanings: it refers both to the people of the region and to the religion, hence Judean, Jewish and Jew. Remarkably, these are not the same, for all Judeans were not Jews and vice versa, but all the meanings are part of the same semantic range of the word. The exact meaning in each occurrence depends on the context and is sometimes questionable. More precisely, the meaning can be divided into four parts: geographical, ethnic, religious and political, and the meaning might include several of these aspects. In English, there are two possible words: Jew (adj. Jewish) and Judean, which emphasize the religious and geographical aspects. </p>
                        <p>For the discussion, I have chosen a wide range of different texts and authors both in Greek and Latin, who represent different genres and religious affiliations, including epigraphical and papyrological documents. The time range is from the 3rd century BCE to the early 5th century CE and the texts are composed all around the Mediterranean. The objective is to give an overview of the different uses of the words in different contexts.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="italic">Inscriptions</hi></p>
                    <p>In the inscription <ref type="ins">IJudO I Ach 45 </ref>(<placeName key="Oropos">Oropus</placeName>, Amphiareion, 300—250 BCE.), which combines a manumission and a dedication in one stele, the dedicator, a freedman, is <ref type="ins">Μόσχος Μοσχίωνος <w lemma="Ἰουδαῖος"> Ἰουδαῖος</w></ref> (r. 11). The text is remarkably distinct: it is the earliest Greek inscription that uses the word <w lemma="Ἰουδαῖος"> Ἰουδαῖος</w> (Cohen 1999, 96), it is the only manumission from the Amfiareion (IJudO I p. 178), the only Jewish/Judean inscription from Oropos, the only text from Antiquity that describes a Jew making an incubation (IJudO I p. 179 and Panayotov 2004, 183) and it also describes a Jew/Judean having a religious experience that includes Greek gods.</p>
                    <p> In this text people are described with three words: their personal name, father’s name and place of origin, for example <ref type="ins">Ἀθηνόδωρος Μνασικῶντος Ὠρώπιος</ref> (r. 7—8). In <ref type="ins"> the sacred law of Oropos</ref> name and city of the people committing an incubation are told to be written down.1 In the Delphoi manumissions this is not the case, place of origin being mentioned in half of the texts (Hopkins 1978, 139). Otherwise the manumission of Moskhos is notably similar with the later Delphoi manumissions(IJudO I p. 178—179).  Leipziger, Gibson, Williams and Schürer think that the term  <w lemma="Ἰουδαῖος">Ἰουδαῖος</w> means here “Jewish” (Leipziger 2021, 16; Gibson 1991, 67; Williams 1997, 250, 255 and App.1; and Schürer 1973, 65).</p>
                  
                    <p>There are three manumission documents from <placeName key ="Delphi">Delphi</placeName> that use the word discussed here. The first one is <ref type="ins"> IJudO I Ach 42</ref> (Delphi, the Polygonal Wall of the Temple of Apollo, 163/2 BCE?): <ref type="ins"> ὄνομα  <w lemma="Ἰουδαῖος">Ἰουδαῖος</w> τὸ γένος  <w lemma="Ἰουδαῖος">Ἰουδαῖον</w></ref>. Here we have a person called Ioudaios who is manumitted. It is noteworthy that usually when a slave is named like this, it refers to their ethnicity instead of religion (IJudO I p. 170; the examples are Κύπριος τὸ γένος Κύπριον and Λίβυς γένος Λίβυς). The second text, <ref type="ins">IJudO I Ach 43</ref> (Delphi, the Polygonal Wall of the Temple of Apollo, 158/7 BCE), is similar to the first one: <ref type="ins">ὀνόματα Ἀντιγόνα τὸ γένος  <w lemma="Ἰουδαῖος">Ἰουδαίαν</w></ref>.>2 In the third case, <ref type="ins">IJudO I Ach 44</ref> (Delphi, the terrace of the Treasury of the Athenians, 2.—1. century BCE), we have a person called Ioudaios who is the manumitter, not the slave: <ref type="ins"> <w lemma="Ἰουδαῖος">Ἰουδαῖος</w> Πινδάρου</ref>, his name occuring in the text several times. The general opinion seems to be that these three people, i.e. the ex-slaves Ioudaios and Antigona and the slave owner Ioudaios, are Jews <note n="3" anchored="true">. IJudO I editors, see the texts in the corpus; Frey 1975, 512—513; Panayotov 2004, 175—176; Cohen 1999, 98; Gibson 1991, 68—69. Gibson says ”of jewish origin”; Schürer 1973, 65; Gruen 2016, 125; Williams 1997, 250 and App.1.</note>. However, Schürer thinks that Ioudaios the manumitter’s Jewishness is uncertain, because he does not take the name as a certain indicator of one’s Jewishness (Schürer 1973, 65).</p>
                    <p>In three or four manumission documents (<ref type="ins"> IJudO I BS 5-7, no. 9</ref> is very fragmentary) from the <placeName key= "Black_Sea">Black sea</placeName>, the community (synagogue) of Jews guarantees the manumission. In <ref type="ins"> BS 5</ref> (<placeName key= "Panticapaeum">Panticapaeum</placeName>, 81 CE) the expression is: <ref type="ins">συνεπινευςάντων…τῆς συναγογῆς τῶν Ἰουδαῖων </ref>(with the community of the Jews providing a joint guardianship). In this document the manumission is said to be done in the prayer house, which supports the religious meaning of Ἰουδαῖος.</p>
                
                    <p>In <placeName key ="Egypt">Egypt</placeName>, the word was in use since Hellenistic times. For example in the dedication <ref type="ins">JIGRE 22</ref> (246—221 BCE, Schedia (Nashwa)) <ref type="ins"> <w lemma="Ἰουδαῖος">οἱ Ἰουδαῖοι</w></ref> dedicate a proseuche in behalf of the Ptolemies. Here the meaning is clearly religious, Jews. Similarily in <ref type="ins">JIGRE 24</ref> (140—116 BCE, Xenephyris), <ref type="ins">25</ref> (140—116 BCE, Nitriai), <ref type="ins">27</ref> (2. or 1. cent. BCE, Athribis) and <ref type="ins">117</ref> (246—221 BCE, Arsinoe-Crocodilopolis).</p>
                
                    <p>The word is used also in later times in both meanings. In the epitaph <ref type="ins">JIWE I 188</ref>  (<placeName key ="Villamesías">Villamesías</placeName>, <placeName key= "Lusitania">Lusitania</placeName>, <placeName key ="Hispania">Spain</placeName>, 1.—3. cent. CE) the deceased is <ref type="ins">Alucius Roscius Cai libertus --  <w lemma="Iudeus">Iudeus</w></ref>, a Jew. The inscription <ref type="ins">IJudO II 40</ref> from <placeName key ="Smyrna">Smyrna</placeName> (list of donors, c. 120 CE) mentions<ref type="ins"> <w lemma="Ἰουδαῖος">οἱ ποτὲ Ἰουδαῖοι</w> </ref>, which Kraabel thinks for semantic reasons means former Judeans and current Smyrnans, not former Jews (Kraabel 1982, 455), but Margaret Williams argues that ποτέ is never used that way in geographical expressions, in which case the meaning would be religious, “former Jews” (Williams 1997, 252). In the epitaph <ref type="ins">JIWE II 567</ref> (city of <placeName key ="Rome">Rome</placeName>, exact location unknown, 3.—4. cent. CE) the deceased is described as follows: <ref type="ins">ἐνθάδε κεῖτη Κυιανος  <w lemma="Ἰουδαῖος">Ἰουδαῖος</w></ref>. There is also a menorah. Here the editor suggests that  <w lemma="Ἰουδαῖος">Ἰουδαῖος</w> means ”Jew” and the name might be Quirinus. The same applies to <ref type="ins">JIWE II 233</ref> (epitaph, Vigna Randanini, <placeName key ="Rome">Rome</placeName>, 3—4. cent. CE) where the deceased is <ref type="ins">Marcia Bona  <w lemma="Iudaeus">Iudea</w></ref> and the stone also has a menorah, which supports the religious meaning. In the epitaph <ref type="ins">IJudO I Ach 40</ref> from <placeName key= "Pireus">Piraeus</placeName>, date unknown, the text reads: <ref type="ins">Δημήτριος Δημητρίου Εἰουδαῖος </ref>(Demetrius son of Demetrius, a Jew).</p>
                
                    <p>The epitaph <ref type="ins">I.J.Afr. 71</ref> (2. cent. CE, Cirta, <placeName key ="Numidia">Numidia</placeName>) reads: <ref type="ins">D(is) M(anibus) Iuliae Victoriae <w lemma="Iudaea">[Iu]deae</w></ref>. And the epitaph <ref type="ins">IJudO I Pan 4</ref> (2.—3. cent. CE., Siklós, Pannonia): <ref type="ins">D(is) M(anibus)Septimiae Mariae <w lemma="Iudaea">Iudaeae</w></ref>. Both Christians and Jews used the DM formula (Williams 1997, 253; She also takes Iulia from Cirta to be Jewish, 260). Kraemer brings up the idea that Maria herself did not have to be Jewish, but her parents gave her a Jewish name because they were interested in Judaism admiring it and thus included Iudeus to their child’s name (Kraemer 1989, 49). This theory has been criticised for making difference between ”real” Jews and people merely interested in Judaism is practically impossible (Van der Horst 1991, 70—71). Additionally, the editors do not agree with the idea of Maria’s trinomina, because her parent’s names only have two parts (IJudO I, p. 16).</p>
                        
                    <p>In the votive inscription <ref type="ins">CIL V 4221</ref> (2. cent. CE, <placeName key ="Brixia"> Brixia</placeName>, <placeName key = "Lombardia">Lombardia)</placeName> the donor describes herself as “Juda”: <ref type="ins">Iunonibus Annia L(ucii) l(iberta) <w lemma="Iudaea">Iuda</w> pro suis v(otum) s(olvit)</ref>. ). Kraemer suggests that Annia had converted to Judaism, polytheism being a remnant of her former religious practises (Kraemer 1989, 42). Solin, on the other hand, proposes an alternative reading: Iuda might have been a mistake, the intended word maybe having being Iulia. He also points out that Iuda was a male name, whereas Annia was a woman (Solin 1983, 743). </p>
                    <p> In the <placeName key ="Dalmatia" >Dalmatian</placeName> funarary inscription <ref type="ins">IJudO I Dal 3</ref> (4. cent. CE, <placeName key= "Salonae">Salonae </placeName>) a distinction is made between Romans, Jews and Christians: <ref type="ins">Romani sive <w lemma="Iudaeus">Iudei</w> vel Crissiani</ref>. Here <w lemma="Iudaeus">Iud(a)eus</w> refers to a religious group and even though in administrative sense Jewishness is not an opposite of Roman, in religious and cultural sense it here is. The term is also used to describe synagoues, for example <ref type="ins">IJudO II 157</ref> (epitaph, dating uncertain,Pargoire, Nikomedeia, <placeName key= "Bithynia">Bithynia</placeName>): <ref type="ins"> τῇ συναγογῇ <w lemma="Ἰουδαῖος">τῶν Ἰουδέων</w></ref>. Maybe also in <ref type="ins">JIWE II 18</ref> (Castel Porziano, <placeName key ="Ostia">Ostia</placeName>, 2nd cent. CE) which perhaps reads <ref type="ins">[synagoga (?)]<w lemma="Iudaeus"> Iudeorum</w></ref>. In the votive inscription <ref type="ins">IJudO I Pan 3</ref> (Dunapentele, <placeName key= "Pannonia">Pannonia</placeName>, 233–235 CE) the votive is made to the <persName type= "divine" key="Deus_Aeternus">Deus Aeternus</persName> in behalf of the emperor, the donor’s name beginning Spondill*, and he is <ref type="ins"> a synag(oga) Ioudeor(um)</ref> (from the Jewish synagogue), the last word being outside frame of tabula ansata.</p>
                
                    <p>There is one inscription where the meaning cannot be geographical. In a funerary inscription from <placeName key ="Rome">Rome</placeName> (3.—4. cent. CE) the deceased is <ref type="ins">Ἀμμιὰς <w lemma="Ἰουδαῖος"> Ἰουδέα</w> ἀπὸ Λαοδικίας </ref><ref type="ins">(CIJ 296)</ref>. For there is no such town as Laodikea in  <placeName key ="Iudaea">Judea</placeName>, the word here must have a religious meaning (Williams 1997, 251 and App. 1 no. 6). Silmilarily in instances where another geographical place is mentioned the meaning of Ἰουδαῖος is more likely religious, for example in the epitaph  <ref type="ins">IJudO I Dal 2</ref> (Senia, <placeName key ="Dalmatia">Dalmatia</placeName>, 3.–4. cent. CE) the deceased is <ref type="ins">Ἀὺρηλιους Διονυσιους Ἰουδεους Τιβεριηνσις</ref> (Aurelius Dionysios, a Jew from Tiberias). </p>
                    
                    <p>Notes</p>
                    <p>1) The sacred law is <ref type="ins">I. Oropos 277</ref> and this commandment is on r. 40—41. The law dates c. 386—373 BCE which makes it older than the Moskhos inscription. About the text see Renberg 2016, 275.</p>
                    <p>2) The word ὀνόματα is in plural, because Antigona is manumitted with her daughters, Theodora and Dorothea. The children are not part of the discussion here because they are not described with the term Ἰουδαῖος.</p>
                    
                    
                    
                    <p><hi rend="italic">Papyri</hi></p>
                <p>Along with the geographical, ethnic and religious meanings, the word has a military aspect, apparent especially in papyri. During Hellenistic times, people described as Ἰουδαῖοι served in armies, which had troops of foreign origin, like Thessalians, Macedonians and Persians, under both Ptolemies and Seleucids (C.P. Jud. I, p. 11—12).</p>
                    <p> <persName key= "Josephus">Josephus</persName> describes the men in Ptolemies’ army in <ref type="lit"><ref corresp= "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=J.+AJ+12.7&amp;fromdoc=Perseus%3Atext%3A1999.01.0145"> AJ 12.7-8</ref> </ref><ref corresp = "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=Perseus%3Atext%3A1999.01.0146%3Abook%3D12 &quot;"> saying</ref> that they were gathered from around Judaea, Jerusalem, Samaria and Gerizim, but not calling them Ἰουδαῖοι. However, he brings up the incident of <persName key = "Alexander_the_Great">Alexander</persName> and the Jewish high priest in <placeName key= "Jerusalem">Jerusalem</placeName>, described by himself in <ref type="lit"><ref corresp= "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=J.+AJ+11.318&amp;fromdoc=Perseus%3Atext%3A1999.01.0145 ">AJ 11.318</ref></ref>, <ref corresp = "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=Perseus%3Atext%3A1999.01.0146%3Abook%3D11 ">where</ref> the high priest keeps his promise not to fight Dareius despite Alexander’s request of support. By connecting the gathering of the Ptolemaic army with the high priest Josephus implies that the people were the same: Jews. The meaning in papyri is more nuanced that Josephus lets understand. The national designations changed when a person was moved from one unit to another, because of which the term Ἰουδαῖος may refer rather to the persons position in the army and the army’s structure than religion (C.P.Jud. I, p. 13—14).</p>
                
                    <p>For example, in <ref type="pap">C. P. Jud. I 18</ref> (deed of renunciation, 260 BCE, Phebichis/Herakleopolites) the other party of the quarrel is: <ref type="pap">συγγραφὴ … καὶ Άλεξάνδρου τοῦ Άνδρονίκου Ἰουδαίου</ref> (writing of Alexander son of Andronikos, Ἰουδαῖος) and as the editors note, the witnesses are of Greek origin. The only religious part of the text is the dating in the beginning which includes deified rulers, thus there is no internal reason to understand Ἰουδαῖος in a religious sense. Yet “Judean” is also problematic for the person might have lived in Egypt for a long time, which on the other hand does apply to the other national designations as well, such as “Macedonian”. The religious and geographical meanings both being problematic, the ethic meaning seems the most plausible, with an emphasis on geography rather than religion, for the designations are based on region, not religion. Hence, I suggest we translate Ἰουδαῖος as “Judean” in Hellenistic military contexts keeping in mind that the people might have never actually been to Judea. To give another example of the same kind, in <ref type="pap">C. P. Jud. I 19</ref> (trial document, 226 BCE, Krokodilopolis / <placeName key="Fayum">Fayum</placeName>) the parties are described:<ref type="pap"> Δωςίθεος … Ἰουδαῖος τῆς ἐπιγονῆς Ἡρακλείαι Διοσδότου Ἰουδαίαι </ref>(Dositheos son of… Judean of the Epigone, to Herakleia daugher of Diosdotos, Jewess). In Herakleia’s case the meaning is more difficult to define, for she was not in the army herself but the use of the term may imply her being close to it by family connections. Calling her Judean seems safer than supposing her religion in a context that has no religious implications, but her being from Judea is unlikely as well. Thus, the meaning is highly debatable, but her being Jewish seems more probable than Judean, for as well known, there were significant Jewish communities in the area. </p>
                    <p>The term also appears outside military context. <ref type="pap">C. P. Jud. I 8</ref> is a fragment of an account (Philadelphia / <placeName key="Fayum">Fayum</placeName>, 256 BCE) and reads: <ref type="pap">Ἀντιγόνης Ἰουδαῖος κε(ράμια) κη </ref>(Antigones the Jew, 28 jars). The context does not allow understanding the nuances of the meaning and neither translation, Jew nor Judean, can be strongly defended based on the text alone, like in the former case of Herakleia, but Jewish seems more probable. Similarly, in one of the letters from the Zenon archive (<ref type="lit">C. P. Jud. I 9</ref> = P. Edg. 108, 253 BCE, Philadelphia / <placeName key="Fayum">Fayum</placeName>), Zenon tells Krotos to get wool from Pasis (a): <ref type="pap">παρὰ Πάσιτος τοῦ Ἰουδαίου</ref> (from Pasis the Jew) and Pasis also receives corn (b): <ref type="pap">Πάσιτι Ἰουδαίω</ref> (to Pasis the Jew). In the petition <ref type="pap">C. P. Jud. I 38</ref> (Krokodilopolis / Fayum, 218 BCE), which concerns a purchase of wool, the petitioner and a wool-merchant Harmiysis writes to the king complaining: <ref type="pap">ἀδικοῦμαι ὑπὸ Σεῶτος Ίουδαίου τῶν κατοικούντων έν Ἀλαβανθίδι </ref>(I am being wronged by Seos, a Jew living in Alabanthis).</p>
                
                    
                    <p><hi rend="italic">Literary sources</hi></p>
                <p>   In the <ref type="lit"><ref corresp="https://www.septuagint.bible/1-maccabees"> 1st Maccabees</ref></ref> (c. 1. cent. BCE), we can divide three major groups in the region: Jews (the rebels, Israelites), the enemies (officials) and a more ambiguous group of the “bad Jews” (Jews but not rebels) and other inhabitants of the region whose religious feelings are unclear, Judeans. The author of the 1st Maccabees usually refers to the religious group using the word Israel and to the region as <placeName key = "Judaea">Judah</placeName>. Hence here Ἰουδαῖος usually but not always refers the region instead of religion.</p>
                    <p>  For the bad Jews, <ref type="lit">1. Macc. 1:11</ref> says <ref type="lit">Εν ταῖς ἡμέραις ἐκείναις ἐξῆλθον ἐξ <placeName key="Israel">᾿Ισραὴλ</placeName> υἱοὶ παράνομοι καὶ ἀνέπεισαν πολλοὺς-- </ref> (<ref corresp="https://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1-Maccabees-Chapter-1/ ">KJV</ref>: In those days went there out of Israel wicked men, who persuaded many) and 1:15 <ref type="lit">καὶ ἐποίησαν ἑαυτοῖς ἀκροβυστίας καὶ ἀπέστησαν ἀπὸ διαθήκης ἁγίας καὶ ἐζευγίσθησαν τοῖς ἔθνεσι καὶ ἐπράθησαν τοῦ ποιῆσαι τὸ πονηρόν </ref>(KJV: And made themselves uncircumcised, and forsook the holy covenant, and joined themselves to the heathen, and were sold to do mischief). Also 1:43: <quote>καὶ πολλοὶ ἀπὸ ᾿Ισραὴλ εὐδόκησαν τῇ λατρείᾳ αὐτοῦ καὶ ἔθυσαν τοῖς εἰδώλοις καὶ ἐβεβήλωσαν τὸ σάββατον</quote> (KJV: Yea, many also of the Israelites consented to his religion, and sacrificed unto idols, and profaned the sabbath). </p>
                    <p> The rebels are described <ref type="lit">τότε συνήχθησαν πρὸς αὐτοὺς συναγωγὴ ῾Ασιδαίων, ἰσχυροὶ δυνάμει ἀπὸ <placeName key="Israel">᾿Ισραὴλ</placeName>, πᾶς ὁ ἑκουσιαζόμενος τῷ νόμῳ· </ref>(2:42) (KJV: Then came there unto him a company of Assideans who were mighty men of Israel, even all such as were voluntarily devoted unto the law). Notably the word Ἰουδαῖος is not used, instead the word used to refer to the religion is Israel. There are other expressions too, such as <quote>τὸ γένος ᾿Ιακώβ </quote> (5:2) (the offspring of <persName type="Jacob" key="bible">Jacob</persName>). The Israel vocabulary is used also for the “bad Jews”: <ref type="lit">πάντες ἄνδρες ἄνομοι καὶ ἀσεβεῖς ἐξ <placeName key= "Israel">᾿Ισραήλ</placeName></ref> (7:5) (KJV: all the wicked and ungodly men of Israel). </p>
                    <p> In the same work, the meaning Judea is used: 1:29 says <ref type="lit">εἰς τὰς πόλεις ᾿Ιούδα</ref> (to the cities of Judah). The next passage<ref type="lit"> (1:30)</ref> talks about Jerusalem and the inhabitants killed there are the people from Israel: <quote>λαὸν πολὺν ἐξ <placeName key="Israel">᾿Ισραήλ</placeName></quote> (lots of people from Israel). Similarly, Jerusalem and cities of Judah are mentioned: <ref type="lit"><placeName key= "Jerusalem">εἰς ῾Ιερουσαλὴμ</placeName> καὶ τὰς πόλεις ᾿Ιούδα </ref>(1:44) (to Jerusalem and to the cities of Judah). </p>
                    <p>  A use of Ἰουδαῖος referring to the rebels is 8:20, which says<ref type="lit"> ᾿Ιούδας ὁ Μακκαβαῖος καὶ οἱ ἀδελφοὶ αὐτοῦ καὶ τὸ πλῆθος τῶν ᾿Ιουδαίων </ref>(KJV: Judas Maccabeus with his brethren, and the people of the Jews). The meaning here is ambiguous for the distinctive feature of the rebels is their religious ideas but on the other hand the context is a speech to the Romans to get support. We have similar uses in 12:3<ref type="lit"> ᾿Ιωνάθαν ὁ ἀρχιερεὺς καὶ τὸ ἔθνος τῶν ᾿Ιουδαίων </ref>(KJV: Jonathan the high priest, and the people of the Jews) and 12:6 <ref type="lit">᾿Ιωνάθαν ἀρχιερεὺς καὶ ἡ γερουσία τοῦ ἔθνους καὶ οἱ ἱερεῖς καὶ ὁ λοιπὸς δῆμος τῶν ᾿Ιουδαίων </ref>(KJV: Jonathan the high priest, and the elders of the nation, and the priests, and the other of the Jews). Representing all Judeans as a unanimous group and as rebels is possibly a rhetoric choice. Speaking of Simon, 13:42 reads: <ref type="lit"> ὁ λαὸς ᾿Ισραὴλ -- ἐπὶ Σίμωνος ἀρχιερέως μεγάλου καὶ στρατηγοῦ καὶ ἡγουμένου ᾿Ιουδαίων</ref> (KJV: Then the people of Israel -- In the first year of Simon the high priest, the governor and leader of the Jews). Here there is in the same sentence the people of Israel and Simon, the leader of οἱ Ἰουδαῖοι. Similarly,14:47: <ref type="lit">--Σίμων -- στρατηγὸς καὶ ἐθνάρχης τῶν ᾿Ιουδαίων </ref>(KJV: Simon -- captain and governor of the Jews). The meaning of ᾿Ιουδαῖος here remains questionable, but the context does seem official and Simon the leader of the whole area, therefore the meaning would be Judeans, including Jews. </p>
                    <p> Notably, in 2:23 there’s an <ref type="lit">ἀνὴρ ᾿Ιουδαῖος </ref>(KJV: one of the Jews) who comes to sacrifice at the altar of Modein against the Maccabees’ will. The strong reaction of the Maccabees indicates that he was not only Judean but also a Jew. Also, the camp of the rebels is described using ᾿Ιουδαῖος: <ref type="lit">ἐπὶ τὴν παρεμβολὴν τῶν ᾿Ιουδαίων </ref>(4:2) (KJV: in upon the camp of the Jews). Speaking of the camp it is clear that the people are Jews, the rebels, not just any Judeans. </p>
                
                    <p>  In the <ref type="lit"><ref corresp="https://www.septuagint.bible/2-maccabees">2nd Maccabees</ref></ref> (c. 1. cent. BCE) describing the content of the book, the author tells that it’s about people of  Ἰουδαϊσμός, who came to control the land even though they were few: 2:21 <ref type="lit">--ὥστε τὴν ὅλην χώραν ὀλίγους ὄντας λεηλατεῖν</ref>. In this book, the people in Judaism are systematically called Ἰουδαῖος, which is notably different from the 1st Maccabees. The first book was originally written in Hebrew by a Judean whereas the Second in Greek by a Diaspora Jew (Schwartz 2014, 12), which explains the different uses of the words.</p>
                    <p>  οἱ Ἰουδαῖοι were a minority in <placeName key ="Jaffa_Joppe">Jaffa (Joppe)</placeName>: <ref type="lit">τοὺς σὺν αὐτοῖς οἰκοῦντας Ἰουδαίους</ref> (12:3) (KJV: the Jews that dwelt among them), also in <placeName key ="Jamnia">Jamnia</placeName> (12:8). Here οἱ Ἰουδαῖοι are Jews, representatives of certain habits and religious ideas, not all Judeans. 8:9 <ref type="lit">τὸ σύμπαν τῶν ᾿Ιουδαίων – γένος </ref>(KJV: the whole generation of the Jews) is about the Jewish nation/people, whom Nikanor was sent to destroy. The object is the rebels, not the whole population. In 8:10 <ref type="lit">ἐκ τῆς τῶν ᾿Ιουδαίων αἰχμαλωσίας </ref>there are Jewish captives. The war is fought against the rebels and <w lemma = "παντοκράτωρ">παντοκράτωρ</w> is said to revenge for them so we are talking about Jews. In the next sentence the same captives are referred as <ref type="lit">ἐπ᾿ ἀγορασμὸν ᾿Ιουδαϊκῶν σωμάτων </ref> (KJV: a sale of the captive Jews). The two adjectives Ἰουδαῖος and Ἰουδαϊκός seem to be synonyms and the latter is used for things, the bodies, and the former for people, captives.  8:36 says <ref type="lit"> ὑπέρμαχον ἔχειν τὸν <w lemma="θεός">Θεὸν</w> τοὺς ᾿Ιουδαίους </ref> (KJV: 36 the Jews had <persName type= "divine" key= "God">God</persName> to fight for them). Here we have a religious context: οἱ Ἰουδαῖοι are the rebels and they are said to have a protector-god, which emphasizes the religiousness of the group. Passage 8:1 <ref type="lit">ἐν τῷ ᾿Ιουδαϊσμῷ </ref>describes the rebels, who are “in Judaism” (David Schwartz arguments that Ἰουδαϊσμός here means indeed the religion, Judaism; Schwartz 2014, 7—8).</p>
                    <p>   Another use of Ἰουδαϊκός is in 13:21 <ref type="lit">Ρόδοκος ἐκ τῆς ᾿Ιουδαϊκῆς</ref> (Rodokos of the Jews). In this chapter the rebels (the followers of Judas) are οἱ Ἰουδαῖοι, for example 13:18 <ref type="lit">τῶν ᾿Ιουδαίων εὐτολμίας </ref>(the courage of Jews). Rodokos was a traitor but in no other instances “bad Jews” are referred to with a different word. Hence it seems that here as well Ἰουδαῖος and Ἰουδαϊκός are synonyms and there is no apparent reason for the change of word. Rodokos is from ἡ Ἰουδαϊκή, the exact meaning remaining unclear.</p>
                
                    <p> <persName key="Cicero">Cicero</persName> (106 – 43 BCE) mentions Jews a few times in his speech <ref type="lit"><ref corresp=" http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=Perseus%3Atext%3A1999.02.0013%3Atext%3DFlac.%3Achapter%3D28 ">Pro Flacco</ref></ref>, dealing with the gold given by Jews around Rome to Jerusalem (aurum Iudaeorum nomine, 28.67). Here the use is clearly religious for he speaks about people residing all over the empire participating a common practise for the Temple. <ref type="lit">Pro Flac. 28.68</ref>: <ref type="lit"> non enim credo religionem et Iudaeorum et hostium impedimento praestantissimo imperatori, sed pudorem fuisse.</ref> (For I do not suppose that the religion of the Jews, our enemies, was any obstacle to that most illustrious general, but that he was hindered by his own modesty.) (Translation by C. D. Yonge, B. A. London. Henry G. Bohn, York Street, Covent Garden, 1856. <ref corresp=" http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=Perseus:text:1999.02.0019:text=Flac.:chapter=28&amp;highlight=jews"> Perseus</ref>)</p>
           
                    <p>   <ref type="lit"><persName key="Strabo">Strabo</persName></ref> (1st cent. BCE – 1st cent. CE) calls the land ἡ Ἰουδαία and tells that οἱ Ἰουδαῖοι are people living in this region  <ref corresp="http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=Strab.+16.2&amp;fromdoc=Perseus%3Atext%3A1999.01.0197">(16.2.2)</ref>. A bit later, describing the <placeName key = "Palestine">Palestinian</placeName> coast, he calls the people of the area again οἱ Ἰουδαῖοι. He describes <placeName key = "Jerusalem">Jerusalem</placeName> as their city: <ref type="lit">τὰ Ἱεροσόλυμα τὴν τῶν Ἰουδαίων μητρόπολιν </ref> <ref corresp="http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=Strab.+16.2&amp;fromdoc=Perseus%3Atext%3A1999.01.0197">(16.2.28)</ref>. They are an <w lemma="ἔθνος">ἔθνος</w> and because of the geographical nature of the work, the meaning is primarily Judean – their cultural or religious customs are not mentioned, and the Diaspora is not taken into account.</p>
                
                <p>    <persName key="Philo">Philo</persName> (c. 20 BCE – 1st cent. CE) uses Ἰουδαῖος for people and Ἰουδαϊκός for things, the meaning of both adjectives being religious. Philo writes from the Diasporan point of view and discusses the universal phenomenon of Judaism, not Judeans.</p>
                    <p> Speaking about conversion, in <ref type="lit">Virt. 108</ref> Philo says that a person should be taken into the τὴν Ἰουδαίων πολιτείαν (community of Jews). The meaning is clearly religious for in the same passage that is mentioned to include divine revelations. In <ref type="lit">Virt. 212</ref> he describes <persName type="Abraham" key="bible">Abraham</persName>:<ref type="lit"> --τοῦ τῶν Ἰουδαίων ἔθνους ὁ πρεσβύτατος γένος μὲν ἦν Χαλδαῖος, πατρὸς δὲ ἀστρονομικοῦ τῶν περὶ τὰ μαθήματα διατριβόντων --</ref> (The most ancient member of the Jewish nation was a Chaldaean by birth, the son of an astrologer, one of those who study the lore of that science--). Philo highlights Abraham’s diverse background bringing up him being <placeName key="Babylon">Chaldaean</placeName> (Text and translation Loeb Philo, On the virtues, p. 228, 292). </p>
                
                    <p> Philo explains <persName type="Moses" key="bible">Moses</persName> in relation to the Jews. <ref type="lit">Mos. 1.1</ref>: <ref type="lit"> Μωυσέως τοῦ κατὰ μέν τινας νομοθέτου τῶν Ἰουδαίων, κατὰ δέ τινας ἑρμηνέως νόμων ἱερῶν -- </ref>(Moses, whom some describe as the legislator of the Jews, others as the interpreter of the Holy Laws). Also <ref type="lit">Mos. 1.7</ref>: τοῦ σύμπαντος Ἰουδαίων ἔθνους ἀρχηγέτης (the founder of the whole Jewish nation). Similarly, Philo’s Flaccus opens with <ref type="lit"> τὴν κατὰ τῶν Ἰουδαίων ἐπιβουλήν </ref>(the policy of attacking the Jews) <ref type="lit">(Flac. 1)</ref>. In the same work, he describes Jews as fellow-citizens of other Alexandrians, referring also to their religious practises: <ref type="lit">-- τοῖς πολίταις αὐτῶν Ἰουδαίοις εἰς τὰς προσευχὰς καὶ τὰ πάτρια νεωτερίζοντες</ref> (--outrage their Jewish fellow-citizens by rioting against their synagogues and ancestral customs.) <ref type="lit">(Flac. 47)</ref> (Text and translation Loeb Philo, Flaccus, p. 302, 328). </p>
                
                    <p> As for Ἰουδαϊκός, in <ref type="lit">Flaccus 73</ref> Philo writes: <ref type="lit">μηδὲν μέρος τῶν Ἰουδαϊκῶν </ref>(no side of Jewish life) (Loeb p. 342), here the neuter plural τὰ Ἰουδαϊκὰ means “Jewish things”. The use of the adjectives is especially demonstrative in <ref type="lit">Flac. 55</ref>: <ref type="lit">πέντε μοῖραι τῆς πόλεώς εἰσιν -- τούτων δύο Ἰουδαϊκαὶ λέγονται διὰ τὸ πλείστους Ἰουδαίους ἐν ταύταις κατοικεῖν </ref>(The city has five quarters -- two of these are called Jewish because most of the Jews inhabit them) (Loeb p. 332). In other words, Ἰουδαῖος describes people, Jews, and Ἰουδαϊκός things, here the quarters. Other authors don’t employ this division as scrupulously.</p>
                <p> <persName key="Josephus">Josephus</persName> (1st cent. CE) lists Jewish cities <ref type="lit">(AJ 13.395)</ref> and here οἱ Ἰουδαῖοι is a group within the region of Judea, hence not all Judeans but Jews. Tessa Rajak argues that for Josephus οἱ Ἰουδαῖοι are Jews and he describes the population of the area using the division Jews-Greeks-barbarians (Rajak 2001, 138—139). Daniel Schwartz divides Josephus’ “Jews” into two: he argues that in his earliest work, War, οἱ Ἰουδαῖοι are Judeans, but later the author shifts to a diasporan point of view and in Antiquities they are Jews, by which Schwartz means that the Jewish law was not dependent on a place but on the religion (Schwartz 2014, 61). Both of these arguments are partly true: as stated, the semantic range of the word includes all of these meanings and indeed, the conflict was not between the whole Judean population and authorities but a smaller group, and Josephus’ aspect seems to have changed during the decades between the two works. Religious practises were in the centre of the conflict and thus calling οἱ Ἰουδαῖοι Jews is justifiable, keeping in mind Schwartz’ argument about the change of the meaning. </p>
                    <p>  However, Schwartz points out that when speaking of the Alexandrian Jewry, calling them Judeans would be misleading for here the geographical meaning has fainted away – these people have lived in Egypt for centuries and they are not Judeans but Jews (Schwartz 2014, 5). <ref type="lit"><ref corresp=" http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=J.+BJ+2.487+&amp;fromdoc=Perseus%3Atext%3A1999.01.0147">BJ 2.487</ref></ref>: <ref type="lit"> Κατὰ δὲ τὴν Ἀλεξάνδρειαν ἀεὶ μὲν ἦν στάσις πρὸς τὸ Ἰουδαϊκὸν τοῖς ἐπιχωρίοις ἀφ᾽ οὗ χρησάμενος προθυμοτάτοις κατὰ τῶν Αἰγυπτίων Ἰουδαίοις Ἀλέξανδρος γέρας τῆς συμμαχίας ἔδωκεν τὸ μετοικεῖν κατὰ τὴν πόλιν ἐξ ἴσου μοίρας πρὸς τοὺς Ἕλληνας. </ref> <ref corresp= "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=J.+BJ+2.487+&amp;fromdoc=Perseus%3Atext%3A1999.01.0148"> (But for Alexandria</ref>, the sedition of the people of the place against the Jews was perpetual, and this from that very time when Alexander [the Great], upon finding the readiness of the Jews in assisting him against the Egyptians, and as a reward for such their assistance, gave them equal privileges in this city with the Grecians themselves--) Here Josephus uses both Ἰουδαῖος and Ἰουδαϊκός. In the first expression, πρὸς τὸ Ἰουδαϊκὸν, the word is in neuter singular, and it could be translated as “the Jewry”. It does not refer to any single person but to the group as a whole. In the next expression we have Jews against <placeName key = "Egypt">Egypt</placeName>, κατὰ τῶν Αἰγυπτίων Ἰουδαίοις, where Ἰουδαῖος is used in masculine plural as “Jews”, not the group but many individuals. </p>
                    
                    <p> The next passage talks about Romans: <ref type="lit"><ref corresp= "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=Perseus%3Atext%3A1999.01.0147%3Abook%3D2%3Asection%3D488">-- ἐπεί τε Ῥωμαῖοι κατεκτήσαντο τὴν Αἴγυπτον, οὔτε Καῖσαρ ὁ πρῶτος οὔτε τῶν μετ᾽ αὐτόν τις ὑπέμεινεν τὰς ἀπ᾽ Ἀλεξάνδρου τιμὰς Ἰουδαίων ἐλαττῶσαι.</ref> </ref><ref type="lit">(BJ 2.488)</ref> <ref corresp= "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=J.+BJ+2.487+&amp;fromdoc=Perseus%3Atext%3A1999.01.0148 ">(when the Romans</ref>  got possession of <placeName key = "Egypt">Egypt</placeName>, neither the first Caesar, nor any one that came after him, thought of diminishing the honors which Alexander had bestowed on the Jews.)The “honors of Jews” is expressed with Ἰουδαῖος in masculine plural.</p>
               
                    <p> In Antiquities, the case of the <placeName key = "Alexandria">Alexandrian</placeName> Jews is similar: they are Jews, not Judeans. In <ref type="lit">AJ 19.278</ref> they are opposed to the Hellenes: <ref type="lit"><ref corresp= "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=Perseus%3Atext%3A1999.01.0145%3Abook%3D19%3Asection%3D278">Στασιάζεται δὲ κατ᾽ αὐτὸν τὸν χρόνον Ἰουδαίων τὰ πρὸς Ἕλληνας ἐπὶ τῆς Ἀλεξανδρέων πόλεως -- </ref></ref><ref corresp= "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=J.+AJ+19&amp;fromdoc=Perseus%3Atext%3A1999.01.0146">(Now about this time there was a sedition between the Jews and the Greeks, at the city of Alexandria;)</ref>. </p>
                
                    <p> The identity of the Jews is further explained in <ref type="lit">AJ 19.281</ref>: <ref type="lit"><ref corresp= "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=Perseus%3Atext%3A1999.01.0145%3Abook%3D19%3Asection%3D281">-- τοὺς ἐν Ἀλεξανδρείᾳ Ἰουδαίους Ἀλεξανδρεῖς λεγομένους -- </ref> </ref><ref corresp= "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=J.+AJ+19&amp;fromdoc=Perseus%3Atext%3A1999.01.0146">(-- the Jews of <placeName key = "Alexandria">Alexandria</placeName>, called Alexandrians--)</ref>. </p>
                
                <p> Josephus only uses Ἰουδαϊκός a few times and he usually uses that adjective to refer to things, Ἰουδαῖος being for people. However, as seen earlier with “Jewry”, this distinction is not absolute.</p>
                    <p> In <ref type="lit">AJ 12.34</ref>: <ref type="lit"><ref corresp= "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=J.+AJ+12.34&amp;fromdoc=Perseus%3Atext%3A1999.01.0145">--τὸ περὶ τῆς τῶν Ἰουδαϊκῶν βιβλίων ἀναγραφῆς δόγμα--</ref></ref> <ref corresp= "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=J.+AJ+12&amp;fromdoc=Perseus%3Atext%3A1999.01.0146">(in writing his sentiments concerning the transcribing of the Jewish books)</ref> the adjective Ἰουδαϊκός refers to books, not people.</p>
                
                    <p> Similarly in <ref type="lit">AJ 14.228</ref>: <ref type="lit"><ref corresp= "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=J.+AJ+14.228&amp;amp;fromdoc=Perseus%3Atext%3A1999.01.0145">-- πολίτας Ῥωμαίων Ἰουδαίους ἱερὰ Ἰουδαϊκὰ ἔχοντας καὶ ποιοῦντας ἐν Ἐφέσῳ πρὸ τοῦ βήματος δεισιδαιμονίας ἕνεκα στρατείας ἀπέλυσα.</ref> </ref>(I have at my tribunal set these Jews, who are citizens of <placeName key = "Rome">Rome</placeName>, and follow the Jewish religious rites, and yet live at <placeName key = "Ephesus">Ephesus</placeName>, free from going into the army, on account of the superstition they are under). We have Ἰουδαῖος for people and Ἰουδαϊκός for rites. Notably these people live in Ephesus, they are mentioned to be Romans and additionally they are Jewish, which here means by religion. Also in <ref type="lit">AJ 14.230</ref>: <ref type="lit"> Ἰουδαίους τοὺς ἐν τῇ Ἀσίᾳ --ὁ ὕπατος -- ἀπέλυσεν τῆς στρατείας </ref><ref corresp= "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=J.+AJ+12&amp;amp;amp;amp;amp;fromdoc=Perseus%3Atext%3A1999.01.0146">(the consul</ref> freed the Jews that are in Asia from going into the armies) we have Jews in Asia.</p>
                
                    <p>  Near the end of the <ref type="lit">Antiquities</ref>, Josephus refers to the topic of <ref type="lit"><ref corresp= "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=J.+AJ+20.258&amp;amp;fromdoc=Perseus%3Atext%3A1999.01.0145 ">War</ref></ref>: <ref type="lit">περὶ τοῦ Ἰουδαϊκοῦ πολέμου βίβλοις </ref><ref corresp= "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=J.+AJ+20&amp;fromdoc=Perseus%3Atext%3A1999.01.0146">(books about the Jewish war) </ref><ref type="lit">(AJ 20.258)</ref>. The context alone doesn’t reveal whether he means “war of Jewish people” or “war of Jewish things/ideas”, but the earlier uses of Ἰουδαϊκός as the thing-adjective would support the latter, or Ἰουδαϊκός could be understood as “Jewry”.</p>
                
                    <p>  Josephus also gives an etymological explanation for the word: <ref type="lit">καὶ οἱ Ἰουδαῖοι πρὸς τὸ ἔργον παρεσκευάζοντο. ἐκλήθησαν δὲ τὸ ὄνομα ἀφ᾽ ἧς ἡμέρας ἐκ Βαβυλῶνος ἀνέβησαν ἐκ τῆς Ἰούδα φυλῆς, ἧς πρώτης ἐλθούσης εἰς ἐκείνους τοὺς τόπους αὐτοί τε καὶ ἡ χώρα τὴν προσηγορίαν αὐτοῖς μετέλαβον  </ref><ref corresp= "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=J.+AJ+11&amp;fromdoc=Perseus%3Atext%3A1999.01.0146 ">(So the Jews </ref> prepared for the work: that is the name they are called by from the day that they came up from Babylon, which is taken from the tribe of Judah, which came first to these places, and thence both they and the country gained that appellation)<ref type="lit"><ref corresp= "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=J.+AJ+11.173&amp;fromdoc=Perseus%3Atext%3A1999.01.0145 ">(AJ 11.173)</ref></ref>. This explanation heightens the geographical meaning but does not exclude the religious one.</p>
                
                <p>  About other designations of the Jews, David Miller has counted that in the first 11 books of Antiquities Josephus uses “Israelites” 186 times and Ἰουδαῖος only 65 times. In the later books Ἰουδαῖος is used 582 times. Thus, Miller concludes, the name of the people changed before or during the Persian era (Miller 2010, 102).</p> 
               
                    <p>   In the <ref type="lit">Gospels</ref> (1. cent. CE) the authors employ Ἰουδαῖος vocabulary diversely; in <persName key="Matthew">Matthew</persName> and <persName key="Luke">Luke</persName> it usually refers to the place, <persName key="Mark">Mark</persName> barely uses the word, whereas <persName key="John">John</persName> uses it a lot, both of people and of the place. What all the Gospels have in common is the “king of the Jews” -expression. <ref corresp= "https://www.sacred-texts.com/bib/vul/joh.htm"><ref type="lit">Vulgata</ref></ref> repeats the same uses with only a few exceptions.</p>
                    <p> As for the place, for example <ref type="lit">Mat. 2:1</ref><ref type="lit">ἐν Βηθλέεμ τῆς Ἰουδαίας</ref>, Vulgata <ref type="lit">in Bethlehem Juda </ref>(in <placeName key = "Betlehem">Betlehem</placeName> of <placeName key = "Judaea">Judaea/Judah</placeName>), 3:1 <ref type="lit">ἐν τῇ ἐρήμῳ τῆς Ἰουδαίας</ref>, Vulgata <ref type="lit">in deserto Judææ </ref>(in the wilderness of Judaea), 4:25 <ref type="lit">ἀπὸ τῆς Γαλιλαίας καὶ Δεκαπόλεως καὶ Ἱεροσολύμων καὶ Ἰουδαίας καὶ πέραν τοῦ Ἰορδάνου,</ref> Vulgata <ref type="lit">de Galilæa, et Decapoli, et de Jerosolymis, et de Judæa, et de trans Jordanem</ref> (from <placeName key = "Galilee">Galilee</placeName>, and from <placeName key = "Decapolis">Decapolis</placeName>, and from <placeName key = "Jerusalem">Jerusalem</placeName>, and from <placeName key = "Judaea">Judaea</placeName>, and from <placeName key = "Transjordan">beyond Jordan</placeName>.), <ref type="lit">Luk. 4:44</ref> <ref type="lit">εἰς τὰς συναγωγὰς τῆς Ἰουδαίας </ref>(to the synagogues of Judaea), but Vulgata <ref type="lit">in synagogis Galilææ</ref> (in synagogues of Galilee), 1:65 <ref type="lit">ἐν ὅλῃ τῇ ὀρεινῇ τῆς Ἰουδαίας, </ref>Vulgata <ref type="lit">super omnia montana Judææ </ref>(in all the mountain country of Judaea), 21:21<ref type="lit"> οἱ ἐν τῇ Ἰουδαίᾳ,</ref> Vulgata<ref type="lit"> qui in Judæa</ref> (the people in Judaea). Luke also uses the other place name: <ref type="lit">εἰς πόλιν Ἰούδα,</ref> Vulgata <ref type="lit">in civitatem Juda</ref> (to a city of Judah) (1:39). John calls the place both with the noun alone and the adjective: <ref type="lit">3:22</ref> <ref type="lit">εἰς τὴν Ἰουδαίαν γῆν</ref>, Vulgata <ref type="lit">in terram Judæam </ref>(to the land of Judea), 11:7 <ref type="lit">εἰς τὴν Ἰουδαίαν</ref>, Vulgata <ref type="lit">in Judæam</ref> (to Judaea). In <ref type="lit">Joh. 7:1</ref> we have both the place and the people living there: <ref type="lit">Καὶ μετὰ ταῦτα περιεπάτει <persName type="Jesus" key="bible">ὁ Ἰησοῦς</persName> ἐν τῇ Γαλιλαίᾳ· οὐ γὰρ ἤθελεν ἐν τῇ Ἰουδαίᾳ περιπατεῖν, ὅτι ἐζήτουν αὐτὸν οἱ Ἰουδαῖοι ἀποκτεῖναι, </ref>Vulgata <ref type="lit">Post hæc autem ambulabat Jesus in <placeName key = "Galilee">Galilæam</placeName>: non enim volebat in Judæam ambulare, quia quærebant eum Judæi interficere </ref>(and after that Jesus walked in Galilee, for he would not walk in Judaea, because οἱ Ἰουδαῖοι/ Judæi seeked to kill him). This highly geographical context would support the geographical meaning, Judeans, but the motive to kill is religious, hence Jews is justifiable as well. Both parts of the double meaning are employed. In Vulgata, the place name is usually the same as in Greek, Iudaea being the most common one.</p>
                    <p>  As for <persName type="Jesus" key="bible">the King of the Jews</persName> (βασιλεὺς τῶν Ἰουδαίων / rex Judæorum), in <ref type="lit">Mat. 2:2</ref> and 27:11, 29, 37 outsiders whose religious affiliations remain unclear call Jesus by that name, whereas in 27:42 the term used by high priests is <ref type="lit"> βασιλεὺς <placeName key = "Israel">Ἰσραήλ</placeName></ref>, Vulgata <ref type="lit">rex Israël</ref> (king of Israel), similarly in <ref type="lit">Mark: 15:2, 9, 12, 26</ref> and high priests 32. Luke only gives the name used by outsiders (<ref type="lit">Luk. 23:3, 37, 38</ref>). In John a Jew, Nathanael, says to Jesus: <ref type="lit">σὺ βασιλεὺς εἶ τοῦ <placeName key="Israel">Ἰσραήλ</placeName></ref>, Vulgata <ref type="lit">tu es rex Israël</ref> (1:49) using the insider’s title. Similarly, the crowd on the way to Jerusalem (12:13). John also repeats the king of the Jews -title in the crucifixion (18:39, 19:3, 19, 21). Notably <persName key="Herod">Herod’s</persName> title employs the place name: <ref type="lit">ἐν ταῖς ἡμέραις Ἡρῴδου βασιλέως τῆς Ἰουδαίας</ref>, Vulgata <ref type="lit">in diebus Herodis, regis Judææ</ref> (in the days of Herod king of Judaea) (Luk. 1:5), like does <persName key="Pontius_Pilatus">Pilatus’</persName>: <ref type="lit">ἡγεμονεύοντος Ποντίου Πιλάτου τῆς Ἰουδαίαςa</ref>, Vulgata <ref type="lit">procurante Pontio Pilato Judæam</ref> (when Pontius Pilatus ruled Judaea) (Luk. 3:1).</p>
                    <p>  As for the people (Ἰουδαῖοι / Iudaei), the only time Matthew talks about Jews is in 28:15: <ref type="lit">διεφημίσθη ὁ λόγος οὗτος παρὰ Ἰουδαίοις</ref>, Vulgata <ref type="lit">Et divulgatum est verbum istud apud Judæos </ref>(this saying is commonly reported among the Jews). Since the context is religious Ἰουδαῖοι/Iudaei could be understood primarily as a religious expression, for the people behind the lie of the soldiers are the high priests their motive being religious. Describing a Joseph, Luke mentions a city of Judeans, <placeName key ="Arimathaea">Arimathaea</placeName>: <ref type="lit">ἀπὸ Ἁριμαθαίας πόλεως τῶν Ἰουδαίων</ref>, Vulgata <ref type="lit">ab Arimathæa civitate Judææ</ref> (23:51). By the way Joseph is described this designation might have a religious meaning, but the city was located in Judaea and hence the meaning is rather geographical, a city of Judeans. John uses the word often in the religious meaning, Jews, for example 1:19 <ref type="lit">οἱ Ἰουδαῖοι ἐξ Ἱεροσολύμων</ref>, Vulgata <ref type="lit">Judæi ab Jerosolymis</ref> (Jews of <placeName key= "Jerusalem">Jerusalem</placeName>),  the context mentioning priests and Levites supports the religious meaning, 2:6 <ref type="lit">κατὰ τὸν καθαρισμὸν τῶν Ἰουδαίων</ref>, Vulgata <ref type="lit">purificationem Judæorum</ref> (the purifying of the Jews), 3:1 <ref type="lit">ἄρχων τῶν Ἰουδαίων</ref>, Vulgata <ref type="lit">princeps Judæorum </ref>(ruler of the Jews), 8:31<ref type="lit"> πρὸς τοὺς πεπιστευκότας αὐτῷ Ἰουδαίους,</ref> Vulgata <ref type="lit">ad eos, qui crediderunt ei, Judæos </ref>(to those Jews which believed on him), 11:55 <ref type="lit">τὸ πάσχα τῶν Ἰουδαίων</ref>, Vulgata <ref type="lit">Pascha Judæorum</ref> (the Passover of the Jews), 19:21<ref type="lit"> οἱ ἀρχιερεῖς τῶν Ἰουδαίων</ref>, Vulgata <ref type="lit">pontifices Judæorum</ref> (the high priests of the Jews). </p>
                
                <p>   Describing <placeName key= "Palestine">Palestine</placeName>, <ref type="lit"><persName key="Cassius Dio">Cassius Dio</persName></ref> (c. 150– 235 CE) says:<quote> Ταῦτα μὲν τότε ἐν τῇ <placeName key = "Palestine">Παλαιστίνῃ</placeName> ἐγένετο· οὕτω γὰρ τὸ σύμπαν ἔθνος, ὅσον ἀπὸ τῆς Φοινίκης μέχρι τῆς <placeName key ="Egypt">Αἰγύπτου</placeName> παρὰ τὴν θάλασσαν τὴν ἔσω παρήκει, ἀπὸ παλαιοῦ κέκληται. ἔχουσι δὲ καὶ ἕτερον ὄνομα ἐπίκτητον· ἥ τε γὰρ χώρα Ἰουδαία καὶ αὐτοὶ Ἰουδαῖοι ὠνομάδαται· ἡ δὲ ἐπίκλησις αὕτη ἐκείνοις μὲν οὐκ οἶδ᾿ ὅθεν ἤρξατο γενέσθαι, φέρει δὲ καὶ ἐπὶ τοὺς ἄλλους ἀνθρώπους ὅσοι τὰ νόμιμα αὐτῶν, καίπερ ἀλλοεθνεῖς ὄντες, ζηλοῦσι. καὶ ἔστι καὶ παρὰ τοῖς Ῥωμαίοις τὸ γένος τοῦτο, κολουσθὲν μὲν πολλάκις, αὐξηθὲν δὲ ἐπὶ πλεῖστον, ὥστε καὶ ἐς παρρησία τῆς νομίσεως ἐκνικῆσαι. κεχωρίδαται δὲ ἀπὸ τῶν λοιπῶν ἀνθρώπων ἔς τε τἆλλα τὰ περὶ τὴν δίαιταν πάνθ᾿ ὡς εἰπεῖν, καὶ μάλισθ᾿ ὅτι τῶν μὲν ἄλλων θεῶν οὐδένα τιμῶσιν, ἕνα δέ τινα ἰσχυρῶς σέβουσιν. οὐδ᾿ ἄγαλμα οὐδὲν οὐδ᾿ ἐν αὐτοῖς ποτε <placeName key= "Jerusalem">τοῖς Ἱεροσολύμοις</placeName> ἔσχον, ἄρρητον δὲ δὴ καὶ ἀειδῆ αὐτὸν νομίζοντες εἶναι περισσότατα ἀνθρώπων 3θρησκεύουσι. καὶ αὐτῷ νεών τε μέγιστον καὶ περικαλλέστατον, πλὴν καθ᾿ ὅσον ἀχανής τε καὶ ἀνώροφος ἦν, ἐξεποίησαν, καὶ τὴν ἡμέραν τὴν τοῦ Κρόνου καλουμένην ἀνέθεσαν, καὶ ἄλλα τε ἐν αὐτῇ ἰδιαίτατα πολλὰ1 ποιοῦσι, καὶ ἔργου οὐδενὸς σπουδαίου προσάπτονται.</quote> </p>
                <p>    (This was the course of events at that time in Palestine; for this is the name that has been given from of old to the whole country extending from Phoenicia to Egypt along the inner sea. They have also another name that they have acquired: the country has been named Judaea, and the people themselves Jews. I do not know how this title came to be given to them, but it applies also to all the rest of mankind, although of alien race, who affect their customs. This class exists even among the Romans, and though often repressed has increased to a very great extent and has won its way to the right of freedom in its observances. They are distinguished from the rest of mankind in practically every detail of life, and especially by the fact that they do not honour any of the usual gods but show extreme reverence for one particular divinity. They never had any statue of him even in Jerusalem itself, but believing him to be unnamable and invisible, they worship him in the most extravagant fashion on earth. They built to him a temple that was extremely large and beautiful, except in so far as it was open and roofless, and likewise dedicated to him the day called the day of Saturn, on which, among many other most peculiar observances, they undertake no serious occupation.) (37.16.5 – 17.3.) (Loeb Cassius Dio, Roman History, Volume III: Books 36-40, p. 126, 128. <ref corresp= "https://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Roman/Texts/Cassius_Dio/37*.html"> Open access</ref>). 
                </p>

                <p>  On one hand, Cassius Dio’s description is highly geographical explaining the territory of <placeName key= "Judaea">Judea</placeName>, which he names Ἰουδαία. This way also Ἰουδαῖοι are strongly connected to the land. In the other hand, he continues explaining the universal nature of Jewishness and describing religious practises, which gives Ἰουδαῖοι the meaning “Jews”. This way the author explains the double meaning of the word, Judean and Jewish.</p>
                
                    <p> <persName key="Tertullian">Tertullian</persName> (c. 155 AD – c. 220 AD) in his <ref type="lit"><ref corresp= "https://www.tertullian.org/latin/apologeticum_becker.htm">Apologeticum</ref></ref> speaks about the Jewish origins of Christianity. In this religious context Iudaeus is always Jewish as a contrast to Christian or Roman. He uses iudaicus for things:<ref type="lit"> -- in quo videtur thesaurus collocatus totius Iudaici sacramenti et inde iam nostri </ref><ref corresp= "https://www.tertullian.org/articles/mayor_apologeticum/mayor_apologeticum_07translation.htm">(in which the treasure of the whole Jewish religion, and hence of ours also)</ref> (19.2) and <ref type="lit">a Iudaico more</ref> (from the Jewish custom) (16.11). As for <persName key="Josephus">Josephus</persName>, a person, he uses the other adjective: <ref type="lit">Iudaeus Iosephus</ref> (the Jew Josephus) (19.6). He also employs the Ἰουδαῖος in plural genitive, “of Jews”: antiquissimis Iudaeorum instrumentis (by most ancient Jewish documents) (21.1). The region Tertullian calls <placeName key= "Judaea">Iudaea</placeName>: <ref type="lit"> apud <placeName key= "Galilee">Galilaeam</placeName>, Iudaeae regionem </ref>(in Galilee, a district of Judea) (21.23). He also mentions <placeName key= "Palestine">Palestine</placeName>: <ref type="lit">Nondum Iudaeum ab Aegypto examen Palaestina susceperat </ref>(Palestine had not yet received its Jewish swarm from <placeName key= "Egypt">Egypt</placeName>) (40.7) and here the people adjective Iudaeus is used of examen. See also <w lemma= "Ἑβραῖος">Ἑβραῖος</w>.</p>
                
                    <p> For <persName key= "John Chrysostom">John Chrysostom</persName> (c. 347 – 407 CE) as well, in his <ref type="lit"><ref corresp= "https://greekdownloads3.files.wordpress.com/2014/08/adversus-judaeos.pdf ">Adversus Judaeos</ref></ref>, Ἰουδαῖοι and gentile are “the others” as a contrary to Christians, and the use is purely religious (Sandwell 2007, 64, 87). In Chrysostom’s works religion is the central feature of one’s identity in an exclusive way (Sandwell 2007, 152), hence being both Greek and Jewish was not possible. The distinctive feature of the Ἰουδαῖοι was their religious beliefs and practises which partly overlapped but critically differed from Christian (Sandwell 2007, 85). He speaks about their practises and beliefs systematically using Ἰουδαῖος of people and Ἰουδαϊκός of things, for example 1.5: <ref type="lit">τοὺς δὲ τὰ Ἰουδαϊκὰ νοσοῦντας</ref> <ref corresp= "https://www.tertullian.org/fathers/chrysostom_adversus_judaeos_01_homily1.htm">(those who are sick with the Judaizing disease)</ref> and <ref type="lit">αἱ τῶν Ἰουδαίων ἑορταὶ </ref>(the Jewish festivals). 3.1:<ref type="lit"> Οἶδα ὅτι πολλοὶ αἰδοῦνται Ἰουδαίους, καὶ σεμνὴν νομίζουσιν εἶναι τὴν ἐκείνων πολιτείαν νῦν </ref>(Many, I know, respect the Jews and think that their present way of life is a venerable one). 3.2: <ref type="lit">Οὐδεὶς Ἰουδαῖος προσκυνεῖ τὸν Θεόν</ref> (no Jew adores God). In 6.1 he mentions both Jews and Judea when speaking of the <ref type = "lit">Septuagint</ref>: <ref type="lit">Πτολεμαῖος ὁ Φιλάδελφος τὰς πανταχόθεν βίβλους συναγαγὼν, καὶ μαθὼν ὅτι καὶ παρὰ Ἰουδαίοις εἰσὶ γραφαὶ περὶ Θεοῦ φιλοσοφοῦσαι, καὶ πολιτείας ἀρίστης, μεταπεμψάμενος ἄνδρας ἐκ τῆς Ἰουδαίας--</ref> (Ptolemy Philadelphus had collected books from all over the world. When he learned that the Jews had writings which treated of <persName type = "divine" key= "God">God</persName> and the ideal state, he sent for men from Judea--). 6.5: <ref type="lit">σεμνὰ καὶ μεγάλα τὰ Ἰουδαίων </ref>(the ceremonies of Jews). 8.1: <quote>ἄλλο τι μικρὸν ἢ μέγα Ἰουδαϊκὸν ἔθος</quote> (any other Jewish ritual great or small). See also <w lemma= "Ἑβραῖος">Ἑβραῖος</w>.</p>   
                </div>
            </div>
            
            <div type="edition" xml:lang="en">
                <div type="textpart" n="catalogue of occurrences">
                    <head>Catalogue of occurrences</head>
                    <p><hi rend="italic">Inscriptions</hi></p>
                    
                    <p><ref type="ins">CIJ 296</ref></p>
                    <p><ref type="ins">CIL V 4221</ref></p>
                    <p><ref type="ins">I.J.Afr. 71</ref></p>
                    <p><ref type="ins">IJudO I Ach 40, 42-45, Pan 3, 4, Dal 2, 3, BS 5—7, 9</ref></p>
                    <p><ref type="ins">IJudO II 40, 157 </ref></p>
                    <p><ref type="ins"> JIGRE 22, 24, 25, 27, 117</ref></p>
                    <p><ref type="ins">JIWE I 188</ref></p>
                    <p><ref type="ins">JIWE II 18, 233, 567</ref></p>
                    
                        
                    <p><hi rend="italic">Papyri</hi></p>
                    <p><ref type="pap">C. P. Jud. I 8, 9, 18, 19, 38 </ref></p>
                   
                        
                    <p><hi rend="italic">Literary sources</hi></p>
                    
                    <p><ref type="lit">Cassius Dio 37.16.5-17.3</ref></p>
                    <p><ref type="lit">Cicero Pro Flac. 28.67-68</ref></p>
                    <p><ref type="lit">Gospel of Matthew 2:1, 2; 3:1; 4:25; 27:11, 29, 37, 42; 28:15</ref></p>
                    <p><ref type="lit">Gospel of Mark 15:2, 9, 12, 26, 32</ref></p>
                    <p><ref type="lit">Gospel of Luke 1:5, 39, 65; 3:1, 22; 4:44; 11:7; 21:21; 23:3, 51</ref></p>
                    <p><ref type="lit">Gospel of John 1:19, 49; 2:6; 3:1; 7:1; 8:31; 11:55 12:13; 18:39; 19:3, 19, 21</ref></p>
                    <p><ref type="lit"> John Chrysostom Adv. Jud. 1.5; 3.1; 3.2; 6.1, 5; 8.1</ref></p>
                    <p> <ref type="lit"> Josephus AJ 11.173; 12.34; 13.395; 14.228, 230; 19.278, 281; 20.258; BJ 2.487, 488</ref></p>
                    <p> <ref type="lit">    1st Maccabees 1:11, 15, 29, 30, 43, 44; 2:23, 42; 4:2; 5:2; 7:5; 8:20; 12:3, 6; 13:42; 14:47</ref></p>
                    <p> <ref type="lit">2nd Maccabees 2:21; 12:3, 8; 8:1, 9, 10, 36; 13:21, 18</ref></p>
                    <p> <ref type="lit">Philo Flac. 1; 47; 55; 73; Mos. 1.1; 7; Virt. 108; 212</ref></p>
                    <p> <ref type="lit"> Strabo 16.2.2, 28</ref></p>
                    <p> <ref type="lit"> Tertullian Apol. 19.2; 16.11; 19.6; 21.1, 23; 40.7</ref></p>
                                        
                </div>
            </div>
            
            <div type="edition" xml:lang="en">
                <div type="textpart" n="discussion / interpretation">
                    <head>Discussion / interpretation</head>             
                    <p>Originally the word group refers to the tribe and kingdom of <placeName key= "Judaea">Judah</placeName>, but in Antiquity it has already got a second meaning, that refers to the religious phenomenon, Judaism or Jewishness. The double meaning remains in use throughout Antiquity, both in Greek and Latin, and with the rise of Christianity the religious meaning gains weight. Authors use the words differently and the exact meaning must be derived from the context. David Miller points out that for ancient people the ambiguity of the word was not as problematic as it is these days, for they didn’t have the same conceptual boundaries and they understood the concept, being able to read the context, but it was not clear what semantic distinctions they made (Miller 2010, 99, 119). However, the distinction between Jews and Judeans did exist in Antiquity, too, for there were conflicts between the authorities and (at least some) Jews, not the whole population of Judea. David Schwartz suggests that the division Jew – Judean, i.e., Diasporan – Judean, describes the extremities of the semantic range, but the real life is more complex and variegated and usually the meaning is something in between (Schwartz 2014, 83—84). David Miller emphasizes the ethnic meaning of the word: it is not only geographical, but describes people with a common background, cultural and religious ideas (Miller 2010, 112, 122). On the other hand, David Schwartz finds the ethnic meaning problematic, for even though it adds the idea of descendance to the geographical meaning, it does not include proselytes (Schwartz 2014, 5—6). If the geographical meaning is chosen for the context, the religious diversity of Judeans should be kept in mind.</p>
                    <p>The original geographical meaning loses some ground for texts that date after the end of the 2nd century CE, for the name of the province was changed to Syria Palestine (Williams 1997, 251). This could apply to official documents, but in everyday language the name Judea, which was used for centuries, may have persisted, which means that for example in graves the religious meaning should not be taken for granted. However, Williams argues that there was “no hard epigraphic evidence” for the geographical meaning in any times and that the religious meaning was the most central one, even though other meanings appear as well (Williams 1997, 252—253, 257). Schwartz agrees and parallels the situation with that of Hellenism: since Hellenistic times Hellenism didn’t require a person to be born in Greece, and similarly Judaism didn’t require descendance from Judah, but was instead religious and cultural, something other than Hellenism (Schwartz 2014, 8).</p>
                    <p>As for different contexts, Williams identifies two uses: in a Jewish context the use of the word is rare, but when it is used, the meaning is laudatory – Jewishness is a quality cherished. In a non-Jewish context the word is used to make difference between Jews and non-Jews (Williams 1997, 254—255). </p>
                    <p>In military context the meaning reflects mainly the structure of the army and only secondarily has an ethic nuance. As for taxation, in Ptolemaic <placeName key= "Egypt">Egypt</placeName> Jews were part of the privileged Hellenes till the end of the 3rd cent. BCE, when they were divided under their own category, οἱ Ἰουδαῖοι, their status likely remaining the same despite the change (Clarysse, Thompson 2006, 147—148). The question is, how was that group defined and what kind of relationship did it have with Jews as a religious group.</p> 
                    <p>For the difference between Ἰουδαῖος and Ἑβραῖος, see <w lemma= "Ἑβραῖος">Ἑβραῖος</w>.</p>                   
                </div>
            </div>

               
                <div type="bibliography" subtype = "corpora">
                <p><hi rend="italic">Corpora</hi></p> 
                    <p>  <title>CIL V</title>	”Corpus Inscriptionum Latinarum V: Inscriptiones Galliae Cisalpinae Latinae. Pars I: Inscriptiones regionis Italiae decimae”, ed. T. Mommsen, Berolini: apud G. Reimerum 1872.</p>
                    <p><title> CIJ</title>	”Corpus Inscriptionum Judaicarum vol. I Europe”, B. Jean-Baptiste Frey, Ktav publishing house, 1975.</p>
                    <p><title>C. P. Jud. I</title> "Corpus papyrorum Judaicorum", eds.Tcherikover, Avigdor, Fuks, Alexander, Stern, Menahem, Magnes Press, Hebrew University by Harvard University Press, 1957.</p>
                <p> <title>I.J.Afr.</title>	”Inscriptions juives et judaïsantes de l’Afrique Romaine”, ed. Y. le Bohec, Antiquités africaines, 1981.</p>
                <p> <title>IJudO I</title>	”Inscriptiones Judaicae Orientis I: Eastern Europe”, eds. D. Noy, A. Panayotov, H. Bloedhorn, Texts and Studies in Ancient Judaism 101, Mohr Siebeck, 2004. </p>
                <p><title>IJudO II</title>	”Inscriptiones Judaicae Orientis II: Kleinasien”, ed. W. Ameling, Texts and Studies in Ancient Judaism 99, Mohr Siebeck, 2004.</p>
                <p><title>JIGRE</title>	”Jewish Inscriptions of the Graeco-Roman Egypt”, eds. W. Horbury, D. Noy, Cambridge University Press, 1992.</p>
                    <p><title>JIWE I</title>	”Jewish inscriptions of Western Europe I: Italy (excluding the City of Rome), Spain and Gaul”, ed. D. Noy, Cambridge University Press, 1993.</p>
                <p><title>JIWE II</title>	”Jewish Inscriptions of Western Europe II: the city of Rome”, ed. D. Noy, Cambridge University Press, 1995.</p>
                </div>
                
                
                <div type="bibliography" subtype = "studies">
                    <p><hi rend="italic">Bibliography</hi></p> 
                    <p>Bauer  1988<title>	“Wörterbuch zum Neuen Testament”,</title> Walter Bauer, de Gruyter, 1988.</p>
                <p> Cohen 1999	”<title>The beginnings of jewishness. Boundaries, Varieties, Uncertainties”</title>, Shaye J.D. Cohen, University of California Press, 1999.</p>
                    <p>Clarysse, Thompson 2006<title>	”Counting the People in Hellenistic Egypt, volume 2. Historical Studies”,</title> W. Clarysse, Dorothy J. Thompson, Cambridge University Press, 2006.</p>
                    <p>Ernout, Meillet 1959	<title>“Dictionnaire étymologique de la langue Latine. Histoire des mots”</title>, A. Ernout, A. Meillet, quatrieme edition, Librairie C. Klingksieck,  1959.</p>
                    <p>Gibson 1991	<title>”The Jewish Manumission Inscriptions of the Bosporus Kingdom”</title>, E. Leigh Gibson, Texts and Studies in Ancient Judaism 75, Mohr Siebeck 1991.</p>
                                <p>Gruen 2016	<title>”Constructs of Identity in Hellenistic Judaism. Essays on Early Jewish Literature and History”</title>, Erich S. Gruen, de Gruyter, 2016.</p>
                    <p>Hopkins 1978	<title>”Conquerors and Slaves”</title>, K. Hopkins, Sociological studies in Roman history, vol. 1, Cambridge University Press, 1978.</p>
                                        <p>  Kraabel 1982<title>	”The Roman Diaspora: six questionable assumptions”</title>, A. T. Kraabel, JJS 33, 1982.</p>
                    <p>Kraemer 1989	<title>”On the meaning of the term ”Jew”</title> in Graeco-Roman inscriptions”, R. S. Kraemer, HTR vol. 82 no. 1, 1989.</p>
                    <p>Leipziger 2021	<title>”Lesepraktiken im Antiken Judentum. Rezeptionsakte, Materialität und Schriftgebrauch”</title>, J. Leipziger, De Gruyter, 2021.</p>
                    <p>Liljeqvist 2010	<title>“Vanhan testamentin heprean ja aramean sanakirja”</title>, Matti Liljeqvist, Finn Lectura, 2010.</p>
                    <p>Maltby 1991	<title> “A lexicon of ancient Latin etymologies”,</title> Maltby, Francis Cairns publications, 1991.</p>
                    <p>Miller 2010	<title>“The Meaning of Ioudaios and its Relationship to Other Group Labels in Ancient ‘Judaism’”,</title> David M. Miller, Currents in Biblical Research, September 2010, Sage 2010.</p>
                    <p> Panayotov 2004	<title>”The jews in the Balkan provinces of the Roman empire: an epigraphic and archaeological survey”</title>, A. Panayotov, diss. University of St Andrews, 2004.</p>
                    <p>Rajak 2001<title>	”Ethnic Identities in Josephus”</title>, T. Rajak, The Jewish Dialogue with Greece and Rome: Studies in Cultural and Social Interaction, ed. T. Rajak, Brill, 2001.</p>
                    <p>Renberg 2016	”<title>Where Dreams May Come. Incubation Sanctuaries in the Greco-Roman World.”</title>, vol. 1, Gil H. Renberg, Brill, 2016.</p>
                    <p>Sandwell 2007<title>	“Religious Identity in Late Antiquity : Greeks, Jews and Christians in Antioch”</title>, Isabella Sandwell, Cambridge University Press, 2007.</p>
                    <p>Schwartz 2014	<title>“Judeans and Jews: four faces of dichotomy in ancient Jewish history”</title>, Daniel R. Schwartz, University of Toronto Press, 2014.</p>
                    <p>Schürer 1973	<title>”The History of the Jewish People in the Age of Jesus Christ (175 B.C. – A.D. 138), vol. III”</title>, E. Schürer, revised and edited by G. Vermes, F. Millar, M. Goodman, T.and T. Clark LTD, 1973.</p>
                    <p>Solin 1983	<title>”Juden und Syrer im westlichen Teil der römischen Welt. Eine ethnisch-demographische Studie mit besonderer Berücksichtigung der sprachlichen Zustände”</title>, H. Solin, ANRW II.29.2, 1983.</p>
                    <p>Van der Horst 1991	<title>”Ancient Jewish Epitaphs. An introductory survey of a millennium of Jewish funerary epigraphy (300 BCE – 700 CE)”,</title> Pieter W. van der Horst, Kok Pharos Publishing House, 1991.</p>
                    <p>Williams 1997	<title>“The Meaning and Function of Ioudaios in Graeco-Roman Inscriptions”</title>, Margaret H. Williams, Zeitschrift für Papyrologie und Epigraphik, Bd. 116 (1997), published by: Dr. Rudolf Habelt GmbH.</p>
                </div>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
